import{_ as k,o as i,c as o,a as n,m as l,t as h,C as b,M as y,U as w,F as c,p,e as f,f as j,q as v}from"./chunks/framework.B1z0IdBH.js";const q={name:"PoemCard",props:{poem:{type:Object,required:!0}}},A={class:"poem-container"},z={class:"review"},M={class:"review-title"},N={class:"review-content"};function x(e,a,s,d,t,u){return i(),o("div",A,[n("div",z,[n("div",M,[a[0]||(a[0]=n("span",{class:"icon"},"question:",-1)),l(h(s.poem.question),1)]),a[2]||(a[2]=n("div",{class:"divider"},null,-1)),n("p",N,[a[1]||(a[1]=n("span",{class:"icon"},"answer:",-1)),l(h(s.poem.answer),1)])])])}const S=k(q,[["render",x],["__scopeId","data-v-af6d0f4f"]]),T=JSON.parse(`[{"question":"kalamu","answer":"kalamu ni kifaa muhimu kwa msomaji au wanafunzi mashuleni maana hutumika kuandikia maneno mbali mbali katika masomo na nyaraka za kielimu na kiofisi ili kuifadhi kumbukumbu na megineo. "},{"question":"inona no iantsoana ny fotoana alohan'ny mitatao vovonana?","answer":"maraina no iantsoana ny fotoana alohan'ny mitatao vovonana"},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਬਾਰਹ ਮਾਹਾ ਮਾਂਝ ਮਹਲਾ ੫ ਘਰੁ ੪ੴ ਸਤਿਗੁਰ ਪ੍ਰਸਾਦਿ ॥ਕਿਰਤਿ ਕਰਮ ਕੇ ਵੀਛੁੜੇ ਕਰਿ ਕਿਰਪਾ ਮੇਲਹੁ ਰਾਮ ॥ਚਾਰਿ ਕੁੰਟ ਦਹ ਦਿਸ ਭ੍ਰਮੇ ਥਕਿ ਆਏ ਪ੍ਰਭ ਕੀ ਸਾਮ ॥ਧੇਨੁ ਦੁਧੈ ਤੇ ਬਾਹਰੀ ਕਿਤੈ ਨ ਆਵੈ ਕਾਮ ॥ਜਲ ਬਿਨੁ ਸਾਖ ਕੁਮਲਾਵਤੀ ਉਪਜਹਿ ਨਾਹੀ ਦਾਮ ॥ਹਰਿ ਨਾਹ ਨ ਮਿਲੀਐ ਸਾਜਨੈ ਕਤ ਪਾਈਐ ਬਿਸਰਾਮ ॥ਜਿਤੁ ਘਰਿ ਹਰਿ ਕੰਤੁ ਨ ਪ੍ਰਗਟਈ ਭਠਿ ਨਗਰ ਸੇ ਗ੍ਰਾਮ ॥ਸ੍ਰਬ ਸੀਗਾਰ ਤੰਬੋਲ ਰਸ ਸਣੁ ਦੇਹੀ ਸਭ ਖਾਮ ॥ਪ੍ਰਭ ਸੁਆਮੀ ਕੰਤ ਵਿਹੂਣੀਆ ਮੀਤ ਸਜਣ ਸਭਿ ਜਾਮ ॥ਨਾਨਕ ਕੀ ਬੇਨੰਤੀਆ ਕਰਿ ਕਿਰਪਾ ਦੀਜੈ ਨਾਮੁ ॥ਹਰਿ ਮੇਲਹੁ ਸੁਆਮੀ ਸੰਗਿ ਪ੍ਰਭ ਜਿਸ ਕਾ ਨਿਹਚਲ ਧਾਮ ॥੧॥ਚੇਤਿ ਗੋਵਿੰਦੁ ਅਰਾਧੀਐ ਹੋਵੈ ਅਨੰਦੁ ਘਣਾ ॥ਸੰਤ ਜਨਾ ਮਿਲਿ ਪਾਈਐ ਰਸਨਾ ਨਾਮੁ ਭਣਾ ॥ਜਿਨਿ ਪਾਇਆ ਪ੍ਰਭੁ ਆਪਣਾ ਆਏ ਤਿਸਹਿ ਗਣਾ ॥ਇਕੁ ਖਿਨੁ ਤਿਸੁ ਬਿਨੁ ਜੀਵਣਾ ਬਿਰਥਾ ਜਨਮੁ ਜਣਾ ॥ਜਲਿ ਥਲਿ ਮਹੀਅਲਿ ਪੂਰਿਆ ਰਵਿਆ ਵਿਚਿ ਵਣਾ ॥ਸੋ ਪ੍ਰਭੁ ਚਿਤਿ ਨ ਆਵਈ ਕਿਤੜਾ ਦੁਖੁ ਗਣਾ ॥ਜਿਨੀ ਰਾਵਿਆ ਸੋ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਤਿੰਨਾ ਭਾਗੁ ਮਣਾ ॥ਹਰਿ ਦਰਸਨ ਕੰਉ ਮਨੁ ਲੋਚਦਾ ਨਾਨਕ ਪਿਆਸ ਮਨਾ ॥ਚੇਤਿ ਮਿਲਾਏ ਸੋ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਤਿਸ ਕੈ ਪਾਇ ਲਗਾ ॥੨॥ਵੈਸਾਖਿ ਧੀਰਨਿ ਕਿਉ ਵਾਢੀਆ ਜਿਨਾ ਪ੍ਰੇਮ ਬਿਛੋਹੁ ॥ਹਰਿ ਸਾਜਨੁ ਪੁਰਖੁ ਵਿਸਾਰਿ ਕੈ ਲਗੀ ਮਾਇਆ ਧੋਹੁ ॥ਪੁਤ੍ਰ ਕਲਤ੍ਰ ਨ ਸੰਗਿ ਧਨਾ ਹਰਿ ਅਵਿਨਾਸੀ ਓਹੁ ॥ਪਲਚਿ ਪਲਚਿ ਸਗਲੀ ਮੁਈ ਝੂਠੈ ਧੰਧੈ ਮੋਹੁ ॥ਇਕਸੁ ਹਰਿ ਕੇ ਨਾਮ ਬਿਨੁ ਅਗੈ ਲਈਅਹਿ ਖੋਹਿ ॥ਦਯੁ ਵਿਸਾਰਿ ਵਿਗੁਚਣਾ ਪ੍ਰਭ ਬਿਨੁ ਅਵਰੁ ਨ ਕੋਇ ॥ਪ੍ਰੀਤਮ ਚਰਣੀ ਜੋ ਲਗੇ ਤਿਨ ਕੀ ਨਿਰਮਲ ਸੋਇ ॥ਨਾਨਕ ਕੀ ਪ੍ਰਭ ਬੇਨਤੀ ਪ੍ਰਭ ਮਿਲਹੁ ਪਰਾਪਤਿ ਹੋਇ ॥ਵੈਸਾਖੁ ਸੁਹਾਵਾ ਤਾਂ ਲਗੈ ਜਾ ਸੰਤੁ ਭੇਟੈ ਹਰਿ ਸੋਇ ॥੩॥ਹਰਿ ਜੇਠਿ ਜੁੜੰਦਾ ਲੋੜੀਐ ਜਿਸੁ ਅਗੈ ਸਭਿ ਨਿਵੰਨਿ ॥ਹਰਿ ਸਜਣ ਦਾਵਣਿ ਲਗਿਆ ਕਿਸੈ ਨ ਦੇਈ ਬੰਨਿ ॥ਮਾਣਕ ਮੋਤੀ ਨਾਮੁ ਪ੍ਰਭ ਉਨ ਲਗੈ ਨਾਹੀ ਸੰਨਿ ॥ਰੰਗ ਸਭੇ ਨਾਰਾਇਣੈ ਜੇਤੇ ਮਨਿ ਭਾਵੰਨਿ ॥ਜੋ ਹਰਿ ਲੋੜੇ ਸੋ ਕਰੇ ਸੋਈ ਜੀਅ ਕਰੰਨਿ ॥ਜੋ ਪ੍ਰਭਿ ਕੀਤੇ ਆਪਣੇ ਸੇਈ ਕਹੀਅਹਿ ਧੰਨਿ ॥ਆਪਣ ਲੀਆ ਜੇ ਮਿਲੈ ਵਿਛੁੜਿ ਕਿਉ ਰੋਵੰਨਿ ॥ਸਾਧੂ ਸੰਗੁ ਪਰਾਪਤੇ ਨਾਨਕ ਰੰਗ ਮਾਣੰਨਿ ॥ਹਰਿ ਜੇਠੁ ਰੰਗੀਲਾ ਤਿਸੁ ਧਣੀ ਜਿਸ ਕੈ ਭਾਗੁ ਮਥੰਨਿ ॥੪॥ਆਸਾੜੁ ਤਪੰਦਾ ਤਿਸੁ ਲਗੈ ਹਰਿ ਨਾਹੁ ਨ ਜਿੰਨਾ ਪਾਸਿ ॥ਜਗਜੀਵਨ ਪੁਰਖੁ ਤਿਆਗਿ ਕੈ ਮਾਣਸ ਸੰਦੀ ਆਸ ॥ਦੁਯੈ ਭਾਇ ਵਿਗੁਚੀਐ ਗਲਿ ਪਈਸੁ ਜਮ ਕੀ ਫਾਸ ॥ਜੇਹਾ ਬੀਜੈ ਸੋ ਲੁਣੈ ਮਥੈ ਜੋ ਲਿਖਿਆਸੁ ॥ਰੈਣਿ ਵਿਹਾਣੀ ਪਛੁਤਾਣੀ ਉਠਿ ਚਲੀ ਗਈ ਨਿਰਾਸ ॥ਜਿਨ ਕੌ ਸਾਧੂ ਭੇਟੀਐ ਸੋ ਦਰਗਹ ਹੋਇ ਖਲਾਸੁ ॥ਕਰਿ ਕਿਰਪਾ ਪ੍ਰਭ ਆਪਣੀ ਤੇਰੇ ਦਰਸਨ ਹੋਇ ਪਿਆਸ ॥ਪ੍ਰਭ ਤੁਧੁ ਬਿਨੁ ਦੂਜਾ ਕੋ ਨਹੀ ਨਾਨਕ ਕੀ ਅਰਦਾਸਿ ॥ਆਸਾੜੁ ਸੁਹੰਦਾ ਤਿਸੁ ਲਗੈ ਜਿਸੁ ਮਨਿ ਹਰਿ ਚਰਣ ਨਿਵਾਸ ॥੫॥ਸਾਵਣਿ ਸਰਸੀ ਕਾਮਣੀ ਚਰਨ ਕਮਲ ਸਿਉ ਪਿਆਰੁ ॥ਮਨੁ ਤਨੁ ਰਤਾ ਸਚ ਰੰਗਿ ਇਕੋ ਨਾਮੁ ਅਧਾਰੁ ॥ਬਿਖਿਆ ਰੰਗ ਕੂੜਾਵਿਆ ਦਿਸਨਿ ਸਭੇ ਛਾਰੁ ॥ਹਰਿ ਅੰਮ੍ਰਿਤ ਬੂੰਦ ਸੁਹਾਵਣੀ ਮਿਲਿ ਸਾਧੂ ਪੀਵਣਹਾਰੁ ॥ਵਣੁ ਤਿਣੁ ਪ੍ਰਭ ਸੰਗਿ ਮਉਲਿਆ ਸੰਮ੍ਰਥ ਪੁਰਖ ਅਪਾਰੁ ॥ਹਰਿ ਮਿਲਣੈ ਨੋ ਮਨੁ ਲੋਚਦਾ ਕਰਮਿ ਮਿਲਾਵਣਹਾਰੁ ॥ਜਿਨੀ ਸਖੀਏ ਪ੍ਰਭੁ ਪਾਇਆ ਹੰਉ ਤਿਨ ਕੈ ਸਦ ਬਲਿਹਾਰ ॥ਨਾਨਕ ਹਰਿ ਜੀ ਮਇਆ ਕਰਿ ਸਬਦਿ ਸਵਾਰਣਹਾਰੁ ॥ਸਾਵਣੁ ਤਿਨਾ ਸੁਹਾਗਣੀ ਜਿਨ ਰਾਮ ਨਾਮੁ ਉਰਿ ਹਾਰੁ ॥੬॥ਭਾਦੁਇ ਭਰਮਿ ਭੁਲਾਣੀਆ ਦੂਜੈ ਲਗਾ ਹੇਤੁ ॥ਲਖ ਸੀਗਾਰ ਬਣਾਇਆ ਕਾਰਜਿ ਨਾਹੀ ਕੇਤੁ ॥ਜਿਤੁ ਦਿਨਿ ਦੇਹ ਬਿਨਸਸੀ ਤਿਤੁ ਵੇਲੈ ਕਹਸਨਿ ਪ੍ਰੇਤੁ ॥ਪਕੜਿ ਚਲਾਇਨਿ ਦੂਤ ਜਮ ਕਿਸੈ ਨ ਦੇਨੀ ਭੇਤੁ ॥ਛਡਿ ਖੜੋਤੇ ਖਿਨੈ ਮਾਹਿ ਜਿਨ ਸਿਉ ਲਗਾ ਹੇਤੁ ॥ਹਥ ਮਰੋੜੈ ਤਨੁ ਕਪੇ ਸਿਆਹਹੁ ਹੋਆ ਸੇਤੁ ॥ਜੇਹਾ ਬੀਜੈ ਸੋ ਲੁਣੈ ਕਰਮਾ ਸੰਦੜਾ ਖੇਤੁ ॥ਨਾਨਕ ਪ੍ਰਭ ਸਰਣਾਗਤੀ ਚਰਣ ਬੋਹਿਥ ਪ੍ਰਭ ਦੇਤੁ ॥ਸੇ ਭਾਦੁਇ ਨਰਕਿ ਨ ਪਾਈਅਹਿ ਗੁਰੁ ਰਖਣ ਵਾਲਾ ਹੇਤੁ ॥੭॥ਅਸੁਨਿ ਪ੍ਰੇਮ ਉਮਾਹੜਾ ਕਿਉ ਮਿਲੀਐ ਹਰਿ ਜਾਇ ॥ਮਨਿ ਤਨਿ ਪਿਆਸ ਦਰਸਨ ਘਣੀ ਕੋਈ ਆਣਿ ਮਿਲਾਵੈ ਮਾਇ ॥ਸੰਤ ਸਹਾਈ ਪ੍ਰੇਮ ਕੇ ਹਉ ਤਿਨ ਕੈ ਲਾਗਾ ਪਾਇ ॥ਵਿਣੁ ਪ੍ਰਭ ਕਿਉ ਸੁਖੁ ਪਾਈਐ ਦੂਜੀ ਨਾਹੀ ਜਾਇ ॥ਜਿੰਨੑੀ ਚਾਖਿਆ ਪ੍ਰੇਮ ਰਸੁ ਸੇ ਤ੍ਰਿਪਤਿ ਰਹੇ ਆਘਾਇ ॥ਆਪੁ ਤਿਆਗਿ ਬਿਨਤੀ ਕਰਹਿ ਲੇਹੁ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਲੜਿ ਲਾਇ ॥ਜੋ ਹਰਿ ਕੰਤਿ ਮਿਲਾਈਆ ਸਿ ਵਿਛੁੜਿ ਕਤਹਿ ਨ ਜਾਇ ॥ਪ੍ਰਭ ਵਿਣੁ ਦੂਜਾ ਕੋ ਨਹੀ ਨਾਨਕ ਹਰਿ ਸਰਣਾਇ ॥ਅਸੂ ਸੁਖੀ ਵਸੰਦੀਆ ਜਿਨਾ ਮਇਆ ਹਰਿ ਰਾਇ ॥੮॥ਕਤਿਕਿ ਕਰਮ ਕਮਾਵਣੇ ਦੋਸੁ ਨ ਕਾਹੂ ਜੋਗੁ ॥ਪਰਮੇਸਰ ਤੇ ਭੁਲਿਆਂ ਵਿਆਪਨਿ ਸਭੇ ਰੋਗ ॥ਵੇਮੁਖ ਹੋਏ ਰਾਮ ਤੇ ਲਗਨਿ ਜਨਮ ਵਿਜੋਗ ॥ਖਿਨ ਮਹਿ ਕਉੜੇ ਹੋਇ ਗਏ ਜਿਤੜੇ ਮਾਇਆ ਭੋਗ ॥ਵਿਚੁ ਨ ਕੋਈ ਕਰਿ ਸਕੈ ਕਿਸ ਥੈ ਰੋਵਹਿ ਰੋਜ ॥ਕੀਤਾ ਕਿਛੂ ਨ ਹੋਵਈ ਲਿਖਿਆ ਧੁਰਿ ਸੰਜੋਗ ॥ਵਡਭਾਗੀ ਮੇਰਾ ਪ੍ਰਭੁ ਮਿਲੈ ਤਾਂ ਉਤਰਹਿ ਸਭਿ ਬਿਓਗ ॥ਨਾਨਕ ਕਉ ਪ੍ਰਭ ਰਾਖਿ ਲੇਹਿ ਮੇਰੇ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਬੰਦੀ ਮੋਚ ॥ਕਤਿਕ ਹੋਵੈ ਸਾਧਸੰਗੁ ਬਿਨਸਹਿ ਸਭੇ ਸੋਚ ॥੯॥ਮੰਘਿਰਿ ਮਾਹਿ ਸੋਹੰਦੀਆ ਹਰਿ ਪਿਰ ਸੰਗਿ ਬੈਠੜੀਆਹ ॥ਤਿਨ ਕੀ ਸੋਭਾ ਕਿਆ ਗਣੀ ਜਿ ਸਾਹਿਬਿ ਮੇਲੜੀਆਹ ॥ਤਨੁ ਮਨੁ ਮਉਲਿਆ ਰਾਮ ਸਿਉ ਸੰਗਿ ਸਾਧ ਸਹੇਲੜੀਆਹ ॥ਸਾਧ ਜਨਾ ਤੇ ਬਾਹਰੀ ਸੇ ਰਹਨਿ ਇਕੇਲੜੀਆਹ ॥ਤਿਨ ਦੁਖੁ ਨ ਕਬਹੂ ਉਤਰੈ ਸੇ ਜਮ ਕੈ ਵਸਿ ਪੜੀਆਹ ॥ਜਿਨੀ ਰਾਵਿਆ ਪ੍ਰਭੁ ਆਪਣਾ ਸੇ ਦਿਸਨਿ ਨਿਤ ਖੜੀਆਹ ॥ਰਤਨ ਜਵੇਹਰ ਲਾਲ ਹਰਿ ਕੰਠਿ ਤਿਨਾ ਜੜੀਆਹ ॥ਨਾਨਕ ਬਾਂਛੈ ਧੂੜਿ ਤਿਨ ਪ੍ਰਭ ਸਰਣੀ ਦਰਿ ਪੜੀਆਹ ॥ਮੰਘਿਰਿ ਪ੍ਰਭੁ ਆਰਾਧਣਾ ਬਹੁੜਿ ਨ ਜਨਮੜੀਆਹ ॥੧੦॥ਪੋਖਿ ਤੁਖਾਰੁ ਨ ਵਿਆਪਈ ਕੰਠਿ ਮਿਲਿਆ ਹਰਿ ਨਾਹੁ ॥ਮਨੁ ਬੇਧਿਆ ਚਰਨਾਰਬਿੰਦ ਦਰਸਨਿ ਲਗੜਾ ਸਾਹੁ ॥ਓਟ ਗੋਵਿੰਦ ਗੋਪਾਲ ਰਾਇ ਸੇਵਾ ਸੁਆਮੀ ਲਾਹੁ ॥ਬਿਖਿਆ ਪੋਹਿ ਨ ਸਕਈ ਮਿਲਿ ਸਾਧੂ ਗੁਣ ਗਾਹੁ ॥ਜਹ ਤੇ ਉਪਜੀ ਤਹ ਮਿਲੀ ਸਚੀ ਪ੍ਰੀਤਿ ਸਮਾਹੁ ॥ਕਰੁ ਗਹਿ ਲੀਨੀ ਪਾਰਬ੍ਰਹਮਿ ਬਹੁੜਿ ਨ ਵਿਛੁੜੀਆਹੁ ॥ਬਾਰਿ ਜਾਉ ਲਖ ਬੇਰੀਆ ਹਰਿ ਸਜਣੁ ਅਗਮ ਅਗਾਹੁ ॥ਸਰਮ ਪਈ ਨਾਰਾਇਣੈ ਨਾਨਕ ਦਰਿ ਪਈਆਹੁ ॥ਪੋਖੁ ਸੋੁਹੰਦਾ ਸਰਬ ਸੁਖ ਜਿਸੁ ਬਖਸੇ ਵੇਪਰਵਾਹੁ ॥੧੧॥ਮਾਘਿ ਮਜਨੁ ਸੰਗਿ ਸਾਧੂਆ ਧੂੜੀ ਕਰਿ ਇਸਨਾਨੁ ॥ਹਰਿ ਕਾ ਨਾਮੁ ਧਿਆਇ ਸੁਣਿ ਸਭਨਾ ਨੋ ਕਰਿ ਦਾਨੁ ॥ਜਨਮ ਕਰਮ ਮਲੁ ਉਤਰੈ ਮਨ ਤੇ ਜਾਇ ਗੁਮਾਨੁ ॥ਕਾਮਿ ਕਰੋਧਿ ਨ ਮੋਹੀਐ ਬਿਨਸੈ ਲੋਭੁ ਸੁਆਨੁ ॥ਸਚੈ ਮਾਰਗਿ ਚਲਦਿਆ ਉਸਤਤਿ ਕਰੇ ਜਹਾਨੁ ॥ਅਠਸਠਿ ਤੀਰਥ ਸਗਲ ਪੁੰਨ ਜੀਅ ਦਇਆ ਪਰਵਾਨੁ ॥ਜਿਸ ਨੋ ਦੇਵੈ ਦਇਆ ਕਰਿ ਸੋਈ ਪੁਰਖੁ ਸੁਜਾਨੁ ॥ਜਿਨਾ ਮਿਲਿਆ ਪ੍ਰਭੁ ਆਪਣਾ ਨਾਨਕ ਤਿਨ ਕੁਰਬਾਨੁ ॥ਮਾਘਿ ਸੁਚੇ ਸੇ ਕਾਂਢੀਅਹਿ ਜਿਨ ਪੂਰਾ ਗੁਰੁ ਮਿਹਰਵਾਨੁ ॥੧੨॥ਫਲਗੁਣਿ ਅਨੰਦ ਉਪਾਰਜਨਾ ਹਰਿ ਸਜਣ ਪ੍ਰਗਟੇ ਆਇ ॥ਸੰਤ ਸਹਾਈ ਰਾਮ ਕੇ ਕਰਿ ਕਿਰਪਾ ਦੀਆ ਮਿਲਾਇ ॥ਸੇਜ ਸੁਹਾਵੀ ਸਰਬ ਸੁਖ ਹੁਣਿ ਦੁਖਾ ਨਾਹੀ ਜਾਇ ॥ਇਛ ਪੁਨੀ ਵਡਭਾਗਣੀ ਵਰੁ ਪਾਇਆ ਹਰਿ ਰਾਇ ॥ਮਿਲਿ ਸਹੀਆ ਮੰਗਲੁ ਗਾਵਹੀ ਗੀਤ ਗੋਵਿੰਦ ਅਲਾਇ ॥ਹਰਿ ਜੇਹਾ ਅਵਰੁ ਨ ਦਿਸਈ ਕੋਈ ਦੂਜਾ ਲਵੈ ਨ ਲਾਇ ॥ਹਲਤੁ ਪਲਤੁ ਸਵਾਰਿਓਨੁ ਨਿਹਚਲ ਦਿਤੀਅਨੁ ਜਾਇ ॥ਸੰਸਾਰ ਸਾਗਰ ਤੇ ਰਖਿਅਨੁ ਬਹੁੜਿ ਨ ਜਨਮੈ ਧਾਇ ॥ਜਿਹਵਾ ਏਕ ਅਨੇਕ ਗੁਣ ਤਰੇ ਨਾਨਕ ਚਰਣੀ ਪਾਇ ॥ਫਲਗੁਣਿ ਨਿਤ ਸਲਾਹੀਐ ਜਿਸ ਨੋ ਤਿਲੁ ਨ ਤਮਾਇ ॥੧੩॥ਜਿਨਿ ਜਿਨਿ ਨਾਮੁ ਧਿਆਇਆ ਤਿਨ ਕੇ ਕਾਜ ਸਰੇ ॥ਹਰਿ ਗੁਰੁ ਪੂਰਾ ਆਰਾਧਿਆ ਦਰਗਹ ਸਚਿ ਖਰੇ ॥ਸਰਬ ਸੁਖਾ ਨਿਧਿ ਚਰਣ ਹਰਿ ਭਉਜਲੁ ਬਿਖਮੁ ਤਰੇ ॥ਪ੍ਰੇਮ ਭਗਤਿ ਤਿਨ ਪਾਈਆ ਬਿਖਿਆ ਨਾਹਿ ਜਰੇ ॥ਕੂੜ ਗਏ ਦੁਬਿਧਾ ਨਸੀ ਪੂਰਨ ਸਚਿ ਭਰੇ ॥ਪਾਰਬ੍ਰਹਮੁ ਪ੍ਰਭੁ ਸੇਵਦੇ ਮਨ ਅੰਦਰਿ ਏਕੁ ਧਰੇ ॥ਮਾਹ ਦਿਵਸ ਮੂਰਤ ਭਲੇ ਜਿਸ ਕਉ ਨਦਰਿ ਕਰੇ ॥ਨਾਨਕੁ ਮੰਗੈ ਦਰਸ ਦਾਨੁ ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਹੁ ਹਰੇ ॥੧੪॥੧॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 133 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਅਰਜਨ ਦੇਵ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਬਾਣੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਹਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"ਹੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ! ਅਸੀ ਆਪਣੇ ਕਰਮਾਂ ਦੀ ਕਮਾਈ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ (ਤੈਥੋਂ) ਵਿੱਛੁੜੇ ਹੋਏ ਹਾਂ (ਤੈਨੂੰ ਵਿਸਾਰੀ ਬੈਠੇ ਹਾਂ), ਮਿਹਰ ਕਰ ਕੇ ਸਾਨੂੰ ਆਪਣੇ ਨਾਲ ਮਿਲਾਵੋ ।(ਮਾਇਆ ਦੇ ਮੋਹ ਵਿਚ ਫਸ ਕੇ) ਚੁਫੇਰੇ ਹਰ ਪਾਸੇ (ਸੁਖਾਂ ਦੀ ਖ਼ਾਤਰ) ਭਟਕਦੇ ਰਹੇ ਹਾਂ, ਹੁਣ, ਹੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ! ਥੱਕ ਕੇ ਤੇਰੀ ਸਰਨ ਆਏ ਹਾਂ । (ਜਿਵੇਂ) ਦੁੱਧ ਤੋਂ ਸੱਖਣੀ ਗਾਂ ਕਿਸੇ ਕੰਮ ਨਹੀਂ ਆਉਂਦੀ,(ਜਿਵੇਂ) ਪਾਣੀ ਤੋਂ ਬਿਨਾ ਖੇਤੀ ਸੁੱਕ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ (ਫ਼ਸਲ ਨਹੀਂ ਪੱਕਦੀ, ਤੇ ਉਸ ਖੇਤੀ ਵਿਚੋਂ) ਧਨ ਦੀ ਕਮਾਈ ਨਹੀਂ ਹੋ ਸਕਦੀ (ਤਿਵੇਂ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੇ ਨਾਮ ਤੋਂ ਬਿਨਾ ਸਾਡਾ ਜੀਵਨ ਵਿਅਰਥ ਚਲਾ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ) । ਸੱਜਣ ਖਸਮ-ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਨੂੰ ਮਿਲਣ ਤੋਂ ਬਿਨਾ ਕਿਸੇ ਹੋਰ ਥਾਂ ਸੁਖ ਭੀ ਨਹੀਂ ਮਿਲਦਾ ।(ਸੁਖ ਮਿਲੇ ਭੀ ਕਿਵੇਂ ?) ਜਿਸ ਹਿਰਦੇ-ਘਰ ਵਿਚ ਪਤੀ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਆ ਵੱਸੇ, ਉਸ ਦੇ ਭਾ ਦੇ (ਵੱਸਦੇ) ਪਿੰਡ ਤੇ ਸ਼ਹਰ ਤੱਪਦੀ ਭੱਠੀ ਵਰਗੇ ਹੁੰਦੇ ਹਨ ।(ਇਸਤ੍ਰੀ ਨੂੰ ਪਤੀ ਤੋਂ ਬਿਨਾ) ਸਰੀਰ ਦੇ ਸਾਰੇ ਸ਼ਿੰਗਾਰ ਪਾਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਬੀੜੇ ਤੇ ਹੋਰ ਰਸ (ਆਪਣੇ) ਸਰੀਰ ਸਮੇਤ ਹੀ ਵਿਅਰਥ ਦਿੱਸਦੇ ਹਨ, (ਤਿਵੇਂ) ਮਾਲਕ ਖਸਮ-ਪ੍ਰਭੂ (ਦੀ ਯਾਦ) ਤੋਂ ਬਿਨਾ ਸਾਰੇ ਸੱਜਣ ਮਿਤ੍ਰ ਜਿੰਦ ਦੇ ਵੈਰੀ ਹੋ ਢੁਕਦੇ ਹਨ । (ਤਾਹੀਏਂ) ਨਾਨਕ ਦੀ ਬੇਨਤੀ ਹੈ ਕਿ (ਹੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ !) ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰ ਕੇ ਆਪਣੇ ਨਾਮ ਦੀ ਦਾਤਿ ਬਖ਼ਸ਼ । ਹੇ ਹਰੀ ! ਆਪਣੇ ਚਰਨਾਂ ਵਿਚ (ਮੈਨੂੰ) ਜੋੜੀ ਰੱਖ, (ਹੋਰ ਸਾਰੇ ਆਸਰੇ-ਪਰਨੇ ਨਾਸਵੰਤ ਹਨ) ਇਕ ਤੇਰਾ ਘਰ ਸਦਾ ਅਟੱਲ ਰਹਿਣ ਵਾਲਾ ਹੈ ।੧।ਚੇਤ ਵਿਚ (ਬਸੰਤ ਰੁੱਤ ਆਉਂਦੀ ਹੈ, ਹਰ ਪਾਸੇ ਖਿੜੀ ਫੁਲਵਾੜੀ ਮਨ ਨੂੰ ਆਨੰਦ ਦੇਂਦੀ ਹੈ, ਜੇ) ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਨੂੰ ਸਿਮਰੀਏ (ਤਾਂ ਸਿਮਰਨ ਦੀ ਬਰਕਤਿ ਨਾਲ) ਬਹੁਤ ਆਤਮਕ ਆਨੰਦ ਹੋ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ । ਪਰ ਜੀਭ ਨਾਲ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਜਪਣ ਦੀ ਦਾਤਿ ਸੰਤ ਜਨਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਮਿਲ ਕੇ ਹੀ ਪ੍ਰਾਪਤ ਹੁੰਦੀ ਹੈ । ਉਸੇ ਬੰਦੇ ਨੂੰ ਜਗਤ ਵਿਚ ਜੰਮਿਆ ਜਾਣੋ (ਉਸੇ ਦਾ ਜਨਮ ਸਫਲਾ ਸਮਝੋ) ਜਿਸ ਨੇ (ਸਿਮਰਨ ਦੀ ਸਹਾਇਤਾ ਨਾਲ) ਆਪਣੇ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਮਿਲਾਪ ਹਾਸਲ ਕਰ ਲਿਆ (ਕਿਉਂਕਿ) ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੀ ਯਾਦ ਤੋਂ ਬਿਨਾ ਇਕ ਖਿਨ ਮਾਤ੍ਰ ਸਮਾ ਗੁਜ਼ਾਰਿਆਂ ਭੀ ਜ਼ਿੰਦਗੀ ਵਿਅਰਥ ਬੀਤਦੀ ਜਾਣੋ ।ਜੇਹੜਾ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਪਾਣੀ ਵਿਚ ਧਰਤੀ ਵਿਚ ਅਕਾਸ਼ ਵਿਚ ਜੰਗਲਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਹਰ ਥਾਂ ਵਿਅਪਕ ਹੈ, ਜੇ ਐਸਾ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਕਿਸੇ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਦੇ ਹਿਰਦੇ ਵਿਚ ਨਾਹ ਵੱਸੇ, ਤਾਂ ਉਸ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਦਾ (ਮਾਨਸਕ) ਦੁੱਖ ਬਿਆਨ ਨਹੀਂ ਹੋ ਸਕਦਾ ।(ਪਰ) ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਬੰਦਿਆਂ ਨੇ ਉਸ (ਸਰਬ ਵਿਆਪਕ) ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਨੂੰ ਆਪਣੇ ਹਿਰਦੇ ਵਿਚ ਵਸਾਇਆ ਹੈ, ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦਾ ਬੜਾ ਭਾਗ ਜਾਗ ਪੈਂਦਾ ਹੈ ।ਨਾਨਕ ਦਾ ਮਨ (ਭੀ ਹਰੀ ਦੇ ਦੀਦਾਰ ਨੂੰ ਤਾਂਘਦਾ ਹੈ, ਨਾਨਕ ਦੇ ਮਨ ਵਿਚ ਹਰੀ‑ਦਰਸਨ ਦੀ ਪਿਆਸ ਹੈ ।ਜੇਹੜਾ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਮੈਨੂੰ ਹਰੀ ਦਾ ਮਿਲਾਪ ਕਰਾ ਦੇਵੇ ਮੈਂ ਉਸ ਦੀ ਚਰਨੀਂ ਲੱਗਾਂਗਾ ।੨। (ਵੈਸਾਖੀ ਵਾਲਾ ਦਿਨ ਹਰੇਕ ਇਸਤ੍ਰੀ ਮਰਦ ਵਾਸਤੇ ਰੀਝਾਂ ਵਾਲਾ ਦਿਨ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ, ਪਰ) ਵੈਸਾਖ ਵਿਚ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਇਸਤ੍ਰੀਆਂ ਦਾ ਦਿਲ ਕਿਵੇਂ ਖਲੋਵੇ ਜੋ ਪਤੀ ਤੋਂ ਵਿੱਛੁੜੀਆਂ ਪਈਆਂ ਹਨ, ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਦੇ ਅੰਦਰ ਪਿਆਰ (ਦੇ ਪ੍ਰਗਟਾਵੇ) ਦੀ ਅਣਹੋਂਦ ਹੈ, (ਇਸ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਉਸ ਜੀਵ ਨੂੰ ਧੀਰਜ ਕਿਵੇਂ ਆਵੇ ਜਿਸ ਨੂੰ) ਸੱਜਣ-ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਵਿਸਾਰ ਕੇ ਮਨ-ਮੋਹਣੀ ਮਾਇਆ ਚੰਬੜੀ ਹੋਈ ਹੈ ? ਨਾਹ ਪੁਤ੍ਰ, ਨਾਹ ਇਸਤ੍ਰੀ, ਨਾਹ ਧਨ, ਕੋਈ ਭੀ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਦੇ ਨਾਲ ਨਹੀਂ ਨਿਭਦਾ ਇਕ ਅਬਿਨਾਸੀ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਹੀ ਅਸਲ ਸਾਥੀ ਹੈ । ਨਾਸਵੰਤ ਧੰਧੇ ਦਾ ਮੋਹ (ਸਾਰੀ ਲੁਕਾਈ ਨੂੰ ਹੀ) ਵਿਆਪ ਰਿਹਾ ਹੈ, (ਮਾਇਆ ਦੇ ਮੋਹ ਵਿਚ) ਮੁੜ ਮੁੜ ਫਸ ਕੇ ਸਾਰੀ ਲੁਕਾਈ ਹੀ (ਆਤਮਕ ਮੌਤੇ) ਮਰ ਰਹੀ ਹੈ । ਇਕ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਸਿਮਰਨ ਤੋਂ ਬਿਨਾ ਹੋਰ ਜਿਤਨੇ ਭੀ ਕਰਮ ਇਥੇ ਕਰੀਦੇ ਹਨ, ਉਹ ਸਾਰੇ ਮਰਨ ਤੋਂ ਪਹਿਲਾਂ ਹੀ ਖੋਹ ਲਏ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ (ਭਾਵ, ਉਹ ਉੱਚੇ ਆਤਮਕ ਜੀਵਨ ਦਾ ਅੰਗ ਨਹੀਂ ਬਣ ਸਕਦੇ) ।ਪਿਆਰ-ਸਰੂਪ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਨੂੰ ਵਿਸਾਰ ਕੇ ਖ਼ੁਆਰੀ ਹੀ ਹੁੰਦੀ ਹੈ, ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਤੋਂ ਬਿਨਾ ਜਿੰਦ ਦਾ ਹੋਰ ਕੋਈ ਸਾਥੀ ਹੀ ਨਹੀਂ ਹੁੰਦਾ ।ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਪ੍ਰੀਤਮ ਦੀ ਚਰਨੀਂ ਜੇਹੜੇ ਬੰਦੇ ਲਗਦੇ ਹਨ, ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੀ (ਲੋਕ ਪਰਲੋਕ ਵਿਚ) ਭਲੀ ਸੋਭਾ ਹੁੰਦੀ ਹੈ ।ਹੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ! (ਤੇਰੇ ਦਰ ਤੇ) ਮੇਰੀ ਬੇਨਤੀ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਮੈਨੂੰ ਤੇਰਾ ਦਿਲ-ਰੱਜਵਾਂ ਮਿਲਾਪ ਨਸੀਬ ਹੋਵੇ ।(ਰੁੱਤ ਫਿਰਨ ਨਾਲ ਚੁਫੇਰੇ ਬਨਸਪਤੀ ਪਈ ਸੁਹਾਵਣੀ ਹੋ ਜਾਏ, ਪਰ) ਜਿੰਦ ਨੂੰ ਵੈਸਾਖ ਦਾ ਮਹੀਨਾ ਤਦੋਂ ਹੀ ਸੋਹਣਾ ਲੱਗ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ ਜੇ ਹਰੀ ਸੰਤ-ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਮਿਲ ਪਏ ।੩।ਜਿਸ ਹਰੀ ਦੇ ਅੱਗੇ ਸਾਰੇ ਜੀਵ ਸਿਰ ਨਿਵਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ, ਜੇਠ ਦੇ ਮਹੀਨੇ ਵਿਚ ਉਸ ਦੇ ਚਰਨਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਜੁੜਨਾ ਚਾਹੀਦਾ ਹੈ ।ਜੇ ਹਰੀ ਸੱਜਣ ਦੇ ਲੜ ਲੱਗੇ ਰਹੀਏ ਤਾਂ ਉਹ ਕਿਸੇ (ਜਮ ਆਦਿਕ) ਨੂੰ ਆਗਿਆ ਨਹੀਂ ਦੇਂਦਾ ਕਿ ਬੰਨ੍ਹ ਕੇ ਅੱਗੇ ਲਾ ਲਏ (ਭਾਵ, ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੇ ਲੜ ਲੱਗਿਆਂ ਜਮਾਂ ਦਾ ਡਰ ਨਹੀਂ ਰਹਿ ਜਾਂਦਾ) ।(ਲੋਕ ਹੀਰੇ ਮੋਤੀ ਲਾਲ ਆਦਿਕ ਕੀਮਤੀ ਧਨ ਇਕੱਠਾ ਕਰਨ ਲਈ ਦੌੜ-ਭੱਜ ਕਰਦੇ ਹਨ, ਪਰ ਉਸ ਧਨ ਦੇ ਚੋਰੀ ਹੋ ਜਾਣ ਦਾ ਭੀ ਤੌਖ਼ਲਾ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ) ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਹੀਰੇ ਮੋਤੀ ਆਦਿਕ ਐਸਾ ਕੀਮਤਿ ਧਨ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਉਹ ਚੁਰਾਇਆ ਨਹੀਂ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ । ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੇ ਜਿਤਨੇ ਭੀ ਕੌਤਕ ਹੋ ਰਹੇ ਹਨ, (ਨਾਮ-ਧਨ ਦੀ ਬਰਕਤਿ ਨਾਲ) ਉਹ ਸਾਰੇ ਮਨ ਵਿਚ ਪਿਆਰੇ ਲੱਗਦੇ ਹਨ ।(ਇਹ ਭੀ ਸਮਝ ਆ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ ਕਿ) ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਆਪ ਤੇ ਉਸ ਦੇ ਪੈਦਾ ਕੀਤੇ ਜੀਵ ਉਹੀ ਕੁਝ ਕਰਦੇ ਹਨ ਜੋ ਉਸ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਨੂੰ ਚੰਗਾ ਲੱਗਦਾ ਹੈ ।ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਬੰਦਿਆਂ ਨੂੰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਨੇ (ਆਪਣੀ ਸਿਫ਼ਤਿ-ਸਾਲਾਹ ਦੀ ਦਾਤਿ ਦੇ ਕੇ) ਆਪਣਾ ਬਣਾ ਲਿਆ ਹੈ, ਉਹਨਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਹੀ (ਜਗਤ ਵਿਚ) ਸ਼ਾਬਾਸ਼ੇ ਮਿਲਦੀ ਹੈ ।(ਪਰ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਜੀਵਾਂ ਦੇ ਆਪਣੇ ਉੱਦਮ ਨਾਲ ਨਹੀਂ ਮਿਲ ਸਕਦਾ) ਜੇ ਜੀਵਾਂ ਦੇ ਆਪਣੇ ਉੱਦਮ ਨਾਲ ਮਿਲ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੋਵੇ, ਤਾਂ ਜੀਵ ਉਸ ਤੋਂ ਵਿੱਛੁੜ ਕੇ ਦੁਖੀ ਕਿਉਂ ਹੋਣ ?ਹੇ ਨਾਨਕ ! (ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੇ ਮਿਲਾਪ ਦੇ) ਆਨੰਦ (ਉਹੀ ਬੰਦੇ) ਮਾਣਦੇ ਹਨ, ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਗੁਰੂ ਦਾ ਸਾਥ ਮਿਲ ਜਾਏ । ਜਿਸ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਦੇ ਮੱਥੇ ਉੱਤੇ ਭਾਗ ਜਾਗੇ, ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਜੇਠ ਮਹੀਨਾ ਸੁਹਾਵਣਾ ਲੱਗਦਾ ਹੈ, ਉਸੇ ਨੂੰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ-ਮਾਲਕ ਮਿਲਦਾ ਹੈ ।੪।ਹਾੜ ਦਾ ਮਹੀਨਾ ਉਸ ਜੀਵ ਨੂੰ ਤਪਦਾ ਪ੍ਰਤੀਤ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ (ਉਹ ਬੰਦੇ ਹਾੜ ਦੇ ਮਹੀਨੇ ਵਾਂਗ ਤਪਦੇ-ਕਲਪਦੇ ਰਹਿੰਦੇ ਹਨ) ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਦੇ ਹਿਰਦੇ ਵਿਚ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ-ਪਤੀ ਨਹੀਂ ਵੱਸਦਾ,ਜੇਹੜੇ ਜਗਤ-ਦੇ-ਸਹਾਰੇ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ (ਦਾ ਆਸਰਾ) ਛੱਡ ਕੇ ਬੰਦਿਆਂ ਦੀਆਂ ਆਸਾਂ ਬਣਾਈ ਰੱਖਦੇ ਹਨ ।(ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਤੋਂ ਬਿਨਾ) ਕਿਸੇ ਹੋਰ ਦੇ ਆਸਰੇ ਰਿਹਾਂ ਖ਼ੁਆਰ ਹੀ ਹੋਈਦਾ ਹੈ, (ਜੋ ਭੀ ਕੋਈ ਹੋਰ ਸਹਾਰਾ ਤੱਕਦਾ ਹੈ) ਉਸ ਦੇ ਗਲ ਵਿਚ ਜਮ ਦੀ ਫਾਹੀ ਪੈਂਦੀ ਹੈ (ਉਸ ਦਾ ਜੀਵਨ ਸਦਾ ਸਹਮ ਵਿਚ ਬੀਤਦਾ ਹੈ) । (ਕੁਦਰਤਿ ਦਾ ਨਿਯਮ ਹੀ ਐਸਾ ਹੈ ਕਿ) ਮਨੁੱਖ ਜੇਹਾ ਬੀਜ ਬੀਜਦਾ ਹੈ, (ਕੀਤੇ ਕਰਮਾਂ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ) ਜੇਹੜਾ ਲੇਖ ਉਸਦੇ ਮੱਥੇ ਉੱਤੇ ਲਿਖਿਆ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ, ਉਹੋ ਜਿਹਾ ਫਲ ਉਹ ਪ੍ਰਾਪਤ ਕਰਦਾ ਹੈ ।(ਜਗਜੀਵਨ ਪੁਰਖ ਨੂੰ ਵਿਸਾਰਨ ਵਾਲੀ ਜੀਵ-ਇਸਤ੍ਰੀ ਦੀ) ਸਾਰੀ ਜ਼ਿੰਦਗੀ ਪਛੁਤਾਵਿਆਂ ਵਿਚ ਹੀ ਗੁਜ਼ਰਦੀ ਹੈ, ਉਹ ਜਗਤ ਤੋਂ ਟੁੱਟੇ ਹੋਏ ਦਿਲ ਨਾਲ ਹੀ ਤੁਰ ਪੈਂਦੀ ਹੈ ।ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਬੰਦਿਆਂ ਨੂੰ ਗੁਰੂ ਮਿਲ ਪੈਂਦਾ ਹੈ, ਉਹ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੀ ਹਜ਼ੂਰੀ ਵਿਚ ਸੁਰਖ਼ਰੂ ਹੁੰਦੇ ਹਨ (ਆਦਰ-ਮਾਣ ਪਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ) ।ਹੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ! ਆਪਣੀ ਮਿਹਰ ਕਰ, (ਮੇਰੇ ਮਨ ਵਿਚ) ਤੇਰੇ ਦਰਸ਼ਨ ਦੀ ਤਾਂਘ ਬਣੀ ਰਹੇ।ਹੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ! (ਤੇਰੇ ਅੱਗੇ) ਨਾਨਕ ਦੀ ਬੇਨਤੀ ਹੈ—ਆਪਣੀ ਮਿਹਰ ਕਰ, (ਕਿਉਂਕਿ) ਹੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ! ਤੈਥੋਂ ਬਿਨਾ ਮੇਰਾ ਕੋਈ ਹੋਰ ਆਸਰਾ ਪਰਨਾ ਨਹੀਂ ਹੈ ।ਜਿਸ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਦੇ ਮਨ ਵਿਚ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੇ ਚਰਨਾਂ ਦਾ ਨਿਵਾਸ ਬਣਿਆ ਰਹੇ, ਉਸ ਨੂੰ (ਤਪਦਾ) ਹਾੜ (ਭੀ) ਸੁਹਾਵਣਾ ਜਾਪਦਾ ਹੈ (ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਦੁਨੀਆ ਦੇ ਦੁੱਖ-ਕਲੇਸ਼ ਭੀ ਦੁਖੀ ਨਹੀਂ ਕਰ ਸਕਦੇ) ।੫।ਜਿਵੇਂ ਸਾਵਣ ਵਿਚ (ਵਰਖਾ ਨਾਲ ਬਨਸਪਤੀ ਹਰਿਆਵਲੀ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ, ਤਿਵੇਂ ਉਹ) ਜੀਵ-ਇਸਤ੍ਰੀ ਹਰਿਆਵਲੀ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ (ਭਾਵ, ਉਸ ਜੀਵ ਦਾ ਹਿਰਦਾ ਖਿੜ ਪੈਂਦਾ ਹੈ) ਜਿਸ ਦਾ ਪਿਆਰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੇ ਸੁਹਣੇ ਚਰਨਾਂ ਨਾਲ ਬਣ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ ।ਉਸ ਦਾ ਮਨ ਉਸ ਦਾ ਤਨ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੇ ਪਿਆਰ ਵਿਚ ਰੰਗਿਆ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ, ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਹੀ (ਉਸ ਦੀ ਜ਼ਿੰਦਗੀ ਦਾ) ਆਸਰਾ ਬਣ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ,ਮਾਇਆ ਦੇ ਨਾਸਵੰਤ ਕੌਤਕ ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਸਾਰੇ ਸੁਆਹ (ਨਿਕੰਮੇ) ਦਿਸਦੇ ਹਨ ।(ਸਾਵਣ ਵਿਚ ਜਿਵੇਂ ਵਰਖਾ ਦੀ ਬੂੰਦ ਸੋਹਣੀ ਲੱਗਦੀ ਹੈ, ਤਿਵੇਂ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ-ਚਰਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਪਿਆਰ ਵਾਲੇ ਬੰਦੇ ਨੂੰ) ਹਰੀ ਦੇ ਨਾਮ ਦੀ ਆਤਮਕ ਜੀਵਨ ਦੇਣ ਵਾਲੀ ਬੂੰਦ ਪਿਆਰੀ ਲੱਗਦੀ ਹੈ, ਗੁਰੂ ਨੂੰ ਮਿਲ ਕੇ ਉਹ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਉਸ ਬੂੰਦ ਨੂੰ ਪੀਣ ਜੋਗਾ ਹੋ ਪੈਂਦਾ ਹੈ (ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੀ ਵਡਿਆਈ ਦੀਆਂ ਨਿੱਕੀਆਂ ਨਿੱਕੀਆਂ ਗੱਲਾਂ ਭੀ ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਮਿੱਠੀਆਂ ਲੱਗਦੀਆਂ ਹਨ, ਗੁਰੂ ਨੂੰ ਮਿਲ ਕੇ ਬੜੇ ਸ਼ੌਕ ਨਾਲ ਸੁਣਦਾ ਹੈ) । ਜਿਸ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੇ ਮੇਲ ਨਾਲ ਸਾਰਾ ਜਗਤ (ਬਨਸਪਤੀ ਆਦਿਕ) ਹਰਿਆ-ਭਰਿਆ ਹੋਇਆ ਹੈ, ਜੋ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਸਭ ਕੁਝ ਕਰਨ ਜੋਗਾ ਹੈ ਵਿਆਪਕ ਹੈ ਤੇ ਬੇਅੰਤ ਹੈ, ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਮਿਲਣ ਵਾਸਤੇ ਮੇਰਾ ਮਨ ਭੀ ਤਾਂਘਦਾ ਹੈ, ਪਰ ਉਹ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਆਪ ਹੀ ਆਪਣੀ ਮਿਹਰ ਨਾਲ ਮਿਲਾਣ ਦੇ ਸਮਰੱਥ ਹੈ । ਮੈਂ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਗੁਰਮੁਖ ਸਹੇਲੀਆਂ ਤੋਂ ਸਦਕੇ ਹਾਂ, ਸਦਾ ਕੁਰਬਾਨ ਹਾਂ ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਨੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦਾ ਮਿਲਾਪ ਹਾਸਲ ਕਰ ਲਿਆ ਹੈ ।ਹੇ ਨਾਨਕ ! (ਬੇਨਤੀ ਕਰ ਤੇ ਆਖ—) ਹੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ! ਮੇਰੇ ਉੱਤੇ ਮਿਹਰ ਕਰ, ਤੂੰ ਆਪ ਹੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਦੇ ਸ਼ਬਦ ਦੀ ਰਾਹੀਂ (ਮੇਰੀ ਜਿੰਦ ਨੂੰ) ਸਵਾਰਨ ਜੋਗਾ ਹੈਂ ।ਸਾਵਣ ਦਾ ਮਹੀਨਾ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਭਾਗਾਂ ਵਾਲੀਆਂ (ਜੀਵ-ਇਸਤ੍ਰੀਆਂ) ਵਾਸਤੇ (ਖੇੜਾ ਤੇ ਠੰਡ ਲਿਆਉਣ ਵਾਲਾ) ਹੈ ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਨੇ ਆਪਣੇ ਹਿਰਦੇ (ਰੂਪ ਗਲ) ਵਿਚ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ (-ਰੂਪ) ਹਾਰ ਪਾਇਆ ਹੋਇਆ ਹੈ ।੬।(ਜਿਵੇਂ) ਭਾਦਰੋਂ (ਦੇ ਤ੍ਰਾਟਕੇ ਤੇ ਘੰੁਮੇ) ਵਿਚ (ਮਨੁੱਖ ਬਹੁਤ ਘਬਰਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ, ਤਿਵੇਂ) ਜਿਸ ਜੀਵ-ਇਸਤ੍ਰੀ ਦਾ ਪਿਆਰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ-ਪਤੀ ਤੋਂ ਬਿਨਾ ਕਿਸੇ ਹੋਰ ਨਾਲ ਲੱਗਦਾ ਹੈ ਉਹ ਭਟਕਣਾ ਦੇ ਕਾਰਨ ਜੀਵਨ ਦੇ ਸਹੀ ਰਸਤੇ ਤੋਂ ਖੁੰਝ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ,ਉਹ ਭਾਵੇਂ ਲੱਖਾਂ ਹਾਰ ਸ਼ਿੰਗਾਰ ਕਰੇ, (ਉਸ ਦੇ) ਕਿਸੇ ਕੰਮ ਨਹੀਂ ਆਉਂਦੇ ।ਜਿਸ ਦਿਨ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਦਾ ਸਰੀਰ ਨਾਸ ਹੋਵੇਗਾ (ਜਦੋਂ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਮਰ ਜਾਇਗਾ) ਉਸ ਵੇਲੇ (ਸਾਰੇ ਸਾਕ-ਅੰਗ) ਆਖਣਗੇ ਕਿ ਇਹ ਹੁਣ ਗੁਜ਼ਰ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ । (ਲੋਥ ਅਪਵਿਤ੍ਰ ਪਈ ਹੈ, ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਛੇਤੀ ਬਾਹਰ ਲੈ ਚੱਲੋ)ਜਮਦੂਤ (ਜਿੰਦ ਨੂੰ) ਫੜ ਕੇ ਅੱਗੇ ਲਾ ਲੈਂਦੇ ਹਨ, ਕਿਸੇ ਨੂੰ (ਇਹ) ਭੇਤ ਨਹੀਂ ਦੱਸਦੇ (ਕਿ ਕਿੱਥੇ ਲੈ ਚੱਲੇ ਹਾਂ) । (ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਸੰਬੰਧੀਆਂ ਨਾਲ (ਸਾਰੀ ਉਮਰ ਬੜਾ) ਪਿਆਰ ਬਣਿਆ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ ਉਹ ਪਲ ਵਿਚ ਹੀ ਸਾਥ ਛੱਡ ਬੈਠਦੇ ਹਨ ।(ਮੌਤ ਆਈ ਵੇਖ ਕੇ ਮਨੁੱਖ) ਬੜਾ ਪਛੁਤਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ, ਉਸ ਦਾ ਸਰੀਰ ਔਖਾ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ, ਉਹ ਕਾਲੁ ਤੋਂ ਚਿੱਟਾ ਪਿਆ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ (ਘਬਰਾਹਟ ਨਾਲ ਇਕ ਰੰਗ ਆਉਂਦਾ ਹੈ ਇਕ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ) ।ਇਹ ਸਰੀਰ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਦੇ ਕੀਤੇ ਕਰਮਾਂ ਦਾ ਖੇਤ ਹੈ, ਜੋ ਕੁਝ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਇਸ ਵਿਚ ਬੀਜਦਾ ਹੈ ਉਹੀ ਫ਼ਸਲ ਵੱਢਦਾ ਹੈ (ਜੇਹੇ ਕਰਮ ਕਰਦਾ ਹੈ, ਤੇਹਾ ਫਲ ਪਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ) ।ਹੇ ਨਾਨਕ ! (ਗੁਰੂ ਦੀ ਕਿਰਪਾ ਨਾਲ) ਉਹ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੀ ਸ਼ਰਨ ਵਿਚ ਆ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ, ਗੁਰੂ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੇ ਚਰਨ-ਰੂਪ ਜਹਾਜ਼ (ਵਿਚ ਚੜ੍ਹਾ) ਦੇਂਦਾ ਹੈ।ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਦਾ ਰਾਖਾ ਤੇ ਹਿਤੂ ਗੁਰੂ ਬਣਦਾ ਹੈ, ਉਹ ਨਰਕ ਵਿਚ ਨਹੀਂ ਪਾਏ ਜਾਂਦੇ ।।੭।।ਹੇ ਮਾਂ ! (ਭਾਦਰੋਂ ਦੇ ਘੰੁਮੇ ਤੇ ਤ੍ਰਾਟਕੇ ਲੰਘਣ ਪਿੱਛੋਂ) ਅੱਸੂ (ਦੀ ਮਿੱਠੀ ਮਿੱਠੀ ਰੁੱਤ) ਵਿਚ (ਮੇਰੇ ਅੰਦਰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ-ਪਤੀ ਦੇ) ਪਿਆਰ ਦਾ ਉਛਾਲਾ ਆ ਰਿਹਾ ਹੈ (ਮਨ ਤੜਫਦਾ ਹੈ ਕਿ) ਕਿਸੇ ਨਾ ਕਿਸੇ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਚੱਲ ਕੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ-ਪਤੀ ਨੂੰ ਮਿਲਾਂ ।ਮੇਰੇ ਮਨ ਵਿਚ ਮੇਰੇ ਤਨ ਵਿਚ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੇ ਦਰਸ਼ਨ ਦੀ ਬੜੀ ਪਿਆਸ ਲੱਗੀ ਹੋਈ ਹੈ (ਚਿੱਤ ਲੋਚਦਾ ਹੈ ਕਿ) ਕੋਈ (ਉਸ ਪਤੀ ਨੂੰ) ਲਿਆ ਕੇ ਮੇਲ ਕਰਾ ਦੇਵੇ ।(ਇਹ ਸੁਣ ਕੇ ਕਿ) ਸੰਤ ਜਨ ਪ੍ਰੇਮ ਵਧਾਣ ਵਿਚ ਸਹੈਤਾ ਕਰਿਆ ਕਰਦੇ ਹਨ, ਮੈਂ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੀ ਚਰਨੀਂ ਲੱਗੀ ਹਾਂ । (ਹੇ ਮਾਂ !) ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਤੋਂ ਬਿਨਾ ਸੁਖ ਆਨੰਦ ਨਹੀਂ ਮਿਲ ਸਕਦਾ (ਕਿਉਂਕਿ ਸੁਖ-ਆਨੰਦ ਦੀ) ਹੋਰ ਕੋਈ ਥਾਂ ਹੀ ਨਹੀਂ ।ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ (ਵਡ-ਭਾਗੀਆਂ) ਨੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ-ਪਿਆਰ ਦਾ ਸੁਆਦ (ਇਕ ਵਾਰੀ) ਚੱਖ ਲਿਆ ਹੈ (ਉਹਨਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਮਾਇਆ ਦੇ ਸੁਆਦ ਭੁੱਲ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ,ਮਾਇਆ ਵੱਲੋਂ) ਉਹ ਰੱਜ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ, ਆਪਾ‑ਭਾਵ ਛੱਡ ਕੇ ਉਹ ਸਦਾ ਅਰਦਾਸਾਂ ਕਰਦੇ ਰਹਿੰਦੇ ਹਨ—ਹੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ! ਸਾਨੂੰ ਆਪਣੇ ਲੜ ਲਾਈ ਰੱਖ ।ਜਿਸ ਜੀਵ-ਇਸਤ੍ਰੀ ਨੂੰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਖਸਮ ਨੇ ਆਪਣੇ ਨਾਲ ਮਿਲਾ ਲਿਆ ਹੈ, ਉਹ (ਉਸ ਮਿਲਾਪ ਵਿਚੋਂ) ਵਿੱਛੁੜ ਕੇ ਹੋਰ ਕਿਸੇ ਥਾਂ ਨਹੀਂ ਜਾਂਦੀ,(ਕਿਉਂਕਿ) ਹੇ ਨਾਨਕ (ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਨਿਸਚਾ ਆ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਸਦੀਵੀ ਸੁਖ ਵਾਸਤੇ) ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੀ ਸ਼ਰਨ ਤੋਂ ਬਿਨਾ ਹੋਰ ਕੋਈ ਥਾਂ ਨਹੀਂ ਹੈ । ਉਹ ਸਦਾ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੀ ਸ਼ਰਨ ਪਈ ਰਹਿੰਦੀ ਹੈ । ਅੱਸੂ (ਦੀ ਮਿੱਠੀ ਮਿੱਠੀ ਰੁੱਤ) ਵਿਚ ਉਹ ਜੀਵ-ਇਸਤ੍ਰੀਆਂ ਸੁਖ ਵਿਚ ਵੱਸਦੀਆਂ ਹਨ, ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਉੱਤੇ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੀ ਕਿਰਪਾ ਹੁੰਦੀ ਹੈ ।੮।ਕੱਤਕ (ਦੀ ਸੁਹਾਵਣੀ ਰੁੱਤ) ਵਿਚ (ਭੀ ਜੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ-ਪਤੀ ਨਾਲੋਂ ਵਿਛੋੜਾ ਰਿਹਾ ਤਾਂ ਇਹ ਆਪਣੇ) ਕੀਤੇ ਕਰਮਾਂ ਦਾ ਸਿੱਟਾ ਹੈ, ਕਿਸੇ ਹੋਰ ਦੇ ਮੱਥੇ ਕੋਈ ਦੋਸ ਨਹੀਂ ਲਾਇਆ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ।ਪਰਮੇਸ਼ਰ (ਦੀ ਯਾਦ) ਤੋਂ ਖੁੰਝਿਆਂ (ਦੁਨੀਆ ਦੇ) ਸਾਰੇ ਦੁੱਖ-ਕਲੇਸ਼ ਜ਼ੋਰ ਪਾ ਲੈਂਦੇ ਹਨ ।ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਨੇ (ਇਸ ਜਨਮ ਵਿਚ) ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੀ ਯਾਦ ਵੱਲੋਂ ਮੂੰਹ ਮੋੜੀ ਰੱਖਿਆ, ਉਹਨਾਂ ਨੂੰ (ਫਿਰ) ਲੰਮੇ ਵਿਛੋੜੇ ਪੈ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ ।ਜੇਹੜੀਆਂ ਮਾਇਆ ਦੀਆਂ ਮੌਜਾਂ (ਦੀ ਖ਼ਾਤਰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਨੂੰ ਭੁਲਾ ਦਿੱਤਾ ਸੀ, ਉਹ ਭੀ) ਇਕ ਪਲ ਵਿਚ ਦੁਖਦਾਈ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦੀਆਂ ਹਨ,(ਉਸ ਦੁਖੀ ਹਾਲਤ ਵਿਚ) ਕਿਸੇ ਪਾਸ ਭੀ ਨਿਤ ਰੋਣੇ ਰੋਣ ਦਾ ਕੋਈ ਲਾਭ ਨਹੀਂ ਹੁੰਦਾ, (ਕਿਉਂਕਿ ਦੁੱਖ ਤਾਂ ਹੈ ਵਿਛੋੜੇ ਦੇ ਕਾਰਨ, ਤੇ ਵਿਛੋੜੇ ਨੂੰ ਦੂਰ ਕਰਨ ਲਈ) ਕੋਈ ਵਿਚੋਲਾ-ਪਨ ਨਹੀਂ ਕਰ ਸਕਦਾ ।(ਦੁਖੀ ਜੀਵ ਦੀ ਆਪਣੀ) ਕੋਈ ਪੇਸ਼ ਨਹੀਂ ਜਾਂਦੀ, (ਪਿਛਲੇ ਕੀਤੇ ਕਰਮਾਂ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ) ਧੁਰੋਂ ਹੀ ਲਿਖੇ ਲੇਖਾਂ ਦੀ ਬਿਧ ਆ ਬਣਦੀ ਹੈ ।(ਹਾਂ !) ਜੇ ਚੰਗੇ ਭਾਗਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ (ਆਪ) ਆ ਮਿਲੇ, ਤਾਂ ਵਿਛੋੜੇ ਤੋਂ ਪੈਦਾ ਹੋਏ ਸਾਰੇ ਦੁੱਖ ਮਿਟ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ ।(ਨਾਨਕ ਦੀ ਤਾਂ ਇਹੀ ਬੇਨਤੀ ਹੈ—) ਹੇ ਮਾਇਆ ਦੇ ਬੰਧਨਾਂ ਤੋਂ ਛੁਡਾਵਣ ਵਾਲੇ ਮੇਰੇ ਮਾਲਕ ! ਨਾਨਕ ਨੂੰ (ਮਾਇਆ ਦੇ ਮੋਹ ਤੋਂ) ਬਚਾ ਲੈ ।ਕੱਤਕ (ਦੀ ਸੁਆਦਲੀ ਰੁੱਤ) ਵਿਚ ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਸਾਧ ਸੰਗਤਿ ਮਿਲ ਜਾਏ, ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੇ (ਵਿਛੋੜੇ ਵਾਲੇ) ਸਾਰੇ ਚਿੰਤਾ ਝੋਰੇ ਮੁੱਕ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ ।੯।ਮੱਘਰ (ਦੇ ਠੰਢੇ-ਮਿੱਠੇ) ਮਹੀਨੇ ਵਿਚ ਉਹ ਜੀਵ-ਇਸਤ੍ਰੀਆਂ ਸੋਹਣੀਆਂ ਲੱਗਦੀਆਂ ਹਨ ਜੋ ਹਰੀ-ਪਤੀ ਦੇ ਨਾਲ ਬੈਠੀਆਂ ਹੁੰਦੀਆਂ ਹਨ ।ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਮਾਲਕ-ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਨੇ ਆਪਣੇ ਨਾਲ ਮਿਲਾ ਲਿਆ, ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੀ ਸੋਭਾ ਬਿਆਨ ਨਹੀਂ ਹੋ ਸਕਦੀ ।ਸਤ-ਸੰਗੀ ਸਹੇਲੀਆਂ ਦੀ ਸੰਗਤਿ ਵਿਚ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੇ ਨਾਲ (ਚਿੱਤ ਜੋੜ ਕੇ) ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦਾ ਸਰੀਰ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦਾ ਮਨ ਸਦਾ ਖਿੜਿਆ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ ।ਪਰ ਜੇਹੜੀਆਂ ਜੀਵ-ਇਸਤ੍ਰੀਆਂ ਸਤਸੰਗੀਆਂ (ਦੀ ਸੰਗਤਿ) ਤੋਂ ਵਾਂਝੀਆਂ ਰਹਿੰਦੀਆਂ ਹਨ, ਉਹ ਇਕੱਲੀਆਂ (ਛੁੱਟੜ) ਹੀ ਰਹਿੰਦੀਆਂ ਹਨ (ਜਿਵੇਂ ਸੜੇ ਹੋਏ ਤਿਲਾਂ ਦਾ ਬੂਟਾ ਪੈਲੀ ਵਿਚ ਨਿਖਸਮਾ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ ।ਇਕੱਲੀ ਨਿਖਸਮੀ ਜਿੰਦ ਨੂੰ ਵੇਖ ਕੇ ਕਾਮਾਦਿਕ ਕਈ ਵੈਰੀ ਆ ਕੇ ਘੇਰ ਲੈਂਦੇ ਹਨ, ਤੇ) ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦਾ (ਵਿਕਾਰਾਂ ਤੋਂ ਉਪਜਿਆ) ਦੁੱਖ ਕਦੇ ਲਹਿੰਦਾ ਨਹੀਂ, ਉਹ ਜਮਾਂ ਦੇ ਵੱਸ ਪਈਆਂ ਰਹਿੰਦੀਆਂ ਹਨ । ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਜੀਵ-ਇਸਤ੍ਰੀਆਂ ਨੇ ਪਤੀ-ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦਾ ਸਾਥ ਮਾਣਿਆ ਹੈ, ਉਹ (ਵਿਕਾਰਾਂ ਦੇ ਹੱਲੇ ਵਲੋਂ) ਸਦਾ ਸੁਚੇਤ ਦਿੱਸਦੀਆਂ ਹਨ (ਵਿਕਾਰ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਉਤੇ ਚੋਟ ਨਹੀਂ ਕਰ ਸਕਦੇ, ਕਿਉਂਕਿ)ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੇ ਗੁਣਾਨੁਵਾਦ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਹਿਰਦੇ ਵਿਚ ਪ੍ਰੋਤੇ ਰਹਿੰਦੇ ਹਨ, ਜਿਵੇਂ ਹੀਰੇ ਜਵਾਹਰ ਤੇ ਲਾਲਾਂ ਦਾ ਹਾਰ ਗਲ ਵਿਚ ਪਾਇਆ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ ।ਨਾਨਕ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਸਤਸੰਗੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਚਰਨਾਂ ਦੀ ਧੂੜ ਮੰਗਦਾ ਹੈ ਜੋ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੇ ਦਰ ਤੇ ਪਏ ਰਹਿੰਦੇ ਹਨ ਜੋ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੀ ਸ਼ਰਨ ਵਿਚ ਰਹਿੰਦੇ ਹਨ ।ਮੱਘਰ ਵਿਚ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਸਿਮਰਨ ਕੀਤਿਆਂ ਮੁੜ ਜਨਮ ਮਰਨ ਦਾ ਗੇੜ ਨਹੀਂ ਵਾਪਰਦਾ ।੧੦।ਪੋਹ ਦੇ ਮਹੀਨੇ ਜਿਸ ਜੀਵ-ਇਸਤ੍ਰੀ ਦੇ ਗਲ ਨਾਲ (ਹਿਰਦੇ ਵਿਚ) ਪ੍ਰਭੂ-ਪਤੀ ਲੱਗਾ ਹੋਇਆ ਹੋਵੇ ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਕੱਕਰ (ਮਨ ਦੀ ਕਠੋਰਤਾ, ਕੋਰਾਪਨ) ਜ਼ੋਰ ਨਹੀਂ ਪਾ ਸਕਦਾ,(ਕਿਉਂਕਿ) ਉਸਦੀ ਬ੍ਰਿਤੀ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੇ ਦੀਦਾਰ ਦੀ ਤਾਂਘ ਵਿਚ ਜੁੜੀ ਰਹਿੰਦੀ ਹੈ, ਉਸ ਦਾ ਮਨ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੇ ਸੋਹਣੇ ਚਰਨਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਵਿੱਝਾ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ ।ਜਿਸ ਜੀਵ-ਇਸਤ੍ਰੀ ਨੇ ਗੋਬਿੰਦ ਗੋਪਾਲ ਦਾ ਆਸਰਾ ਲਿਆ ਹੈ, ਉਸ ਨੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ-ਪਤੀ ਦੀ ਸੇਵਾ ਦਾ ਲਾਭ ਖੱਟਿਆ ਹੈ, ਮਾਇਆ ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਪੋਹ ਨਹੀਂ ਸਕਦੀ, ਗੁਰੂ ਨੂੰ ਮਿਲ ਕੇ ਉਸ ਨੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੀ ਸਿਫ਼ਤਿ-ਸਾਲਾਹ ਵਿਚ ਚੱੁਭੀ ਲਾਈ ਹੈ ।ਜਿਸ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਤੋਂ ਉਸ ਨੇ ਜਨਮ ਲਿਆ ਹੈ, ਉਸੇ ਵਿਚ ਉਹ ਜੁੜੀ ਰਹਿੰਦੀ ਹੈ, ਉਸ ਦੀ ਲਿਵ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੀ ਪ੍ਰੀਤ ਵਿਚ ਲੱਗੀ ਰਹਿੰਦੀ ਹੈ ।ਪਾਰਬ੍ਰਹਮ ਨੇ (ਉਸ ਦਾ) ਹੱਥ ਫੜ ਕੇ (ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਆਪਣੇ ਚਰਨਾਂ ਵਿਚ) ਜੋੜਿਆ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ, ਉਹ ਮੁੜ (ਉਸ ਦੇ ਚਰਨਾਂ ਤੋਂ) ਵਿੱਛੁੜਦੀ ਨਹੀਂ ।(ਪਰ) ਉਹ ਸੱਜਣ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਬੜਾ ਅਪਹੁੰਚ ਹੈ, ਬੜਾ ਡੂੰਘਾ ਹੈ, ਮੈਂ ਉਸ ਤੋਂ ਲਖ ਵਾਰੀ ਕੁਰਬਾਨ ਹਾਂ । ਹੇ ਨਾਨਕ ! (ਉਹ ਬੜਾ ਦਿਆਲ ਹੈ) ਦਰ ਉੱਤੇ ਡਿੱਗਿਆਂ ਦੀ ਉਸ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਨੂੰ ਇੱਜ਼ਤ ਰੱਖਣੀ ਹੀ ਪੈਂਦੀ ਹੈ ।ਜਿਸ ਉੱਤੇ ਉਹ ਬੇ-ਪਰਵਾਹ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਮਿਹਰ ਕਰਦਾ ਹੈ, ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਪੋਹ ਦਾ ਮਹੀਨਾ ਸੁਹਾਵਣਾ ਲੱਗਦਾ ਹੈ ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਸਾਰੇ ਹੀ ਸੁਖ ਮਿਲ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ ।੧੧।ਮਾਘ ਵਿਚ (ਮਾਘੀ ਵਾਲੇ ਦਿਨ ਲੋਕ ਪ੍ਰਯਾਗ ਆਦਿਕ ਤੀਰਥਾਂ ਤੇ ਇਸ਼ਨਾਨ ਕਰਨਾ ਬੜਾ ਪੁੰਨ ਸਮਝਦੇ ਹਨ,ਪਰ ਤੂੰ ਹੇ ਭਾਈ !) ਗੁਰਮੁਖਾਂ ਦੀ ਸੰਗਤਿ ਵਿਚ (ਬੈਠ, ਇਹੀ ਹੈ ਤੀਰਥਾਂ ਦਾ) ਇਸ਼ਨਾਨ, ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੀ ਚਰਨ ਧੂੜ ਵਿਚ ਇਸ਼ਨਾਨ ਕਰ (ਨਿਮ੍ਰਤਾ-ਭਾਵ ਨਾਲ ਗੁਰਮੁਖਾਂ ਦੀ ਸੰਗਤਿ ਕਰ, ਉਥੇ) ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਜਪ, ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੀ ਸਿਫ਼ਤਿ-ਸਾਲਾਹ ਸੁਣ, ਹੋਰ ਸਭਨਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਇਹ ਨਾਮ ਦੀ ਦਾਤਿ ਵੰਡ, (ਇਸ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ) ਕਈ ਜਨਮਾਂ ਦੇ ਕੀਤੇ ਕਰਮਾਂ ਤੋਂ ਪੈਦਾ ਹੋਈ ਵਿਕਾਰਾਂ ਦੀ ਮੈਲ (ਤੇਰੇ ਮਨ ਤੋਂ) ਲਹਿ ਜਾਇਗੀ, ਤੇਰੇ ਮਨ ਵਿਚੋਂ ਅਹੰਕਾਰ ਦੂਰ ਹੋ ਜਾਇਗਾ ।(ਸਿਮਰਨ ਦੀ ਬਰਕਤਿ ਨਾਲ) ਕਾਮ ਵਿਚ ਕ੍ਰੋਧ ਵਿਚ ਨਹੀਂ ਫਸੀਦਾ, ਲੋਭ-ਕੁੱਤਾ ਭੀ ਮੁੱਕ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ (ਲੋਭ, ਜਿਸ ਦੇ ਅਸਰ ਹੇਠ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਕੁੱਤੇ ਵਾਂਗ ਦਰ ਦਰ ਤੇ ਭਟਕਦਾ ਹੈ) ।ਇਸ ਸੱਚੇ ਰਸਤੇ ਉੱਤੇ ਤੁਰਿਆਂ ਜਗਤ ਉਸ ਦੀ ਸੋਭਾ ਕਰਦਾ ਹੈ ।ਅਠਾਹਠ ਤੀਰਥਾਂ ਦਾ ਇਸ਼ਨਾਨ, ਸਾਰੇ ਪੁੰਨ ਕਰਮ, ਜੀਵਾਂ ਉੱਤੇ ਦਇਆ ਕਰਨੀ ਜੋ ਧਾਰਮਿਕ ਕੰਮ ਮੰਨੀ ਗਈ ਹੈ (ਇਹ ਸਭ ਕੁਝ ਸਿਮਰਨ ਦੇ ਵਿਚ ਹੀ ਆ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ) ।ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰ ਕੇ ਜਿਸ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਨੂੰ (ਸਿਮਰਨ ਦੀ ਦਾਤਿ) ਦੇਂਦਾ ਹੈ, ਉਹ ਮਨੁੱਖ (ਜ਼ਿੰਦਗੀ ਦੇ ਸਹੀ ਰਸਤੇ ਦੀ ਪਛਾਣ ਵਾਲਾ) ਸਿਆਣਾ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ ਹੇ ਨਾਨਕ ! (ਆਖ—) ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਪਿਆਰਾ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਮਿਲ ਪਿਆ ਹੈ, ਮੈਂ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਤੋਂ ਸਦਕੇ ਹਾਂ । ਮਾਘ ਮਹੀਨੇ ਵਿਚ ਸਿਰਫ਼ ਉਹੀ ਸੱੁਚੇ ਬੰਦੇ ਆਖੇ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ, ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਉੱਤੇ ਪੂਰਾ ਸਤਿਗੁਰੂ ਦਇਆਵਾਨ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ (ਤੇ ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਸਿਮਰਨ ਦੀ ਦਾਤਿ ਦੇਂਦਾ ਹੈ) ।੧੨।(ਸਿਆਲੀ ਰੁੱਤ ਦੀ ਕਰੜੀ ਸਰਦੀ ਪਿੱਛੋਂ ਬਹਾਰ ਫਿਰਨ ਤੇ ਫੱਗਣ ਦੇ ਮਹੀਨੇ ਵਿਚ ਲੋਕ ਹੋਲੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਰੰਗ-ਤਮਾਸ਼ਿਆਂ ਦੀ ਰਾਹੀਂ ਖ਼ੁਸ਼ੀਆਂ ਮਨਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ, ਪਰ) ਫੱਗਣ ਵਿਚ (ਉਹਨਾਂ ਜੀਵ-ਇਸਤ੍ਰੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਅੰਦਰ) ਆਤਮਕ ਆਨੰਦ ਪੈਦਾ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ, ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਦੇ ਹਿਰਦੇ ਵਿਚ ਸੱਜਣ-ਹਰੀ ਪਰਤੱਖ ਆ ਵੱਸਦਾ ਹੈ, ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਨਾਲ ਮਿਲਣ ਵਿਚ ਸਹਾਇਤਾ ਕਰਨ ਵਾਲੇ ਸੰਤ ਜਨ ਮਿਹਰ ਕਰ ਕੇ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਨਾਲ ਜੋੜ ਦੇਂਦੇ ਹਨ,ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੀ ਹਿਰਦਾ-ਸੇਜ ਸੁੰਦਰ ਬਣ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ, ਉਹਨਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਸਾਰੇ ਹੀ ਸੁੱਖ ਪ੍ਰਾਪਤ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ, ਫਿਰ ਦੁੱਖਾਂ ਲਈ (ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਹਿਰਦੇ ਵਿਚ) ਕਿਤੇ ਰਤਾ ਥਾਂ ਨਹੀਂ ਰਹਿ ਜਾਂਦੀ । ਉਹਨਾਂ ਵਡ-ਭਾਗਣ ਜੀਵ-ਇਸਤ੍ਰੀਆਂ ਦੀ ਮਨੋ-ਕਾਮਨਾ ਪੂਰੀ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ, ਉਹਨਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਹਰੀ-ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਖਸਮ ਮਿਲ ਪੈਂਦਾ ਹੈ,ਉਹ ਸਤ-ਸੰਗੀ ਸਹੇਲੀਆਂ ਨਾਲ ਰਲ ਕੇ ਗੋਵਿੰਦ ਦੀ ਸਿਫ਼ਤਿ-ਸਾਲਾਹ ਦੇ ਗੀਤ ਅਲਾਪ ਕੇ ਆਤਮਕ ਆਨੰਦ ਪੈਦਾ ਕਰਨ ਵਾਲੀ ਗੁਰਬਾਣੀ ਗਾਂਦੀਆਂ ਹਨ ।ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਵਰਗਾ ਕੋਈ ਹੋਰ, ਉਸ ਦੀ ਬਰਾਬਰੀ ਕਰ ਸਕਣ ਵਾਲਾ ਕੋਈ ਦੂਜਾ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਕਿਤੇ ਦਿੱਸਦਾ ਹੀ ਨਹੀਂ ।ਉਸ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਨੇ (ਉਹਨਾਂ ਸਤ-ਸੰਗੀਆਂ ਦਾ) ਲੋਕ ਪਰਲੋਕ ਸਵਾਰ ਦਿੱਤਾ ਹੈ, ਉਹਨਾਂ ਨੂੰ (ਆਪਣੇ ਚਰਨਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਲਿਵ-ਲੀਨਤਾ ਵਾਲੀ) ਐਸੀ ਥਾਂ ਬਖ਼ਸ਼ੀ ਹੈ ਜੋ ਕਦੇ ਡੋਲਦੀ ਹੀ ਨਹੀਂ । ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਨੇ ਸੰਸਾਰ-ਸਮੁੰਦਰ ਤੋਂ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਨੂੰ (ਹੱਥ ਦੇ ਕੇ) ਰੱਖ ਲਿਆ ਹੈ, ਜਨਮਾਂ ਦੇ ਗੇੜ ਵਿਚ ਮੁੜ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੀ ਦੌੜ ਭੱਜ ਨਹੀਂ ਹੁੰਦੀ ।ਹੇ ਨਾਨਕ ! (ਆਖ—) ਸਾਡੀ ਇਕ ਜੀਭ ਹੈ, ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੇ ਅਨੇਕਾਂ ਹੀ ਗੁਣ ਹਨ (ਅਸੀ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਬਿਆਨ ਕਰਨ ਜੋਗੇ ਨਹੀਂ ਹਾਂ, ਪਰ) ਜੇਹੜੇ ਜੀਵ ਉਸ ਦੀ ਚਰਨੀਂ ਪੈਂਦੇ ਹਨ (ਉਸ ਦਾ ਆਸਰਾ ਤੱਕਦੇ ਹਨ) ਉਹ (ਸੰਸਾਰ-ਸਮੁੰਦਰ ਤੋਂ) ਤਰ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ ।ਫੱਗਣ ਦੇ ਮਹੀਨੇ ਵਿਚ (ਹੋਲੀਆਂ ਆਦਿਕ ਵਿਚੋਂ ਅਨੰਦ ਲੱਭਣ ਦੇ ਥਾਂ) ਸਦਾ ਉਸ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੀ ਸਿਫ਼ਤਿ-ਸਾਲਾਹ ਕਰਨੀ ਚਾਹੀਦੀ ਹੈ, ਜਿਸ ਨੂੰ (ਆਪਣੀ ਵਡਿਆਈ ਕਰਾਣ ਦਾ) ਰਤਾ ਭਰ ਭੀ ਲਾਲਚ ਨਹੀਂ ਹੈ (ਇਸ ਵਿਚ ਸਾਡਾ ਹੀ ਭਲਾ ਹੈ) ।੧੩ਜਿਸ ਜਿਸ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਨੇ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਜਪਿਆ ਹੈ, ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਸਾਰੇ ਕਾਰਜ ਸਫਲ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ,ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਨੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਨੂੰ ਪੂਰੇ ਗੁਰੂ ਨੂੰ ਆਰਾਧਿਆ ਹੈ, ਉਹ ਸਦਾ-ਥਿਰ ਰਹਿਣ ਵਾਲੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੀ ਹਜ਼ੂਰੀ ਵਿਚ ਸੁਰਖ਼ਰੂ ਹੁੰਦੇ ਹਨ ।ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੇ ਚਰਨ ਹੀ ਸਾਰੇ ਸੁੱਖਾਂ ਦਾ ਖ਼ਜ਼ਾਨਾ ਹਨ, (ਜਿਹੜੇ ਜੀਵ ਚਰਨੀਂ ਲੱਗਦੇ ਹਨ, ਉਹ) ਔਖੇ ਸੰਸਾਰ-ਸਮੁੰਦਰ ਵਿਚੋਂ (ਸਹੀ-ਸਲਾਮਤ) ਪਾਰ ਲੰਘ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ,ਉਹਨਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦਾ ਪਿਆਰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੀ ਭਗਤੀ ਪ੍ਰਾਪਤ ਹੁੰਦੀ ਹੈ, ਮਾਇਆ ਦੀ ਤ੍ਰਿਸ਼ਨਾ-ਅੱਗ ਵਿਚ ਉਹ ਨਹੀਂ ਸੜਦੇ ।ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਵਿਅਰਥ ਝੂਠੇ ਲਾਲਚ ਖ਼ਤਮ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ, ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਮਨ ਦੀ ਭਟਕਣਾ ਦੂਰ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ,ਉਹ ਮੁਕੰਮਲ ਤੌਰ ਤੇ ਸਦਾ-ਥਿਰ ਹਰੀ ਵਿਚ ਟਿਕੇ ਰਹਿੰਦੇ ਹਨ, ਉਹ ਆਪਣੇ ਮਨ ਵਿਚ ਇਕੋ ਪਰਮ ਜੋਤਿ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਨੂੰ ਵਸਾ ਕੇ ਸਦਾ ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਸਿਮਰਦੇ ਹਨ ।ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਉੱਤੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਮਿਹਰ ਦੀ ਨਜ਼ਰ ਕਰਦਾ ਹੈ (ਆਪਣੇ ਨਾਮ ਦੀ ਦਾਤਿ ਦੇਂਦਾ ਹੈ) ਉਹਨਾਂ ਵਾਸਤੇ ਸਾਰੇ ਮਹੀਨੇ ਸਾਰੇ ਦਿਹਾੜੇ ਸਾਰੇ ਹੀ ਮੁਹੂਰਤ ਸੁਲੱਖਣੇ ਹਨ (ਸੰਗ੍ਰਾਂਦ ਆਦਿਕ ਦੀ ਪਵਿਤ੍ਰਤਾ ਦੇ ਭਰਮ-ਭੁਲੇਖੇ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਨਹੀਂ ਪੈਂਦੇ) । ਹੇ ਹਰੀ ! (ਮੇਰੇ ਉੱਤੇ) ਮਿਹਰ ਕਰ, ਮੈਂ ਨਾਨਕ (ਤੇਰੇ ਦਰ ਤੋਂ ਤੇਰੇ) ਦੀਦਾਰ ਦੀ ਦਾਤਿ ਮੰਗਦਾ ਹਾਂ ।੧੪।\\""},{"question":"文章からキーワードを選び、その解釈を述べなさい。 インフルエンザは、いつも12月から3月の寒いときに広がります。国立感染症研究所によると、今年は5月下旬になっても、うつる人が多くなっています。この季節にインフルエンザが広がったことは、10年ぐらいありませんでした。今年はほかのウイルスも広がっています。いつもは夏から秋に増える「RSウイルス感染症」や、夏に多い「ヘルパンギーナ」がうつった人も増えています。専門家は「新型コロナウイルスが広がってから、ほかの病気のウイルスはあまり広がりませんでした。このため、ウイルスから体を守る免疫が少なくなって、インフルエンザなどがうつる人が増えていると思います。今年5月にマスクなどの厳しいルールがなくなって、ウイルスが広がりやすくなっていると考えています」と話しています。専門家は、せきや熱などがあったら、静かに休んで、周りの人にうつさないように気をつけてほしいと言っています。","answer":"この文章に含まれるキーワードとその解釈は以下です。- インフルエンザ: 1）のどや気管などが、ウイルスによってただれる病気。かぜに似ているが、高い熱が出て、うつりやすい。流行性感冒。流感。- 広がり: 1）広くなる。2）広々と見わたせる。3）行きわたる。4）大きくなる。- 下旬: 1）月の二十一日から終わりまでの、約十日間。- 広がっ: 1）日本脳炎やインフルエンザなどの病気を起こす、ふつうの顕微鏡では見えないような、非常に小さな生物。ビールス。- ウイルス: 1）害を受けないように、防ぐ。2）決めたとおりにする。- 守る: 1）病気にかかりにくくしている体のはたらき。前に一度その病気にかかったり、予防接種を受けたりするとできる。2）それに慣れてしまって、気にしなくなること。- 免疫: 1）お面。仮面。2）ほこりなどを吸わないように、口や鼻をおおう布。3）ガスなどを吸わないように、消防士などが顔につけるお面。防毒面。4）野球・ソフトボールで、キャッチャーや球審が顔につけるお面。5）顔。顔だち。- マスク: 1）規則。決まり。- ルール: 1）のどや気管が刺激されて、急に激しく出る強い息。- せき: 1）場所を変える。2）ものごとを進める。3）感染させる。"},{"question":"Cé hé Pío Baroja? ","answer":"Scríbhneoir Spáinnise ó Thír na mBascach a bhí i bPío Baroja y Nessi, a rugadh i San Sebastián (Donostia) ar an 28 Nollaig 1872 agus a fuair bás i Maidrid ar an 30 Deireadh Fómhair 1956. Bascach a bhí ann féin, ach ní raibh mórán measa aige ar theanga a cheantair dhúchais, cé go raibh téamaí Bascacha agus radharcra na Tíre Bascaí le haithint ina lán scríbhinní a tháinig óna pheann.Rinne sé staidéar le bheith ina dhochtúir, ach níor chleacht sé an cheird seo riamh - go bunúsach, ní raibh ann ach amhábhar don úrscéal El árbol de la ciencia (\\"Crann an Eolais\\"). Is é saol na mac léinn atá faoi chaibidil ag Baroja sa leabhar seo. Chaith sé seal i mbun bhácús a mhuintire, rud atá le haithint i saothair eile leis, ar nós La Busca (\\"An Cuardach\\")."},{"question":"Које биљке које помажу при јачању имунитета?","answer":"Биљке које помажу при јачању имунитета• Шипурак• Зова• Ехинацеа• Жалфија• Сремуш1-2 шоље дневно било које биљке могу да ојачају имунитет. Основне биљке које имају дејство да јачају имунитет, јер имају антимикробно дејство. Биљка може деловати против микроорганизама (вируси, бактерије, гљивице, плесан)."},{"question":"એલોન રીવ કસ્તુરી કોણ છે?","answer":"એલોન રીવ મસ્ક એક ઉદ્યોગપતિ અને રોકાણકાર છે.મસ્ક સ્પેસએક્સના સ્થાપક, અધ્યક્ષ, સીઈઓ અને ચીફ ટેકનોલોજી અધિકારી છે;એન્જલ રોકાણકાર, સીઈઓ, પ્રોડક્ટ આર્કિટેક્ટ અને ટેસ્લાના ભૂતપૂર્વ અધ્યક્ષ, ઇન્ક .;માલિક, અધ્યક્ષ અને એક્સ કોર્પના સીટીઓ;કંટાળાજનક કંપની અને ઝાઇના સ્થાપક;ન્યુરલિંક અને ઓપનએઆઈના સહ-સ્થાપક;અને મસ્ક ફાઉન્ડેશનના પ્રમુખ.બ્લૂમબર્ગ અબજોપતિ અનુક્રમણિકા અનુસાર, ડિસેમ્બર 2023 સુધીમાં 222 અબજ ડોલરની અંદાજિત ચોખ્ખી કિંમત અને ફોર્બ્સના જણાવ્યા અનુસાર મુખ્યત્વે ટેસ્લા અને સ્પેસએક્સમાં તેના માલિકીના હોડમાંથી, તે વિશ્વના સૌથી ધનિક વ્યક્તિ છે.શ્રીમંત દક્ષિણ આફ્રિકન મસ્ક પરિવારના સભ્ય, એલોન મસ્કનો જન્મ પ્રેટોરિયામાં થયો હતો અને 18 વર્ષની ઉંમરે કેનેડા સ્થળાંતર કરતા પહેલા પ્રેટોરિયા યુનિવર્સિટીમાં સંક્ષિપ્તમાં ભાગ લીધો હતો, તેની કેનેડિયન જન્મેલી માતા દ્વારા નાગરિકત્વ પ્રાપ્ત કર્યું હતું.બે વર્ષ પછી, તેણે કેનેડામાં કિંગ્સ્ટન ખાતેની ક્વીન્સ યુનિવર્સિટીમાં મેટ્રિક કર્યો.પાછળથી કસ્તુરી યુનિવર્સિટી ઓફ પેન્સિલવેનિયામાં સ્થાનાંતરિત થઈ, અને ત્યાં અર્થશાસ્ત્ર અને ભૌતિકશાસ્ત્રમાં સ્નાતકની ડિગ્રી પ્રાપ્ત કરી.તેઓ 1995 માં સ્ટેનફોર્ડ યુનિવર્સિટીમાં ભાગ લેવા કેલિફોર્નિયા ગયા.જો કે, મસ્ક બે દિવસ પછી બહાર નીકળી ગયો અને તેના ભાઈ કિમ્બલ સાથે, city નલાઇન સિટી ગાઇડ સ Software ફ્ટવેર કંપની ઝિપ 2 ની સહ-સ્થાપના કરી.સ્ટાર્ટઅપ કોમ્પાક દ્વારા 1999 માં 307 મિલિયન ડોલરમાં હસ્તગત કરવામાં આવી હતી, અને તે જ વર્ષે મસ્કના સહ-સ્થાપના X.com, એક સીધી બેંક, તેણે બનાવેલા 12 મિલિયન ડોલર સાથે.X.com પેપાલની રચના માટે 2000 માં મૂંઝવણમાં ભળી ગયો.\\""},{"question":"Si quhet monedha e Shqipërisë?","answer":"Monedha e Shqipërisë quhet lek."},{"question":"Tôi đã tiêm mũi một vaccine Covid-19 (2/10/2021) bị sốc phản vệ độ 3 và hiện tại tôi đang có bầu được 6 tháng, tâm lý bất an nên tôi không dám tiêm các mũi vắc xin tiếp theo. Xin bác sĩ tư vấn trường hợp của tôi có thể truyền được kháng thể này không ạ?","answer":"Nguyên tắc là khi bị sốc phản vệ với vaccine Covid-19 chúng ta có thể chuyển qua vaccine khác. Ví dụ, nếu quý khách sốc phản vệ với vaccine Pifzer, chúng ta có thể chuyển qua vaccine AstraZeneca hoặc vaccine của Trung Quốc.Quý khách hỏi có tiêm được kháng thể đơn dòng không khi đang mang thai 6 tháng, thì hiện tại trong nghiên cứu về kháng thể đơn dòng không có đối tượng bệnh nhân đang có thai. Do đó, chỉ khi nào thuốc đã nghiên cứu trên nhóm đối tượng phụ nữ đang mang thai thì nhóm đối tượng này mới có thể tiêm được. Do đó, tôi nghĩ quý khách ở thời điểm này không nên tiêm và nên khám ở bệnh viện và xin tiêm loại vaccine Covid-19 dành cho phụ nữ đang mang thai."},{"question":"救生艇有廁所嗎？","answer":"通常情況下，救生艇沒有廁所設施。"},{"question":"Kodi magawo atatu a ndime yachitsanzo ndi ati?","answer":"Zigawo za Ndime. Ndime imakhala ndi chiganizo cha mutu, mfundo zomwe zikukulirakulira, ndi chiganizo chomaliza. Ndikofunika kukulitsa ndikukambirana mutu wa ndime yanu. Ngati ndime yanu ili ndi ziganizo 2-3 zokha, pali mwayi woti simunapange mokwanira."},{"question":"Inona no atao hoe riba malagasy?","answer":"Ny riba dia midika ho: haren-tsaina, fomba amam-panao, vakomanitra (Hanitra nentim-drazana). Tany am-boalohany, dia fomba amam-pahendrena Malagasy no niantsoana azy, avy eo izy niova hoe fomba amam-panao, fa taty aoriana no niovany hoe Riba, fa ny dinihana ao anatiny dia ny tontolom-piainana Malagasy."},{"question":"ما هي المصادر الرئيسية لتلوث الهواء؟ ","answer":"تلوث الهواء يمكن أن ينشأ من مصادر متنوعة، وتتنوع هذه المصادر بحسب الموقع الجغرافي والنشاطات الاقتصادية والصناعية. إليك بعض المصادر الرئيسية لتلوث الهواء:-المركبات الآلية: انبعاثات السيارات والشاحنات ووسائل النقل الأخرى تسهم في تلوث الهواء بملوثات مثل غازات العادم والجسيمات الدقيقة.-الصناعة: المصانع والمرافق الصناعية تطلق غازات وجسيمات تلوث الهواء، مثل ثاني أكسيد الكبريت وثاني أكسيد النيتروجين والجسيمات العضوية.-الطاقة: محطات توليد الكهرباء التي تعتمد على الوقود الأحفوري مثل الفحم والنفط والغاز تسهم في إطلاق العديد من الملوثات الهوائية.-الزراعة: استخدام المبيدات الكيميائية والأسمدة في الزراعة يمكن أن يسهم في إطلاق ملوثات هوائية.-حرائق الغابات: الحرائق الكبيرة في الغابات تسبب في إطلاق غازات وجسيمات ملوثة إلى الهواء.-النفايات: حرق النفايات، خاصة إذا كانت تحتوي على مواد كيميائية، يمكن أن يؤدي إلى إطلاق ملوثات.-التدفئة والتبريد: استخدام أنظمة التدفئة والتبريد التي تعتمد على الوقود الأحفوري يمكن أن يسهم في إطلاق ملوثات هوائية.تحديد مصادر التلوث وتحسين التكنولوجيا وتبني ممارسات صديقة للبيئة هي أمور مهمة للحد من تأثيرات تلوث الهواء."},{"question":"السؤال: ما نوع جمع الصلاة التي يجوز للمسلمين وقت المطر؟","answer":"الجواب: جمع التقديم فقط."},{"question":"Wọn tun ti ji awọn arinrin-ajo meji gbe l’Akoko","answer":"Iṣẹlẹ ijinigbe to n waye lagbegbe Akoko tun gbọna mi-in yọ pẹlu bi wọn tun ṣe ji obinrin oniṣowo kan, Agnes Akọgun, ati awakọ rẹ, Okio, gbe lalẹ ọjọ Isẹgun, Tusidee, ọsẹ ta a wa yii. Obinrin oniṣowo ọhun ati awakọ rẹ la gbọ pe wọn ji gbe laarin ilu Ugbe, nijọba ibilẹ Ariwa Ila-Oorun Akoko, si Uba-Ọka nijọba ibilẹ Guusu Iwọ-Oorun Akoko. Awọn ọja aṣọ ti obinrin naa n ta ni wọn lo n ko lọ si Uba-Ọka, lasiko ti awọn ajinigbe ọhun da wọn lọna, ti wọn si ko wọn wọnu igbo lọ. Ni kete tawọn eeyan ti gbọ nipa iṣẹlẹ yii ni wọn lawọn ọdẹ, awọn fijilante atawọn ọlọpaa Ọka Akoko ti n wa gbogbo inu aginju to wa lagbegbe naa boya wọn le ri wọn gba pada. Awọn ajinigbe ọhun la gbọ pe wọn ko ti i kan si ẹnikẹni ninu awọn ẹbi awọn ti wọn ji gbe naa ni gbogbo asiko ta a fi n ko iroyin yii jọ lọwọ."},{"question":"Que atriz fez a narração em Gossip Girl?","answer":"A atriz Kristen Bell foi narradora da série durante todas as seis temporada"},{"question":"अध्ययन बानीमा ढिलाइ हटाउन प्रभावकारी तरिकाहरू के हुन्?","answer":"कार्यहरूलाई स-साना टुक्राहरूमा विभाजन गर्ने, प्राप्त गर्न सकिने लक्ष्यहरू सेट गर्ने, समय-व्यवस्थापन प्रविधिहरू प्रयोग गर्ने, र आत्म-अनुशासन अभ्यास अध्ययनमा ढिलाइको सामना गर्न प्रभावकारी हुन्छ।"},{"question":"Takip eden paragrafa bir devam metni yaz:  İklim değişikliğinin birçok olumsuz etkisi vardır. Bunlar arasında artan sıcaklık, deniz seviyelerinin yükselmesi, aşırı hava olayları (kasırgalar, kuraklık, sel gibi), su ","answer":"kaynaklarının azalması, denizlerin asitlenmesi ve biyolojik çeşitlilik kaybı gibi etkiler bulunur. Bu değişiklikler, ekosistemleri, ekonomileri ve toplumları olumsuz etkileyebilir."},{"question":"පහත කවිය කුමන වර්ගයේ කවියක්ද?කැලේ ගිහින් ඉනි කැපුවා කැත්ත        දනීවෙලේ ගිහින් වැට බැන්දා නියර         දනීපැලේ ගිහන් පැල් රැක්කා පැදුර          දනීමෙදා යලේ වී නැතුවා දෙයියෝ          දනී","answer":"මෙම කවිය පැ ල් කවියකි."},{"question":"Ẹ wo wọn o, Mọsuru atawọn ẹgbẹ ẹ ti wọn dumbu iyaale ile ati ọlọkada bii ẹran l’Ado-Odo","answer":"Awọn ọkunrin marun-un yii leeyan ko ba maa pe ni apani-ma-yọda, nitori ka ni ki i ṣe pe wọn fẹnu ara wọn jẹwọ pe awọn lawọn dumbu iyawo oniyawo torukọ ẹ n jẹ Memunat Akinde ati ọlọkada kan torukọ tiẹ n jẹ Ibikunle Ajọsẹ ni, ko sẹni to yoo mọ pe awọn ni wọn ṣiṣẹ ibi naa lọjọ kin-in-ni, oṣu kẹwaa, ọdun 2020, ti wọn deede dawati.Jẹẹjẹ ni Memunat to n ta ẹja fẹẹ lọọ ra ọja rẹ lọja Idoleyin, l’Ado-Odo, Ibikunle Ajọsẹ ni ọlọkada to gbe e lọjọ naa, afi bo ṣe jẹ alọ awọn mejeeji lawọn ẹbi wọn ri, ti wọn ko ri abọ wọn.Ọkọ Memuna lo lọọ fi to wọn léti lẹka olu ileeṣẹ ọlọpaa to wa l’Ado -Odò pe oun ko ri iyawo oun to lọ sójà lati ọjọ akọkọ ninu oṣu kẹwaa mọ, bawọn ọlọpaa ṣe bẹrẹ iṣẹ abẹnu ti wọn yoo fi ri obinrin ẹni ọdun marundinlaaadọta (45) naa niyẹn pẹlu ọlọkada ti wọn jọ dawati.Ọkan ninu awọn marun-un yii lọwọ kọkọ ba, Okediran Mọnsuru lo n jẹ, Badagry ni wọn ti ri i mu gẹgẹ bi DSP Abimbọla Oyeyẹmi ti i ṣe Alukoro ọlọpaa ipinlẹ Ogun ṣe wi.Monsuru ti wọn ri mu lo ṣokunfa bi ọwọ ṣe ba Ajaoba Monday, Akewusola Wajud ati Nupo Pona.Àwọn mẹrẹẹrin jẹwọ pe ọkunrin ogbologboo ajagungbalẹ kan ti wọn n pe ni Lebo lawọn n ṣiṣẹ fun.Wọn ni awọn lawọn da Memuna ati Ibikunle lọna labule Abisoye, awọn gbe wọn wọnu ile akọku kan ninu igbo, awọn so wọn lọwọ atẹsẹ, awọn si pe Lebo lori foonu pe ọwọ awọn ti ba ẹran meji o.Wọn ni nigba ti Lebo de, o paṣẹ pe kawọn dumbu awọn eeyan meji yii.Nigba naa ni Okediran Mọnsuru, Ajaoba Monday ati  Akewuṣọla Wajud di awọn ti wọn fẹẹ pa naa mu,  Nupo Pona si fi ada mimu kan dumbu wọn bii ẹran!Wọn ni bawọn ṣe pa wọn tan lawọn pe afurasi karun-un, iyẹn Dasu Sunday, to jẹ babalawo.Bi Sunday ṣe de ni gbogbo wọn kun ẹran ara Memuna ati Ibikunle, wọn ṣa wọn si wẹwẹ, wọn si ko ẹran awọn eeyan tawọn araale wọn n wa naa sinu apo, Sunday Babalawo si gbe e lọ sibi ti yoo ti sọ wọn di ètùtù oogun owo.Ojubọ ti Sunday ti n ṣoro ẹ ni awọn ọlọpaa ti pada ri ori Memuna, wọn si ni gbogbo awọn to ṣiṣẹ yii ti wa latimọle, afi Lebo, olori wọn nìkan, lọwọ ko ti i ba, ti wọn n wa a gidigidi.Awọn to wa latimọle yii ko ni i pẹẹ de kootu fun ijẹjọ, gẹgẹ bi CP Edward Awolọwọ Ajogun ti paṣẹ."},{"question":"కింది ప్రశ్నకు సమాధానం ఇవ్వండిప్లాస్మాపొర జీవ రసాయనిక నిర్మాణాన్ని తెలపండి. పొర లోపల లిపిడ్ అణువుల అమరిక ఎలా ఉంటుంది?","answer":"1. ప్లాస్మాపొర (కణత్వచం) ప్రోటీన్లు మరియు కార్బోహైడ్రేట్లతో నిర్మితమై ఉంటుంది.2. కణత్వచం రెండు వరుసల లిపిడ్ అణువులతో ఏర్పడి ఉంటుంది.3. పొర లోపల లిపిడ్ అణువులు ధృవ (జలాకర్షక) శీర్షాలు వెలుపలి వైపునకు మరియు అధ్రువ (జలవికర్షక)తోక లోపలివైపుకు ఉంటాయి.4. ఈ అమరిక వలన అధృవ సంతృప్త హైడ్రోకార్బన్ తోకలు. జల వాతావరణం నుంచి రక్షింపబడతాయి.5. కణత్వచం యొక్క ప్లూయిడ్ మొజాయిక్ నమూనాను సింగర్ మరియు నికల్సన్లు ప్రతిపాదించారు.6. ఇది స్వర్వత్రా ఆమోదించబడిన నమూనా. దీని ప్రకారం అర్ధ ద్రవ స్థితిలో ఉన్న లిపిడ్ పొర, ప్రొటీన్ అణువుల పార్శ్వ కదలికలకు వీలు కలిగిస్తుంది."},{"question":"السؤال: ما هو أوّل مذهبٍ ديني ظهر في الإسلام؟","answer":"الجواب: المذهب الحنفي."},{"question":"Misy karazany firy ny asa?","answer":"Misy roa ny karazan'asa izay:- ny asa mampiasa herim-batana. - ny asa mampiasa herin-tsaina."},{"question":"Đọc đoạn văn sau và đưa ra một tiêu đề phụ hợp với nội dung: Hiện chưa rõ các mảnh vỡ của quả tên lửa đẩy nói trên đi theo quỹ đạo nào, Bộ Chỉ huy Không gian Mỹ thông báo ngày 30/7 trên Twitter, theo Bloomberg. Trong khi đó, cơ quan hàng không vũ trụ Trung Quốc ngày 31/7 thông báo các mảnh vỡ tên lửa rơi xuống vùng biển tại Tây Nam Philippines và \\"đại đa số\\" mảnh vụn đã cháy hết trong quá trình trở lại Trái Đất. Thông báo từ phía Trung Quốc bị một quan chức Mỹ chỉ trích. \\"Trung Quốc đã không chia sẻ thông tin quỹ đạo chi tiết trong lúc tên lửa Trường Chinh 5B rơi trở lại Trái Đất\\", Tổng giám đốc NASA Bill Nelson nói trong một tuyên bố. \\"Mọi quốc gia du hành vũ trụ cần tuân thủ cách thực hành tốt nhất và làm tròn bổn phận chia sẻ loại thông tin này từ sớm để tạo điều kiện cho việc dự đoán rủi ro va chạm có thể xảy ra, đặc biệt là đối với thiết bị đẩy có trọng tải nặng như Trường Chinh 5B\\", ông Nelson nói. Trước đó, các nhà phân tích cho biết phần thân tên lửa sẽ cháy hết khi xuyên qua không khí rơi trở lại mặt đất. Nhưng vì kích cỡ lớn, phần thân này vẫn sẽ để lại nhiều mảnh nhỏ với diện tích rơi bao phủ một vùng dài khoảng 2.000 km, rộng 70 km, theo Reuters. Tên lửa Trường Chinh 5B được phóng đi hôm 24/7 để đưa module phòng thí nghiệm Vấn Thiên lên trạm vũ trụ mới mà Trung Quốc đang xây dựng trên quỹ đạo. Đây là lần thứ 3 loại tên lửa mạnh nhất của Trung Quốc được sử dụng từ sau lần phóng đầu tiên vào năm 2020. Các mảnh vụn của một tên lửa Trường Chinh 5B từng rơi xuống Bờ Biển Ngà vào năm 2020, gây thiệt hại cho một số tòa nhà ở nước này nhưng không gây ra thương tích.","answer":"Mảnh vỡ tên lửa Trung Quốc rơi xuống Ấn Độ Dương"},{"question":"寿司屋ではお茶のこと、すごろくではゴールを意味する言葉といえば何？","answer":"あがりです。"},{"question":"Ibinzana 1: Wazalelwa waza wakhulela eDallas, wayengunyana kaMargot (owazalelwa eBirmingham) noRoss Perot. Ibinzana 2: Wazalelwa waza wakhulela eDallas, wayengunyana kaRoss Perot (owazalelwa eBirmingham) noMargot. Umbuzo: Ngaba isivakalisi 1 nesivakalisi 2 zithetha into enye? Ewe okanye Hayi?","answer":"Hayi"},{"question":"Büyük İskender nereleri fethetti?","answer":"Büyük İskender, Makedonya Kralı II. Philip'in oğlu olarak Makedonya'da doğmuş ve Makedonya İmparatorluğu'nun hükümdarı olarak tanınmıştır. Büyük İskender, kısa sürede gerçekleştirdiği askeri kampanyalar ve fetihlerle tarihte önemli bir figür haline gelmiştir. İşte Büyük İskender'in fethettiği bazı önemli bölgeler:1. Anadolu (M.Ö. 334-333): Büyük İskender, Pers İmparatorluğu'nun batı sınırlarına yönelik ilk seferine Anadolu üzerinden başlamıştır. Granikos Nehri Muharebesi ve İssos Muharebesi'nde Pers kralı III. Darius'u mağlup ederek Anadolu'nun birçok bölgesini ele geçirmiştir.2. Mısır (M.Ö. 332): İskender, Mısır'ı fethederek kent merkezi İskenderiye'yi kurdu. Mısır'ı fethi, kendisine \\"Pharao\\" (firavun) unvanını kazandırmıştır.3. Pers İmparatorluğu (M.Ö. 331-330): Büyük İskender, Gaugamela Muharebesi'nde Pers Kralı III. Darius'u mağlup ederek Pers İmparatorluğu'nun başkenti olan Babil'i ele geçirdi. Ardından Pers İmparatorluğu'nun büyük bir bölümünü kontrolü altına aldı.4. Orta Doğu (M.Ö. 330): İskender, Pers İmparatorluğu'nun ardından Mezopotamya, Fenike ve Filistin gibi bölgeleri fethetti.5. Afganistan ve Hindistan (M.Ö. 327-326): İskender, İndus Vadisi'ne kadar ilerleyerek Afganistan ve Hindistan'ı fethetti. Bu dönemde, savaşlar ve yerel direnişlere rağmen, İskender'in orduları çok uzaklara ulaştı.Büyük İskender'in fetihleri, Makedonya İmparatorluğu'nun sınırlarını genişletti ve kısa ömrüne rağmen tarih boyunca büyük bir askeri lider ve imparator olarak hatırlanmasını sağladı. Ancak İskender'in ölümünden sonra, imparatorluğu generalleri arasında bölündü ve Helenistik Dönem başladı."},{"question":"Berikan jawapan untuk teka-teki berikut: Golongan orang Itali yang kaya memandu kenderaan mewah ini.","answer":"Jawapannya ialah Maserati"},{"question":"የጣልያን ፋሺስት ጦር ከኢትዮጵያ ተሸንፎ ከወጣ በኋላ ቀዳማዊ ኃይለ ሥላሴ ወደ ሀገራቸው ከስደት የተመለሱት መቼ ነበር?","answer":" በ፲፱፻፴፫ ዓ.ም. ።"},{"question":"නව ගෝකණ්ණ විහාරය අද පිහිටා ඇත්තේ කොහේද?","answer":"නව ගෝකණ්ණ විහාරය ෆෙඩ්රික් කොටුව තුළ, ලක්ෂ්‍යයට උතුරින් සහ කොටුවේ දොරටුවට ආසන්නව පිහිටා ඇත. එය පූජනීය ස්ථානයක් ලෙස ක්‍රියා කරන අතර විවිධ කාලවලදී මතු වූ බෞද්ධ කෞතුක වස්තු කිහිපයක් එහිදී දැකගත හැකිය."},{"question":"Pilih jawapan yang betul untuk soalan berikut: Apakah maksud bahaya semasa memandu di jalan raya?A. Tanda isyarat lalu lintas yang mencukupi di persimpangan jalanB. Usia kenderaan yang tuaC. Halangan di jalan seperti keadaan jalan yang tidak sempurna. ","answer":"Jawapannya ialah C. Halangan di jalan seperti keadaan jalan yang tidak sempurna. "},{"question":"የሶቅራጥስ አስተሳሰቦች ከሞላ ጎደል ለቀሪው ትውልድ ያስተላለፈው ማን ይባላል?","answer":"ፕላቶ"},{"question":"Content: ਅਦਾਲਤ ਨੇ ਇਹ ਹੁਕਮ ਮਨੁੱਖੀ ਹੱਕਾਂ ਦੀ ਉਲੰਘਣਾ ਨੂੰ ਰੋਕਣ ਵਾਸਤੇ ਦਿੱਤਾ ਹੈ। ਖ਼ਬਰ ਏਜੰਸੀ ਪੀਟੀਆਈ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਕੋਰਟ ਨੇ ਕੈਮਰੇ ਪੁਲਿਸ ਸਟੇਸ਼ਨ ਨੇ ਹਰ ਹਿੱਸੇ ਯਾਨੀ, ਥਾਣੇ ਦੇ ਐਂਟਰੀ ਅਤੇ ਐਗਜਿਟ ਪੁਆਇੰਟਸ, ਲਾਕ ਅਪ, ਕੋਰੀਡੋਰ, ਲਾਬੀ, ਰਿਸੈਪਸ਼ਨ ਏਰੀਆ, ਸਬ ਇੰਸਪੈਕਟਰ ਅਤੇ ਇੰਸਪੈਕਟਰ ਦੇ ਕਮਰੇ, ਵਾਸ਼ਰੂਮ ਦੇ ਬਾਹਰ ਲਗਾਏ ਜਾਣੇ ਚਾਹੀਦੇ ਹਨ। ਇਹ ਰਿਕਾਰਡਿੰਗ 18 ਮਹੀਨਿਆਂ ਲਈ ਰੱਖਣੀ ਪਏਗੀ।ਅਦਾਲਤ ਨੇ ਕਿਹਾ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਕੈਮਰੇ ਦੇ ਨਾਲ-ਨਾਲ ਆਡੀਓ ਰਿਕਾਰਡਿੰਗ ਤੇ ਨਾਈਟ ਵਿਜ਼ਨ ਵੀ ਲਗਾਇਆ ਜਾਣਾ ਚਾਹੀਦਾ ਹੈ।ਇਸ ਦੇ ਨਾਲ ਹੀ ਸੁਪਰੀਮ ਕੋਰਟ ਨੇ ਕੇਂਦਰ ਨੂੰ ਸੀਬੀਆਈ (CBI), ਐਨਆਈਏ (NIA), ਇਨਫੋਰਸਮੈਂਟ ਡਾਇਰੈਕਟੋਰੇਟ (ED) ਦੇ ਦਫ਼ਤਰਾਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਵੀ ਆਡੀਓ ਰਿਕਾਰਡਿੰਗਜ਼ ਦੇ ਨਾਲ-ਨਾਲ ਸੀਸੀਟੀਵੀ ਕੈਮਰੇ ਵੀ ਲਗਾਏ ਜਾਣ ਦੇ ਨਿਰਦੇਸ਼ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਹਨ। ਇਹ ਉਹ ਏਜੰਸੀਆਂ ਹਨ ਜੋ ਜਾਂਚ ਕਰਦੀਆਂ ਹਨ ਅਤੇ ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਕੋਲ ਗ੍ਰਿਫ਼ਤਾਰ ਕਰਨ ਦੀ ਪਾਵਰ ਹੈ। ਜਸਟਿਸ ਰੋਹਿਂਟਨ ਐੱਫ. ਨਰੀਮਨ, ਜਸਟਿਸ ਕੇ ਐਮ ਜੋਸਫ਼ ਅਤੇ ਜਸਟਿਸ ਅਨਿਰੁਧ ਬੋਸ ਦੀ ਬੈਂਚ ਨੇ ਇਹ ਹੁਕਮ ਜਾਰੀ ਕੀਤੇ ਹਨ।ਅਦਾਲਤ ਨੇ ਕਿਹਾ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਇਹ ਕੇਂਦਰ ਅਤੇ ਰਾਜ ਸਰਕਾਰਾਂ ਲਈ ਜ਼ਰੂਰੀ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਅਜਿਹੇ ਸੀਸੀਟੀਵੀ ਖਰੀਦੇ ਜਾਣ ਅਤੇ ਵੱਧ ਤੋਂ ਵੱਧ ਸਮੇਂ ਲਈ ਰਿਕਾਰਡਿੰਗ ਸੁਰੱਖਿਅਤ ਰੱਖੀ ਜਾਵੇ।ਇਸ ਤੋਂ ਇਲਾਵਾ ਸੁਪਰੀਮ ਕੋਰਟ ਨੇ ਨਾਰਕੋਟਿਕਸ ਕੰਟਰੋਲ ਬਿਊਰੋ (NCB), ਡਾਇਰੈਕਟੋਰੇਟ ਆਫ ਰੈਵੇਨਿਊ ਇੰਟੈਲੀਜੈਂਸ (DRI) ਅਤੇ ਸੀਰਿਅਸ ਫ੍ਰੋਡ ਇਨਵੈਸਟੀਗੇਸ਼ਨ ਆਫ਼ਿਸ (SFIO) ਦੇ ਦਫ਼ਤਰਾਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਵੀ ਆਡੀਓ ਰਿਕਾਰਡਿੰਗਜ਼ ਵਾਲੇ ਸੀਸੀਟੀਵੀ ਕੈਮਰੇ ਲਗਾਉਣ ਦੇ ਆਦੇਸ਼ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਹਨ। ਬੈਂਚ ਨੇ ਕਿਹਾ ਕਿ ਜਿਵੇਂ ਕਿ ਇਹ ਏਜੰਸੀਆਂ ਜ਼ਿਆਦਾਤਰ ਇੰਟੈਰੋਗੇਸ਼ਨ ਆਪਣੇ ਦਫ਼ਤਰਾਂ 'ਚ ਹੀ ਕਰਦੀਆਂ ਹਨ, ਇਸ ਲਈ ਜ਼ਰੂਰੀ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਜਿਥੇ ਅਜਿਹੀ ਇੰਟੈਰੋਗੇਸ਼ਨ ਹੁੰਦੀ ਹੈ ਜਾਂ ਜਿਥੇ ਇਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਮੁਲਜ਼ਮਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਰੱਖਿਆ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ, ਉਥੇ ਸੀਸੀਟੀਵੀ ਜ਼ਰੂਰ ਰੱਖੇ ਜਾਣ।","answer":"ਸੁਪਰੀਮ ਕੋਰਟ ਨੇ ਇੱਕ ਅਹਿਮ ਆਦੇਸ਼ ਜਾਰੀ ਕਰਦਿਆਂ ਸਾਰੇ ਸੂਬਿਆਂ ਤੇ ਕੇਂਦਰ-ਸ਼ਾਸਿਤ ਪ੍ਰਦੇਸ਼ਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਆਪਣੇ ਸਾਰੇ ਪੁਲਿਸ ਸਟੇਸ਼ਨਾਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਹਰ ਪਾਸੇ ਸੀਸੀਟੀਵੀ ਕੈਮਰੇ ਲਗਾਉਣ ਨੂੰ ਕਿਹਾ ਹੈ।"},{"question":"దేశభక్తుల వల్ల దేశ ప్రజలకు కలిగే ప్రయోజనాలు వ్యాసంగా రాయండి.","answer":"దేశమును ప్రేమించుమన్నా – మంచి అన్నది పెంచమన్నాసొంతలాభం కొంత మానుక – పొరుగువారికి తోడుపడవోయ్.ఇది దేశభక్తుని లక్షణం. తాను, తన కుటుంబం బాగుంటే చాలనుకోడు దేశభక్తుడు. తన చుట్టూ ఉన్న వారి క్షేమంలోనే తన క్షేమం ఉందని భావిస్తాడు.చుట్టూ ఉన్న అన్యాయాలను, అక్రమాలను చూస్తూ సామాన్యుడు తలదించుకొని వెళతాడు. నా ఒక్కడితో ఏమౌతుంది అనే నిర్వేదంలో ఉంటాడు. అలాంటి సామాన్యులను ఒక్కతాటి మీదకు తెచ్చి వారి వెనక తాను ఉన్నాననే ధైర్యాన్ని ఇస్తాడు దేశభక్తుడు. అవినీతిపై మడమతిప్పని పోరాటం చేస్తున్న అన్నా హజారే దీనికి మంచి ఉదాహరణ.దేశభక్తుడు నిరాడంబర జీవితాన్ని గడుపుతూ దేశ ప్రజలకు ఆదర్శంగా నిలుస్తాడు. ప్రజలు కూడా తనలాగే నిరాడంబరంగా జీవించేలా ప్రేరేపిస్తాడు. గాంధీజీ నిరాడంబర జీవనం చూసి, అలాగే నిరాడంబర జీవనం గడిపిన పొట్టి శ్రీరాములు, బులుసు సాంబమూర్తి మనకు తెలుసు.దేశభక్తుడు క్రమశిక్షణకు, పనిపట్ల నిబద్దతకు ప్రాముఖ్యమిస్తాడు. పొదుపును పాటిస్తాడు. ప్రజల కోసం తన సుఖాన్ని త్యాగం చేస్తాడు. జాతిని నిర్వీర్యం చేసే కులమత వైషమ్యాలను పక్కన పెడతాడు. మానవతే తన మతమని చాటుతాడు.ఇలాంటి దేశభక్తుల మూలంగా దేశప్రజలు చైతన్యవంతులౌతారు. వారి బాటలో సామాన్యులు కూడా మాన్యులవుతారు.ప్రఖ్యాత ఇంజనీర్లు కె.యల్. రావు, మోక్ష గుండం విశ్వేశ్వరయ్య దేశ సాంకేతిక అభివృద్ధికి కృషి చేసిన దేశభక్తులు. వారానాడు నిర్మించిన ఆనకట్టల వల్ల దేశ ప్రజల ఆహార సమస్యతీరింది.కందుకూరి వీరేశలింగం, గురజాడ అప్పారావు, కొమఱ్ఱాజు లక్ష్మణరావు వంటి సంఘసంస్కర్తల వల్ల సంఘంలోని మూఢాచారాలు తగ్గాయి.స్త్రీలలో స్వేచ్ఛాకాంక్షను పెంచి, తమ స్థితిని బాగు చేసుకోవాలనే తపన పెంచి, స్త్రీలను చైతన్య పరచిన ఉన్నవ లక్ష్మీబాయమ్మ, కనుపర్తి వరలక్ష్మమ్మ వంటి దేశభక్తురాళ్ళెందరో!తమ ధన, మాన, ప్రాణాలను సైతం తృణ ప్రాయంగా దేశం కోసం త్యాగం చేసే దేశభక్తుల వల్ల ప్రజల్లో విద్య, ధర్మం, నీతి, సంఘంపట్ల చైతన్యం ఏర్పడతాయి."},{"question":"fenoy ny banga :\\"Torabato avy any andanitra ny fahafatesana , _\\"","answer":"\\"ka tsy fantatra izay ho latsahany.\\""},{"question":"請回答這個問題：地球上最古老的民歌是哪一首？","answer":"答案：中國的《茉莉花》"},{"question":"Okpara n lọọ ri Awolọwọ lẹwọn ni Calabar, o fẹẹ lọọ fẹjọ Akintọla ati awọn ọrẹ rẹ sun nibẹ ni","answer":"Ni Ọjọbọ, Alamisi, ọjọ kọkandinlogun, oṣu kọkanla, 1964, wọn ju Mark Ogbod sẹwọn ọdun kan niluu Owerri, nilẹ Ibo lọhun-un ti wọn n pe ni Eastern Region nigba naa. Ẹwọn oṣelu lọkunrin naa lọọ ṣe. Idi si ni pe wọn ti n wa a tipẹ, oun nikan lọmọ ile-igbimọ aṣofin ilẹ Ibo yii to jẹ ọmọ ẹgbẹ NPC, ẹgbẹ awọn Sardauna lati ilẹ Hausa. Bawo ni ẹgbẹ awọn Hausa yoo ṣe rọwọ mu nilẹ Ibo; bawo ni ọmọ Ibo kan ko ṣe ni i ri ẹgbẹ mi-in ṣe ju ẹgbẹ wọn nilẹ Hausa lọ. Nigba toun naa yoo si ko si wọn lọwọ, wọn ba kaadi idibo ojilelẹgbẹta-din-mẹfa (634) lọwọ rẹ, n lawọn yẹn ba sọ pe kaadi to fẹẹ fi ṣojooro nibi ibo to n bọ ni. Mark Ogbodo ni ki i ṣe bẹẹ, awọn kan ti ko mọwe ni wọn ko kaadi naa waa foun pe ki oun fọna han wọn nidii ẹ. Adajọ loun o gba, o lo da oun loju pe o fẹẹ lo kaadi naa fun ojooro ni. Ni wọn ba la a mẹwọn.Oun nikan ko lo n lọ sẹwọn bẹẹ, bi awọn ẹgbẹ oṣelu mẹtẹẹta ti wọn lagbara ju nigba naa ṣe n sọ awọn alatako wọn sẹwọn ati atimọle niyẹn. Ẹgbẹ NPC lo lagbara nilẹ Hausa, Dẹmọ lo lagbara nilẹ Yoruba, NCNC lo si jẹ apaṣẹ nilẹ Ibo. Gbogbo wọn ni wọn ko si fẹ alatako kan ni agbegbe wọn, eyi lo ṣe jẹ bi ibo ti n sun mọle ni wọn n rọ awọn eeyan da satimọle, tabi sẹwọn, lai woju wọn. Ni ọjọ kẹrin ti wọn sọ Ogbodo sẹwọn nilẹ Ibo, awọn mejidinlọgbọn aṣaaju UPGA ni awọn ọlọpaa Western Region mu ni ilu Ọta ati Atan. Ẹṣẹ kan naa ni wọn ṣẹ nibi mejeeji, wọn ni wọn waa wo iwe iforukọsilẹ lati da wahala silẹ nibẹ ni. Bẹẹ ohun ti awọn yẹn n wi ni pe ọpọlọpọ orukọ to wa ninu awọn iwe naa ki i ṣe orukọ awọn eeyan ti wọn n gbe adugbo tawọn, Ọlọrun lo mọ ibi ti wọn ti ko wọn wa, bẹẹ orukọ tawọn gan-an ko si ninu iwe.Ni ọgbọnjọ, oṣu kọkanla, 1964 yii, kan naa, wọn ju awọn aṣaaju ẹgbẹ UPGA mẹta sẹwọn ni Abẹokuta. Ẹni akọkọ ninu wọn ni Fọlọrunṣọ Ọyalọwọ. Ọmọ ẹgbẹ AG ni, o si ti figba kan jẹ aṣaaju ile-igbimọ aṣofin Western Region. Oun atawọn mẹji mi-in ni wọn ju sẹwọn, wọn ni wọn n ṣepade lai gbaṣẹ. Awọn tọhun lawọn ko ṣepade, ọrọ lasan lawọn n sọ; awọn ọlọpaa to mu wọn ni aaye ko si fun iru adurosọrọ bẹẹ lasiko naa, nitori wọn ko le bura pe ki i ṣe ọrọ oṣelu lawọn n sọ. Lọjọ yii kan naa ni wọn wọ awọn mẹta mi-in lọ sile-ẹjọ ni Ebute-Mẹta, l’Ekoo, ohun ti wọn tori ẹ wọ wọn bẹẹ ni pe wọn ni wọn n rin nitosi ile Alaaji Tijani, ẹni to fẹẹ du ipo lasiko ibo naa lorukọ ẹgbẹ Dẹmọ. Bi nnkan ti ri lasiko yii ree, ko si ọmọ ẹgbẹ Action Group, NCNC, tabi UPGA to gbọdọ ta felefele nilẹ Yoruba: bi ọwọ Dẹmọ ba to o, ẹwọn lo n lọ.Ohun ti wọn si ṣe n ṣe bayii ni pe ẹru n ba olori ẹgbẹ naa gan-an, iyẹn Oloye Ladoke Akintọla. Bi ẹgbẹ Dẹmọ ba ja kulẹ, ti ẹgbẹ alajọṣepọ awọn ati NPC ti wọn jọ n jẹ NNA ko ba wọle, to ba jẹ UPGA to jẹ ẹgbẹ alajọṣepọ AG ati NCNC lo wọle ibo awọn aṣofin naa, ti ijọba si di tiwọn, omi gbẹ leyin ẹja fun Akintọla niyi, ohun buruku yoo si maa ja lu ara wọn fun un ni. Awọn UPGA tilẹ ti n leri: KIngsley Mbadiwe, ọkan pataki ninu awọn aṣaaju UPGA, ni ti Ọlọrun ba le ba awọn ṣe e, lẹsẹkẹsẹ ti awọn ba ti wọle lawọn yoo tu ile-igbimọ aṣofin West ka, ti awọn yoo si ṣeto ibo tuntun fun wọn, nitori ibo ti wọn n lo lọwọlọwọ bẹẹ ki i ṣe ibo to dara, ibo ti asiko rẹ ti pari ni, o yẹ ki wọn ti dibo mi-in, ki wọn le mọ bi Akintọla lero leyin tabi ko ni. Mbadiwe  yii ni lojoojumọ ni Akintọla n ti awọn UPGA mọle, ṣugbọn asiko ẹsan ti sun mọle fun un, ijọba yoo bọ lọwọ rẹ laipẹ jọjọ.Eeyan ko ni i gbọ iru eleyii ko ma mura si ọrọ ara rẹ, ohun to jẹ ki Akintọla ati ẹgbẹ Dẹmọ rẹ ṣi maa fi gbogbo ara ja niyi. Ni ọjọ kẹrin, oṣu kejila, 1964, awọn ẹgbẹ Action Group fi ẹdun ọkan sọrọ, wọn ni ohun ti awọn n wi gan-an lo delẹ yii, wọn ni ijọba Akintọla ti sọ ilẹ Yoruba di ilu to n sinru fawọn ara ilẹ Hausa. Ẹgbẹ naa ni gbogbo ere ati iwa ti Akintọla n hu bayii ni bi yoo ti tẹ awọn aṣaaju ilẹ Hausa lọrun, ti wọn yoo le duro ti i lati le ṣeru idibo to n bọ naa. AG ni Akintọla mọ iwa awọn, nigba to jẹ ọkan ninu awọn aṣaaju awọn loun naa tẹlẹ. O mọ iwa awọn pe iwa ka maa rẹ mẹkunnu jẹ, ka maa gba lọwọ talaka lati fi tọju awọn olowo ati alapamaṣiṣẹ ọmọọba ti awọn Hausa n hu lọdọ wọn lọhun-un ni ko jẹ ki awọn ba Sardauna atawọn eeyan rẹ ṣe, ṣugbọn iwa naa ni Akintọla gba mọra bayii, koda, oun naa ti n ṣe bii wọn.Awọn AG ni Akintọla fẹẹ ta Yoruba fun awọn Hausa ni, awọn ko si ni i gba fun un. Ọrọ naa ka Akintọla lara, nitori o mọ pe bii igba ti wọn fẹẹ ba toun jẹ nilẹ Yoruba ni. Ọjọ keji lo ti jade, to si kede pe oun naa mọ o, oun mọ pe gbogbo awọn aṣaaju AG ni wọn koriira oun. Laarin Ọja Oje, n’Ibadan, lo ti n sọ ọ. O ni ko sohun meji ti wọn fi koriira oun ju pe oun sọ fun wọn pe ko yẹ ko jẹ ẹya kan ṣoṣo (Ijẹbu) pere ni yoo maa ko gbogbo ọrọ ilẹ Yoruba si apo ara wọn. O ni awọn eeyan mẹrin pere ti wọn jẹ Ijẹbu ni wọn n ko owo awọn agbẹ gbogbo ilẹ Yoruba sapo, pe ohun ti oun wi to dija ree, ti wọn ni ki oun mu ori wa, ki oun fi ọrun silẹ, idi ti wọn ko si fi fẹran oun niyẹn. Loootọ lawọn ọmọ Dẹmọ n pariwo, ti wọn n fo soke, bi Akintọla ti n sọrọ rẹ, ṣugbọn ọpọlọpọ wọn naa lo mọ pe ọrọ naa ki i ṣe ododo, ipolongo oṣelu lasan ni.Ọrọ naa ko yọ awọn oniroyin paapaa silẹ, bi oniroyin kan ba gbe iroyin ti ko mọdi daadaa jade, ẹsẹkẹsẹ ni wọn yoo gbe e. Ohun to ṣẹlẹ si ọkan ninu olotuu iwe iroyin Azikiwe funra ẹ ree, iyẹn West African Pilot. Wọn mu olootu yii, Herbert Unegbu, l’Ekoo, wọn ni iwe iroyin rẹ gbe iroyin kan jade, nibi ti ẹni kan ti sọrọ pe, ‘Ẹ dibo fun UPGA ki Awolọwọ le jade lẹwọn.’ Wọn ni iru iroyin bẹẹ ki i ṣe ohun to yẹ ki beba rẹ gbe jade. Kia lawọn ọlọpaa ti ṣu u rugudu, nigba ti yoo si ba ara rẹ, ninu ọgba ẹwọn ni. Bẹe naa lawọn tọọgi ẹgbẹ Dẹmọ lu ẹni kan pa ni Sango-Ọta. Amuda Anjọrin ni, wọn ni UPGA lo n ṣe. Ko jọ pe wọn fẹẹ lu u pa, o jọ pe wọn kan fẹẹ fi lilu naa halẹ mọ ọn ni. Ṣugbon wọn ti lu u ju debii pe nigba ti yoo fi de ọsibitu, o ti ku pata. Awọn ti wọn si waa lu u ti fẹsẹ fẹ ẹ.Pẹlu gbogbo ẹ naa ni wọn dajọ idibo ọhun gan-an, wọn  ni ọjọ kọkanlelọgbọn, oṣu kejia, 1964, ni wọn yoo dibo naa, nigba naa ni wọn si tu ile-igbimọ aṣofin ka, ti wọn ni ki kaluku gba ile ẹ lọ, ko si ile-igbimọ mọ, o tun di igba ti wọn ba dibo fun awọn aṣofin tuntun. Michael Okpara, olori NCNC to tun jẹ olori UPGA, ni oun yoo tun ṣe kampeeni kaakiri West, ki wọn le mọ idi ti gbogbo wọn yoo fi jade dibo. Alaaji Dauda Adegbenro, olori ẹgbẹ AG, ti i ṣe igbakeji Okpara ninu UPGA loun naa yoo de awọn ilu kan. Kia lawọn Demọ ti mura ija, wọn gbe kọọfiu kalẹ ni Ogbomọsọ, wọn ni konile gbele, o loju ibi ti Okpara ati Adegbenro le de ni West; ẹni ba kọja aala rẹ, kele yoo gbe e. Ọrọ yii n bọrọ mi-in, kinni naa ka Okpara lara. Lo ba ni oun n lọ si Calabar, lọgba ẹwọn ti Ọbafẹmi Awolọwọ wa, ki oun lọọ fi ẹjọ Akintọla atawọn ọrẹ rẹ sun aṣaaju awọn naa, ko le fawọn nimọran lori ohun ti awọn yoo ṣe. N l’Okpara ba kọri si Calabar."},{"question":"*إلى أي جهة يشير النجم القطبي ؟","answer":"إلى الشمال"},{"question":"Ireto misy fanambarana ireto:\\"Ny bisikileta no fomba tiany indrindra hijerena ny zavaboary\\" sy \\"Tian'izy ireo ny mampiasa bisikileta ho fitaovana hitadiavana ny any ivelany.\\" mitovy ny resahan'ireo?","answer":"Eny, samy miresaka momba ny hazo hatao rehefa mitondra bisikileta any ivelany ireo fanambarana roa ireo."},{"question":"Manomeza ankamantatra momba ny sakay?","answer":"Indro misy ankamantatra iray momba ny sakay:Fanontaniana: \\"Hano aho hinanako anao.\\"Valiny: \\"Sakay\\""},{"question":"පහත ජන කවිය සම්පූර්ණ කරන්න දමා තැල්ල කරවට ගෝමර කැටියා","answer":"දමා තැල්ල කරවට ගෝමර කැටියාතමා බෙල්ල ගඟ පහළට රුව කැටියාරුවන්වැල්ල ගඟ පිට අඟනක් සිටියානුඹම පල්ල මේ මුළු සක්වල වටියා"},{"question":"சாலை விபத்துக்கள் நடந்தால் செய்ய வேண்டியது என்ன?","answer":"* நம் வாழ்க்கையில் பிறப்பும் இறப்பும் ஒரு நாணயத்தின் இருபக்கங்களைப் போல. பிறப்பு என்பது பெரும் மகிழ்வையும் பரவசத்தையும் கொடுப்பது. மரணம் என்பது  பெருந்துயரை அளிப்பது. மரணத்தை தவிர்க்க முடியாது. ஆனால், ஒரு கொடூர  விபத்தால் நடக்கும் மரணத்தை நாம் தடுக்க முடியும். ஒரு இயல்பான மரணத்தை விட ஒரு விபத்தால் ஏற்படும் துர்மரணம் மிகக் கொடியது. ஏனெனில், அவ்வகை மரணங்கள் மறைந்திருந்து திடீரென தாக்குகின்றன.* ஒரு விபத்து நடந்தால் அங்கு உடனே செய்ய வேண்டியவை என்ன என்பது நம்மில் பலருக்கும் தெரியவில்லை. விபத்தால் திகைப்புற்று பதறிப் போய் என்ன செய்வது என்று தெரியாமல் நாம் திக்குமுக்காடிப் போகிறோம். அல்லது 108 ஆம்புலன்சுக்கு தகவல் தெரிவித்துவிட்டு, காயம்பட்டவரையே வெறித்து பார்த்துக் கொண்டு இருக்கிறோம்.* நெடுஞ்சாலைப் பயணம் ஒன்றை மேற்கொள்ளுகிறீர்கள் என்று வைத்துக் கொள்வோம். அப்போது, எதிர்பாராதவிதமாக ஒரு விபத்து ஏற்படுகிறது. உங்களுடன் வந்த சகா ஒருவருக்கு பலத்தக் காயம். அப்போது நீங்கள் செய்ய வேண்டியது என்ன?* பதட்டப்படாமல் அமைதியாக, முறையாக ஆனால் விரைவாக முதலுதவியை தொடங்குங்கள். காயம் பட்டவருக்கு பெரிய அளவில் இரத்தக் கசிவு இருக்கிறதா? என்பதை முதலில் கவனித்து, அதை நிறுத்தவோ தடுக்கவோ முதலில் முயற்சி செய்யுங்கள். சுத்தமான துணி கொண்டு, காயத்தைக் கட்டியோ, துடைத்தோ நிலைமையை கட்டுக்குள் கொண்டு வர முயற்சி செய்யுங்கள். மார்புக்குள், மண்டையோட்டுக்குள் அல்லது அடிவயிரில் காயம் பட்டு இரத்தம் வெளியேறினால் அதை உடனடியாக நாம் கண்டறிய முடியாது. ஆனால், மூக்கு வழியாகவோ காது வழியாகவோ, நுரையீரல் வழியாக வரும் இருமல் மூலமாகவோ அல்லது குடலில் இருந்து வரும் வாந்தி மூலமாகவோ இரத்தம் வெளிவரும். சில அறிகுறிகள் மூலம் இதை நாம் உணரலாம். காயம்பட்டவர் மயக்க நிலையில் இருப்பார். தோல் வெளிறி, குளிர்ந்து போய் இருக்கும். அதிகமான வியர்வை வழிய, காயம் பட்டவர் தாகமாக இருப்பதாக உணர்வார். இந்த வகை காயம்பட்டோரை உடனடியாக மருத்துவமனைக்கு அழைத்துச் செல்ல முயற்சிகள் மேற்கொள்ளப்படவேண்டும்.* தீ, உடைந்த கண்ணாடிகள் மற்றும் மின்சாரம் பாய்கின்ற ஒயர்கள் இவை தாக்கும் அபாயம் இருந்தால், அங்கிருந்து காயம்பட்டவரை அப்புறப்படுத்தி, பாதுகாப்பான இடத்தில் கிடத்துங்கள். வேடிக்கைப் பார்க்கக் குழுமி இருக்கும் கூட்டத்தை விலக்கி, அப்புறப்படுத்தி காயம்பட்டவருக்கு புதிய காற்று கிடைக்க வழிவகை செய்யுங்கள். பாதிக்கப்பட்டவரிடம் மென்மையாகவும், ஆறுதலாகவும் பேசி அவருக்கு நம்பிக்கை ஊட்டுங்கள். வாகனத்திற்கு ஏற்பாடு செய்து விபத்தில் பாதிக்கப்பட்டவரை மிக மிக அருகில் உள்ள மருத்துவமனைக்கு அழைத்துச் செல்லுங்கள். பாதிக்கப்பட்டவரின் குடும்பத்திற்கு தகவலை தெரியப்படுத்துங்கள். முதலுதவி செய்பவர்கள் அளவுக்கதிகமாக எதையும் செய்ய முயலக்கூடாது. நிலைமை மோசமாகிவிடாத அளவுக்கு உதவினாலே போதுமானது.* விபத்து நடந்த நிமிடத்தில் இருந்து விபத்துக் களத்திலிருந்து மிக அருகில் உள்ள மருத்துவமனைக்கு நோயாளியை கொண்டு செல்லப்படும் நேரம் மிகவும் பொன்னானது. இதை மருத்துவர்கள் “பொன்னான நேரம்”(Golden Time) என்று தான் சொல்கிறார்கள். ஏனெனில் இந்த நேரத்தில் தான் சுவாசக் குறைபாடு மற்றும் குறைந்த இரத்த அழுத்தத்தின் காரணமாக பெரும்பாலான நோயாளிகள் இறந்து விடுகிறார்கள். அதனால், விபத்தால் பாதிக்கப்பட்டவரை விரைந்து மருத்துவமனைக்கு அழைத்து செல்லுதல் மிகவும் அவசியம். 108 க்கு தொலைபேசித் தகவல் சொல்லியாகிவிட்டது என்று கடமை உணர்வோடு காத்திருத்தல் போதுமானது அல்ல.* பொன்னான நேரம் என்று சொல்லக்கூடிய அந்த முதல் ஒரு மணி நேர சிகிச்சையை அனைத்து தனியார் மருத்துவமனைகளும் செய்யலாம் என்ற விதி இருக்கிறது. அதுவும் இலவசமாக செய்யவேண்டும். பிறகு, அரசு மருத்துவமனைக்கோ அல்லது பல்வேறு வசதிகள் கொண்ட பெரிய தனியார் மருத்துவமனைக்கோ நோயாளியை அழைத்து செல்லலாம். காப்பீடு கோரிக்கைக்கு இதனால் எந்த சிக்கலும் பிற்காலத்தில் நேராது.* முதலில் விபத்து அடைந்த நபரின் நிலைமை என்ன என்பதை நாம் அறிந்து கொள்ள வேண்டும். அதில் மூன்று நிலைகள் இருக்கின்றன. மூச்சு விடமுடியாத நிலை அல்லது இதயத்துடிப்பு இன்மை, பெருமளவு இரத்தம் வெளியாகுதல், நினைவிழந்த மயக்க நிலைமை. இந்த மூன்று நிலையில் உள்ள காயம் பட்டோருக்கு, திறமையாக முதலுதவி செய்தால் அவர்களின் மேலான உயிரை நிச்சயம் காப்பாற்ற முடியும்.* காயம் பட்டவர் நினைவிழந்த நிலையில் இருந்தால் விபத்தால் அவரது காற்றுப்பாதை, அதாவது மூச்சுக்குழல் அடைப்பட்டு இருக்கும் வாய்ப்பு தொண்ணூறு சதம் வாய்ப்பு இருக்கிறது. அப்போது அவர் மிகவும் சத்தமாகவும், மிகுந்த சிரமத்துடனும் மூச்சு விடுவார். இது பல காரணங்களால் நிகழ்கிறது. விபத்தின்போது, அவரது தலை முன்னோக்கி சாய்ந்து, அதனால் அவரது மூச்சுப் பாதை குறுகி இருக்கலாம். தொண்டை தசை அதன் கட்டுப்பாட்டை இழந்து, அதனால் அவரது நாக்கு உள்ளே தள்ளப்பட்டு, காற்றுப் பாதை அடைக்கப்பட்டு இருக்கலாம். அல்லது, உமிழ்நீர், வாந்தி போன்றவை தொண்டையின் பின்பகுதியில் அடைத்துக்கொண்டு காற்றை தடுத்துக்கொண்டு இருக்கலாம்.* இதுபோன்ற எந்த சூழ்நிலையும், காயம் பட்டவரின் மரணத்திற்கு காரணமாகிவிடும். அதனால், முதலுதவி செய்வோர் உடனடியாக, காயம்பட்டவர் மூச்சு விட ஏதுவாக அவரது மூச்சுக் காற்றுப்பாதையை திறக்க வேண்டியது மிகவும் அவசியம். அவர் எந்நிலையில் விழுந்து கிடந்தாலும் அவரது தலை மேல் நோக்கி, அதாவது, அவர் தலை சற்று மேல் நோக்கி சாய்ந்து, அவரது முகவாய்க் கட்டை மேல் நோக்கிய நிலையில் இருக்கும்படி தூக்கி வைக்க வேண்டும். இதனால் நாக்கு தூக்கப்பட்டு, தொண்டையின் உள்ளிருந்து காற்றுப்பாதை தெளிவடைகிறது.* காற்றுப்பாதை ஒரு தடவை திறந்து விடப்பட்டால் விபத்துக்குள்ளானவர் தானாகவே மூச்சு விட ஆரம்பித்துவிடுவார். ஆனால், இந்த முதலுதவி செய்யப்பட்டும், அவரால் மூச்சு விட முடியாவிட்டால், உடனடியாக செயற்கை மூச்சு விடும் முறையை ஆரம்பிக்க வேண்டும்.* காயம்பட்டவரின் அருகில் முட்டிப்போட்டு உட்காருங்கள். கழுத்து, மார்பு மற்றும் இடுப்பு இவற்றை சுற்றியுள்ள ஆடைகளை தளர்த்துங்கள். காயம்பட்டோரின் முகவாய்கட்டையை முன்னோக்கித் தூக்குங்கள். அடையாள விரல் மற்றும் நடு விரல்களால் அவரது நெற்றியைப் பின்புறமாக அழுத்துங்கள். இதனால், அவரது தாடை தூக்கப்பட்டு நாக்கு முன்னேறி காற்றுப்பாதை தெளிவாக்கப்படும்.* காற்றுப்பாதையை நீங்கள் திறந்து விட்டு இருந்தாலும் கூட, வாந்தி அல்லது உடைந்த பற்கள் அல்லது உணவு போன்றவை காற்றுப்பாதையை அடைத்துக் கொண்டு இருக்கக்கூடும். சாத்தியமானால், எந்தப் பொருள் உங்கள் கண்ணுக்கு தென்பட்டாலும், அவற்றை உடனடியாக நீக்கிவிட வேண்டும்.* காயம்பட்டவரின் தலையை ஒரு பக்கமாக திருப்புங்கள். உங்கள் முதல் இரண்டு விரல்களையும் வாயினுள் விட்டு துழாவுங்கள். ஆனால், ஒளிந்திருக்கும் பொருள்களை தேட முயல வேண்டாம். எந்த பொருளையும் தொண்டைக்கு கீழே தள்ளிவிடாமல் கவனமாக இருங்கள். பிறகு, மறுபடியும் அவர் மூச்சுவிடுதலை பரிசோதியுங்கள்.* இதிலும் அவர் மூச்சு விட சிரமப்படுகிறார் என்றால், அவர் மூச்சுவிடுதலை மீண்டும் உருவாக்க ஒரு உத்தி உள்ளது. அதன் பெயர் செயற்கை மூச்சுமுறை. உண்மையிலேயே மிகச்சிறந்த முறை. அது எது தெரியுமா? உங்களது சொந்த நுரையீரல் காற்றைக் காயம்பட்டவரின் நுரையீரலுக்குள் உங்கள் வாய் மூலம் அவரது வாய்க்குள் ஊதுவதுதான்.* அகலமாக உங்கள் வாயை திறங்கள். ஆழமான மூச்சு எடுங்கள். உங்கள் விரல்களால் காயம்பட்டவரின் மூக்கு துவாரங்களை கிள்ளுவது போல் பிடித்துக் கொள்ளுங்கள். அவரது வாயை உங்கள் உதடுகளால் மூடி விடுங்கள். இருமுறை மூச்சு ஊதியபின்பு, கழுத்து நாடியை பரிசோதியுங்கள். இதயத் துடிப்பு இருக்கிறதா? என்பதை பரிசோதியுங்கள். இதயம் துடித்தால், நாடி உணரப்பட்டால் மூச்சு ஊதுதலை ஒரு நிமிடத்திற்கு 12 முதல் 16 தடவை தொடர்ந்து செய்யவேண்டும். அவர் இயற்கையான மூச்சு விடும்வரை இப்படி நீங்கள் தொடர்ந்து உதவலாம்.* அவரது இதயம் துடிக்கவில்லை என்று வைத்துக் கொள்வோம். இதற்கு வெளிப்புற மார்பு அழுத்தத்தை உடனடியாக மேற்கொள்ள வேண்டும். இதயம் வேலை செய்யாததை கீழ்க்கண்ட குறிகளின் மூலம் நம்மால் எளிதில் அறிய முடியும். அவரது முகம், கண் இமைகளின் உட்புறம், விரல் நகம் ஆகியவை வெளிறி நீல நிறமாக இருக்கும். கண்மணிகள் விரிந்திருக்கும். கழுத்தில் நாடித் துடிப்பு இருக்காது.* இதற்கு முதலுதவி மேற்கொள்ள, காயம்பட்டவரை அவர் முதுகு சமமாக இருக்கும்வகையில், தரையிலோ, பலகையிலோ படுக்க வைக்கலாம். உங்கள் கையால் ஒரு நல்ல “தட்டு” ஒன்றை கீழ் மற்றும் இடது கோரை “ஸ்டெர்ணம்” என்னும் பகுதியில், அதாவது, அவரது இடது மார்பின் மேல் பகுதியில் கொடுக்க வேண்டும். பொதுவாக இது இதயம் மீண்டும் துடிக்கச் செய்ய உதவும். ஒருவேளை இதற்கும் இதயம் மசியவில்லை என்றால், தொடர்ந்து 10 அல்லது 15 நொடிகள் முயற்சி செய்யலாம். ஒரு நொடிக்கு ஒரு தட்டு என்ற வகையில் முயற்சியினை மேற்கொள்ள வேண்டும். இது செயற்கை மூச்சு விடும் முறையோடு சேர்ந்து செய்யப்படவேண்டும்.* இவ்வாறு சில முயற்சிகளை நாம் செய்வதன் மூலம், அவரது உடல் விபத்தால் கடுமையான இழப்பை சந்தித்த போதிலும் விழிப்புடன் இருக்கும். பிறகு, ஆம்புலன்ஸ் மூலமாக மருத்துவமனைக்கு கொண்டுசெல்லும்போது, கை தேர்ந்த மருத்துவர்களின் சிகிச்சைக்கு அவரது உடல் ஒத்துழைக்கும்.* இந்த செய்முறைகளை படிக்கும்போது நம்மால் இதை எல்லாம் செய்ய முடியுமா என்ற மலைப்பு ஏற்படுவது உண்மையே. ஆனால், சில நாள் பயிற்சிகளின் மூலம் இந்த முதலுதவி நுணுக்கங்களை நாம் கற்றுக்கொண்டால், மிகவும் இக்கட்டான சூழ்நிலையில் நமக்கு அது நிச்சயம் கை கொடுக்கும்."},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਆਸਾ ਮਹਲਾ ੫ ਅਸਟਪਦੀਆ ਘਰੁ ੨ ੴ ਸਤਿਗੁਰ ਪ੍ਰਸਾਦਿ॥ ਪੰਚ ਮਨਾਏ ਪੰਚ ਰੁਸਾਏ॥ ਪੰਚ ਵਸਾਏ ਪੰਚ ਗਵਾਏ ॥੧॥ ਇਨੑ ਬਿਧਿ ਨਗਰੁ ਵੁਠਾ ਮੇਰੇ ਭਾਈ ॥ ਦੁਰਤੁ ਗਇਆ ਗੁਰਿ ਗਿਆਨੁ ਦ੍ਰਿੜਾਈ ॥੧॥ ਰਹਾਉ ॥ ਸਾਚ ਧਰਮ ਕੀ ਕਰਿ ਦੀਨੀ ਵਾਰਿ ॥ ਫਰਹੇ ਮੁਹਕਮ ਗੁਰ ਗਿਆਨੁ ਬੀਚਾਰਿ ॥੨॥ ਨਾਮੁ ਖੇਤੀ ਬੀਜਹੁ ਭਾਈ ਮੀਤ ॥ਸਉਦਾ ਕਰਹੁ ਗੁਰੁ ਸੇਵਹੁ ਨੀਤ ॥੩॥ਸਾਂਤਿ ਸਹਜ ਸੁਖ ਕੇ ਸਭਿ ਹਾਟ ॥ ਸਾਹ ਵਾਪਾਰੀ ਏਕੈ ਥਾਟ ॥੪॥ ਜੇਜੀਆ ਡੰਨੁ ਕੋ ਲਏ ਨ ਜਗਾਤਿ ॥ ਸਤਿਗੁਰਿ ਕਰਿ ਦੀਨੀ ਧੁਰ ਕੀ ਛਾਪ ॥੫॥ ਵਖਰੁ ਨਾਮੁ ਲਦਿ ਖੇਪ ਚਲਾਵਹੁ ॥ ਲੈ ਲਾਹਾ ਗੁਰਮੁਖਿ ਘਰਿ ਆਵਹੁ ॥੬॥ ਸਤਿਗੁਰੁ ਸਾਹੁ ਸਿਖ ਵਣਜਾਰੇ ॥ ਪੂੰਜੀ ਨਾਮੁ ਲੇਖਾ ਸਾਚੁ ਸਮ੍ਹਾਰੇ ॥੭॥ ਸੋ ਵਸੈ ਇਤੁ ਘਰਿ ਜਿਸੁ ਗੁਰੁ ਪੂਰਾ ਸੇਵ ॥ ਅਬਿਚਲ ਨਗਰੀ ਨਾਨਕ ਦੇਵ ॥੮॥੧॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 430 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਅਰਜਨ ਦੇਵ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਬਾਣੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਹਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"(ਹੇ ਭਾਈ! ਜਿਸ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਨੂੰ ਗੁਰੂ ਨੇ ਗਿਆਨ ਦੀ ਦਾਤਿ ਦਿੱਤੀ ਉਸ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਨੇ ਆਪਣੇ ਸਰੀਰ-ਨਗਰ ਵਿਚ ਸਤ ਸੰਤੋਖ ਦਇਆ ਧਰਮ ਧੀਰਜ—ਇਹ) ਪੰਜੇ ਪ੍ਰਫੁਲਤ ਕਰ ਲਏ, ਤੇ, ਕਾਮਾਦਿਕ ਪੰਜੇ ਨਾਰਾਜ਼ ਕਰ ਲਏ, (ਸਤ ਸੰਤੋਖ ਆਦਿਕ) ਪੰਜ (ਆਪਣੇ ਸਰੀਰ ਨਗਰ ਵਿਚ) ਵਸਾ ਲਏ, ਤੇ, ਕਾਮਾਦਿਕ ਪੰਜੇ (ਨਗਰ ਵਿਚੋਂ) ਕੱਢ ਦਿੱਤੇ ।੧। ਗੁਰੂ ਨੇ (ਜਿਸ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਨੂੰ) ਆਤਮਕ ਜੀਵਨ ਦੀ ਸੂਝ ਪੱਕੀ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਦੇ ਦਿੱਤੀ (ਉਸ ਦੇ ਅੰਦਰੋਂ) ਵਿਕਾਰ-ਪਾਪ ਦੂਰ ਹੋ ਗਿਆ, ਤੇ, ਹੇ ਮੇਰੇ ਵੀਰ! ਇਸ ਤਰੀਕੇ ਨਾਲ ਉਸ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਦਾ ਸਰੀਰ-ਨਗਰ ਵੱਸ ਪਿਆ ।੧। ਰਹਾਉ। (ਹੇ ਭਾਈ! ਜਿਸ ਗੁਰੂ ਨੇ ਗਿਆਨ ਬਖ਼ਸ਼ਿਆ, ਉਸ ਨੇ ਆਪਣੇ ਸਰੀਰ-ਨਗਰ ਦੀ ਰਾਖੀ ਵਾਸਤੇ) ਸਦਾ-ਥਿਰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੇ ਨਿੱਤ ਦੇ ਸਿਮਰਨ ਦੀ ਵਾੜ ਦੇ ਲਈਗੁਰੂ ਦੇ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਗਿਆਨ ਨੂੰ ਸੋਚ-ਮੰਡਲ ਵਿਚ ਟਿਕਾ ਕੇ ਉਸ ਨੇ ਆਪਣੇ ਖਿੜਕ (ਗਿਆਨ-ਇੰਦ੍ਰੇ) ਪੱਕੇ ਕਰ ਲਏ ।੨।ਹੇ ਮੇਰੇ ਮਿੱਤਰ! ਹੇ ਮੇਰੇ ਭਾਈ! ਤੁਸੀ ਵੀ ਸਦਾ ਗੁਰੂ ਦੀ ਸਰਨ ਲਵੋ, ਸਰੀਰ-ਪੈਲੀ ਵਿਚ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਬੀਜਿਆ ਕਰੋਸਰੀਰ-ਨਗਰ ਵਿਚ ਨਾਮ ਸਿਮਰਨ ਦਾ ਸੌਦਾ ਕਰਦੇ ਰਹੋ ।੩। ਹੇ ਭਾਈ! ਜੇਹੜੇ (ਸਿੱਖ-) ਵਣਜਾਰੇ (ਗੁਰੂ-) ਸ਼ਾਹ ਦੇ ਨਾਲ ਇੱਕ-ਰੂਪ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਸਾਰੇ ਹੱਟ (ਸਾਰੇ ਗਿਆਨ-ਇੰਦ੍ਰੇ) ਸ਼ਾਂਤੀਆਤਮਕ ਅਡੋਲਤਾ, ਤੇ ਆਤਮਕ ਆਨੰਦ ਦੇ ਹੱਟ ਬਣ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ ।੪।(ਹੇ ਭਾਈ! ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਗੁਰੂ ਨੇ ਗਿਆਨ ਦੀ ਦਾਤਿ ਦਿੱਤੀ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਸਰੀਰ-ਨਗਰ ਵਾਸਤੇ) ਗੁਰੂ ਨੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ-ਦਰ ਤੋਂ ਪਰਵਾਨ ਹੋਈ ਹੋਈ ਮਾਫ਼ੀ ਦੀ ਮੋਹਰ ਬਖ਼ਸ਼ ਦਿੱਤੀਕੋਈ (ਪਾਪ ਵਿਕਾਰ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਹਰਿ-ਨਾਮ ਸੌਦੇ ਉਤੇ) ਜਜ਼ੀਆ ਡੰਨ ਮਸੂਲ ਨਹੀਂ ਲਾ ਸਕਦਾ (ਕੋਈ ਵਿਕਾਰ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਆਤਮਕ ਜੀਵਨ ਵਿਚ ਕੋਈ ਖ਼ਰਾਬੀ ਪੈਦਾ ਨਹੀਂ ਕਰ ਸਕਦਾ) ।੫। ਹੇ ਮੇਰੇ ਮਿੱਤਰ! ਹੇ ਮੇਰੇ ਭਾਈ! ਗੁਰੂ ਦੀ ਸਰਨ ਪੈ ਕੇ ਤੁਸੀ ਭੀ ਹਰਿ-ਨਾਮ ਸਿਮਰਨ ਦਾ ਸੌਦਾ ਲੱਦ ਕੇ (ਆਤਮਕ ਜੀਵਨ ਦਾ) ਵਪਾਰ ਕਰੋ(ਉੱਚੇ ਆਤਮਕ ਜੀਵਨ ਦਾ) ਲਾਭ ਖੱਟੋ ਤੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੇ ਚਰਨਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਟਿਕਾਣਾ ਪ੍ਰਾਪਤ ਕਰੋ ।੬। (ਹੇ ਭਾਈ! ਨਾਮ ਦਾ ਸਰਮਾਇਆ ਗੁਰੂ ਦੇ ਪਾਸ ਹੈ) ਗੁਰੂ (ਹੀ ਇਸ ਸਰਮਾਏ ਦਾ) ਸਾਹੂਕਾਰ ਹੈ (ਜਿਸ ਪਾਸੋਂ ਆਤਮਕ ਜੀਵਨ ਦਾ) ਵਣਜ ਕਰਨ ਵਾਲੇ ਸਿੱਖ ਹਰਿ-ਨਾਮ ਦਾ ਸਰਮਾਇਆ ਹਾਸਲ ਕਰਦੇ ਹਨ(ਜਿਸ ਸਿੱਖ ਨੂੰ ਗੁਰੂ ਨੇ ਗਿਆਨ ਦੀ ਦਾਤਿ ਦੇ ਦਿੱਤੀ ਹੈ ਉਹ) ਸਦਾ-ਥਿਰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਨੂੰ ਆਪਣੇ ਹਿਰਦੇ ਵਿਚ ਸਾਂਭ ਕੇ ਰੱਖਦਾ ਹੈ (ਇਹੀ ਹੈ) ਲੇਖਾ-ਹਿਸਾਬ (ਜੋ ਉਹ ਨਾਮ-ਵਣਜ ਵਿਚ ਕਰਦਾ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ) ।੭। ਉਹ ਇਸ (ਐਸੇ ਹਿਰਦੇ-) ਘਰ ਵਿਚ ਵੱਸਦਾ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ ਜੋ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੇ ਰਹਿਣ ਵਾਸਤੇ (ਵਿਕਾਰਾਂ ਵਿਚ) ਕਦੇ ਨਾਹ ਡੋਲਣ ਵਾਲੀ ਨਗਰੀ ਬਣ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ ਹੇ ਨਾਨਕ! (ਆਖ—ਹੇ ਭਾਈ!) ਪੂਰਾ ਗੁਰੂ ਜਿਸ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਨੂੰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੀ ਸੇਵਾ-ਭਗਤੀ ਦੀ ਦਾਤਿ ਬਖ਼ਸ਼ਦਾ ਹੈ \\""},{"question":"Kenapakah tugu negara dibina di Malaysia?","answer":"Tugu Negara di Malaysia telah dibina sebagai tanda memperingati pejuang negara melawan tentera British."},{"question":"Quelle est la position aujourd'hui officielle des scientifiques concernant l'origine de la Lune et ses effets sur la Terre? Pourquoi avons-nous arrêté de l’étudier ?","answer":"La Terre, la Lune… la vie ! L’histoire de la formation de la Lune est l’une des grandes questions de la planétologie contemporaine. La théorie la plus en vogue aujourd’hui fut imaginée à la fin des années 1970. Voilà 4,5 milliards d’années, la Terre encore en formation croise un bolide de la taille de Mars. Le choc est gigantesque. Les deux corps fusionnent et dispersent en orbite des débris qui s’agglutinent ensuite rapidement pour donner naissance à la Lune. L’étude de la Lune ne s'est pas arrêtée avec la fin des missions habitées, ce grâce à l’envoi de sondes automatiques. Smart 1, l'une d'elles, est une mission européenne qui a débuté ses observations en janvier 2005. L’exploration habitée de la Lune pourrait reprendre d’ici 2020 ! La Lune est bien sûr responsable des marées. Mais on lui doit surtout la stabilité de nos climats et peut-être l’entretien des courants océaniques. Sans la Lune, nous ne serions sûrement pas là pour commenter son absence."},{"question":"What does the SPF in sunscreen stand for?","answer":"The SPF on sunscreen stands for sun protection factor, a relative measurement for the amount of time the sunscreen will protect you from ultraviolet (UV) rays."},{"question":"Explain the difference between supervised and unsupervised learning","answer":"Most statistical learning problems fall into one of two categories: supervised or unsupervised learning. If for each observation of the predictor measurement, there is an associated responsemeasurement, then it is then classified as supervised learning. If response variable is absent then it is an example of unsupervised learning. "},{"question":"Ак түстүү жаныбарлар же альбиностор...","answer":"Альбинизм – бул гендик жаңылуу жана аны жаратылыштын касиети деп эсептеген туура эмес. Аны дарылоо да мүмкүн болбогондуктан бул жаныбарларды түбөлүк табигый түсүнөн ажыратчу дефект болуп эсептелет. Эгер түгөй жаныбарлардын экөө тең альбинизм оорусу менен жабыркаса, анысы тукум улайт, а бирок бирөөсү гана ооруса, баласы ден соолугу чың болуп туулат.Ак арстан -учурда дүйнө жүзүндө болгону 300 ак арстан бар. Алар ТАРдын (Түштүк Африка Республикасы) батышындагы – абдан чоң зоопаркта – Санбондо жашашат. Бул жерден алар аңчылардан (браконьерлерден) сак болуп жана да ачкачылык менен ар кандай илдеттерден коркпой жашай алышат. Алар гана эмес башка дагы кээде кездешүүчү жаныбарлардын түрлөрү бул жерден көбөйүп, келечек кура алышат.Аман калган ак түстүү тыйын чычкан - эгер сиздер , буга чейин бул тууралуу билбеген болсоңуздар, айбанаттар альбинизм-тукумдаштарына абдан негативдүү көз карашта болушат. Өзгөчө бул жагдайда тыйын чычкандарда абдан коркунучтуу: өзгөчөлүү түстөгү тыйын чычкандары тукумдаштары бала кезинен эле жок кылып өлтүрүп салышат. Андыктан мындай жаныбарды токойдон кезиктирүү абдан кыйын. Ошол себептүү, сиздер көрүп турган тыйын чычкан кантип аман калды экен деп таңгаласың.Өзгөчөлүү эки баштуу ак жылан - Ялталык зоопаркта жыландардын кээде кездешчү түрү – эки баштуу королдук жылан-альбинос пайда болду. Зоопарктын директорунун айтымында, бул жылан эки баштуу болуп жаралган жыландардын арасында аман калган миллиондун бири болуп саналат.Ак акыра альбинизм менен оорушпайбы?Биз айтып аткан ак түстүү акыралар жаратылышта өтө эле сейрек кездешет. Атайын адис Чарльз Фолинин ою боюнча, жираф альбинизм тукумунан эмес, бирок анын денесинде тактары башкалардан айырмалангандыктан ал мутация да болушу ыктымал.Кенгуру-альбиносторКенгуру-альбиностор жаратылыштын өзгөчө жандыктары. Эсеп боюнча, мындай кенгурулардын бирөө 10-15 кадимки кенгуруга туш келет. Германиянын түндүгүндөгү Марлов деген жаратылыш паркында Альберта аттуу ак түстүү альбинос-кенгуру жашайт. Жакында атайын айбанаттарды изилдеген сайттардын бири Альберта бөбөктүү болгонун жазды. Таңгалыштуу, анын тууган баласы ак эмес, а кадимки кенгурулардай кара түстө. Ага Жоу деген ысым ыйгарышкан.Кереметтүү ак павлиндерНегизинен павлиндерди (кыргоол түрүнө кирүүчү кооз жүндүү тоок) декоративдик максатта кармашат, тактап айтканда азыр аларды кооздук үчүн багып калышты. Ал эми мурда аны кадимки канаттуулардай эле эт азыгы катары колдонушчу. Павлиндер суукка жакшы чыдай алышпайт жана да каалоолору жок көбөйүшпөйт, башка канаттуулардын түрлөрү менен оңою менен тил табыша алышпайт. Дан азыктары, өсүмдүктөр жана курт-кумурскалар менен тамактанышат. Ак павлиндер Пакистан менен Индияда жашашат жана чынында эле көркү көздү суктандырат.Кээде кездешүүчү аллигаторлорКээде кездешүүчү аллигаторлорду жаратылыштан кезиктирүү кыйын. Анткени, табиятынан мыкаачы келген жырткыч тукумдаштары аларды аман койбоору шексиз. "},{"question":"No contexto da física, explique o significado de Colisões.","answer":"Colisões referem-se a interações entre objetos que resultam em forças mútuas e possíveis alterações em suas trajetórias. As colisões podem ser elásticas, em que a energia total é preservada, ou inelásticas, onde ocorre uma perda de energia cinética."},{"question":"ஒகேனக்கல் பகுதியில் நாம் பார்க்க வேண்டிய இடங்களைக் கூறுக.","answer":"ஒகேனக்கல் நீர்வீழ்ச்சி, மான் பூங்கா, முதலைப் பண்ணை ."},{"question":" கேள்வி:கௌதம புத்தரின் மேற்கோள் ஒன்றை தரவும்.","answer":"பதில்:புத்தர் என்று அழைக்கப்படும் சித்தார்த்த கௌதமர், கிமு 567 இல் இமயமலையின் அடிவாரத்தில் உள்ள சிறிய ராஜ்யமான லும்பினியில் பிறந்தார். அவர் தனது அரச வாழ்க்கையைத் துறந்து நாடோடி துறவி வாழ்க்கை முறையைக் கடைப்பிடித்தார். பிச்சை, தவம், தியானம் போன்ற வாழ்க்கை வாழ்ந்த பிறகு, இப்போது இந்தியாவில் இருக்கும் போத்கயாவில் அவர் ஞானம் பெற்றார். அதீத சந்நியாசத்தைத் தவிர்க்கும் அதே வேளையில், சிற்றின்ப இன்பத்தை, இறுதியில் நிர்வாணம் அல்லது அறியாமை, ஏக்கம், மறுபிறப்பு மற்றும் துக்கத்திலிருந்து தப்பிக்க அனுமதிக்கும் ஒரு நடுத்தர பாதைக்கு அவர் வாதிட்டார். நோபல் எட்டு மடங்கு பாதை, பின்வருவனவற்றை உள்ளடக்கிய மனப் பயிற்சி முறை, அவரது போதனைகளின் சுருக்கம்.சரியான பார்வைசரியான தீர்மானம்சரியான பேச்சுசரியான நடத்தைசரியான வாழ்வாதாரம்சரியான முயற்சிசரியான நினைவாற்றல்சரியான சமாதி"},{"question":"Hãy tiếp tục đoạn văn sau: Thành viên Jimin của BTS từng theo một chế độ ăn kiêng cực đoan, không lành mạnh để giảm cân. Tính cách trên mạng của Jungkook BTS thay đổi ra sao khi lớn hơn Người hâm mộ đang bàn tán về việc thành viên Jungkook của BTS trên Internet đã thay đổi như thế nào sau thời niên thiếu. Jimin là một trong những thành viên BTS đã từng thử các chế độ ăn kiêng giảm cân trong quá khứ. Mục đích là để giảm cân cho màn trình diễn của nhóm, cũng như trông đẹp cho bản thân. Giọng ca chính của BTS chia sẻ rằng anh ấy đã thực hiện chế độ này một cách chăm chỉ vì muốn mình trông thật \\"đẹp trai\\" trước gương. Các nguồn tin cho rằng đây là thời","answer":"kỳ ra mắt album Wings và ca khúc Blood, Sweat And Tears. Giảm 10kg trong 10 ngày Theo KpopStarz, chế độ ăn kiêng của Jimin liên quan đến việc hạn chế tiêu thụ bữa ăn một cách tối đa và việc tiêu thụ thức ăn diễn ra một lần trong ngày. Nói tóm lại, thành viên BTS chỉ ăn 1 bữa mỗi ngày, mặc dù không rõ Jimin đã dùng thức ăn gì vào thời điểm đó. Tuy nhiên, đã có những tuyên bố nói rằng anh chàng hạn chế ăn 2 ức gà mỗi ngày cho chế độ này. Kèm theo đó là uống rất nhiều nước, giúp anh vượt qua phần còn lại của ngày. Chế độ ăn uống lành mạnh Tuy nhiên, hiện tại Jimin không còn tuân theo chế độ ăn kiêng như cũ vì những rủi ro và nguy hiểm của nó. Anh thậm chí còn được báo cáo rằng đã trải qua những tác động bất lợi của chế độ ăn kiêng có hại kể trên, khiến nam idol phải sửa đổi thói quen ăn uống của mình. Theo Channel-Korea, sức khỏe của thành viên BTS suy yếu đến mức ngất xỉu trong buổi diễn tập. Vì vậy, anh đã thay thế nó bằng một chế độ ăn uống phù hợp và ăn uống thường xuyên. Tuy nhiên, vẫn chưa biết những thực phẩm cụ thể mà Jimin ăn những ngày này. Nguồn tin cũng cho biết anh ưu tiên chất đạm hơn chất béo và tập trung vào rau và trái cây. BXH sao Hàn tháng 7: Diễn viên 30 tuổi hot hơn BTS và Blackpink Mới đây, Viện Nghiên cứu Kinh doanh Hàn Quốc đã công bố bảng xếp hạng (BXH) danh tiếng của các ngôi sao trong tháng 7/2022."},{"question":"Qual é a capital da República Checa?","answer":"Praga."},{"question":"What is the difference between a tree and a graph?","answer":"A tree is a hierarchical data structure with a single root, while a graph is a collection of nodes and edges where nodes can have multiple connections."},{"question":"Escribe la continuación de este texto : Barakah () hija de Tha'alaba bin Amr, conocida como Umm Ayman (: أمّ أيمن‎), fue la segunda madre del Profeta del Islam, Mahoma; era una joven abisinia esclava de Abd Allah ibn Abd al-Muttalib, o de su esposa Aminah. Desde la muerte de Aminah, Umm Ayman cuidó de su hijo, como niñera. Mahoma más tarde la liberó, pero ella continuó sirviendo afectuosamente a él y su familia por largo tiempo, especialmente estuvo presente en las batallas de Uhud... ","answer":"Y Jáybar. Mahoma la presentaba como una mujer celestial."},{"question":"Nahoana no zava-dehibe eo amin’ny fiaraha-monina ny fitovian’ny lahy sy ny vavy zo?","answer":"Zava-dehibe ny fitovian’ny lahy sy ny vavy zo satria mampirisika ny rariny ara-tsosialy, ny fanajana ny zon’olombelona, ​​ny fampandrosoana ara-toekarena, ary manampy amin’ny famoronana fiarahamonina  mirindra kokoa."},{"question":"ই-বুক নিয়ে অনুচ্ছেদ লিখুন।","answer":"ই-বুক বা ইলেকট্রনিক বুক হচ্ছে বইয়ের আদলে প্রকাশিত ডিজিটাল বই। এই বই হচ্ছে একাধারে চিত্র ও কথার সমন্বয়ে প্রকাশিত বই যা কম্পিউটার বা অন্য যেকোনো ইলেকট্রনিক যন্ত্রের মাধ্যমে সংগ্রহ করা যায় এবং পড়া যায়। ই-বুক তথাকথিত পুস্তক বা বইয়ের মতো কাগজে ছাপানো আকারে প্রকাশিত নয়। তবে ছাপানো বইয়ের মতোই একে পড়া যায় ই- রিডারের মাধ্যমে। ১৯৪০ সালের দিকে ই-বুকের ধারণা প্রথম প্রবর্তিত হয়। সর্বপ্রথম প্রকাশিত ই-বুক হচ্ছে— ইনডেক্স থমেসটিকাস যা ১৯৪৯ সালে প্রকাশিত হয়। এটি তৈরিতে কাজ করেছিলেন রবার্টো বুসা। এছাড়াও ১৯৪৯ সালে ই-বুক প্রকাশ করেন অ্যাঞ্জেলা লুইস রব্যাজ। ২০০৯ সালের আগস্ট পর্যন্ত প্রকাশিত ই-বুকের সংখ্যা দুই লক্ষেরও বেশি, যা বর্তমানে তিন লক্ষের কাছাকাছি পৌঁছে গিয়েছে। ই-বুক পড়ার প্রবণতা দিন দিন বাড়ছে। কারণ, এটি সস্তা ও সহজলভ্য। ই-বুক তৈরিতে ছাপানো বইয়ের চেয়ে কম খরচ হয় তাই ই-বুক নিঃসন্দেহে সাশ্রয়ী। আবার ই-বুক সহজলভ্যও। কারণ এটি ইন্টারনেট থেকে যখন খুশি সংগ্রহ করা যায়। আধুনিক যান্ত্রিক ও বিশ্বায়নের যুগের সাথে তাল মিলিয়ে চলতে সকল পাঠককেই ই-বুকের প্রতি আগ্রহী হতে হবে। কারণ, ই-বুক স্বল্পসময়ে ও সহজলভ্য উপায়ে বিনোদন ও জ্ঞানার্জনের আদর্শ মাধ্যম।"},{"question":"సమాజంలోని మూఢనమ్మకాల్ని నిర్మూలించడానికి మీరిచ్చే సలహాలు, సూచనలు ఆధారంగా చేసుకుని వ్యాసం వ్రాయండి.","answer":"సమాజం అంటే సమూహం అని అర్థం. మానవ సమాజమనగా మానవుల సమూహమని అర్థం. అనూచానంగా మనదేశంలో ‘మానవుల మనుగడ కల్పించేందుకై మహర్షులు కొన్ని నీతి నియమాల్ని ఏర్పాటుచేశారు. అలాగే మన సమాజంలో కొన్ని మూఢాచారాలు, మూఢనమ్మకాలు నెలకొనియున్నాయి. అయితే మానవాళి ఆ మూఢాచారాల్ని, మూఢనమ్మకాల్ని గుడ్డిగా నమ్మటం వల్ల పతనానికి దారితీశాయి. మానవాళి వృద్ధి చెందలేదు.కాలానుగతంగా నేడు మానవ సమాజంలో అనేక మార్పులు వచ్చాయి. బాల్యవివాహాలు, సతీసహగమనాలు, జీవహింస చెయ్యటం, ప్రకృతి వైద్యమంటూ మానవుల్ని వల్లకాటికి పంపడం, చేతబడులు చెయ్యటం, దుష్టశక్తుల్ని వశం చేసుకొనుట మున్నగు దురాచారాలు ఎన్నో నెలకొనియున్నాయి. అయితే వీటిని గ్రహించి కూకటి వ్రేళ్ళతో సమూలంగా నాశనం చేయుటకు కొంతమంది సంఘ సంస్కర్తలు నడుం బిగించారు.వారిలో కందుకూరి వీరేశలింగం పంతులు, ఈశ్వరచంద్ర విద్యాసాగర్, రాజారామమోహనరాయ్ వంటి పెద్దలు ముందుగా స్త్రీలకు ప్రత్యేక పాఠశాలల్ని ఏర్పాటు చేసి స్త్రీలకు విద్య నేర్పించారు. ఆ తర్వాత బాల్య వివాహాల్ని రద్దు చేసి శాసనాలతో ‘చట్టం చేశారు. వితంతు వివాహాల్ని పునరుద్ధరించారు. సమాజంలో దయ్యాలు, భూతాలు లేవని నిరూపించి ప్రజల్ని జాగృతులు చేశారు. అదేవిధంగా భూతవైద్యాన్ని, చేతబడుల్ని నిర్మూలించారు. శకునాల్ని నమ్మవద్దనీ, అవి కేవలం మానవుల చిత్తభ్రమలని తెలియజేశారు.ముఖ్యంగా మానవుల్లో నెలకొనియున్న అంటరానితనాన్ని నిర్మూలించారు. భగవంతుని సృష్టిలో మానవులందరూ ఒకటేయనీ, మూఢనమ్మకాల్ని తరిమి తరిమి కొట్టండనీ హెచ్చరించారు.కనుక మానవులందరు పరమత సహనాన్ని పాటిస్తూ, మంచిని గ్రహించాలి. సమాజంలో నెలకొనియున్న మూఢనమ్మకాల్ని తరిమికొట్టాలి."},{"question":"Ответьте на этот сложный вопрос: Какую медаль завоевала Шэрон Стюард на Играх Содружества в 1990 году?","answer":"Шэрон Стюард завоевала бронзовую медаль на Играх Содружества в 1990 году, в соревновании по бегу на 800 метров."},{"question":"Shin akwai banbanci tsakanin azuzuwan kalmomi da Nahahu?","answer":"Azuzuwan kalmomi da kuma rukunan nahawu duka abu guda ne; wato Ɗanjuma ne da Ɗanjummai. Dangane da abin da ya shafi wannan rubutu kuwa, mun kira su da suna Azuzuwan Kalmomi."},{"question":"Kebuluran meninggalkan kesanyanglebih burukkeranaorang yang lapar sanggup melakukan apa-apasahajauntukmengisi perut mereka.","answer":"Ayat di atas ialah ayat majmuk campuran"},{"question":"文章からキーワードを選び、その解釈を述べなさい。 物の値段が高くなって、家庭ではお金がかかって大変です。群馬県高崎市の団体は、困っている家庭のために「制服バンク」をしています。この団体は「フードバンクM・高崎」です。「制服バンク」では、群馬県の学校を卒業した人や家族に、制服などを寄付してもらいます。そして、新しい制服などを買うのが大変な人たちに渡しています。団体には、50ぐらいの学校の制服など200点が集まりました。ランドセルは、群馬県以外からの寄付もお願いしていて、20個集まりました。団体は、もっとたくさん集めたいと考えています。団体の人は「学校で使う物を買うのはほとんど3月で、10万円以上かかります。困っているときは、ぜひ利用してください」と話していました。","answer":"この文章に含まれるキーワードとその解釈は以下です。"},{"question":"வினா:                       மாமல்லபுரம் குடைவரைக் கோயில்களில் எத்தனை உள்ளன?(அ)      16(ஆ)     25(இ)      30(ஈ)       40","answer":"விடை:                     25தமிழ்நாட்டின் குடைவரை கட்டிடங்கள் தமிழ்நாட்டில் அமைந்த குடைவரைக் கோயில்கள், குகைச் சிற்பங்கள், குகை ஓவியங்களின் பட்டியல் பின்வருமாறுகழுகுமலை வெட்டுவான் கோயில்[3]அரகண்டநல்லூர்க் குடைவரைஅரளிப்பட்டிக் குடைவரைஆவூர்க் குடைவரைஏழடிப்பட்டம் சமணர் படுக்கைகள் கல்வெட்டுகள்கந்தன் குடைவரைகீழ்மாவிலங்கைக் குடைவரைகுடுமியான்மலை குடைவரைகுரங்கணில்முட்டம் குடைவரைகுன்றக்குடி குடைவரை கோயில்சாளுவன்குப்பம் அதிரணசண்ட பல்லவேஸ்வரம்சாளுவன்குப்பம் புலிக்குடைவரைசிங்கப்பெருமாள்கோயில் குடைவரைசிங்கவரம் குடைவரைசித்தன்னவாசல் குகை ஓவியங்கள்பசுபதேசுவரர் குடைவரைக் கோயில்ஏழடிப்பட்டம் சமணர் படுக்கைகள் கல்வெட்டுகள்சிதறால் மலைக் கோவில்சீயமங்கலம் குடைவரைக் கோயில்தளவானூர் குடைவரைக் கோயில்தாந்தோன்றிமலை கல்யாணவெங்கடரமணசுவாமி கோயில்திருக்கழுங்குன்றம் குடைவரைதிருக்கோளக்குடிக் குடைவரைதிருச்சிராப்பள்ளி குடைவரைதிருப்பரங்குன்றம் முருகன் கோவில்"},{"question":"Hoe kan ik bijdragen aan Spark?","answer":"Spark is een open source project en iedereen kan eraan bijdragen."},{"question":"Yaraanta Zinc-ga.","answer":"Calaamadaha ugu waa weyn waa koritaan xumocarruurta ah, timaha oo ka buuba (daata),dhaawacyo kala duwan oo maqaarka ah, maqaarfiifiiqan, nabarrada oo ciyaw (dhaqso) u raysanwaaya, caabuq soo noqnoqda, shuban ba’an,cunto rabitaan liita, dhadhan iyo urinta oo luma,daal, iyo ma dhaleysnimo raga ku timaadda."},{"question":"فرش ماشینی با چه جنسی پرزدهی کمتری دارد؟","answer":"فرش‌هایی که از جنس آکریلیک هیت ست شده هستند پرزدهی پایینی دارند. (الیاف آکریلیک به پشم نزدیک است )"},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਅਸੰਖ ਪੂਜਾ ਅਸੰਖ ਤਪ ਤਾਉ ॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 3 ਤੋਂ ਲਈ ਗਈ ਇੱਕ ਤੁਕ ਦਾ ਵਾਕ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਨਾਨਕ ਦੇਵ ਜੀ ਇਸ ਬਾਣੀ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਹਨ।ਇਸਦਾ ਮਤਲਬ ਇਹ ਹੈ,\\"ਕਈ ਜੀਵ ਪੂਜਾ ਕਰ ਰਹੇ ਹਨ। ਅਤੇ ਅਨਗਿਣਤ ਹੀ ਜੀਵ ਤਪ ਸਾਧ ਕਰ ਰਹੇ ਹਨ।\\""},{"question":"Em quais cidades japoneses foram explodidas as bombas nucleares?","answer":"As bombas atômicas estadunidenses “Little Boy” e “Fat Man” foram lançadas, respectivamente, nas cidades japonesas de Hiroshima, em 06 de Agosto de 1945, e Nagasaki, em 09 de Agosto de 1945. O papel dos bombardeamentos na rendição do Japão e a justificativa ética dos Estados Unidos para executar tal ataque tem sido objeto de debate acadêmico e popular há décadas. J. Samuel Walker escreveu em abril de 2005 sobre a historiografia recente sobre o assunto que \\"a controvérsia sobre o uso da bomba parece certa para continuar.\\" Ele escreveu: \\"A questão fundamental que tem dividido os estudiosos ao longo de um período de quase quatro décadas é se o uso da bomba era necessário para conseguir a vitória na Guerra do Pacífico em condições satisfatórias para os Estados Unidos\\"."},{"question":"লোপা টিভিতে একটি প্রামাণ্য চিত্র দেখছিল, একটি দেশের স্বৈরাচারী সরকারকে হটানোর জন্য বিরোধী দল ও জনগণ তুমুল আন্দোলন করছে এবং ঐ সরকারকে উচ্ছেদ না করা পর্যন্ত তারা রাস্তায় অবস্থান নিয়েছে। লোপা পাঠ্যবইয়ে পড়েছে স্বৈরাচারী সরকার পতনের জন্য বাংলাদেশেও গণআন্দোলন হয়েছে। পুনরায় সংসদীয় সরকার পদ্ধতি সংবিধানে অন্তর্ভুক্ত হয়েছে এবং একটি গণতান্ত্রিক দেশ হিসেবে আর্থ-সামাজিক ও সাংস্কৃতিক ক্ষেত্রে বাংলাদেশ এগিয়ে চলেছে।উদ্দীপকের শেষোক্ত বাক্যের যথার্থতা পাঠ্যপুস্তকের আলোকে বিশ্লেষণ কর।","answer":"সংবিধানে পুনরায় সংসদীয় পদ্ধতির অন্তর্ভুক্তি এবং আর্থ-সামাজিক ও সাংস্কৃতিক ক্ষেত্রে বাংলাদেশের এগিয়ে যাওয়া বিষয়ে— উদ্দীপকে নির্দেশিত বাক্যটি যথার্থ।১৯৯০ সালের গণআন্দোলনের কারণে সে বছরের ৬ই ডিসেম্বর জেনারেল এরশাদ পদত্যাগে বাধ্য হন। এরপর সকল দলের অংশগ্রহণে ১৯৯১ সালের ২৭শে ফেব্রুয়ারি অনুষ্ঠিত নির্বাচনের মাধ্যমে বাংলাদেশে সরকার পরিবর্তনের গণতান্ত্রিক ধারা চালু হয়। রাষ্ট্রপতি শাসিত সরকার থেকে সংসদীয় সরকার পদ্ধতি পুনঃপ্রবর্তন ও সংবিধানে তা অন্তর্ভুক্ত হয়। এরপর থেকে বিভিন্ন কার্যকর পরিকল্পনার মাধ্যমে অর্থনীতি, কৃষি, শিক্ষা, স্বাস্থ্য, চিকিৎসা, নারীর ক্ষমতায়ন, শিশু ও মাতৃ মৃত্যুহার হ্রাস, ক্রীড়াঙ্গন, প্রযুক্তি প্রতিটি ক্ষেত্রেই বাংলাদেশ এগিয়ে যাচ্ছে।উদ্দীপকে দেখা যায়, স্বৈরাচারী সরকার পতনের পর পুনরায় সংসদীয় সরকার প্রবর্তন হয়েছে এবং আর্থ-সামাজিক ও সাংস্কৃতিক ক্ষেত্রে উন্নয়ন সাধিত হচ্ছে। এখানে নব্বই পরবর্তী বাংলাদেশের রাজনৈতিক, অর্থনৈতিক ও অন্যান্য অবস্থার কথা বলা হয়েছে। বাংলাদেশে ১৯৯১ সালে গণতন্ত্র পুনর্যাত্রা করেছে। ১৯৭২ সালে বাংলাদেশে দারিদ্র্যের হার ছিল ৭০ শতাংশ। সরকারি বিভিন্ন নীতি ও কৃষক শ্রমিকসহ জনগণের সম্মিলিত চেষ্টায় বাংলাদেশে দারিদ্র্যের হার ২৪ শতাংশে নেমে এসেছে। বাংলাদেশকে ২০২১ সালের মধ্যে একটি মধ্যম আয়ের দেশে রূপান্তরিত করার লক্ষ্যে বাংলাদেশ সরকার কাজ করে যাচ্ছে। শিক্ষার হার পাকিস্তান আমলের ১৭ ভাগ থেকে বেড়ে ৬৫ ভাগে উন্নীত হয়েছে। নারীর ক্ষমতায়ন ও স্বাস্থ্যরক্ষা, শিশুদের সুরক্ষা, খাদ্য নিরাপত্তা অর্জনেও ব্যাপক অগ্রগতি হয়েছে।অতএব বলা যায়, নব্বই পরবর্তী সময়ে গণতন্ত্রের পুনর্যাত্রা শুরু হওয়ার পর নানা পরিকল্পনার মাধ্যমে বাংলাদেশ সকল ক্ষেত্রে দ্রুত এগিয়ে যাচ্ছে।"},{"question":"ചോദ്യം: MLB ചരിത്രത്തിലെ ഏറ്റവും കൂടുതൽ സ്ട്രൈക്കൌട്ടുകൾ ഉള്ളത് ആര്‌? ഉത്തരം:","answer":"മേജർ ലീഗ് ബേസ്ബോളിൽ ഏറ്റവും കൂടുതൽ സ്‌ട്രൈക്ക്ഔട്ടുകൾ നേടിയത് നോളൻ റയാനാണ്. 27 വർഷത്തെ റെക്കോർഡ് കരിയറിൽ അദ്ദേഹം 5,714 ബാറ്റർമാരെ പുറത്താക്കി."},{"question":"Chọn câu trả lời đúng cho câu hỏi sau: Mùa đông ở châu Nam Cực kéo dài mấy tháng?A. 5 thángB. 8 thángC. 10 tháng","answer":"Câu trả lời đúng: B. 8 thángMùa đông ở châu Nam Cực kéo dài từ tháng 3 đến tháng 10 hàng năm, trong đó tháng 7, 8 là thời điểm lạnh nhất. Nhiệt độ trung bình vào mùa đông thường khoảng - 60 tới - 65 độ C. Châu Nam Cực ghi nhận ngày lạnh nhất là 21/7/1983 với nhiệt độ nhiều nơi hạ tới - 98 độ C."},{"question":"కింది ప్రశ్నకు సమాధానం ఇవ్వండిసాధారణ కొల్లాయిడ్ ద్రావణానికి, మిసెల్లకు గల భేదం ఏమిటి?","answer":"1. కొన్ని పదార్థాలు అల్పగాఢతల వద్ద సాధారణబలమైన విద్యుద్విశ్లేషకాలుగా ప్రవర్తించే పదార్థాలు, అయితే అధిక గాఢతల వద్ద కొల్లాయిడ్ల ప్రవర్తనను ప్రదర్శిస్తాయి. దీనికి కారణం సముచ్ఛములను ఏర్పరచడం ఈ విధంగా సముచ్ఛయం చెంది ఏర్పడిన కణాలను మిసెల్లు అంటారు.2. వీటినే సముచ్ఛయ కొల్లాయిడ్లు అంటారు.3. ఇవి లయోఫిలిక్, లయోఫోబిక్ భాగాలు కలిగి ఉంటాయి.4. మిసెల్లలో 100 లేదా అంతకంటే ఎక్కువ సంఖ్యలో సాధారణ అణువులు ఉంటాయి.5. కొల్లాయిడ్ ద్రావణం విలీనంలో ఈ కొల్లాయిడ్లు వ్యక్తిగత విద్యుద్విశ్లేష్యకాలుగా తిరిగి మారతాయి."},{"question":"පහත ගීතය සම්පුර්ණ කරන්න.මා  අමතක වී යාවීදුරු රට ගියදා  නුඹ මා හැරදා","answer":"මා  අමතක වී යාවීදුරු රට ගියදා  නුඹ මා  හැරදාමා  අමතක වී යාවිකාලය හිමිහිට පියඹාවීකෙදිනක හෝ  අප හමුවේවීලොවට හොරා සැඟවී රහසේසැනසුනි නම් මා නුඹ තුරුලේමගෙන් නොලද රැකවල් මැද්දේපාළු කියයි නුඹ තනි යහනේමටත් හොරා ඉකිබිඳ රහසේනැවතුනිනම් නුඹ මා තුරුලේමෙවන් මිහිරි හැඟුමන් දෙහදේරැඳී තියේවිද හෙට දවසේමා  අමතක වී යාවී //"},{"question":"س273- دولة عربية حكمها جعفر النميري ؟","answer":"ج273- السودان"},{"question":"මනෝවිද්‍යාවේ පියා  ?","answer":"සිග්මන් ෆ්රොයිඩ්"},{"question":"ایا اخلاق موضوعي یا هدفي دي؟ ایا موږ کولی شو اخلاقي اصول ولرو چې په نړیواله کچه د ټولو کلتورونو او ټولنو لپاره معتبر وي؟","answer":"د اخلاقي تابعیت او مقصدیت تر مینځ بحث د اخلاقو مرکزي برخه ده. موضوع پوهان استدلال کوي چې اخلاق د شخصي احساساتو او کلتوري باورونو پر بنسټ والړ دي، له یو شخص څخه بل شخص او کلتور ته کلتور توپیر لري. هدف پوهان په دې باور دي چې ځینې اخلاقي اصول په نړیواله کچه معتبر دي، د انفرادي یا کلتوري لید څخه خپلواک دي. ننګونه د دې نړیوالو اصولو په پیژندلو کې ده، په مختلفو ټولنو کې د اخلاقي باورونو تنوع په پام کې نیولو سره."},{"question":"Décide si le mot «nord-ouest» est utilisé dans le même sens dans les deux phrases suivantes. Réponds par oui ou par non.Phrase 1: Le nord-ouest est ordinairement froid et pluvieux.Phrase 2: Or, en 1915, le professeur A. Lacroix découvrait dans des échantillons rapportés du nord-ouest de Madagascar, une roche comparable, mais non identique qu’il appela « fasibitikite ».","answer":"Réponse: non."},{"question":"Tìm những chi tiết hoang đường, kì ảo trong truyện Thánh Gióng. Những chi tiết đó có tác dụng gì trong việc thể hiện nội dung?","answer":"- Những chi tiết hoang đường, kì ảo trong truyện Thánh Gióng:+ Bà mẹ ướm vào vết chân lạ rất to ở trên đồng mà thụ thai.+ Mang thai dài tận mười hai tháng; ba tuổi mà cậu bé chẳng biết đi đứng, nói cười.+ Khi sứ giả đến tìm người tài giỏi giúp cứu nước, Gióng bỗng dưng cất tiếng nói với mẹ xin đi đánh giặc.+ Gióng lớn nhanh như thổi, ăn cơm bao nhiêu cũng không no, áo rộng bao nhiêu vừa mặc xong đã đứt chỉ.+ Nghe tin giặc đến, Gióng vươn vai biến thành một tráng sĩ cao lớn.+ Ngựa sắt mà kêu hí lại phun thêm lửa.+ Nhổ tre ven đường đánh giặc, giặc tan vỡ.+ Khi dẹp giặc xong, Gióng và ngựa sắt từ từ bay lên trời.+ Lửa ngựa phun thiêu cháy một làng, khiến tre ngả màu vàng óng; vết chân ngựa biến thành ao hồ,...- Tác dụng của những chi tiết trên trong việc thể hiện nội dung: Xây dựng biểu tưởng về một người anh hùng chống giặc ngoại xâm cứu nước, qua đó bộc lộ lòng yêu nước và sức mạnh của dân tộc."},{"question":"Ìlèdí","answer":"Ìlẹ̀dí fún ọmọdé, ìlẹ̀dí tàbí ìlàpọ̀n fún àgbà tàbí páàdì fún àwọn obìnrin jẹ́ ohun èlò kan tí ó máa ń gba omi bíi ìtọ̀ àti ìgbẹ́ ènìyàn dúró lára ọmọ ìkókó tàbí ọmọdé. Ó tún jẹ́ ohun èlò tí àwọn obìnrin máa ń lò láti fi gba ẹ̀jẹ̀ dúró lásìkò tí wọ́n bá ń ṣe ǹkan oṣù, tàbí tí wọ́n bá bímọ, bẹ́ẹ̀ wọ́n máa ń lòó láti fi fí ojú ara àwọn obìnrin tí wọ́n bá ṣiṣẹ́ abẹ fún. Ó ṣe pàtàkì kí wọ́n máa pààrọ̀ ìlẹ̀dí ní àìmọye ìgbà nínú ọjọ́ kan, ìyẹn bí ǹkan oṣù náà bá ṣe pọ̀ sí. Wọ́n máa ń ṣe ìlẹ̀dí látara àwọn ohun èlò oríṣiríṣi, ìyẹ̀n bí wọ́n bá ṣe fẹ́ kó rí.Ṣíṣe rẹ̀ dá lórí orílẹ̀-èdè tí wọ́n bá ti ń pèsè e rẹ̀, tabí ilé-iṣẹ́ tí wọ́n bá ti ń ṣeé jáde. Bí àpẹẹrẹ, orílẹ̀-èdè Amẹ́ríkà ń lo ohun-èlò Kotex láti pèsè ìlẹ̀dí tí wọ́n ń pè ní Always, Equate, àti Stayfree. Ìlẹ̀dí Lil-lets náà wà káàkiri àwọn orílẹ̀-èdè tí wọ́n ti ń sọ èdè Gẹ̀ẹ́sì. Irúfẹ́ àwọn ìlẹ̀dí tí a ti mẹ́nu bà yí kò sí fún àwọn aláàárẹ̀ tí agbẹ̀du ìtọ̀ wọn ti daṣẹ́ sílẹ̀, àmọ́ àwọn mìíràn máa ń lò wọ́n fún irúfẹ́ àwọn aláàárẹ̀ bẹ́ẹ̀. Bí ó tilẹ̀ jẹ́ wípé àwọn olùpèsè àwọn ohun-èlò yìí kìí sọ gbogbo ohun tí wọ́n fi pèlò ọjà wọn jáde, àmọ́ àwọn ohun tí ó gbajúmọ̀ nínú rẹ̀ ni bleached rayon, (cellulose tí a ṣe látara wood pulp), òwú àti iké wà. Láfikún, wọ́n máa ń fi tùràrí aládìídùn àti oògùn apakòkòrò àìfojúrí si. Wọ́n máa ń fi àwọn èròjà ẹbu láílọ́ọ̀nù si kí ó le ní agbára láti gba omi dúró, èyí ni ó máa ń wú púkẹ́ nínú ìlẹ̀dí nígbà tí omi wọ́n bá wọ̀ọ́.Lápapọ̀, bí wọ́n ṣe to àwọn èròjà tí a ti kà sẹ́yìn yí lẹ́sẹẹ́sẹ ni: \\"èròja Kotex tí wọ́n lọ̀ pọ̀ mọ́ ẹbu láílọ́ọ̀nù ni wọ́n fi sí àárín òwú tí wọ́n fi òórùn adídùn pò, òwú yìí ni wọ́n rán mọ́ aṣọ fúlọ́fúlọ́ tí wọ́n fi ike gbámú ní eteetí kí ó lè ṣeé wọ̀ sí abẹ́ aṣọ fún ẹnikẹ́ni tí ó bá fẹ́ lòó. Láti sọ ìlẹ̀dí tí wọ́n ti lò nù, a lè sọọ́ sí inú àpò tabí ààtàn tí a bò, bẹ́ẹ̀ ni wọ́n lè gbe lọ sí ilé-iṣẹ́ tí wọ́n ti ń ṣe àtúnrọ àwọn ohun-èlò kí wọ́n fi ṣe ǹkan mìíràn jáde fún lílò. Oríṣiríṣi ìlẹ̀dí ni ó wà tí a lè sọnù."},{"question":"قم بكتابة مقال يجيب على هذا السؤال من أين أتى اسم مدينة الصويرة ؟.","answer":"أقدم الإشارات التاريخية العربية للموقع ترجع إلى القرن العاشر الميلادي، بأسماء «المعمورة» أو «الحلق» أو «حلق سبو». ذكر لابن عذاري المراكشي|ابن عذاري المراكشي اسم «المعمورة» في كتابه «المعجب في تلخيص أخبار المغرب» كتسمية لمصب نهر سبو في المحيط الأطلسي. يرجع بعض المؤرخين (و ضمنهم أبو القاسم الزياني) تأسيس المدينة إلى بني يفرن، في القرن العاشر الميلادي، قبل أن يبسط المرابطون حكمهم على منطقة الغرب الإسلامي."},{"question":"MAGTA LAGA BIXINAYO HADDII HAWEENEY LA DILO !SINAANTA DHIIGGA MUSLIMIINTA RAG IYO DUMAR?","answer":"Waxaa ah mid uu ka yaq yaqsado ruuxa damiirka aadaminimo uu kujiro, in marka ay nooshahay qofka dumarka ihi aysan wax shuqul ah ku lahayn qolada ay ka dhalatay hiil iyo hoona aan looga baahnayn, laakiin maalinka ay dhimato ay magteeda iska qaadanayaan dad ay isku qabiil wadaagaan. Marka ay nooshahay waxaa la yiraahdaa; “Naagi tag mooyee tol ma leh”. Laakiin dhiigeeda ayaa hadhaw laga dhacaa ilmeheedii iyo saygeedii. Halkaasna waxaa ka caddaanaya in ay mararka qaarkood ay dumarku yihiin badeeco si khayaano ah ugu yaalla maal ka samayn. Marka ay guursanayso waxaa si aan qarsoodi lahayn looga gaday ninka guursanaya iyo ehelkiis haddii ay kaalmaynayaan. Marka ay dhimatana ninkii horay xoolihiisa ugu baxshay iyo caruurtii ay ka geeriyootay waxba kama helayaan. Sida aan ogsoonnahay waxa uu Ilaahay ku caddeeyey guud ahaanba aayadaha ka hadlaya magdhawga, in dhibanaha la door geliyo tii u roon laba midood; in mag laga siiyo qofkii laga dilay iyo in loo dilo qofkii ka dilay. Khiyaar gelintaasi waxa ay qof kaste oo caqli adeegsanaya tusinaysaa in Shariicadu ay la muusanowsan tahay qofka qofkiisii waayey. "},{"question":"ကျွန်ုပ်၏အင်္ဂလိပ်စာကို မည်သို့တိုးတက်နိုင်မည်နည်း။","answer":"ဤအရာများသည် သင်၏စကားပြောအင်္ဂလိပ်စာကို တိုးတက်စေရန် သင်အသုံးပြုနိုင်သော နည်းပညာများဖြစ်သည်။စကားပြောပါ။ : အခြေခံအားဖြင့် အင်္ဂလိပ်စကား ပိုကောင်းအောင်ပြောရန် အကောင်းဆုံးနည်းလမ်းမှာ စကားများများပြောခြင်းဖြစ်သည်။ တတ်နိုင်သမျှ မတူညီသောလူများနှင့် မကြာခဏလေ့ကျင့်ပါ။ သင်၏မိတ်ဆွေများ၊ ၎င်းတို့၏မိသားစုများ၊ လုပ်ဖော်ကိုင်ဖက်များ၊ အတန်းဖော်များ၊ ရုံးစာတိုက်နှင့် သင်သွားရောက်လည်ပတ်သည့် အခြားနေရာများရှိ အင်္ဂလိပ်စကားပြောဆိုသူများနှင့် စကားများများပြောပါ။ အကယ်၍ သင်သည် သင့်နိုင်ငံ၌ သင်ယူနေပါက၊ အတန်းပြီးနောက် သင့်အတန်းဖော်များနှင့် တွေ့ဆုံခြင်း၊ ဘာသာစကားဖလှယ်သည့် လုပ်ဖော်ကိုင်ဖက်တစ်ဦးကို ရှာဖွေခြင်း သို့မဟုတ် သင်ယူသူများ၏ အွန်လိုင်းအသိုင်းအဝိုင်းတွင် ပါဝင်ခြင်းဖြင့် သင်၏လေ့ကျင့်ချိန်ကို တိုးမြှင့်လိုက်ပါ။သင်၏ပြောဆိုမှုများကို ပြန်လည်သုံးသပ်ပါ။ : သင့်စကားဝိုင်းပြီးသွားသောအခါတွင် ပြန်လည်သုံးသပ်ရန် အချိန်ယူပါ။ ဘယ်လိုသွားတာလဲ။ ဘယ်လောက်နားလည်မယ်ထင်လဲ။ အဲဒီအကြောင်းအရာနဲ့ ပတ်သက်ပြီး သင်ဘယ်လောက်အဆင်ပြေခဲ့လဲ။ မသိတဲ့ စကားလုံးတွေ တွေ့ဖူးလား။ ဤနည်းဖြင့် ၎င်းကို တွေးတောခြင်းက နောက်တစ်ကြိမ်ပြောဆိုမှုအတွက် သင်၏ယုံကြည်မှုကို တိုးစေသည်။နားထောင်ပြီး ဖတ်ပါ။ : စကားပြောဖို့အတွက် စကားလုံးတွေလိုပါတယ်။ စာသင်ချိန်သည် ဝေါဟာရလေ့လာရန်အတွက် ကောင်းမွန်သော်လည်း သင့်အား သင်တိုးပေးနိုင်သည့် အခြားနည်းလမ်းများ ရှိပါသည်။ ရုပ်ရှင်ကြည့်ခြင်း၊ တေးဂီတနားထောင်ခြင်း၊ ရေဒီယိုနှင့် ပေါ့တ်ကာစ်များနားထောင်ခြင်း။ စာအုပ်များ၊ မဂ္ဂဇင်းများနှင့် ဘလော့ဂ်များကို ဖတ်ပါ။ နားထောင်ခြင်းနှင့် စာဖတ်သည့်အခါ၊ စိတ်ဝင်စားဖွယ်ကောင်းသော အသုံးအနှုန်းများ၊ ဘန်းစကားအသုံးအနှုန်းများနှင့် တူညီသောအသုံးအနှုန်းများကို ရှာဖွေပါ၊ ဤအကြောင်းအရာအသစ်ကို ချရေးပြီး သင်နှင့်မရင်းနှီးသည့်အရာများကို ရှာဖွေပါ။ မှတ်စုများပြင်ဆင်ပါ။ : စကားပြောရာတွင် ကြောက်ရွံ့မှု၏ တစ်စိတ်တစ်ပိုင်းမှာ ဘာပြောရမှန်းမသိသည့် ခံစားချက်ဖြစ်သည်။ ဒါကို တိုက်ဖျက်ဖို့အတွက် မှတ်စုများကို ပြင်ဆင်ပါ။ မင်းဆရာဝန်ဆီသွားနေတာလား။ သင်ချိန်းဆိုခြင်းမပြုမီ သင့်အခြေအနေနှင့်ပတ်သက်သော ဝေါဟာရနှင့် သင်လိုအပ်မည့် အသုံးများသော အသုံးအနှုန်းအချို့ကို သုတေသနပြုပါ။ ဘေလ်မပေးမီ၊ စားသောက်ဆိုင်တွင် စားသောက်ခြင်း၊ အလုပ်အင်တာဗျူးများ၊ တိုင်ကြားချက်တစ်ခု ပြုလုပ်ခြင်း သို့မဟုတ် သင်စိတ်ပူပန်စေမည့် အခြားအခြေအနေများအတွက် အသုံးပြုပါ။သင့်အသံကို မှတ်တမ်းတင်ပါ။ : လူအများစုသည် ၎င်းတို့၏အသံကို မှတ်တမ်းတင်ထားသည်ကို မကြားချင်ကြသော်လည်း၊ ၎င်းသည် သင်၏စကားပြောခြင်းကို မြှင့်တင်ရန်အတွက် အလွန်အကျိုးရှိသောနည်းလမ်းဖြစ်သည်။ တိပ်ခွေပေါ်တွင် သင့်ကိုယ်သင် ကြားနေရခြင်းသည် သင်သဘောမပေါက်နိုင်သောအရာများကို ပြသသည်။ အခြားတစ်ဖက်တွင်၊ သင်၏စကားသည် သင်ထင်သည်ထက် များစွာသာလွန်ကြောင်း ကြားသိရသည့်အတွက် အံ့ဩသွားနိုင်သည်။ ဘောနပ်စ်အမှတ်များအတွက်၊ သင်၏အသံသွင်းချက်ကို သင့်ဆရာ သို့မဟုတ် မူရင်းစကားပြောသူမိတ်ဆွေထံ ယူဆောင်ပြီး သင့်အား တုံ့ပြန်ချက်ပေးခိုင်းပါ။စကားလုံးတစ်လုံးတည်းမဟုတ်ဘဲ စကားစုများကို လေ့လာပါ။ : သင်၏ သွက်လက်မှုကို တိုးမြှင့်ရန် နောက်ထပ် အကြံပြုချက်မှာ စကားလုံးများထက် စကားစု အမျိုးမျိုးကို အသုံးပြု၍ ပြောဆိုရန် ဖြစ်သည်။ (မင်းရဲ့ မိခင်ဘာသာစကားနဲ့ တစ်ချိန်လုံး ဒီလိုလုပ်နေတာ ဖြစ်နိုင်တယ်။) \\"ဟဲလို၊ ဒီနေ့ နေကောင်းလား\\" လို့ အလိုအလျောက် မေးမယ့်အစား \\"What's up, man?\\" ကဲ့သို့သော အခြားအသုံးအနှုန်းများကို ရွေးချယ်ခြင်းဖြင့် ၎င်းကို ရောနှောလိုက်ပါ။ \\"ဟေ့ကောင်!\\" ဒါမှမဟုတ် \\"ဘယ်လိုနေလဲ သူငယ်ချင်း\\" (သတိထားပါ- အချို့သောအသုံးအနှုန်းများသည် အလွန်အလွတ်သဘောဖြစ်ပြီး အချို့သောအခြေအနေများအတွက် မသင့်တော်ပါ။)ပျော်ပါ : သင်ပျော်နေတဲ့အခါ အသစ်တစ်ခုကို သင်ယူရတာ ပိုလွယ်ပါတယ်။ အထီးကျန်နေချိန်၊ အင်္ဂလိပ်လို နာမည်ကြီးသီချင်းတွေနဲ့အတူ သီဆိုခြင်း သို့မဟုတ် ကျပန်းရွေးချယ်ထားသော အကြောင်းအရာများအတွက် တစ်မိနစ်ကြာ \\"လက်ငင်းပြောဆိုမှုများ\\" ပြုလုပ်ခြင်းဖြင့် သင်၏ စကားပြောလေ့ကျင့်မှုထဲသို့ ရီစရာကို ထည့်သွင်းပါ။"},{"question":"Sur quel continent se trouve la France ?","answer":"Le continent où se trouve la France s’appelle l’Europe. L’Europe compte 53 pays, dont la France."},{"question":"Sheeg Salaada Faralka (Waajib) Ah Oo Haweenka Waajib Ku Ahayn?","answer":"Waa Salaada Jimcaha Ah."},{"question":"Hãy hoàn thiện đoạn văn sau: Lịch thi đấu U16 Đông Nam Á 2022: 31/7 - 17:00: Việt Nam 5-1 Singapore 31/7 - 20:00: Indonesia 2-0 Philippines Lịch thi đấu vòng 10 V-League 2022: 31/7 - 17:00: Thanh Hóa 1-0 Viettel (On Sports +) 31/7 - 19:15: Hà Nội 2-1 SLNA (VTV6, VTV5 On Football, Next Sports) Lịch thi đấu chung kết bóng đá nữ châu Âu 2022: 31/7 - 23:00: Anh 2-1 Đức Lịch thi đấu vòng 1 Ligue 2: 31/7 - 00:00: Guingamp 4-0 Pau FC Lịch thi đấu tranh Siêu cúp Pháp: 1/8 - 01:00: Paris SG 4-0 Nantes Lịch thi đấu tranh Siêu cúp Đức 31/7 - 01:30: Leipzig 3-5 Bayern Munich.","answer":"Lịch thi đấu giao hữu CLB: 31/7 - 01:15: Tottenham 0-1 Roma 31/7 - 01:30: Inter Milan 2-2 Lyon 31/7 - 06:30: New York Red Bulls 0-2 Barca 31/7 - 09:00: Real Madrid 2-0 Juventus 31/7 - 22:00: MU 1-1 Rayo Vallecano 1/8 - 00:00: Leicester 1-0 Sevilla 1/8 - 00:45: Leeds Utd 6-2 Cagliari 1/8 - 00:45: Wolves 1-1 Farence 1/8 - 01:30: Napoli 1-1 Mallorca."},{"question":"Ndàx man ngaa jubbanti mbind mii?(Fàttalikuleen,) ba Muusaa waxee aw nitam: \\"Yàlla digal na leen ngeen reyu nag\\". Ñu ne ko: \\"Moo ndax danga nuy ñaawal? \\". Mu ne: \\"Yàlla na ma Yàlla musal ci bokk ci way-réer ña\\".","answer":"Waaw! Mi ngii:(Fàttlikuleen,) ba Muusaa wàxee aw nitam: \\"Yàlla digal na léen ngéen ray u nag\\". Ñu ne ko: \\"Moo ndàx da nga nu'y ñaawal? \\". Mu ne: \\"Yàlla na ma Yàlla musal ci bokk ci wayréer ña\\"."},{"question":"Est-ce que tu peux me raconter une blague ?","answer":"Est-ce que tu peux me raconter une blague ?La plage dit à l’océan: dire que tout le monde aime l’eau c’est assez vague."},{"question":"Tôi có cháu trai, năm nay 4 tuổi, đi khám bác sỹ mắt xác định bị cận thị, một bên 9, một bên 10. Hiện cháu đang đeo kính cận nhưng do còn nhỏ nên không đeo liên tục. Xin cho lời khuyên về cách điều trị để gia đình thực hiện.","answer":"Bố mẹ phải tìm cách để cho con chấp nhận việc đeo kính liên tục, ví dụ như cho con tự chọn gọng kính, cho con thấy rằng khi con nhìn, vẽ, chơi… dễ dàng hơn. Với độ tuổi này cần khám định kỳ 3 tháng/lần để theo dõi sự thay đổi của số kính; kiểm tra tổn thương ở đáy mắt do cận thị cao gây ra. Từ đó bác sĩ sẽ cho bạn những lời khuyên cụ thể.Trường hợp của cháu nên tránh các vận động mạnh như chơi các trò chơi dễ bị chấn thương mắt."},{"question":"যে-কোন নতুন সদস্যই পরিচালনা পর্ষদের নির্বাচনের মাধ্যমে সহযোগী সদস্যের মর্যাদায় আসীন হতে পারে। পরবর্তীতে সম্ভাব্যতা যাচাইয়ের পরই পূর্ণ সদস্য হতে পারবে। ফিজি এবং মার্কিন যুক্তরাষ্ট্র আইসিসির প্রথমদিককার সহযোগী সদস্য ছিল।১৯৮১ সালে শ্রীলঙ্কা সদস্য হিসাবে যোগদান করে।১৯৮৯ সালে আবারো এর নাম পরিবর্তন করা হয়। এবার নামকরণ করা হয় 'ইন্টারন্যাশনাল ক্রিকেট কাউন্সিল' যা অদ্যাবধি প্রচলিত। ১৯৯১ সালে দক্ষিণ আফ্রিকা পুণরায় পূর্ণ সদস্য হিসেবে নির্বাচিত হয়। এরপর ১৯৯২ সালে জিম্বাবুয়েকে পূর্ণ সদস্যের মর্যাদা দেয়া হয়।[2]  ২০০০ সালে বাংলাদেশকে ১০ম টেস্টভূক্ত দল হিসেবে অন্তর্ভূক্ত করা হয়।[2] সাম্প্রতিক সময়ে সর্বশেষ আফগানিস্তান ও আয়ারল্যান্ডকে টেস্ট খেলুড়ে দল হিসেবে উন্নিত করা হয় [4]। বর্তমানে আইসিসির সর্বমোট সদস্য দলের সংখ্যা ১০৫টি।[5][6]উপরের অনুচ্ছেদের জন্য একটি শিরোনাম তৈরি করুন","answer":"আন্তর্জাতিক ক্রিকেট কাউন্সিলের সদস্যদের তালিকা |"},{"question":"Hãy tìm một số hình ảnh  có trục đối xứng trong thực tế.","answer":"Một số hình ảnh có trục đối xứng trong thực tiễn: +) Hình con bướm+) Hình chiếc lá+) Hình con chuồn chuồnTrên thực tế, có nhiều hình khác có trục đối xứng, bạn có thể tự tìm thêm."},{"question":"Wann wurde der Film \\"Leo: Bloody Sweet\\" veröffentlicht und wer sind die Hauptakteure? ","answer":"Der tamilischsprachige Film Leo: Bloody Sweet (abgekürzt Leo) wurde 2023 von dem Regisseur Lokesh Kanagaraj veröffentlicht. Die Hauptrollen spielen Joseph Vijay Chandrasekhar (bekannt unter dem Namen Vijay) als Parthiban/Leo Das, Sanjay Balraj Dutt als Antony Das, Srinivasa Sarja (bekannt unter dem Namen Arjun) als Harold Das und Trisha Krishnan als Sathya.  "},{"question":"Write a dialogue between two friends discussing the impact of literature on their lives.","answer":"दो दोस्तों के बीच एक संवाद बनाएं जिनमें साहित्य के उनके जीवन पर क्या प्रभाव है।"},{"question":"‘Yahoo’ lawọn eleyii n ṣe l’Ajah ti EFCC fi ko wọn","answer":"Mejilelogun (22) ni gbogbo wọn, afurasi ọdaran ni wọn, bi wọn ṣe maa lu awọn eeyan ni jibiti lori atẹ ayelujara ni wọn n fojoojumọ aye wọn wa, idi iṣẹ buruku ọhun si lọwọ ti tẹ wọn lọjọ Iṣẹgun, Tusidee, ọsẹ yii.Atẹjade kan latọdọ Ọgbẹni Wilson Uwajuren to jẹ Alukoro fun ajọ to n gbogun ti iwa jibiti ati ṣiṣẹ owo mọkumọku nni, EFCC, sọ pe inu ile oniyara-pupọ kan to wa ni Terra Annex Estate, laduugbo Ṣangotẹdo, l’Ajah, nipinlẹ Eko lawọn afurasi naa fori pamọ si, ibẹ ni wọn ti n huwa apamọlẹkun-jaye wọn.O ni aipẹ yii lawọn gba ipe latọdọ awọn araadugbo kan ti wọn fura si awọn gende wọnyi, wọn ni ki EFCC waa bawọn yẹ iṣẹ ọwọ wọn wo, lawọn ọtẹlẹmuyẹ ba bẹrẹ si i tọpasẹ awọn afurasi naa tọwọ fi ba wọn.Orukọ wọn ni Muyiwa Adetọla, Adeolu Demilade, Abel Oriṣetimẹyin, Lekan Ademọla, Abayọmi Qudus, Isaac Chibueze, Ayẹni Ọlanrewaju, Aminu Kelvin, Ajama Patrick, and Nesta Olotu.Awọn to ku ni Odaro Edogiawere, Ayọ Balogun, Mustapha Hassan, Musbaudeen Ọlamilekan, Adewumi Adebayo, Charles Akpene, Joshua Ugwuomore, Ayẹni Damilola, Ogundare Kayọde, Kara Uzuegbu, Akindele Samuel, ati Ọladimeji Ashiru.Alukoro EFCC ni gbogbo awọn ti a darukọ yii ti n ran awọn ọtẹlẹmuyẹ ajọ naa lọwọ ninu iwadii wọn. Awọn irinṣẹ bii kọmputa alagbeletan, foonu ati awọn nnkan mi-in ni wọn ka mọ wọn lọwọ.O ni tiwadii ba ti pari, gbogbo wọn lawọn maa wọ de kootu,"},{"question":"இந்திய தேசத்தின் தந்தை யார் ?","answer":"மகாத்மா காந்தி என்று அழைக்கப்படும் மோகன்தாஸ் கரம்சந்த் காந்தி, இந்தியாவில் நமது தேசத்தின் தந்தை என்று அழைக்கப்படும் ஒரு தேசியத் தலைவர் மற்றும் சமூக சீர்திருத்தவாதி ஆவார்."},{"question":"Anisan'ny baobab lehibe indrindra misy ny baobab fanta-daza hita ao Mahajanga. Firy taona no nomina io baobab io ?","answer":"Ny baobab ao Mahajanga dia eo amin'ny 275 taona .( mety latsaka na mahery)."},{"question":"السؤال: متى تم صلح الحديبية؟","answer":"الإجابة: في العام السادس من الهجرة."},{"question":"请解释“八字没见一撇”的意思。","answer":"这句谚语比喻事情毫无眉目,未见端绪。"},{"question":"what important event is this text about: جم اولوگنویان عضو تیم ملی ترکیه بود که در مسابقات قهرمانی جام جهانی تیمی ۲۰۰۹ که در باکو، جمهوری آذربایجان برگزار شد، به مقام قهرمانی رسید. وی در مسابقات قهرمانی تکواندو جهان ۲۰۰۹ که در کپنهاگ دانمارک برگزار شد، مدال برنز را از آن خود کرد. در همان سال، وی در مسابقات قهرمانی زیر ۲۱ سال اروپا که در ویگو اسپانیا برگزار گردید، قهرمان اروپا شد. وی در مسابقات قهرمانی تکواندو اروپا ۲۰۱۰ که در سن پترزبورگ روسیه برگزار شد، مدال برنز را در دسته خروس‌وزن بدست آورد.","answer":"در این متن بیش از یک رویداد مهم وجود دارد که بین آنها تفاوتی وجود ندارد. این رویدادها عبارتند از:مسابقات قهرمانی جام جهانی تیمی تکواندو جهان ۲۰۰۹ در آذربایجانمسابقات قهرمانی تکواندو جهان ۲۰۰۹  در دانمارکمسابقات قهرمانی زیر ۲۱ سال اروپا در اسپانیامسابقات قهرمانی تکواندو اروپا ۲۰۱۰ در روسیه"},{"question":"Bu metin hangi önemli olayla ilgilidir: Bunun üzerine 10 yıldır ayrı çalışan iki sol örgüt, Halk ve Bayrak partileri Davud Han'a karşı yeniden birleştiler. Komünist Perşem Partisi'nden Mir Ali Ekber Heybar'ın öldürülmesi üzerine ülke içinde komünistlerin Davud Han'a karşı başlattıkları muhalefet, 17 Nisan 1978 tarihinde yapılan cenaze töreni, hükûmet darbesinin başlangıcı oldu. Heybar'ın cenaze törenine 11 bin kişinin katılması Davud Han'ı endişelendirdi. Davud Han, hemen harekete geçerek aralarında Babrak Karmal ve Nur Muhammed Teraki’nin de bulunduğu komünist Halk ve Perçem liderlerini 24 Nisan'da hapsetti. Tutuklananlardan Halk kanadı lideri Hafızullah Amin'in ordu içindeki gücüne dayanarak gerçekleştirdiği darbeyle Davud Han devrildi, kendisi ve aile üyelerinin çoğu öldürüldü, 27 Nisan 1978 tarihinde Afganistan Demokratik Cumhuriyeti'nin kurulduğu ilan edildi.","answer":"darbeyle"},{"question":"नेपालमा कति जिल्ला छन् ?","answer":"नेपालमा ७७ जिल्ला छन् ।"},{"question":"Given the below title and summary of an article, generate a short article or the beginning of a long article to go along with them. Title: బైరిపురం: పంచాయితీ ఎన్నికల్లో ఒక్కసారి కూడా ఓటు వేయని గ్రామమిది.. ఏకగ్రీవాలతో ఇక్కడ అభివృద్ధి జరిగిందా?nSummary: ఇప్పటివరకు జరిగిన ఏ పంచాయితీ ఎన్నికల్లోనూ ఆ గ్రామ పంచాయతీలో ఉన్న 1,100 మంది ఓటర్లకు ఓటు వేసే అవసరమే రాలేదు.nArticle (Max 500 characters):","answer":"పంచాయితీ ఎన్నికలు ఒక్కసారి కూడా జరగని ఆ గ్రామ పంచాయితీ శ్రీకాకుళం జిల్లాలో ఉంది. ఏకగ్రీవాలు ప్రస్తుత పంచాయితీ ఎన్నికల్లో హాట్ టాపిక్. అయితే, పంచాయితీ వ్యవస్థ ఏర్పడినప్పటి నుంచి ఏకగ్రీవమే తప్ప...ఎన్నికలే జరగని గ్రామ పంచాయతీ బైరిపురం. ఇది ఆంధ్రా-ఒడిశా సరిహద్దుల్లో ఉంది. బైరిపురానికి మరో ప్రత్యేకత కూడా ఉంది. ఈ ఏకగ్రీవ పంచాయితీలో ఇప్పటివరకూ ఒక్క పోలీసు కేసు కూడా నమోదు కాకపోవడం విశేషం. ‘‘ఆ ఊళ్లో ఒక్క పంచాయతీ ఎన్నికా జరగలేదు.. ఒక్క కేసూ నమోదవ్వలేదు’’అయితే ఇక్కడి ప్రజల మధ్య వివాదాలు రాకుండా ఉండలేదు. "},{"question":"Ẹwọn n run nimu Ọmọlade, iya onirẹsi lo lu ni jibiti owo nla n’Ileefẹ","answer":"Apo irẹsi ọgọrun-un ni wọn ni Oyetoro Ọmọlade gba lọwọ Alhaja Eluwọle Sẹrifat lọja tuntun Odo-Ogbe, niluu Ileefẹ, lai sanwo, idi niyi to fi dero ile-ẹjọ Majisreeti lọsẹ to kọja.Nnkan bii aago kan ọsan ọjọ kẹwaa, oṣu kẹfa, ọdun yii, ni Ọmọlade, ẹni ọdun mẹtalelogoji, lọọ gba irẹsi naa, eleyii ti owo rẹ le ni miliọnu meji naira (#2,050,000.00).Gẹgẹ bi agbefọba to n ṣe ẹjọ naa ṣe sọ, adehun ọjọ marun-un pere lo wa laarin Ọmọlade ati Alhaja Eluwọle pe yoo fi sanwo irẹsi yii, ṣugbọn ṣe ni olujẹjọ kuna lati mu adehun aarin wọn ṣẹ.O ni ṣe lo sọ owo irẹsi yẹn di tiẹ, eleyii to nijiya labẹ ipin irinwo o din mẹtadindinlogun (383) ati okoolenirinwo o din ẹyọ kan (419) abala ikẹrinlelọgbọn ofin iwa ọdaran tipinlẹ Ọṣun.Lẹyin ti olujẹjọ sọ pe oun ko jẹbi ẹsun meji ti wọn fi kan an ni agbẹjọro rẹ, Ademọla Adeyẹmọ, rọ ile-ẹjọ lati fun un ni beeli pẹlu irọrun.Ninu idajọ rẹ, Majisreeti A.A. Ayẹni faaye beeli silẹ fun olujẹjọ pẹlu ẹgbẹrun lọna ẹẹdẹgbẹta naira ati oniduuro meji ni iye kan naa. Lẹyin naa lo sun igbẹjọ si ọjọ kẹrinlelogun, oṣu kẹsan-an, ọdun yii.Ninu iroyin mi-in, awọn ọlọpaa ti wọ ọmọkunrin ẹni ọdun mẹẹẹdọgbọn kan, Felix Iyokegh, lọ si kootu, ọjọ kẹtala, oṣu kẹjọ, ọdun yii, lo ji owo ni otẹẹli to ti n ṣiṣẹ gẹgẹ bii manija.Agbefọba to n ṣe ẹjọ naa, Inspẹkitọ Emmanuel Abdullahi, ṣalaye fun kootu pe ṣe ni wọn gba Felix gẹgẹ bii manija nileetura ACJAP Guest House, to wa lagbegbe Mokuro, niluu Ileefẹ.Ṣugbọn ṣe lo ji ẹgbẹrun lọna aadoje naira (#130,000) to jẹ ti Ọgbẹni Taiwo Awoṣeemọ lọjọ naa, eleyii to nijiya labẹ ofin iwa ọdaran tipinlẹ Ọṣun n lo. Agbẹjọro rẹ, Barisita Okoh Wonder, ṣeleri pe ti ile-ẹjọ ba le fun un ni beeli, yoo fi awọn oniduuro ti wọn lorukọ silẹ, bẹẹ ni ko ni i sa lọ fun igbẹjọ.Majisreeti A. A. Ayẹni fun Felix ni beeli pẹlu ẹgbẹrun lọna ọgọrun-un naira ati oniduuro meji ni iye kan naa. Lẹyin naa lo sun igbẹjọ si ọjọ kẹrinlelogun, oṣu kẹsan-an, ọdun yii."},{"question":"Sheeg Maxaal La Oran Jiray Ninkii Dilay Cali Bin Abii Daalib?","answer":"Waxa La Oran Jiray Ninkii Dilay Cali Bin Abii Daalib C/Raxmaan Bin Muljan."},{"question":"வினா:மெக்கன்சி குளோபல் இன்ஸ்டிடியூட் என்ற நிறுவனம் உலகின் 46 நாடுகளில் மேற்கொள்ளப்படும் 800 விதமான வேலைகளை பகுப்பாய்வு செய்ததில் உலகின் ஐந்தில் ஒரு மடங்கு வேலைகள் ரோபாட்களில் பயன்பாட்டால் பறிபோகும் என்று கண்டறிந்துள்ளது.ஜெர்மனி மற்றும் அமெரிக்கா போன்ற பணக்கார நாடுகளில் உள்ள மூன்றில் ஒரு பங்கு தொழிலாளர்கள் மற்ற வேலைகளுக்கு தக்கவைத்துக்கொள்ளப்படுவார்கள் என்றும் அந்த அறிக்கையில் கூறப்பட்டுள்ளது. இயந்திரங்களை இயக்குபவர்கள் மற்றும் உணவுத் தயாரிப்பு பணிகளில் ஈடுபட்டுள்ளவர்கள் இதன் காரணமாக அதிகளவில் பாதிக்கப்படுவார்கள் என்று அந்த அறிக்கை கூறுகிறது.தானியங்கிமயம் செய்வதற்கு அதிகம் செலவிட இயலாத ஏழை நாடுகள் வேலை இழப்பினால் பாதிக்கப்படாதென்று மெக்கன்சி நிறுவனம் தெரிவித்துள்ளது.இந்தியாவை பொறுத்தவரை 9 சதவீத வேலைகள் மட்டுமே வளர்ந்து வரும் தொழில்நுட்பங்களால் பாதிக்கப்படுமென்றும் அதில் குறிப்பிடப்பட்டுள்ளது.அடமானத் தொழில் செய்வோர், சட்டம் சார்ந்த பணியாளர்கள், கணக்காளர்கள், மற்றும் அலுவலக உதவிப் பணியாளர்கள் இந்த ரோபோ பெருக்கத்தால் வேலை இழக்கும் அபாயத்தில் இருப்பர். மனித தொடர்புகள் தேவைப்படும் வேல...அதிகபட்சம் 4000 எழுத்துகளுக்கு கட்டுரையைத் தொடரவும்:","answer":"விடை:ைகளான மருத்துவர்கள், வழக்கறிஞர்கள், ஆசிரியர்கள் மற்றும் மதுபானம் பரிமாறுகிறவர்கள் போன்றவற்றில் தானியங்கிமயத்திற்கான வாய்ப்பு குறைவாக உள்ளதென மெக்கன்சி தெரிவித்துள்ளது.குறைந்த ஊதியத்தை பெறும் வேலைகளான தோட்டக்கலை, பிளம்பிங் மற்றும் பராமரிப்பு சார்ந்த பணிகள் போன்றவை தானியங்கிமயத்தால் குறைவாக பாதிக்கப்படும் என்று அந்த ஆய்வு கணித்துள்ளது.வளர்ந்த நாடுகளில் குறைந்த கல்வி தேவைப்படும் வேலைகள் குறைந்துவிடும் என்பதால் அங்கு பல்கலைக்கழக கல்வியின் தேவை அதிகரிக்கும்.வசெவ்வாய் கிரகத்துக்கு செல்லப்போகும் ரோபோ தயார் (காணொளி) வரோபோ கைகள் செய்த உலகின் முதல் கண் அறுவை சிகிச்சை (காணொளி) தானியங்கிமயத்தின் காரணமாக அமெரிக்காவில் மட்டும் 2030ம் ஆண்டுக்குள் 3.9 முதல் 7.3 கோடி வேலைகள் பறிபோகும் வாய்ப்பிருந்தாலும், அதில் வேலையிழக்கும் 2 கோடி  பேர் எளிதாக மற்ற துறைகளுக்கு மாறுவதற்கான வாய்ப்புள்ளதாகவும் மெக்கன்சியின் அறிக்கையில் தெரிவிக்கப்பட்டுள்ளது.இங்கிலாந்தில் இதே குறிப்பிட்ட காலத்தில் 20 சதவீத வேலைகள் தானியங்கிமயம் செய்யப்படும் என்று அதில் கணிக்கப்பட்டுள்ளது.1900களின் தொடக்கத்தில் விவசாயத்திலிருந்து தொழிற்சாலை சார்ந்த வேலைக்கு  உலகளாவிய தொழில்கள் உருமாற்றம் பெற்றதைப் போன்று இந்த மாற்றமும் இருக்க வாய்ப்புள்ளதாக இந்த அறிக்கையை எழுதியவர்கள் நம்புகிறார்கள்.1980களில் கணினியின் அறிமுகம் தொழில்நுட்ப உதவி, இணைய வணிகம் போன்ற பல்வேறு புதுவிதமான வேலைகள் உருவாக வழிவகுத்ததைப் போலவே இந்த புதிய ரோபோ தொழில் நுட்பமும் புதுவிதமான வேலைவாய்ப்புகளை உருவாக்கும் என்றும் அதில் தெரிவிக்கப்பட்டுள்ளது.இந்தப் புதிய சிக்கலை எதிர்கொண்டு தமது குடிமக்களைக் காப்பாற்ற புதிய திட்டங்களை வகுக்கும்படி அரசுகளைக் கேட்டுக்கொண்டுள்ளது இந்த ஆய்வறிக்கை. பிற செய்திகள்:நம் இரவுகளை வெளிச்ச மாசிடம் இழக்கிறோமா? (காணொளி)சமூக ஊடகங்களில் பிபிசி தமிழ் :"},{"question":"Angel Falls, Venezuela, ndiyo yepamusoro-soro asi iripi yechipiri-pamusoro-soro?","answer":"Nepo Angel Falls muVenezuela akabata mutsauko wekuve mapopoma epamusoro-soro pasi rose, mapopoma echipiri-akakwirira ndeyeTugela Falls muSouth Africa. Tugela Falls iri muMakomo eDrakensberg uye inozivikanwa nekukasira kwayo kunoshamisa. Inoratidza kusiyana-siyana kwezvishamiso zvechisikigo mumakondinendi akasiyana, sezvo mapopoma aya achipa maonero anofema uye achibatsira mukunaka kwenzvimbo dzawo."},{"question":"Ọwọ ọlopaa ti tẹ awọn afurasi mẹta lori rogbodiyan to ṣelẹ lasiko ibo abele l’Ekiti","answer":"Kọmiṣanna ọlọpaa Ekiti, CP Tunde Mobayọ, ti kede pe ara obinrin ọlọpaa tibọn ba lasiko atundi ibo to waye niluu Omuo-Ekiti lọjọ Abamẹta, Satide, to kọja, ti n ya nileewosan ti wọn ti n tọju ẹ.Rogbodiyan to da wahala yii silẹ yii lo waye lasiko ti wọn n dibo fun ipo aṣofin ẹkun idibo Ila-Oorun Ekiti lẹyin iku Ọnarebu Juwa Adegbuyi, eeyan mẹta lo si dagbere faye, nigba tawọn mi-in farapa.Mobayọ ṣalaye pe ko si ootọ ninu iroyin to n lọ kaakiri lati ọjọ iṣẹlẹ naa pe ọlọpaa-binrin ọhun dagbere faye nitori bo tilẹ jẹ pe ẹsẹ kan aye ẹsẹ kan ọrun lo wa, itọju to n gba ti n yọri si rere.Bakan naa lo kede pe afurasi mẹta lọwọ ti tẹ lori ọrọ naa, awọn agbofinro lo si lọọ mu wọn nibi ti wọn sapamọ si, bẹẹ ni wọn wa ni olu-ileeṣẹ ọlọpaa to wa l’Ado-Ekiti.O waa ṣeleri pe gbogbo awọn to lọwọ si ipaniyan ati rogbodiyan to waye naa ni wọn yoo foju wina ofin.Ẹwẹ, ajọ eleto idibo (INEC) ti sun ibo naa siwaju di ọjọ mi-in. Adari ajọ naa l’Ekiti, Ọmọwe Tella Adeniran, lo sọ eleyii di mimọ pẹlu alaye pe bi ajọ naa ṣe n gbiyanju lati ṣeto idibo to dangajia, o han gbangba pe awọn kan ko ti i setan fun alaafia nilẹ yii.Bakan naa ni Gomina Kayọde Fayẹmi, Oloye Ṣẹgun Oni, Ayọdele Fayoṣe atawọn mi-in ti bẹnu atẹ lu iṣẹlẹ yii.Bi Fayẹmi ṣe koro oju si wahala ọhun to si ni dandan ni kawọn ọlọpaa mu gbogbo awọn to lọwọ si i ni Oni bẹnu atẹ lu iwa jagidijagan naa, to si fagi le gbogbo eto ipolongo ẹ lati bu ọla fun awọn ti nnkan ṣẹlẹ si, ṣugbọn Fayoṣe naka aleebu si ẹgbẹ All Progressives Congress (APC) pẹlu ẹsun pe wọn mọ-ọn-mọ maa pa araalu nitori wọn ti kẹyin sijọba wọn."},{"question":"Kiedy ostatnio podwyższono płacę minimalną w Ontario?","answer":"1 stycznia 2018"},{"question":"Harufa nawa ne a yaren turanci?","answer":"26"},{"question":"મને ડૉ. અપૂર્વ રાવલ શાહ એક પ્રેરક વક્તા વિશે કહો.","answer":"ડો. અપૂર્વ રાવલ શાહ એક મનોવિજ્ઞાની અને પ્રેરક વક્તા છે જે લોકોને ચિંતા, હતાશા અને અન્ય માનસિક સ્વાસ્થ્ય પડકારો દૂર કરવામાં મદદ કરવામાં નિષ્ણાત છે. તે 'માઇન્ડફુલનેસ મેટર્સ' સંસ્થાના સ્થાપક છે, જે માનસિક સ્વાસ્થ્ય અને સુખાકારી પર કાઉન્સેલિંગ, વર્કશોપ અને રીટ્રીટ્સ ઓફર કરે છે."},{"question":"ਕਬਾਇਲੀ ਅੰਤਰ ਵਿਆਹ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ ?","answer":"ਆਪਣੇ ਹੀ ਕਬੀਲੇ ਦੇ ਅੰਦਰ ਵਿਆਹ ਕਰਵਾਉਣ ਨੂੰ ਕਬਾਇਲੀ ਅੰਤਰ-ਵਿਆਹ ਕਹਿੰਦੇ ਹਨ ।"},{"question":"Sombintantara sa tantara an-dampihazo sa tantara foronina ny boky « Lavakombarika » ?","answer":"Sombintantara ny boky Lavakombarika, izay nosoratan'i Clarisse RATSIFANDRIAMANANA ahitana sombintantara miisa 16 io boky io."},{"question":"Maine ma’anar \\"label\\" a Hausa?","answer":"Yana nufin lakabin"},{"question":"Apakah punca kantung mata?","answer":"Dibawah adalah beberapa maklumat mengenai punca kantung mata atau 'eyebag':1. Tidak Cukup Tidur:Apabila tidak mendapat tidur atau rehat yang mencukupi, mata seseorang itu boleh terkena 'eyebag'. Sudah tentu jika tidak mendapat tidur yang cukup keadaan mata akan terganggu.2. Alahan:Menurut MayoClinic, seseorang itu memang boleh terkena 'eyebag' jika mempunyai alahan. Walau bagaimanapun, 'eyebag' di bawah mata adalah satu kebimbangan kosmetik dan tidak memerlukan rawatan khusus.Rawatan di rumah dan pertukaran gaya hidup boleh membantu mengurangkan atau menghapuskan bengkak mata. Punca yang lain ialah merokok, faktor genetik atau keturunan, atau pengkekalan cecair terutamanya apabila bangun tidur atau menikmati makanan masin"},{"question":"Apakah maksud \\"bagai menanti laki pulang maling\\"?","answer":"Ia bermaksud selalu dalam kegelisahan."},{"question":"Apakah maksud \\"hati batu\\"?","answer":"\\"Hati batu\\" bermaksud orang yang degil."},{"question":"కింది ప్రశ్నకు సమాధానం ఇవ్వండిబ్లిస్టర్ కాపర్ అంటే ఏమిటి? ఎందుకు దానిని అలా అంటారు?","answer":"కాపర్మాటీ నుండి కాపర్ను నిష్కర్షణం చేయునపుడు బ్లాస్ట్ కొలిమిలో చర్యలు పూర్తి అయిన తరువాత దాదాపు ఐరన్ పూర్తిగా లోహమలంగా తీసివేయబడుతుంది. క్యూప్రస్ ఆక్సైడ్, క్యూప్రస్ సల్ఫైడ్లు చర్య జరిపి కాపర్ లోహం ఏర్పడుతుంది.2Cu2O + Cu2S → 6Cu + SO2ద్రవ లోహాన్ని ఇసుక అచ్చుల్లోపోసి చల్లారుస్తారు. SO, వాయువు బయటికి పోతుంది. ఇలా ఏర్పడిన కాపర్ను “బ్లిస్టర్ కాపర్” అంటారు. దీనిలో 98% శుద్ధత ఉంటుంది."},{"question":"Yini ngisole sengathi udinga okuzokunika umfutho wokukhuluma njesisi?Umfutho wani manje Mphemba?(Ekhuluma kunyuke izwi) Hhayi bo! Kanti lowaya muntu akangenangayini lapha endlini?Hhayi bo! Uma usungithethisa kangaka izothini manje ingane?Nakhu ngigulelwa unkosikazi ephathwa izindlebe bo! Umbuzo wami uthikanti lowaya mlisa akangenanga yini lapha endlini? Musa-keukungitshela indaba yoZinhle abazothini lapha. Ngiphendule-ke.Akangenanga umlisa wesibhamu?Ungenile.Wafike wathini?Kukhona amfunayo.Sonto, wakhulumisa okwengane nje? Chaza konke okufanele ngikwazi.(Ekhuluma engazwakali) Hhayi, uthe kunabafana abajahayo, manjeubebheka ukuthi abangenanga yini lapha.Ukuze ilunge le nto ake ngithinte abomthetho bazoyilungisa yonke le nto.(Akhiphe iselula ephaketheni)Cha! Sithandwa sami asikho isidingo. (Abambe isandla sikaMbheleesineselula)Yini indaba sengathi kukhona okufihlayo nje sisi?(Ezikhalikhalisa) Akukho myeni wami. Ukuthi isibhamu saleya ndodasingithuse kakhulu. Ngisadidekile namanje ingakho kungathi angaziukuthi kumele ngithini. Manje amaphoyisa azongibuza imibuzo eminingi.(Washo esikhihla isililo)(Afake iselula ephaketheni bese anga uSonto.) Ubungasho ngani sonkelesi sikhathi ngize ngikuthethise kangaka s'thandwa sami?(Eciphiza) Ngisadidekile namanje Mphemba wami.1. Ngubani uZinhle okuvela igama lakhe kulesi siqeshana osifundile?","answer":"UZinhle indodakazi kaMbhele noSonto."},{"question":"Inona no azo hamaritana ny kabary?","answer":"Ny kabary dia lahateny, atao amin'ny feo avo, ampahibemaso ho ren’ny be sy ny maro ary tenenina amin'ny fomba kanto. Entina hampitana hafatra."},{"question":"පහත තේරවිල්ල විසඳන්න.නම කියනා විට දිය සිහි වෙනවාදියට දැමුවොතින් දියයට යනවාදියේ නෙමෙයි මෙහු ගොඩම ඉන්නවාබඩට අනිනකොට කටත් අරිනවා","answer":"ඉබ්බා"},{"question":"Chọn đáp án đúng cho câu hỏi sau:Thực dân Pháp đã thực hiện kế hoạch nào sau đây ở Đông Dương vào cuối năm 1950?A. Kế hoạch Nava.B. Kế hoạch Đờ Lát đơ Tátxinhi.C. Kế hoạch Rơve.D. Kế hoạch Bôlae.","answer":"Đáp án: b. kế hoạch đờ lát đơ tátxinhi."},{"question":"கொடுக்கப்பட்ட வேர் வார்த்தையைப் பயன்படுத்தி சொற்றொடர்களை உருவாக்கவும்: 'கேள்'(எழுவாய்த் தொடர், வினைமுற்றுத் தொடர், வினாத் தொடர்)","answer":"விடை :மாணவன் கேட்டான் – இது எழுவாய்த் தொடர் ஆகும்.கேட்டார் ஆசிரியர் – இது வினைமுற்றுத் தொடர் ஆகும்.யார் கேட்பவர்? – இது வினாத் தொடர் ஆகும்."},{"question":"Complete a seguinte frase: O Sudão foi uma república autoritária onde todo o poder estava nas mãos do presidente Omar Hasan Ahmad al-Bashir; ele e o seu partido estavam no poder desde o","answer":"golpe militar de 30 de Junho de 1989 até sua derrocada em 11 de abril de 2019."},{"question":" கேள்வி:  வாழ்க்கைப் போரில் வெற்றி பெறுவதற்கான வழிகளைக் கமுகுமரம் வாயிலாக ந. பிச்சமூர்த்தி ஆசிரியர் எவ்வாறு உணர்த்துகிறார்?","answer":"கமுகு பிறந்த இடம்:அடர்ந்த இருள் போன்ற நிழல் பரப்புகின்ற பெருமரங்களின் இடையே கமுகு பிறந்தது. பெருமரங்களின் நிழல் என்னும் இருள் அதன் வளர்ச்சிக்குத் தேவையான ஒளியமுதைத் தடுத்தது. பெருமரங்களின் நிழலை வெறுத்த கமுகு தான் வளரத் தேவையான ஒளியமுதைப் பெற்று உயிர்ப்புப் பெற போராட துவங்கியது.கமுகின் போராட்டம்:கமுகு மரம் கடுமையாகப் பெருமரங்களுடன் முட்டிமோதும் முயற்சியைத் தொடங்கியது. விண்ணிலிருந்து வரும் தன் உயிர்ப்பாகிய ஒளியமுதைத் தேடியது. மீண்டும், மீண்டும் உயர முயற்சித்தது. கதிரவனின் ஒளிக்கதிர்களாகிய விரல்களின் அழைப்பைக் கண்டது. பெருமரங்களின் இருட்டில் இருந்து கொண்டே தன் கிளையை வளைத்து ஒளியை நோக்கி நீட்டத் தொடங்கியது; வளர்ந்தது. பெரு மரங்களை முட்டி மோதும் துணிச்சலையும், முயற்சியையும் பெற்றதால் கமுகு வளைந்து, நெளிந்து, நீண்டு வளர்ந்தது. மலர்ச்சி பெற்றது.வாழ்க்கைப் போர்:வாழ்க்கையிலும் இருள் போன்ற நிழல் சூழ்ந்த நிலைகள் ஏற்படலாம். ஒளியமுதை நம்பி, வேண்டி, கமுகு துணிச்சலான முயற்சியில் ஈடுபட்டது போல, நாமும் வாழ்க்கைப் போரில் நம்பிக்கை தன்முனைப்பு, விடாமுயற்சி, உடையவர்களாய் இருந்தால் வாழ்வு மலர்ச்சி பெறும்.முடிவுரை:“பெருமரத்துடன் சிறுகமுகு போட்டியிடுகின்றது, அதுவே வாழ்க்கைப் போர். முண்டி போதும் துணிவே இன்பம் உயிரின் முயற்சியே வாழ்வின் மலர்ச்சி”. இயற்கையின் போராட்டங்களையும், வாழ்வின் அனுபவங்களையும் இணைத்து அறிவுத் தெளிவுடன் வாழ்க்கைப் போரைச் சந்திப்போம்; முயல்வோம்; வெற்றி பெறுவோம்."},{"question":"Quem foi a primeira pessoa a viajar no Espaço?","answer":"O primeiro ser humano a viajar no Espaço foi Yuri Gagarin, com 27 anos, no dia 12 de abril de 1961."},{"question":"Apakah maksud \\"air apus\\"?","answer":"Kawasan berair yang sangat dalam."},{"question":" Inona avy ireo fomba atao mba hisorohana ny tsy fahitan-tory amin’ny alina ?","answer":" Ireto avy no fomba atao mba hisorohana ny tsy fahitan-tory amin’ny alina : -Mamorona fahazarana tsara amin’ny fatoriana izany hoe fiezahana mandeha matory amin’ny ora mitovy isaky ny alina.-Manamboatra ny fomba fisakafoanana. Raha ohatra ka manana olana amin’ny tsy fahitan-tory, dia mila jerena manokana ny fomba fisakafoanana. Ny tsara dia ahena ny fihinanana ireo sakafo sokajiana ho manaitaitra, toy ny sakay, kafe, siramamy be loatra."},{"question":"Inona ny teny mitovy hevitra amin'ny \\"Manome\\"?","answer":"Ny teny mitovy hevitra amin'ny \\"Manome\\" dia \\"Manolotra\\"."},{"question":"Awọn araalu binu nitori b’ọlọpaa ṣe ti awọn OPC to mu Wakilu niluu Ayetẹ mọle","answer":"Titi di ba a ṣe n sọ yii lawọn eeyan n fi ibinu wọn han kaakiri ori ẹrọ ayelujara lori igbesẹ ti awọn ọlọpaa gbe pẹlu bi wọn ṣe ti mẹrin ninu awọn ọmọ ẹgbẹ OPC to lọọ mu ọkunrin Fulani to n da awọn eeyan Ibarapa, paapaa ju lọ ilu Ayetẹ laamu, iyẹn Iskilu Wakili.Awọn araalu ni iwa to ku diẹ kaato ni awọn agbofinro hu. Wọn ni dipo to fi yẹ ki wọn maa yin awọn ọmọ OPC to fori laku lọ lati lọọ mu awọn eeyan naa, niṣe ni wọn tun ti wọn mọle.Ọkunrin yii ni wọn lo wa ninu awọn Fulani to n kọju ija si awọn eeyan Ibarapa, bẹẹ lo n fi maaluu jẹ oko wọn. Igba kan si wa to ta okun di awọn abule kan niluu naa, to ni awọn ara ilu naa ko gbọdọ debẹ, ẹni ti oun ba ri nibẹ, a jẹ pe ile aye ti su u ni, nitori oun maa pa a ni.O pẹ ti awọn ara ilu Ayetẹ ti n pariwo ọkunrin to ti di ẹrujẹjẹ fun wọn ni ilu naa, ti wọn si n kegbajare fun ijọba lati gba wọn lọwọ rẹ. Ṣugbọn ijọba ko ri nnkan ṣe sọrọ naa nitori wọn ko ri awọn agbofinro ti wọn ṣeleri lati ko wa ki wọn le fi lọọ koju ọkunrin naa.Awọn ọmọ ẹgbẹ OPC lo dihamọra, ti wọn si wa ọkunrin Fulani yii lọ. Oju bọrọ kọ la fi n gbọmọ lọwọ ekurọ lọrọ naa da ko too di pe wọn ri ọkunrin naa mu ni ọjọ Aiku, Sannde, nitori ṣe ni wọn ni awọn ọmọ to wa lọdọ rẹ bẹrẹ si i yinbọn mọ awọn OPC yii.Lẹyin ti wọn ri ọkunrin naa atawọn ọmọ kan ti wọn ba nibẹ pẹlu rẹ mu ni wọn fa a le ọlọpaa lọwọ.Ṣugbọn iyalẹnu lo jẹ pe mẹrin ninu awọn ọmọ ẹgbẹ OPC ti wọn ṣiṣẹ naa lawọn ọlọpaa mu. Ẹsun ti wọn fi kan wọn ni pe wọn dana sun ile Wakili, wọn si tun dana sun obinrin agbalagba kan sinu ile naa.Alukoro ileeṣẹ ọlọpaa sọ ninu atẹjade kan to fi sita ni ọjọ Aiku, Sannde, ọsẹ yii pe loootọ ni aọn eeyan naa wa lagọọ ọlọpaa, awọn si mu wọn ki wọn le sọ ohun ti wọn ba mọ nipa bi wọn ṣe dana sun ile Wakilu, ti ẹni kan si jona mọle nibẹ.Wọn ni ileeṣẹ ọlọpaa ko ni i gba awọn araalu laaye lati ṣe ofin lọwọ ara wọn. Wọn ni awọn maa wadii iṣẹlẹ naa, awọn yoo si gbe igbeṣẹ to yẹ lai ṣegbe lẹyin ẹnikẹni.Alukoro ileeṣẹ ọlọpaa Ọyọ ni kọmiṣanna ti paṣẹ pe ki aọn gbe Wakili lọ si ileewosan nitori aiya ara rẹ."},{"question":"كمل الفقرة:الدوحة ـ كأنك تبني بيتا في الهواء، أو تزرع شجرة في السحاب، بهذه الكلمات يمكن وصف عملية الزراعة المائية \\"بدون تربة\\". ومع ظهور هذه الفكرة الزراعية قبل","answer":"فترة فإنها وجدت زخما كبيرا خلال معرض إكسبو قطر للبستنة 2023، من خلال طرح نموذج مبتكر يعتمد على تحلية المياه المستخدمة في النباتات واستزراع الأسماك بجانب المواد المعاد تدويرها."},{"question":"යෝධ පැන්ඩා කන්නේ මොනවාද?","answer":"යෝධ පැන්ඩා යනු ෆොලිවර්ඩ් වර්ගයකි, උණ රිකිලි සහ කොළ එහි ආහාර වේලෙන් 99% කට වඩා වැඩි ප්‍රමාණයක් අඩංගු වේ."},{"question":"Apakah maksud 'jalan tengah'? Berilah satu contoh ayat untuknya.","answer":"Ia bermaksud mengambil keputusan yang tidak berat sebelah. Contoh ayat: Saya mengambil jalan tengah supaya kedua-dua pihak yang bertelingkah dapat didamaikan."},{"question":"ලෝකයේ මුහුදු මට්ටමට පහළින් පිහිටි විශාලතම නගරය කුමක්ද?","answer":"ලෝකයේ මුහුදු මට්ටමට පහළින් පිහිටි විශාලතම නගරය අසර්බයිජානයේ අගනුවර වන බාකු නගරයයි."},{"question":"Inona no teoria momba ny faharanitan-tsaina amin'ny fluid sy kristaly?","answer":"Ny teoria momba ny faharanitan-tsaina amin'ny fluid, natolotr'i Raymond Cattell, dia manondro ny fahaiza-manaon'ny saina, fa ny faharanitan-tsaina kristaly kosa dia mahakasika ny fahalalana sy ny fahaiza-manao voaangona rehefa mandeha ny fotoana."},{"question":"புற்று நோயை குணப்படுத்துவது?","answer":"விடை: கோபால்ட் - 60"},{"question":"සවුදිය පුරන්න කියන්නේ මොකද්ද?","answer":"ප්‍රීති අවස්තාවක මධුවිත පානය කිරීමට පෙර සියලු දෙනා සිය වීදුරු ඉහළට කර කෙනෙකුගේ සුවය, යහපත පැතීම. උදා: බටහිර විවාහයකදී, සභාව අමතා කතා කරන දෙවන මනාලයා යුවලට සුභ පතා සව්දිය පුරනවා"},{"question":"નીચેના શબ્દસમૂહ માટે એક શબ્દ આપો:સો વર્ષ પૂરા થવાં તે – શતાબ્દી અથવા સો વર્ષ પૂરાં થયે ઊજવાતો મહોત્સવ","answer":"શતાબ્દી મહોત્સવ "},{"question":"మొదటి పదం 3.5, పదాంతరము సున్న (0) గా గల అంకశ్రేఢి 108వ పదము ఎంత ?","answer":"a = 3.5, d = 0∴ a108 = a + 107d = 3.5 + 0 = 3.5"},{"question":"Sila huraikan bidang kuasa Yang di-Pertuan Agong dalam bidang kehakiman.","answer":"Yang di-Pertuan Agong berperanan besar dalam bidang kehakiman.Pertama sekali, Yang di-pertuan Agong berkuasa melantik hakim mahkamah atasan atas nasihat Perdana Menteri setelah dipertimbangkan oleh Suruhanjaya Pelantikan Kehakiman dan berunding dengan Majlis Raja-Raja. Hakim mahkamah atasan termasuk Ketua Hakim Negara Mahkamah Persekutuan, Presiden Mahkamah Rayuan, Hakim Besar Mahkamah Tinggi di Malaya, Hakim Besar Mahkamah Tinggi di Sabah dan Sarawak, Hakim-hakim Mahkamah Agung, Hakim-hakim Mahkamah Rayuan dan Mahkamah Tinggi.Di samping itu, baginda boleh melantik mana-mana orang yang layak dilantik sebagai Hakim Mahkamah Tinggi untuk menjadi Pesuruhjaya Kehakiman (yang mempunyai kuasa sebagai Hakim Mahkamah Tinggi) atas nasihat Perdana Menteri selepas berunding dengan Ketua Hakim Negara Mahkamah PersekutuanSelain daripada itu, Yang di-Pertuan Agong juga boleh memanjangkan perkhidmatan seorang hakim yang berumur lebih 65 tahun. Bagaimana pun lanjutan perkhidmatan itu tidak melebihi enam bulan setelah mencapai umur 65 tahun.Walaupun begitu, baginda tidak mempunyai kuasa untuk menyingkirkan seseorang hakim atas kemahuannya.Akhirnya, Yang di-Pertuan Agong boleh mengampunkan seseorang yang telah dihukum atas nasihat Lembaga Pengampunan. Baginda berkuasa mengampunkan, menangguhkan atau meringankan hukuman yang dijatuhkan oleh Mahkamah Tentera can juga Mahkamah Syariah diMelaka, Pulau Pinang, Sabah, Sarawak dan Wilayah-wilayah Persekutuan."},{"question":"Cảm xúc nào xuyên suốt bài thơ Tiếng gà trưa? Em hiểu người xưng “cháu” trong bài thơ là ai?","answer":"- Cảm xúc xuyên suốt bài thơ là cảm xúc, tình cảm của người cháu với bà và ổ trứng hồng. - Cảm xúc đó được khơi gợi từ tiếng gà trưa trên đường mà người cháu đang hành quân xa nhà.- Người xưng cháu trong bài thơ chính là tác giả Xuân Quỳnh đang trên đường hành quân, nghe được tiếng gà trưa và nhớ về người bà yêu quý."},{"question":"1- сүйлөм: Small Business Saturday United Kingdom программасы Улуу Британияда 2013-жылы, Америка Кошмо Штаттарындагы Small Business Saturday программасынын ийгилигинен кийин пайда болгон. 2- сүйлөм: Small Business Saturday UK программасы 2013-жылы Улуу Британияда, Америка Кошмо Штаттарындагы Small Business Saturday программасынын ийгилигинен кийин ишке киргизилген. Суроо: Биринчи жана экинчи сүйлөмдөрдүн мааниси бирдейби? ","answer":"Ооба"},{"question":"Sọ fúnmi nípa Ìpínlẹ̀ Adamawa.","answer":"Ìpínlẹ̀ Adamawa jẹ́ ìpínlẹ̀ kan ní agbègbè àríwá-ìlà-oòrùn orílẹ̀-èdè Nàìjíríà, tí ó pín ààlà pẹ̀lú Ìpínlẹ̀ Borno sí àríwá ìwọ̀-oòrùn, Gombe sí ìwọ̀-oòrùn, àti Taraba gúúsù-ìwọ̀-oòrùn nígbàtí ààlà ìlà-oòrùn rẹ̀ di apákan ààlà orílẹ̀-èdè pẹ̀lú orílẹ̀-èdè Cameroon. Orúkọ rẹ̀ jẹ yọ látara ìtàn ẹ́míréétì ti Adamawa, pẹ̀lú olú-ìlú ẹ́míréétì tẹ́lẹ̀rí ti Yola tí ó jẹ́ gẹ́gẹ́ bí olú-ìlú Ìpínlẹ̀ Adamawa. Ìpínlẹ̀ náà jẹ́ ọ̀kan lára àwọn ìpínlẹ̀ oríṣiríṣi àkóónú ní orílẹ̀ èdè Nàìjíríà pẹ̀lú áwọn ọ̀wọ́ ẹ̀yà onílùú tí ó lé ní ọgọ́rùn-ún. Wọ́n dáa sílẹ̀ ní ọdún 1991 nígbàtí ìpínlẹ̀ Gongola tẹ́lẹ̀rí túká di ìpínlẹ̀ Adamawa àti ìpínlẹ̀ Taraba.Láàárín àwọn ìpínlẹ̀ mẹ́rìndínlógójì ti orílẹ̀ èdè Nàìjíríà, ìpínlẹ̀ Adamawa jẹ́ ìpínlẹ̀ ẹlẹ́ẹ̀kẹjọ tí ó gbòòrò jùlọ ní ààyè tàbí agbègbè, àti ẹlẹ́ẹ̀kọkàndínlógún ní iye pẹ̀lú ènìyàn tí ó tó mílíọ́nnù mẹ́rinlé-ní-ìdámẹ́rin gẹ́gẹ́ bí àbájáde ìkànìyàn ọdún 2016.Ohun tí a wá mọ̀ sí ìpínlẹ̀ Adamawa ti ní olùgbé láti bí ọ̀pọ̀ ọdún sẹ́yìn kún fún àwọn oríṣiríṣi ẹ̀yà pẹ̀lú Bwatiye (Bachama), Bali, Bata (Gbwata), Gudu, Mbula-Bwazza, àti Nungurab (Lunguda) ní àáríngbùngbùn agbègbè náà; Kamwe sí àríwá àti àáríngbùngbùn agbègbè náà; Jibusí gúúsù tí ó naṣẹ̀; Kilba, Marghi, Waga, àti Wula ní ìlà-oòrùn, àti Mumuye ní gúúsù nígbàtí àwọn Fulani gbé jákèjádò ìpínlẹ̀ náà lemọ́lemọ́ gẹ́gẹ́ bí darandaran. Ìpínlẹ̀ Adamawa jẹ́ àkóónú oriṣ́iríṣi ẹ̀sìn nígbàtí ìwọ̀n bí àrùndínlọ́gọ́ta àwọn ènìyàn olùgbé jẹ́ Mùsùlùmí (Sunni) àti ìwọ̀n 30% jẹ́ krìstẹ́nì (nípàtàkì Lutheran, EYN, ECWA, àti ìjọ aláṣọ ara) nígbàtí àwọn ìwọ̀n mẹ́ẹ̀dógún jẹ́ àwọn ẹlẹ́sìn ìbílẹ̀."},{"question":"السؤال: من هو أول مولود في الإسلام ؟","answer":"الإجابة: النعمان بن البشير "},{"question":"Ismail Essam","answer":"Ismail Essam (ti a bi ni ọjọ karun oṣu kejo, ọdun 1967) jẹ elere idaraya ati ojogbon lati orilẹ-ede Egipti . Ó ń díje nínú tafàtafà .Essam dije ni Olimpiiki Igba ooru 2000 ati 2004 ni tafàtafà ẹni kọọkan ti awọn ọkunrin. O ti ṣẹgun ninu ipele akọkọ ti imunikuro ni igba mejeeji, gbigbe ipo 56th lapapọ ni 2000 ati 62nd ni 2004."},{"question":"බත් සමග ආහාරයට ගන්නා එළවළු, මාළු  යන්නට තනි වචනයක් දෙන්න.","answer":"ව්‍යාංජන"},{"question":" Kumuu ahaa Asxaabigii Nebiguﷺ, yidhi waxaa dileysa koox xadgudubtay","answer":" Wuxuu ahaa Camaar binu Yaasir (RC)"},{"question":"War maxaa dhacay?","answer":"War maxaa dhacey? Yaa waalay madashii akhriska ee bilneyd? Waa maxay boqolkan nooc ee calanka ahi? 40K waallaalo ah ayaynu ahayn ee yaa inna kala guray? Yaa inna kala geeyay ee midba gooni ka dhigay? Meeshi miyayna lahayn maamul? Gefka kowaad, waxa iska leh, ninkan Calanka buluugga ah meesha soo sudhay! Soomaali hal calan oo inna mideeya malaha! Jabbuuti calan bey leedahay. Soomaliya calan bey leedahay. Dowlad-deegaanka mid bey leeyihiin... Sidaa uun u sii wad. Haddaba, maalinta Soomaali oo dhan midowdo innoo saara Hal calan, inta ka horreysa maya! Hadda waa sida ay anniga ila tahay."},{"question":"පහත වචනයට අදාළ විරුද්ධ පද කුමක්ද?සුදාන්ත ","answer":"දුර්දාන්ත"},{"question":"Ułóż pytanie do podanej odpowiedzi: Żabowate należą do rządu płazów bezogonowych.","answer":"Oto pytanie do powyższej odpowiedzi: Do jakiego rządu płazów należą żabowate?"},{"question":"* كم عظمة في جمجمة الإنسان ؟","answer":"22 عظمة"},{"question":"Kiwango gani cha orodha kati ya orodha nyingi za mji wa Grainger ni Grainger Market haijaorodheshwa kama? Kwa sababu ya swali lililotangulia, andika muktadha unaotoa jibu. Inaweza kuwa sentensi 1 - 20. Muktadha:","answer":"Soko la Grainger lilichukua nafasi ya soko la awali lililojengwa mnamo 1808 lililoitwa Soko la Mchinjaji. Soko la Grainger lenyewe, lilifunguliwa mnamo 1835 na lilikuwa soko la kwanza la ndani la Newcastle. Lilipofunguliwa mwaka wa 1835, lilisemekana kuwa mojawapo ya masoko makubwa na maridadi zaidi huko Ulaya. Ufunguzi huo uliadhimishwa na karamu kubwa ya chakula cha jioni iliyohudhuriwa na wageni 2,000. Jumba la Sanaa la Laing lina mchoro wa tukio hili. Isipokuwa paa la mbao ambalo liliharibiwa na moto mnamo 1901 na kubadilishwa na matao ya chuma ya latticed, soko hilo liko katika hali yake ya asili. Grainger Market usanifu, kama wengi katika Grainger Town, ambayo ni ama daraja I au II waliotajwa, ilikuwa waliotajwa daraja I mwaka 1954 na English Heritage."},{"question":"Daga cikin muhimman ayyukan waziri, akwai?","answer":"ba wa sarki shawara."},{"question":"Ci ban kembaar la réwum Afghanistan nékk","answer":"Réwum Afghanistan mu ngi nékk ci kembaar bi ñuy wakh Asie"},{"question":"Vilken är Sveriges fjärde största stad?","answer":"Uppsala är Sveriges fjärde mest befolkade stad med över 165 000  invånare (tätort) enligt Statistiska centralbyrån, 24 november 2021."},{"question":"What is the meaning of the acronym GTPAL in the healthcare context?","answer":"The acronym GTPAL is a medical shorthand used by healthcare professionals to document and communicate important information about a woman's obstetric history, particularly during pregnancy and childbirth. Each letter in GTPAL represents a different aspect of this history:G: Gravida - This refers to the total number of pregnancies a woman has had, regardless of the pregnancy outcome (whether it resulted in a live birth, stillbirth, or abortion). For example, if a woman has been pregnant three times, she would be referred to as \\"G3.\\"T: Term births - This indicates the number of pregnancies that reached full term (typically 37 weeks or more) and resulted in a live birth. For example, if a woman has had one full-term pregnancy resulting in a live birth, it would be noted as \\"T1.\\"P: Preterm births - This represents the number of pregnancies that ended before reaching full term but resulted in a live birth. If a woman had one preterm pregnancy that resulted in a live birth, it would be documented as \\"P1.\\"A: Abortions - Abortions refer to pregnancies that ended before 20 weeks gestation, either spontaneously (miscarriage) or intentionally (induced abortion). The number of pregnancies that ended in abortion is indicated by the letter \\"A.\\" For example, if a woman had two miscarriages, it would be noted as \\"A2.\\"L: Living children - This denotes the number of living children a woman has at the time of assessment or delivery. If a woman has two living children, it would be documented as \\"L2.\\"By using the GTPAL acronym, healthcare providers can quickly understand a woman's obstetric history, which is essential for providing appropriate prenatal care and managing pregnancies effectively. It allows healthcare teams to assess potential risk factors and tailor their care plans accordingly."},{"question":"A criação do Sistema Único de Saúde (SUS) como uma política para todos constitui-se uma das mais importantes conquistas da sociedade brasileira no século XX. O SUS deve ser valorizado e defendido como um marco para a cidadania e o avanço civilizatório. A democracia envolve um modelo de Estado no qual políticas protegem os cidadãos e reduzem as desigualdades. O SUS é uma diretriz que fortalece a cidadania e contribui para assegurar o exercício de direitos, o pluralismo político e o bem-estar como valores de uma sociedade fraterna, pluralista e sem preconceitos, conforme prevê a Constituição Federal de 1988.Segundo o texto, duas características da concepção da política pública analisada são:a) Paternalismo e filantropia.b) Liberalismo e meritocracia.c) Universalismo e igualitarismo.d) Nacionalismo e individualismo.e) Revolucionarismo e coparticipação.","answer":"A resposta correcta é a alternativa: c) Universalismo e igualitarismo."},{"question":"Šio XIX a. vokiečių astronomo ir geodezininko pavardę galima rasti viename iš keturių Lietuvoje esančių UNESCO pasaulio paveldo sąrašo objektų pavadinime. Kokia mokslininko pavardė?","answer":"Frydrichas Georgas Wilhelmas Struvė. Jo garbei pavadintas per visą Lietuvą besidriekiantis Struvės geodezinis lankas, įtrauktas į UNESCO paveldo objektų sąrašą."},{"question":"اگر به ایران سفر کردم از کدام شهرها دیدن کنم؟","answer":"ایران شهرهای بسیار زیبایی دارد در سفر به ایران پیشنهاد میکنم حتما از شهرهای شیراز، اصفهان، کرمان، رشت و کردستان دیدن کنید."},{"question":"Iza no mpitarika ny Firaisana Sovietika tamin'ny fotoanan'ny Revolisiona Oktobra tamin'ny 1917?","answer":"Lenin, izay Vladimir Ilyich Ulyanov no tena anarany, no mpitarika ny Firaisana Sovietika tamin'ny fotoanan'ny Revolisiona Oktobra tamin'ny 1917."},{"question":"fehezanteny voalohany : Noho ny toerana stratejika ao amin’ny ranomasimbe Indianina dia voataonan’ny kolontsaina vahiny isan-karazany i Madagasikara, anisan’izany ny Arabo, Afrikanina, Eoropeanina ary Aziatika. Hita amin’ny lafiny samihafa amin’ny kolontsaina malagasy ireo fitaomana ireo, manomboka amin’ny sakafo ka hatramin’ny mozika ka hatramin’ny finoana ara-pivavahana.fehezanteny faharoa : Noho ny hahabetsahan'ny mpitsidika sy miala sasatra ao Madagasikara dia maro ny firenena vahiny maka tahaka ny fomba amam-panao sy  ny kolontsaina  Malagasy, anisan'izany ny Arabo, Afrikana, Eoropeanina ary Aziatika. Hita taratra izany amin'ny mozika, ny sakafo sy ny dihy ataon'izy ireo.Mifanaraka ve ireo fehezanteny roa ireo?","answer":"Tsia, mifanipaka ireo fehezanteny ireo, ny fehezanteny voalohany milaza fa ny vahiny no nahavoataona ny kolontsaina malagasy kanefa ny fehezanteny faharoa kosa dia mamadika ny hevitr'izany."},{"question":"నగరజీవనంలోని అనుకూల అంశంపై కవిత రాయండి.","answer":"నవ్య నాగరికతకు నిలయం – నగర జీవనంభవ్య భవితకు ఆదర్శం – నగర జీవితంఉపాధి అవకాశాలకు నిలయంఉన్నత స్థితికెపుడు ఆలవాలందీనభత్యం ఎంతైనా లభించు నచటకూలివానికెపుడు పర్వమే అచటదినదినాభివృద్ధి చెందురచటకోర్కె లీడేరు సర్వము నచటదొరకని వస్తువు లేవీ ఉండవచటతెలియని విద్యలేవీ ఉండవచటసదుపాయాలు ఎన్నెన్నో కలవచటసకల నిధులు సమకూరునచటనిజం నిజం నగర జీవనంసౌఖ్యాలకు మూలం నగర జీవితం"},{"question":"yaa lagu soo dejiyey kutubka Towraad?","answer":" Nebi Muuse CS."},{"question":"Fan mooy gëblag réewum Bahreïn?","answer":"Gëblag réewum Bahreïn mu ngi tudd Manama."},{"question":"Franca Brown","answer":"Franca Obianuju Brown (bíi ni ọjọ́ kẹtàdínlógún oṣù karùn-ún, ọdún 1967), jẹ́ òṣèré lórílẹ̀-èdè Nàìjíríà. Ó gbà àmì ẹ̀yẹ City People Movie Special Recognition Award láti ọ̀dọ̀ City People Entertainment Awards ní ọdún 2016.Brown bẹ̀rẹ̀ ẹ̀kọ́ ìbẹ̀rẹ̀ pẹ̀pẹ̀ rẹ̀ ní ilé ẹ̀kọ́ St Mary's Primary School ní ìlú Onitsha ní ìpínlẹ̀ Anambra. Ó gboyè nínú ìmò òfin láti ilé ẹ̀kọ́ gíga tí Ahmadu Bello University. Ó tẹ̀ síwájú sí ilé ẹ̀kọ́ gíga tí University of Jos níbi tí ó tí gboyè nínú ìmò eré orí ìtàgé.Brown gbajúmọ̀ gẹ́gẹ́ bí òṣèré fún ipá tí ó kó nínú eré Behind The Clouds. Kí ó tó kópa nínú eré náà, ó má ń ṣe eré orí ìtàgé rán pé. Ó kópa nínú eré rán pé tí àkọ̀rí rẹ̀ jẹ́ Swam Karagbe. Brown jẹ́ adarí fún eré, òun sì ni ó dárí eré Women at Large.Ní ọdún 2019, ọmọ ọ̀dọ̀ rẹ̀ dáná sun ilé rẹ̀Ní ọdún 2016, ó gbà àmì ẹ̀yẹ City People Movie Special Recognition Award láti ọ̀dọ̀ City People Entertainment Awards."},{"question":"文章から主要な単語を特定し、それを定義しなさい。 EUは2011年の福島第一原子力発電所の事故のあと、日本から食べ物を輸入するときの規則を厳しくしてきました。福島県や宮城県など10の県でとれた魚や山菜などを輸入するときは、放射線の検査をした証明が必要でした。農林水産省によると、EUとノルウェー、アイスランドは8月3日にこの規則をやめました。スイスは、大使館によると15日から規則をやめる予定です。検査をしたり証明をしたりする必要がなくなったため、輸出が多くなると考えられています。農林水産省は「規則がなくなったことは、災害を受けた地域が前のように戻ることに役に立ちます」と話しています。中国や韓国、台湾、香港などの国と地域では輸入の規則が続いています。","answer":"この文章の中での主要な単語とその定義は以下のようになっています。- EU: 1）ドイツ・フランスなどヨーロッパの国々が、共同で国の安全をはかったり経済を運営したりしようとする組織。- とれ: 1）魚・鳥などが得られる。2）とることができる。- 山菜: 1）山や野原に生えている、食べられる草や木の芽。ワラビ・ゼンマイ・タラノメなど。- 放射線: 1）ウランやラジウムなどの放射性元素がこわれて、他の元素に変わるときに出すもの。大量に浴びると有害である。- 検査: 1）悪いところがないかを調べること。- 証明: 1）ものごとの正しさや、真実などをはっきり示すこと。- 農林水産省: 1）農業・林業・水産業・畜産業などについての仕事をする、国の役所。農水省。- 災害: 1）台風・地震・洪水・火事などによる災難。- 地域: 1）ある範囲に区切られた土地。"},{"question":"வினா:நாம் அன்றாட வாழ்வில்  வளர்க்கும் கால்நடைகள்,  விலங்குகள் பற்றி  எழுதுக .","answer":"விடை : கால்நடைகள் என்பது உணவு, நார்ச்சத்து மற்றும் உழைப்பு உள்ளிட்ட பல்வேறு நோக்கங்களுக்காக மனிதர்களால் வளர்க்கப்படும் விலங்குகள். பன்றிகள், செம்மறி ஆடுகள், ஆடுகள், மாடுகள், குதிரைகள் மற்றும் கோழிகள் உட்பட பல வகையான கால்நடைகள் உலகம் முழுவதும் வளர்க்கப்படுகின்றன. இந்த விலங்குகள் பொதுவாக பண்ணைகள் அல்லது பண்ணைகளில் வைக்கப்படுகின்றன.  பொதுவாக மேய்ச்சல் நிலங்களில் (மேய்ச்சல் நிலங்கள்) மேய்ச்சலுக்கு அனுமதிக்கப்படுகின்றன. சில சந்தர்ப்பங்களில், கால்நடைகள் உயிரியல் பூங்காக்கள் அல்லது பிற சிறைபிடிக்கப்பட்ட சூழல்களில் வைக்கப்படலாம். கால்நடை விலங்குகளின் பராமரிப்பு மற்றும் மேலாண்மை விலங்கு இனம் மற்றும் அது பராமரிக்கப்படும் நோக்கத்தைப் பொறுத்து பெரிதும் மாறுபடும்."},{"question":"Beszélj a Debreceni Nagytemplom építészetéről és stílusáról.","answer":"A Debreceni Nagytemplom a barokk stílus egyik kiemelkedő példája. Impozáns homlokzatával és gazdag díszítéseivel a város egyik jelképévé vált."},{"question":"Jawab soalan yang rumit ini: Pada tahun apakah suami ahli matematik Anneli Cahn Lax dilahirkan?","answer":"Suami ahli matematik Anneli Cahn Lax dilahirkan pada tahun 1926."},{"question":"இரண்டு பெண்களை வைத்து ஒரு கடி ஜோக் சொல்லவும்.","answer":"பெண் 1: காலையிலே ரசம் வச்சேன், மாமியார் தான் இன்னைக்கு வெள்ளிக்கிழமை சாம்பார் வையின்னு சொன்னாங்க.பெண் 2: அப்புறம் என்னடி செஞ்ச?பெண் 1: அதுல 4 கத்திரிக்காயை வெட்டிபோட்டேன். சாம்பார் ரெடி ஆகிருச்ச்சு."},{"question":"问题：三星公司在人工智能领域有何进展？","answer":"答案：三星公司在人工智能领域进行了重要的研发和投资，推出了智能助手Bixby和智能家居解决方案等。"},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਗਉੜੀ ਮਹਲਾ ੫ ॥ਹਰਿ ਸਿਮਰਤ ਸਭਿ ਮਿਟਹਿ ਕਲੇਸ ॥ਚਰਣ ਕਮਲ ਮਨ ਮਹਿ ਪਰਵੇਸ ॥੧॥ਉਚਰਹੁ ਰਾਮ ਨਾਮੁ ਲਖ ਬਾਰੀ ॥ਅੰਮ੍ਰਿਤ ਰਸੁ ਪੀਵਹੁ ਪ੍ਰਭ ਪਿਆਰੀ ॥੧॥ ਰਹਾਉ ॥ਸੂਖ ਸਹਜ ਰਸ ਮਹਾ ਅਨੰਦਾ ॥ਜਪਿ ਜਪਿ ਜੀਵੇ ਪਰਮਾਨੰਦਾ ॥੨॥ਕਾਮ ਕ੍ਰੋਧ ਲੋਭ ਮਦ ਖੋਏ ॥ਸਾਧ ਕੈ ਸੰਗਿ ਕਿਲਬਿਖ ਸਭ ਧੋਏ ॥੩॥ਕਰਿ ਕਿਰਪਾ ਪ੍ਰਭ ਦੀਨ ਦਇਆਲਾ ॥ਨਾਨਕ ਦੀਜੈ ਸਾਧ ਰਵਾਲਾ ॥੪॥੭੫॥੧੪੪॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 194 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਅਰਜਨ ਦੇਵ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਬਾਣੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਹਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਸਿਮਰਿਆਂ ਮਨ ਦੇ ਸਾਰੇ ਕਲੇਸ਼ ਮਿਟ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ (ਹੇ ਭਾਈ !) ਆਪਣੇ ਮਨ ਵਿਚ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੇ ਸੋਹਣੇ ਚਰਨ ਵਸਾਈ ਰੱਖ ।।੧।ਹੇ ਪਿਆਰੀ ਜੀਭ ! ਲੱਖਾਂ ਵਾਰੀ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਉਚਾਰਦੀ ਰਹੁ ਤੇ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਆਤਮਕ ਜੀਵਨ ਵਾਲਾ ਨਾਮ-ਰਸ ਪੀਂਦੀ ਰਹੁ ।੧।ਰਹਾਉ।ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਅੰਦਰ ਆਤਮਕ ਅਡੋਲਤਾ ਦੇ ਵੱਡੇ ਸੁਖ ਆਨੰਦ ਬਣੇ ਰਹਿੰਦੇ ਹਨ ।੨।(ਹੇ ਭਾਈ ! ਜੇਹੜੇ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਸਭ ਤੋਂ ਸ੍ਰੇਸ਼ਟ ਆਤਮਕ ਆਨੰਦ ਦੇ ਮਾਲਕ-ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਜਪਦੇ ਹਨ, ਉਹ ਆਤਮਕ ਜੀਵਨ ਹਾਸਲ ਕਰ ਲੈਂਦੇ ਹਨ(ਹੇ ਭਾਈ ! ਨਾਮ-ਰਸ ਪੀਣ ਵਾਲੇ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਆਪਣੇ ਅੰਦਰੋਂ) ਕਾਮ, ਕਰੋਧ, ਲੋਭ, ਅਹੰਕਾਰ (ਆਦਿਕ ਵਿਕਾਰ) ਨਾਸ ਕਰ ਲੈਂਦੇ ਹਨ ।ਗੁਰੂ ਦੀ ਸੰਗਤਿ ਵਿਚ ਰਹਿ ਕੇ ਉਹ (ਆਪਣੇ ਮਨ ਵਿਚੋਂ) ਸਾਰੇ ਪਾਪ ਧੋ ਲੈਂਦੇ ਹਨ ।੩।ਹੇ ਦੀਨਾਂ ਉਤੇ ਦਇਆ ਕਰਨ ਵਾਲੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ! ਮਿਹਰ ਕਰ ਤੇ ਨਾਨਕ ਨੂੰ ਗੁਰੂ ਦੇ ਚਰਨਾਂ ਦੀ ਧੂੜ ਬਖ਼ਸ਼ ।੪।੭੫।੧੪੪।\\""},{"question":"Waa gartay in ay ugu horrayso arkaanul-iimaanka in la rumeeyo Ilaahay. Haddaba waa maxay \\"in Ilaahay la rumeeyo\\"?","answer":"In Ilaahay la rumeeyo waxay tahay: 1) In la rumeeyo inuu Alle jiro.2) In la rumeeyo inuu Alle wax walba abuuray oo isagu adduunka maamulo nolol iyo dhimashoba, isla markaana uu isagu makhluuqa kala xukumi doono. 3) In la rumeeyo inuu kelidii caabudid xaq u leeyahay.4) In la qiro magacyadiisa iyo sifooyinkiisa. (Makhluuqa= uunka, waxa la abuuray. Waxaa soo hoos gelaya waxkasta oo jira Alle mooyaane."},{"question":"السؤال: هل يفطر الصائم إذا دخل ماءٌ إلى جوفه دون قصدٍ أثناء الوضوء؟","answer":"الجواب: لا يفسد الصيام ولا يفطر الصائم لأنّ الله تعالى رفع القلم عن المخطئ والناسي."},{"question":"ਅਸੰਖ ਨਾਵ ਅਸੰਖ ਥਾਵ ॥ ਅਗੰਮ ਅਗੰਮ ਅਸੰਖ ਲੋਅ ॥ ਅਸੰਖ ਕਹਹਿ ਸਿਰਿ ਭਾਰੁ ਹੋਇ ॥ਅਖਰੀ ਨਾਮੁ ਅਖਰੀ ਸਾਲਾਹ ॥ ਅਖਰੀ ਗਿਆਨੁ ਗੀਤ ਗੁਣ ਗਾਹ ॥ ਅਖਰੀ ਲਿਖਣੁ ਬੋਲਣੁ ਬਾਣਿ ॥ ਅਖਰਾ ਸਿਰਿ ਸੰਜੋਗੁ ਵਖਾਣਿ ॥ ਜਿਨਿ ਏਹਿ ਲਿਖੇ ਤਿਸੁ ਸਿਰਿ ਨਾਹਿ ॥ ਜਿਵ ਫੁਰਮਾਏ ਤਿਵ ਤਿਵ ਪਾਹਿ ॥ਜੇਤਾ ਕੀਤਾ ਤੇਤਾ ਨਾਉ ॥ ਵਿਣੁ ਨਾਵੈ ਨਾਹੀ ਕੋ ਥਾਉ ॥ਕੁਦਰਤਿ ਕਵਣ ਕਹਾ ਵੀਚਾਰੁ ॥ ਵਾਰਿਆ ਨ ਜਾਵਾ ਏਕ ਵਾਰ ॥ ਜੋ ਤੁਧੁ ਭਾਵੈ ਸਾਈ ਭਲੀ ਕਾਰ ॥ ਤੂ ਸਦਾ ਸਲਾਮਤਿ ਨਿਰੰਕਾਰ ॥੧੯॥","answer":"(ਕੁਦਰਤਿ ਦੇ ਅਨੇਕ ਜੀਵਾਂ ਤੇ ਹੋਰ ਬੇਅੰਤ ਪਦਾਰਥਾਂ ਦੇ) ਅਸੰਖਾਂ ਹੀ ਨਾਮ ਹਨ ਤੇ ਅਸੰਖਾਂ ਹੀ (ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੇ) ਥਾਂ ਟਿਕਾਣੇ ਹਨ। (ਕੁਦਰਤਿ ਵਿਚ) ਅਸੰਖਾਂ ਹੀ ਭਵਣ ਹਨ ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਤਕ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਦੀ ਪਹੁੰਚ ਹੀ ਨਹੀਂ ਹੋ ਸਕਦੀ। (ਪਰ ਜੋ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਕੁਦਰਤਿ ਦਾ ਲੇਖਾ ਕਰਨ ਵਾਸਤੇ ਸ਼ਬਦ) 'ਅਸੰਖ' (ਭੀ) ਆਖਦੇ ਹਨ, (ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੇ) ਸਿਰ ਉੱਤੇ ਭੀ ਭਾਰ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ (ਭਾਵ, ਉਹ ਭੀ ਭੁੱਲ ਕਰਦੇ ਹਨ, 'ਅਸੰਖ' ਸ਼ਬਦ ਭੀ ਕਾਫੀ ਨਹੀਂ ਹੈ) ।(ਭਾਵੇਂ ਅਕਾਲ ਪੁਰਖ ਦੀ ਕੁਦਰਤਿ ਦਾ ਲੇਖਾ ਲਫ਼ਜ਼ 'ਅਸੰਖ' ਤਾਂ ਕਿਤੇ ਰਿਹਾ, ਕੋਈ ਭੀ ਸ਼ਬਦ ਕਾਫ਼ੀ ਨਹੀਂ ਹੈ, ਪਰ) ਅਕਾਲ ਪੁਰਖ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਭੀ ਅੱਖਰਾਂ ਦੀ ਰਾਹੀਂ ਹੀ (ਲਿਆ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ) , ਉਸ ਦੀ ਸਿਫ਼ਿਤ-ਸਾਲਾਹ ਭੀ ਅੱਖਰਾਂ ਦੀ ਰਾਹੀਂ ਹੀ ਕੀਤੀ ਜਾ ਸਕਦੀ ਹੈ। ਅਕਾਲ ਪੁਰਖ ਦਾ ਗਿਆਨ ਭੀ ਅੱਖਰਾਂ ਦੀ ਰਾਹੀਂ ਹੀ (ਵਿਚਾਰਿਆ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ) । ਅੱਖਰਾਂ ਦੀ ਰਾਹੀਂ ਹੀ ਉਸਦੇ ਗੀਤ ਅਤੇ ਗੁਣਾਂ ਦਾ ਵਾਕਫ਼ ਹੋ ਸਕੀਦਾ ਹੈ। ਬੋਲੀ ਦਾ ਲਿਖਣਾ ਤੇ ਬੋਣਾ ਭੀ ਅੱਖਰਾਂ ਦੀ ਰਾਹੀਂ ਹੀ ਦੱਸਿਆ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ। (ਇਸ ਕਰਕੇ ਸ਼ਬਦ 'ਅਸੰਖ' ਵਰਤਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ, ਉਂਝ) ਜਿਸ ਅਕਾਲ ਪੁਰਖ ਨੇ (ਜੀਵਾਂ ਦੇ ਸੰਜੋਗ ਦੇ) ਇਹ ਅੱਖਰ ਲਿਖੇ ਹਨ, ਉਸ ਦੇ ਸਿਰ ਉੱਤੇ ਕੋਈ ਲੇਖ ਕਹੀਂ ਹੈ (ਭਾਵ, ਕੋਈ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਉਸ ਅਕਾਲ ਪੁਰਖ ਦਾ ਲੇਖਾ ਨਹੀਂ ਕਰ ਸਕਦਾ) । ਜਿਸ ਜਿਸ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਉਹ ਅਕਾਲ ਪੁਰਖ ਹੁਕਮ ਕਰਦਾ ਹੈ ਉਸੇ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ (ਜੀਵ ਆਪਣੇ ਸੰਜੋਗ) ਭੋਗਦੇ ਹਨ।ਇਹ ਸਾਰਾ ਸੰਸਾਰ, ਜੋ ਅਕਾਲ ਪੁਰਖ ਨੇ ਬਣਾਇਆ ਹੈ, ਇਹ ਉਸ ਦਾ ਸਰੂਪ ਹੈ ('ਇਹੁ ਵਿਸੁ ਸੰਸਾਰੁ ਤੁਮ ਦੇਖਦੇ, ਇਹੁ ਹਰਿ ਕਾ ਰੂਪੁ ਹੈ, ਹਰਿ ਰੂਪੁ ਨਦਰੀ ਆਇਆ') । ਕੋਈ ਥਾਂ ਅਕਾਲ ਪੁਰਖ ਦੇ ਸਰੂਪ ਤੋਂ ਖ਼ਾਲੀ ਨਹੀਂ ਹੈ, (ਭਾਵ, ਜਿਹੜੀ ਥਾਂ ਜਾਂ ਪਦਾਰਥ ਵੇਖੀਏ ਉਹੀ ਅਕਾਲ ਪੁਰਖ ਦਾ ਸਰੂਪ ਦਿੱਸਦਾ ਹੈ, ਸ੍ਰਿਸ਼ਟੀ ਦਾ ਜ਼ੱਰਾ ਜ਼ੱਰਾ ਅਕਾਲ ਪੁਰਖ ਦਾ ਸਰੂਪ ਹੈ) ।ਮੇਰੀ ਕੀਹ ਤਾਕਤ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਕਰਤਾਰ ਦੀ ਕੁਦਰਤਿ ਦੀ ਵੀਚਾਰ ਕਰ ਸਕਾਂ? (ਹੇ ਅਕਾਲ ਪੁਰਖ!) ਮੈਂ ਤਾਂ ਤੇਰੇ ਉਤੋਂ ਇਕ ਵਾਰੀ ਭੀ ਸਦਕੇ ਹੋਣ ਜੋਗਾ ਨਹੀਂ ਹਾਂ (ਭਾਵ, ਮੇਰੀ ਹਸਤੀ ਬਹੁਤ ਹੀ ਤੁੱਛ ਹੈ) । ਹੇ ਨਿਰੰਕਾਰ! ਤੂੰ ਸਦਾ-ਥਿਰ ਰਹਿਣ ਵਾਲਾ ਹੈਂ, ਜੋ ਤੈਨੂੰ ਚੰਗਾ ਲੱਗਦਾ ਹੈ, ਉਹੀ ਕੰਮ ਭਲਾ ਹੈ, (ਭਾਵ, ਤੇਰੀ ਰਜ਼ਾ ਵਿਚ ਰਹਿਣਾ ਹੀ ਅਸਾਂ ਜੀਵਾਂ ਲਈ ਭਲੀ ਗੱਲ ਹੈ) ।19।"},{"question":"Dame un ejemplo de trivia en está categoría : libros. ","answer":"¿Quién es la escritora de Un secreto en mi colegio?. "},{"question":"آسٹریلیا کا دارالحکومت کیا ہے؟","answer":"آسٹریلیا کے دارالحکومت کے بارے میں اکثر ابہام پیدا ہوتا ہے کیونکہ سڈنی اور میلبورن ملک کے دو مشہور اور آبادی والے شہر ہیں۔ تاہم، نہ تو سڈنی اور نہ ہی میلبورن آسٹریلیا کا دارالحکومت ہے۔کینبرا کو خاص طور پر 1913 میں آسٹریلیا کے دارالحکومت کے طور پر منتخب کیا گیا تھا کیونکہ یہ سڈنی اور میلبورن کے درمیان واقع تھا، اس طرح یہ دو ممتاز شہروں کے درمیان ایک سمجھوتے کے طور پر کام کر رہا تھا۔ یہ فیصلہ دارالحکومت کی حیثیت کے لیے بڑے شہروں کے درمیان کسی قسم کی دشمنی کو روکنے اور ایک غیر جانبدار اور مقصد کے مطابق دارالحکومت کے قیام کے لیے کیا گیا تھا۔جبکہ سڈنی اور میلبورن بڑے ثقافتی اور اقتصادی مراکز ہیں، کینبرا ملک کے انتظامی اور سیاسی دارالحکومت کے طور پر کام کرتا ہے، جہاں اہم سرکاری اداروں جیسے کہ آسٹریلوی پارلیمنٹ ہاؤس رہائش پذیر ہے۔ یہ انوکھا انتظام ان لوگوں کے لیے کچھ الجھنوں کا باعث بن سکتا ہے جو آسٹریلیا کے دارالحکومت کی تاریخ سے واقف نہیں ہیں۔"},{"question":"Khi bị cháy ở nhà cao tầng, bạn sẽ thoát nạn như thế nào?a) Chạy lênb) Đi bằng thang máyc) Chạy xuống bằng cầu thang bộ theo biển chỉ dẫn thoát nạn trong tòa nhà.d) Ở trong phòng đóng kín cửa lại","answer":"Đáp án: c"},{"question":"السؤال: من هو اول من اسلم من الرجال؟","answer":"الإجابة: أبو بكر الصديق "},{"question":"Эзелтен кыргыз наркы экен, мал таанылса жан түшүш, ат чабылбай даңаза кылбай кан түшүш, кан жолуна ат чабышты унутканыбыз нарк бузган болбойбу?-деген ким?а) Чубак б) Бакайв) Акбалта г) Серек","answer":"Эзелтен кыргыз наркы экен, мал таанылса жан түшүш, ат чабылбай даңаза кылбай кан түшүш, кан жолуна ат чабышты унутканыбыз нарк бузган болбойбу?-деген Серек. Туура жообу г) варианты болот."},{"question":"问：奥本海默的教育背景是什么？","answer":"答：奥本海默在哈佛大学获得了化学学士学位，然后在哥廷根大学获得了博士学位。"},{"question":"Кыргыз тилинде метонимиялык  жол менен пайда болгон көп маанилүү сөздөрдү кандай түшүндуруп бере аласың? Ага карат мисал келтире кетчи.","answer":"Жарайт, анде эмесе кеттик! Кыргыз тилинде метонимияда нерселердин ортосундагы байланыш-катыш ар түрдүү мүнөздө болот: -Адам менен анын кийиминин ортосундагы байланыш: Ак жоолук жылмайып эшиктен кирип келди. - Идиш менен анын ичиндеги нерсенин ортосундагы байланыш: Бир аз күтүп турсан болмок, казан кайнап алды. -Ар кандай наамдагы зат менен нерсенин ортосундагы байланыш: Жусуптун калем акысына деп жыйырма пачка индийскийди айдап жүргөн автолавкасын колтуктай чыккан тура. - Сан менен нерсенин ортосундагы байланыш: Биринчи, сахнага чыгып коюнуз. - Орун менен адамдардын ортосундагы байланыш: Зал ичи кол чаап жиберди. - Иш орду же мекеме менен адамдардын ортосундагы байланыш: Бул продукт Тойбосско тиешелүү. - Автор менен анын чыгармаларынын ортосундагы байланыш: Шекспирди жана Айтматовду окуганымда жан дүйнөмө башкача сезимдер келди.- Кыргыз тилинде адамдардын кызматын, кесип-өнөрүн, социалдык абалын билдирет:Доктор, бул ооруну кантип дарыласа болот? - Даам менен нерсенин ортосундагы байланыш: Ачка экенин билгенден кийин, сумкасынан таттуусун алды.- Нерсе менен ал жасалган материалдын ортосундагы байланыш: Анын апасынын оозу деле алтын, колу деле алтын.   Жооп канааттандырарлык эле болдубу?"},{"question":"\\"චූඩා මාණික්‍ය\\"චූඩා  කියන වචනෙ තේරුම මොකක්ද ? යෙදෙන වෙනත් තැන් තියනවද?","answer":"චූඩාමාණික්‍යය > ශිඛාමණි> සිළුමිණ (වුණා යැයි සිතමි)චූඩා/ ශිඛා/ සිළු යන වචන \\"මුදුන\\" යන අර්ථයෙන් යෙදේ."},{"question":"පහත ගීතය රචනා  කලේ කව්ද ?වනන්තරේ මහ රූස්ස ගහ කොළබිමට සමතලා කර අම්මේරාස්සයි වගෙ යන්ත්‍ර සූත්තරමහ සද්දෙන් යනවා අම්මේසිමෙන්ති කළු ගල් ලොරි පිට පටවාවේල්ල බඳිනා හැටි අම්මේබලාන ඉන්නට දවසක නුඹවත්එක්කරගෙන එන්නං අම්මේබින්තැන්නේ මම දහ දුක් විඳලා එදා ගමට ආදා අම්මේඋඹේ අතින් මගෙ දෑතේ කර ගැට අත ගාලා නාඬන් අම්මේමහියංගනයේ හේවිසියේ හඬ හැන්දෑවට ඇහුණම අම්මේසිල් අරගෙන උඹ ඉන්නා තාලේ අනේ මතක් වෙනවා අම්මේවත්ත පහළ පොල් අතු අහුලන්නට උදෙන්ම යන්න එපා අම්මේඋදේ රැයින් ඔය පිනි බාලා උඹ ලෙඩා දුකා වෙයි මගෙ අම්මේගිනි මද්දහනේ බැරි බැරි ගානේ ගම්මැද්දේ නොගිහින් අම්මේරැයක් නෑර මට හීනෙන් පෙනි පෙනි මං එනතුරු ඉඳහන් අම්මේ","answer":"අජන්තා  රණසිංහ"},{"question":"Apakah maksud \\"bendera putih\\"? Berilah contoh ayat untuknya.","answer":"Ia bermaksud mengaku kalah. Contoh ayat: Tentera musuh terpaksa mengibarkan bendera putih kerana tidak sanggup menentang serangan kerajaan Melaka yang hebat itu."},{"question":"Cé hé Hugh O'Flaherty? ","answer":"Ba shagart Éireannach Caitliceach Rómhánach é Hugh O'Flaherty, nó Aodh Ó Flatharta, an \\"falcaire fiáin na Vatacáine\\" (28 Feabhra 1898 – 30 Deireadh Fómhair 1963). I rith an Dara Cogadh Domhanda, bhí an Monsignor gníomhach sa Róimh ar son na bpríosúnach, ar son Giúdaigh agus éinne eile a d’fhéadfadh a bheith tógtha ag na húdaráis.Deirtear gur shábháil an Flathartach na mílte daoine i rith an uafáis. Chabhraigh an Moinsíneoir le breis is sé mhíle duine teacht slán ó Gestapo na Naitseach san iomlán, is cosúil.As Cathair Saidhbhín (i gContae Chorcaí) ab ea é ó dhúchas. Ba dhuine an-mheabhrach é. Bhí ardoideachas air –bronnadh trí cinn de dhochtúireachtaí air agus bhí máistreacht aige ar sheacht gcinn de theangacha. Níorbh aon iontas é gur choinnigh an Eaglais sa Róimh é, seachas é a chur ar ais ag obair i bparóiste éigin."},{"question":"¿Cuál es la respuesta a la siguiente adivinanza? Soy una animal muy elegante, veloz y poco fiero; y cuando quiero calzarme voy a casa del herrero.","answer":"el caballo"},{"question":"Ipa pfupiso yechinyorwa chinotevera:“Kuekisesaiza muviri kunobatsira zvikuru kune zvose zviri zviviri utano hwomuviri nepfungwa. Pamusoro pezvakanakira kurovedza muviri, sekuvandudza hutano hwemoyo uye kuwedzera simba remhasuru, zviitiko zvekunze zvinopawo mukana wekuona kunaka uye kugadzikana kwechisikigo. Inogona kuwedzera manzwiro ekugara zvakanaka uye kuderedza kushushikana uye kufunganya. Zvakakosha kugashira zvakanakira kurovedza muviri kwekunze uye kuzvibatanidza mumuitiro wako wenguva dzose. ”","answer":"pfupiso yechinyorwa ndiyoinotevera:Kuekisesaiza muviri kune zvakanakira hutano hwemuviri nepfungwa, kusanganisira kuwedzera kugara zvakanaka uye kuderedza kushushikana uye kufunganya. Zvakakosha kuisa maekisesaizi ekunze mumuitiro nemumagariro wako."},{"question":"Posita Ṣẹgun Oni gba igboro kan l’Ekiti, wọn lo tun fẹẹ ṣe gomina lẹẹkan si i","answer":"Kaakiri awọn ilu kan nipinlẹ Ekiti lawọn eeyan ti n ri posita Enjinnia Ṣẹgun Oni bayii, bo tilẹ jẹ pe eto ipolongo ibo gomina ko ti i bẹrẹ ni ipinlẹ naa.Ni awọn ibi kan niluu Ado Ekiti bii Ajilosun, Baṣiri, Ijigbo, ojuna Ilawẹ, Okeyinmi, atawọn ilu nla nla bii Ikẹrẹ-Ekiti, Ifaki, atawọn ibomi-in nipinlẹ naa ni wọn ti n ri aworan ọkunrin yii pẹlu asia ẹgbẹ oṣelu PDP to n tọka si i pe o n bọ waa ṣe gomina ipinlẹ naa lẹẹkan si i.Ṣe ṣaaju asiko yii ni awuyewuye ti n lọ nigboro wi pe ọkunrin naa ṣi tun fẹẹ pada waa ṣe gomina l’Ekiti, ni bayii ti awọn eeyan si ti ri i ninu agbada nla pẹlu fila bii ti Awolowo lori, ti asia ẹgbẹ oṣelu PDP naa tun wa loke tente posita ọhun, lo mu awọn eeyan maa sọ pe ọrọ naa ki i ṣe awuyewuye mọ, ootọ pọnbele ni.Ohun ti wọn si kọ sinu posita ọhun ni; “Ṣẹgun Oni, fun ipo Gomina, fun ilọsiwaju ọjọ ọla.”Ẹgbẹ kan to n jẹ Ekiti PDP Progressives ni wọn lo tẹ posita ọhun sita, awọn naa si ni wọn sọ pe wọn n polongo ibo fun ọkunrin oloṣẹlu naa bayii l’Ekiti.Laarin ọdun 2007 si ọdun 2010, lọkunrin yii fi dari ipinlẹ Ekiti gẹgẹ bii gomina nigba kan, ki igbimọ to n gbọ ẹjọ madaru to waye ninu eto idibo l’Ekiti, eyi ti Dokita Kayọde Fayẹmi pe, ti Adajọ Ayọ Isa Salami si jẹ alaga igbimọ kotẹmilọrun ọhun fi yọ Ṣẹgun Oni danu. Bi Kayọde Fayẹmi, ọmọ ẹgbẹ oṣelu Action Congress ṣe di gomina niyẹn.Ninu irin-ajo oṣelu ẹ naa ni Ṣẹgun Oni ti darapọ mọ ẹgbẹ oṣelu APC  lọdun 2014 lati kin Fayẹmi lẹyin, bẹẹ oun naa ni igbakeji alaga gbogbogboo ẹgbẹ APC lapa Guusu orilẹ-ede yii lasiko naa.Ọdun 2020, to kọja yii lo pada sinu ẹgbẹ oṣelu PDP, ẹsun to si fi kan Fayẹmi ti i ṣe gomina ipinlẹ ọhun bayii ni pe bii agbelẹhee loun ri ninu ẹgbẹ APC.Bo tilẹ jẹ pe ọkunrin oloṣelu yii paapaa ko ti i fẹnu ara ẹ sọ pe oun fẹẹ ṣe gomina lẹẹkan si i, sibẹ ̀ohun tawọn eeyan n sọ bayii ni pe pẹlu posita yii, o jọ pe ọkunrin naa n ba nnkan bọ lori idije-dupo gomina Ekiti lọdun 2022."},{"question":"Oyetọla fofin de isin aisun ọdun tuntun l’Ọṣun","answer":"Gbọnmọ-gbọnmọ nijọba ipinlẹ Ọṣun n lọgun rẹ bayii pe ko gbọdọ si ipejọpọ kankan fun isin aisun ọdun to yẹ ko waye lalẹ Ọjọbọ, Tọsidee, to n bọ yii.Atẹjade kan ti Akọwe ijọba ipinlẹ Ọṣun, Ọmọọba Wọle Oyebamiji, fi sita nirọlẹ ọjọ Aiku, Sannde, ọsẹ yii lo ti ke si awọn agbofinro lati ṣan ṣokoto wọn giri, ki wọn si fi panpẹ ofin gbe awọn to ba pe jọ pọ lati ṣe isin naa.Oyebamiji ṣalaye pe ọwọ yẹpẹrẹ lọpọlọpọ ṣi fi mu ọrọ ajakalẹ arun Koronafairọọsi, ijọba ko si gbọdọ fọwọ lẹran woran.Oyebamiji ni bii ina inu ẹẹrun ni arun naa n ran kaakiri bayii, gbogbo ilana idena rẹ si lo pọn dandan bayii pe ki awọn araalu maa tẹlẹ.O ni awọn agbofinro yoo maa lọ kaakiri lati ri i pe ko si isin aisun ọdun (Cross over nights) nibikibi nipinlẹ Ọṣun, nitori ojuṣe ijọba ni lati pese aabo fun ẹmi awọn araalu.Akọwe ijọba yii ni ko si aaye akunfaya nileejọsin; yala ṣọọṣi tabi mọṣalaasi, bẹẹ ni fifọwọ pẹlu omi to mọ ati lilo oogun apakokoro ṣe pataki, ojuṣe gbogbo eeyan si ni lati le Korona jinna nipinlẹ Ọṣun."},{"question":"Hãy chọn đáp án đúng nhất cho câu hỏi sau:Khi đang ở trong siêu thị, nếu phát hiện siêu thị đang bị cháy, bạn sẽ làm gì?a) Hô hoán cho mọi người chạyb) Tới nơi có cháy để chữa cháyc) Gọi điện cho lực lượng Cảnh sát PCCCd) Bình tĩnh, báo động có cháy, ngắt cầu giao điện, dùng phương tiện chữa cháy tại chỗ chữa cháy và gọi điện báo cho lực lượng","answer":"Đáp án c."},{"question":"සිඟිති\\" යන තද්ධිත පදයේ \\"ඉති\\" ප්‍රත්‍යය යෙදී ඇත්තේ,ස්වල්පාර්ථයෙන් ද?අතිශයාර්ථයෙන් ද?","answer":"ස්වල්පාර්ථයෙන්සුඟ + ඉතිසිඟිතිඅතිශයාර්ථය ( ඉතා කුඩා)"},{"question":"Атадан калган нарктарыбыз дегенде кандай түшүнөсүз?","answer":"-нике кыюу-бул дагы бир катар ырасмылары менен аткарылган, жол-\\rжоболору сөзсүз аткарылган;\\r-бала төрөлгөндө сүйүнчүлөө жана сүйүнчү берүү- сүйүнчүлөө –бул, \\rмыйзамдуу бала төрөлгөнүн элге жарыялоо болгон, сүйүнчүлөбөө - демек, \\rбалынын төрөлүшү мыйзамсыз сыяктуу сезилген, а сүйүнчүлөгөндө анын \\rсүйүнүчүн бөлүшүү, ырымдап бир нерсе берүү-нарктуулук болгон;\\r"},{"question":"Sao nào bị “giáng cấp” không còn là hành tinh trong hệ Mặt Trời?","answer":"Sao Diêm Vương (Pluto) từng được coi là một hành tinh. Tuy nhiên, Sao Diêm Vương mất trạng thái hành tinh ngày 24/8/2006 khi một nhóm nhà khoa học trong Hiệp hội Thiên văn học quốc tế bỏ phiếu để làm rõ định nghĩa về hành tinh.Các nhà khoa học thống nhất 3 tiêu chí để phân loại một thiên thể là một hành tinh: Bay trong quỹ đạo quanh Mặt Trời; Đủ lớn để có hình dạng gần tròn; Quỹ đạo phải tách bạch với các vật thể khác.Theo những tiêu chí này, sao Diêm Vương không được coi là hành tinh bởi quỹ đạo hình elip dẹt của nó cắt qua quỹ đạo của sao Hải Vương."},{"question":"Peribahasa : Dianjak layu, dianggur mati","answer":"Maksud : Sesuatu yang tidak boleh diubah-ubah lagi, jika berdemikian juga maka buruklah akibatnya."},{"question":"Sheeg magaca saddexan ee halgame Xalane, meesha uu ku geeriyooday iyo            sanadkii  uu geeriyooday? ","answer":" Waa Max’ed Cabdulle Xalane waxa uu ku geeriyooday Tog Wajaale sanadkii 1964."},{"question":"O que significa 'Notificação das Partes'?","answer":"'Notificação das Partes' envolve a comunicação oficial das decisões, despachos ou atos processuais às partes envolvidas no processo, garantindo que tenham conhecimento das ações tomadas."},{"question":"《清明上河图》是一幅什么样的画作？","answer":"清明上河图是中国北宋时期画家张择端创作的一幅绘画作品，完成于公元1085年。这幅画作是一幅长卷，以水墨为主，描绘了北宋都城汴京（今天的河南省开封市）繁忙的市井景象。清明上河图是中国绘画史上的杰作，被誉为中国绘画艺术的巅峰之一。这幅画整体上分为上、中、下三段，共有五十四个场景，呈现出了当时城市的繁荣景象，包括各种商业活动、日常生活、宗教仪式、社交场合等。画中人物形态各异，生动有趣，建筑物、桥梁、船只等细节也描绘得非常细腻。清明上河图不仅是一幅绘画作品，也是对当时社会、文化、风俗的生动描绘，具有极高的历史和艺术价值。"},{"question":"اكمل الفقرة التالية: وتُزرع الأراضي المحيطة بالبحيرة بعدد من المحاصيل، مثل الذرة وعباد الشمس والبرسيم، التي تحتاج إلى ريها بكميات كبيرة من المياه.","answer":"وفي تصريحات لوسائل إعلام محلية، أكد مدير الري بالمنطقة أردوغان أوزون أن المنطقة تشهد أعلى نسب جفاف خلال السنوات الأخيرة، إذ وصلت البحيرة إلى أدنى مستوى لها."},{"question":"கேள்வி: கோரியாலி விசை என்றால் என்ன?","answer":"விடை: காற்று, நீர், எரிபொருள்கள் முதலிய சுழல்தொகுதிகளில் கணக்கீடுகளை எளிமையாக்கச் சில சமயங்கள் பயன்படும் கற்பனை விசை. பிரஞ்சு இயற்பியலார் கோரியாலி 1835 இல் முதன்முதலில் இக்கருத்தைப் பயன்படுத்தினார்.கோரியாலிஸ் விளைவு என்பது ஒரு இயற்பியல் நிகழ்வாகும். ராக்கெட்டுகள் செயற்கைகோள்கள் போன்றவற்றில் விண்வெளி வீரர்கள் பயணம் செய்யும் போது இந்த கோரியாலிஸ் விளைவை அனுபவிக்க நேரிடும். விண்வெளி வீரர்கள் பயணம் செய்யும் ராக்கெட் அல்லது செயற்கைகோள்கள் போன்றவற்றை தங்களது இயக்கத்தின் போது சுழற்சி அடையும்."},{"question":"No futebol paulista, o que é o derby?","answer":"O derby paulista se refere ao confronto entre Corinthians e Palmeiras."},{"question":"Inona no rafitra velona lehibe indrindra eran-tany, ahitana vatohara an'arivony ary any amin'ny Oseana Pasifika?","answer":"Ny haran-dranomasina lehibe indrindra eran-tany, voaforon'ny haran-dranomasina an'arivony ary any amin'ny Oseana Pasifika, dia ny Great Barrier Reef."},{"question":"Làm bài nói cho bài tập: Các văn bản đã học: “Người đàn ông cô độc giữa rừng” (Đoàn Giỏi), “Dọc đường xứ Nghệ” (Sơn Tùng) và “Buổi học cuối cùng” (Đô-đê) đều có những nội dung thể hiện lòng yêu nước. Ý kiến của em như thế nào?","answer":"Kính thưa thầy/ cô giáo và các bạn! Trong những tiết học trước chúng ta đã được tìm hiểu các văn bản: “Người đàn ông cô độc giữa rừng” (Đoàn Giỏi), “Dọc đường xứ Nghệ” (Sơn Tùng) và “Buổi học cuối cùng” (Đô-đê), các văn bản đó đều có những nội dung thể hiện lòng yêu nước. Vậy lòng yêu nước là gì và được biểu hiện cụ thể như nào chắc hẳn trong mỗi bạn ngồi đây đều có câu trả lời riêng của mình. Bản thân tôi nhận thấy cả ba văn bản đều có nội dung liên quan đến tinh thần yêu nước nhưng mỗi văn bản có cách thể hiện rất khác nhau.Trước hết chúng ta cần hiểu yêu nước là yêu mảnh đất mình sinh ra và lớn lên, yêu tiếng nói, yêu con người; là hành động sẵn sàng đấu tranh bảo vệ Tổ Quốc mỗi lúc nguy nan. Vì thế mà biểu hiện của lòng yêu nước cũng khác nhau ở mỗi thời, mỗi hoàn cảnh.Trong thời chiến tranh loạn lạc, tình yêu nước được biểu hiện là đấu tranh chống giặc ngoại xâm, như nhân vật Võ Tòng trong “Người đàn ông cô độc giữa rừng” (Đoàn Giỏi). Võ Tòng yêu nước được thể hiện ở việc giết tên địa chủ tham lam độc ác, ở việc làm những mũi tên tẩm độc để bắn giặc Pháp. Hành động làm vũ khí thầm lặng nhưng lại thể hiện được tấm lòng lớn lao, chính vì thế mà ông Hai đã trịnh trọng cảm ơn người anh em của mình “xin đa tạ chú! Đa tạ chú!”. Lời cảm ơn không chỉ của ông Hai mà còn của nhân dân, đất nước.Tình yêu nước còn được thể hiện ở việc yêu tiếng mẹ đẻ, trân trọng, giữ gìn tiếng mẹ đẻ. Nhân vật thầy Ha-men trong “Buổi học cuối cùng” (Đô-đê) là gương mặt tiêu biểu cho tấm lòng yêu nước tha thiết ấy. Được tin buổi học cuối cùng, thầy đã ăn vận trang trọng khác mọi ngày với chiếc áo rơ-đanh-gốt màu xanh lục diềm lá sen…mũ lụa đen thêu, thái độ dịu dàng ân cần với học trò. Bài giảng cuối cùng của thầy say sưa dịu dàng về thứ tiếng mà thầy cho là hay nhất thế giới, trong sáng nhất, vững vàng nhất và thầy nhấn mạnh phải giữ lấy nó trong chúng ta và đừng bao giờ quên lãng nó. Tình cảm của thầy H-men còn được thể hiện trong những dòng chữ cuối cùng, cầm một hòn phấn dằn mạnh hết sức và thầy viết thật to “NƯỚC PHÁP MUÔN NĂM”.Đó là tình yêu nước trong thời chiến tranh, lọa lạc, còn ở thời bình tình yêu nước lại được biểu hiện ở tình yêu gia đình, tình yêu giữa con người với von người, ở việc giữ gìn bản sắc dân tộc. Trong văn bản “Dọc đường xứ Nghệ” (Sơn Tùng) tình yêu nước là câu chuyện về nhân vật lịch sử như Lý Nhật Quang chăm lo cho đời sống nhân dân, là phê phán vua Thục Phán chủ quan khinh địch để mất nước của cụ Phó bảng và các con. Yêu nước còn là việc am hiểu, giải thích cặn kẽ về các địa danh như hòn Hai Vai, núi Trống Thủng, núi Cờ Rách… là nhớ ơn đại thi hào Nguyễn Du…Như vậy chúng ta không nên hiểu lòng yêu nước một cách hạn hẹp, chẳng hạn quan niệm: chỉ ra trận đánh giặc mới là yêu nước. Yêu nước còn được thể hiện bằng nhiều cách thức, nhiều hành động ... khác nhau. Bản thân tôi còn ngồi trên ghế nhà trường cũng thể hiện lòng yêu nước của mình bằng việc học hành thật tốt, nghe lời ông bà cha mẹ và thầy cô, hòa thuận với an hem, bạn bè. Trên đây là bài nói của tôi về lòng yêu nước qua các văn bản đã học, cảm ơn thầy/cô và các bạn đã lắng nghe. Rất mong nhận được sự góp ý từ phía thầy/cô và các bạn."},{"question":"王国维《人间词话》将词分为三种境界，第三种境界是什么？","answer":"众里寻他千百度，蓦然回首，那人却在灯火阑珊处。"},{"question":"O que significa o ditado popular: \\"Quando um burro fala, o outro abaixa as orelhas\\"?","answer":"A frase quer dizer que é preciso escutar enquanto uma pessoa fala, sem ficar a interrompendo.Exemplo: “Não atrapalhe o discurso! Quando um burro fala, o outro abaixo a orelha!”"},{"question":"கேள்வி : பசிப்பிணி எனும் பாவி - இவ்வரி இடம் பெற்ற நூல் ","answer":"பதில் :  மணிமேகலை"},{"question":"కావేరిమహారాజులుంగారీగ్రహారం  అన్నది చిత్తూరు జిల్లాకు చెందిన వెదురుకుప్పం మండలంలోని  లోని గ్రామం, ఇది 2011 జనగణన ప్రకారం 166 ఇళ్లతో మొత్తం 638 జనాభాతో 650 హెక్టార్లలో విస్తరించి ఉంది. సమీప పట్టణమైన తిరుపతి కి 35 కి.మీ. దూరంలో ఉంది. గ్రామంలో మగవారి సంఖ్య 306, ఆడవారి సంఖ్య 332గా ఉంది. షెడ్యూల్డ్ కులాల సంఖ్య 269 కాగా షెడ్యూల్డ్ తెగల సంఖ్య 8. గ్రామం యొక్క జనగణన లొకేషన్ కోడ్ 596203[1].","answer":"కావేరిమహారాజులుంగారీగ్రహారం"},{"question":"ام كلير اديتها 47 دولار عشان تروح المحل. كلير اشترت أربعة أرغفة عيش وعلبتين لبن. كل رغيف عيش بيكلف 2 دولار وكل علبة لبن بتكلف 2 دولار. اتبقى لكلير فلوس قد ايه؟ خلينا نرد خطوة بخطوة:","answer":"تكلفة أرغفة العيش 4 × 2 دولار = 8 دولار. تكلفة اللبن 2 × 2 دولار = 4 دولار. مجموع تكلفة البقالة هي 8 دولار + 4 دولار = 12 دولار. اتبقى كلير 47 دولار - 12 دولار = 35 دولار. الإجابة: 35 دولار."},{"question":"Fenoy ny banga : \\"Ny rano no miala amin'ny _.\\"","answer":"Ny rano no miala amin'ny lainga."},{"question":"Inona no mampifandray an'i Catalonia, Andalusia, Cantabria, Galicia ? ","answer":"Samy faritra ao Espaina no mampifandray an'i Catalonia, Andalusia, Cantabria, Galicia."},{"question":"Cé hé Michael Lydon? ","answer":"Polaiteoir Éireannach ab ea Michael Lydon. Bhí sé ina bhall d'Fhianna Fáil. Rugadh sé ar an 10 Deireadh Fómhair 1907 agus fuair sé bás ar an 15 Bealtaine 1977. "},{"question":"राष्ट्रको अर्थतन्त्र निर्माणमा सिँचाइको कस्तो भुमिका हुन्छ ?","answer":"राष्ट्रको अर्थतन्त्र निर्माणमा सिँचाइको महत्त्वपूर्ण भुमिका हुन्छ । नेपालमा स्तित ६ सय भन्दा बढी नदीहरु बाह्रै महिना निरन्तर बगिरहन्छन् । यिनै नदीनालाहरुलाई कुलो, पैनी वा नहर निर्माण गरेर भूमिमा पर्याप्त सिँचाइ पुर्‍याउन सके राष्ट्रले खाद्यान्नमा परिनिर्भर हुनुपर्दैन । सिँचाइको उचित व्यवस्थापन गरेर धर्तीको उर्वराशक्ति बढाई प्रशस्त खाद्यान्न उत्पादन गरी विदेशमा निर्यात गरी वैदेशिक मुद्रा आर्जन गरी राष्ट्रिय अर्थतन्त्रलाई बलियो बनाउन सक्छौं । सिँचाइलाई आधुनिक र प्रविधिमैत्री बनाउन सकेमा खाद्यान्नमा आत्मनिर्भर हुन सक्छौं । रोजगारका अवसरहरु सिर्जना हुन्छन् अनि राजस्वमा वृद्धि हुन्छ । तसर्थ सम्पूर्ण उर्वर भूमिलाई सिचाइ पुर्‍याउन सकेमा राष्ट्रको अर्थतन्त्र दह्रो हुनेछ । "},{"question":"மனித உரிமை தினம் எப்போது?","answer":"மனித உரிமை தினம் டிசம்பர் 10"},{"question":" Waxaad sheegtaa Asxaabiyadii Rasuulkuﷺ, ku kafnay khamiis kiisii","answer":" Waxay ahayd Faadima binu-Asad (Cali binu Abii Taalib hooyadii) (RC)"},{"question":"问：在金融行业中，什么是区块链技术？","answer":"答：区块链技术是一种分布式数据库技术，它通过加密和去中心化的方式保证数据的安全和透明。"},{"question":"Мага дүйнөдөгү кызыктардан жазып бере аласыңбы?","answer":"Кашкулак бир түндө 76 метр туннелди каза алат."},{"question":"Lẹyin ọdun mẹtalelogun to ti n jokoo, Yinka Ayefẹlẹ ti le dide kọrin bayii","answer":"Gbajugbaja akọrin Tungba nni, Joel Ọlayinka Ayefẹlẹ, ti n dide duro bi ẹ ṣe n ka iroyin yii, eyi si jẹ lẹyin ọdun mẹtalelogun to ni ijamba ọkọ to kan eegun ẹyin rẹ.Ki i ṣe pe Yinka Ayẹfẹlẹ ṣiṣẹ abẹ lo fi le duro lori ẹsẹ rẹ lasiko yii, ọkan ninu awọn ololufẹ rẹ ti wọn n pe ni Ọnarebu Dare Akande, ti inagijẹ ẹ n jẹ Obama l’Amẹrika lo ra kẹkẹ kan to yatọ si ti ijokoo fun Yinka.Bo tilẹ jẹ pe o le jokoo ninu ẹ to ba wu u, sibẹ, bọtinni kan wa lara kẹkẹ naa to jẹ beeyan ba ti tẹ nnkan ti yoo fi naro bayii, kẹkẹ naa yoo ga soke ni, ẹni to si wa ninu ẹ yoo le duro lai si iṣoro kankan.Alẹ ọjọ Ẹti, Furaidee, to kọja yii ni Yinka Ayefẹlẹ ṣafihan kẹkẹ aramanda naa, niṣe lo duro ninu ẹ girigiri to si n rẹrin-in ayọ, kedere lo si han pe ẹbun pataki naa dun mọ ọn ninu gidi.Oju opo Instagiraamu ni Ayefẹlẹ gba lọ, nibi lo ti ṣafihan fidio kan to ti duro ninu kẹkẹ yii, bẹẹ lo n dupẹ lọwọ Darẹ Akande, o loun lo ra kẹkẹ naa foun.Lẹyin eyi lo tun kọ akọle kan to ka bayii pe‘’Ara tù mi pupọ bayii kuro ninu inira mi… Ọnarebu Dare Akande lo ra eyi fun mi (kẹkẹ naa). O o ni i mọ inira ni gbogbo ọjọ aye rẹ. O ṣeun pupọ, Dare Akande ti n jẹ Obama l’Amẹrika. Mo le dide kọrin bayii nibikibi. O jẹ ki igbagbọ mi pe ma a ṣi dide rin tun le kun si i. Mo gbagbọ.’’Bẹẹ ni Yinka Ayefẹlẹ fi ẹmi imoore ati idunnu han si ẹni to ṣe e loore nla yii, to jẹ ko le duro lori ẹsẹ rẹ lẹyin ọdun gbọgbọrọ.Ọjọ kejila, oṣu kejila, ọdun 1997, ni Yinka Ayefẹlẹ nijamba ọkọ to kan egungun ẹyin rẹ, latigba naa ni ko ti le dide mọ, ti ko si le fẹsẹ rẹ rin. Ṣugbọn ni bayii, Ayefẹlẹ ti n dide naro, o si ti n dide kọrin nibikibi."},{"question":"Кандай бешик ырларынан билесиз?","answer":"\\"Алдей, алдей\\", сөзү, обону: Гүлзада РыскуловаАй балкып жайнайт асманда,Асылым уктап жатканда.Аруулап шоола чачырайт,Арбалып таттуу уйкуңа.Бешиктеги ай наристем,Бек болсочу деп мен тилейм.Элине эмгек өтөгөн,Эр болсунчу деп мен тилейм.Алдей, алдей, алдей,алдей, алдей, алдей жан балам.Талпынып калса данегим,Жайнайт го менин карегим.Ак сүтүм берип балкыдым,Аман бир өссүн тирегим.Жарыгым менин чырагым,Жайнабай кантип турамын.Жараткан берген белегим,Данегим менин, данегим.Алдей, алдей, алдей,алдей, алдей, алдей жан балам."},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਗਉੜੀ ਮਹਲਾ ੫ ॥ਅਨਿਕ ਰਸਾ ਖਾਏ ਜੈਸੇ ਢੋਰ ॥ਮੋਹ ਕੀ ਜੇਵਰੀ ਬਾਧਿਓ ਚੋਰ ॥੧॥ਮਿਰਤਕ ਦੇਹ ਸਾਧਸੰਗ ਬਿਹੂਨਾ ॥ਆਵਤ ਜਾਤ ਜੋਨੀ ਦੁਖ ਖੀਨਾ ॥੧॥ ਰਹਾਉ ॥ਅਨਿਕ ਬਸਤ੍ਰ ਸੁੰਦਰ ਪਹਿਰਾਇਆ ॥ਜਿਉ ਡਰਨਾ ਖੇਤ ਮਾਹਿ ਡਰਾਇਆ ॥੨॥ਸਗਲ ਸਰੀਰ ਆਵਤ ਸਭ ਕਾਮ ॥ਨਿਹਫਲ ਮਾਨੁਖੁ ਜਪੈ ਨਹੀ ਨਾਮ ॥੩॥ਕਹੁ ਨਾਨਕ ਜਾ ਕਉ ਭਏ ਦਇਆਲਾ ॥ਸਾਧਸੰਗਿ ਮਿਲਿ ਭਜਹਿ ਗੋੁਪਾਲਾ ॥੪॥੫੫॥੧੨੪॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 190 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਅਰਜਨ ਦੇਵ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਬਾਣੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਹਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"ਜਿਵੇਂ ਪਸ਼ੂ (ਪੱਠਿਆਂ ਨਾਲ ਢਿੱਡ ਭਰ ਲੈਂਦੇ ਹਨ, ਤਿਵੇਂ ਸਾਧ ਸੰਗਤਿ ਤੋਂ ਵਾਂਜਿਆ ਰਹਿ ਕੇ ਆਤਮਕ ਮੌਤ ਮਰਿਆ ਹੋਇਆ ਮਨੁੱਖ) ਅਨੇਕਾਂ ਸੁਆਦਲੇ ਪਦਾਰਥ ਖਾਂਦਾ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈਤੇ (ਸੰਨ੍ਹ ਤੋਂ ਫੜੇ ਹੋਏ) ਚੋਰਾਂ ਵਾਂਗ (ਮਾਇਆ) ਦੇ ਮੋਹ ਦੀ ਰੱਸੀ ਨਾਲ (ਹੋਰ ਹੋਰ ਵਧੀਕ) ਜਕੜਿਆ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ ।੧।ਹੇ ਭਾਈ ! ਜੇਹੜਾ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਸਾਧ ਸੰਗਤਿ ਤੋਂ ਵਾਂਜਿਆ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ, ਉਸ ਦਾ ਸਰੀਰ ਮੁਰਦਾ ਹੈ (ਕਿਉਂਕਿ ਉਸ ਦੇ ਅੰਦਰ ਆਤਮਕ ਮੌਤੇ ਮਰੀ ਹੋਈ ਜਿੰਦ ਹੈ)ਉਹ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਜਨਮ ਮਰਨ ਦੇ ਗੇੜ ਵਿਚ ਪਿਆ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ, ਜੂਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਦੁੱਖਾਂ ਦੇ ਕਾਰਨ ਉਸ ਦਾ ਆਤਮਕ ਜੀਵਨ ਹੋਰ ਹੋਰ ਕਮਜ਼ੋਰ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ ।੧।ਰਹਾਉ।(ਆਤਮਕ ਮੌਤੇ ਮਰਿਆ ਮਨੁੱਖ) ਅਨੇਕਾਂ ਸੋਹਣੇ ਸੋਹਣੇ ਕੱਪੜੇ ਪਹਿਨਦਾ ਹੈ (ਗਰੀਬ ਮੈਲੇ ਕੱਪੜਿਆਂ ਵਾਲੇ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਉਸ ਤੋਂ ਡਰਦੇ ਰਤਾ ਪਰੇ ਪਰੇ ਰਹਿੰਦੇ ਹਨ ।ਸੋ, ਗਰੀਬਾਂ ਦੇ ਵਾਸਤੇ ਉਹ ਇਉਂ ਹੀ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ) ਜਿਵੇਂ ਪੈਲੀ ਵਿਚ (ਜਾਨਵਰਾਂ ਨੂੰ) ਡਰਾਣ ਲਈ ਬਨਾਉਟੀ ਰਾਖਾ ਖੜਾ ਕੀਤਾ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ ।੨।(ਹੋਰ ਪਸ਼ੂ ਆਦਿਕਾਂ ਦੇ) ਸਾਰੇ ਸਰੀਰ (ਕਿਸੇ ਨ ਕਿਸੇ) ਕੰਮ ਆ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ ।ਜੇ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਨਹੀਂ ਜਪਦਾ, ਤਾਂ ਇਸ ਦਾ ਜਗਤ ਵਿਚ ਆਉਣਾ ਵਿਅਰਥ ਹੀ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ ।੩।ਹੇ ਨਾਨਕ ! ਆਖ—ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਮਨੁੱਖਾਂ ਉਤੇ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਇਆਵਾਨ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈਉਹ ਸਾਧ ਸੰਗਤਿ ਵਿਚ (ਸਤ ਸੰਗੀਆਂ ਨਾਲ) ਮਿਲ ਕੇ ਜਗਤ ਦੇ ਪਾਲਣਹਾਰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦਾ ਭਜਨ ਕਰਦੇ ਹਨ ।੪।੫੫।੧੨੪।\\""},{"question":"ఇచ్చిన గేయానికి ప్రతిపదార్ధాలు మరియు భావం రాయండి:పట్టవలెరా దీని బలిమినికొట్టవలెరా మరుని రాజ్యంకట్టవలెరా గండపెండెంరసిక మండలిలో","answer":"ప్రతిపదార్థం :దీనిన్ = ఈ కన్యనుబలిమిని = బలవంతంగానైనాపట్టవలెరా = పొందాలిమరుని రాజ్యం = దానితో మన్మథ రాజ్యాన్నికొట్టవలెరా = జయించాలిరసిక మండలిలో = రసికుల సమూహాలలోగండపెండెం = ప్రత్యేకతనుకట్టవలెరా = చాటుకోవాలిభావం :బలవంతంగా అయినా ఈ కన్యను పొందాలి. మన్మథ రాజ్యాన్ని జయించాలి. రసికుల సమూహంలో గొప్పవాడినని అనిపించుకోవాలి."},{"question":"Đọc phần 5 trong bài Bức tranh của em gái tôi ngữ văn lớp 6 và trả lời các câu hỏi:a) Tại sao người anh “muốn khóc quá”?b) Câu nói “Không phải con đâu. Đấy là tâm hồn và lòng nhân hậu của em con đấy!” cho em hiểu gì về người anh?c) Điều gì đã tạo nên sự bất ngờ cho kết thúc truyện?","answer":"a) Người anh “muốn khóc quá” vì cậu ngỡ ngàng trước những tình cảm của người em dành cho mình, trong khi bản thân thì cáu kỉnh, ghen tị, tự ti, mặc cảm. Cậu cảm thấy bản thân không xứng với tình cảm mà em dành cho mình.b) Câu nói “Không phải con đâu. Đấy là tâm hồn và lòng nhân hậu của em con đấy!” cho em thấy người anh đã nhận ra những hành động, suy nghĩ trước đây của mình là vô lí, sai trái, cảm thấy tình cảm của em dành cho mình quá lớn.c) Điều đã tạo nên sự bất ngờ cho kết thúc truyện là bức tranh mà Kiều Phương vẽ anh trai mình. Khi nhìn bức tranh đó, người anh trai mới vỡ lẽ, thấy xấu hổ vì những hành động mình đã làm."},{"question":"السؤال: من هي التي تزوجها النبي وجعل مهرها عتقها؟","answer":"الإجابة: صفية بنت حيي بن الأخطب"},{"question":"*شحال عدد السنوات اللي كي دور فيها زحل دورة كاملة على الشمس؟","answer":"29 عاما ، 46 يوم"},{"question":"ما هو أشهر نوع من أنواع الأسماك التي تعيش في البحر الميت ؟","answer":"البحر الميت يخلو من الكائنات الحية."},{"question":"بحثت في الإنترنت عن إجابة لهذا السؤال ما هو أكبر وأضخم حيوان في العالم ؟. لكني لم أجد إجابة ، هل تستطيع الإجابة عليه؟","answer":"بالتأكيد الإجابة الصحيحة هي الحوت الأزرق."},{"question":"வினா: வஞ்சிப்பாவின் ஓசை?","answer":"விடை: தூங்கலோசை "},{"question":"ปรัชญาทางเศรษฐกิจที่พระบาทสมเด็จพระมหาภูมิพลอดุลยเดชมหาราช บรมนาถบพิตรมีพระราชดำรัสแก่ชาวไทย มีชื่อว่าอะไร","answer":"เศรษฐกิจพอเพียง"},{"question":"பெரியாரின் எழுத்துகளிலிருந்து  மேற்கோள் ஒன்றை தரவும்.","answer":"நமது மக்களின் மரியாதை காட்டும் தன்மைகள் எல்லாம் செத்துப்போனவர்களிடமே யொழியே, இருப்பவர்களிடம் இல்லை."},{"question":"Waa kuma qoraa?","answer":"Qoraagu waa laf-dhabbarka bulshada, haddii la rabo bulsho in ay jirto waxaa muhiim ah, in la helloqoraa, qoraagu wuxuu ka turjumayaa jiritaanka luqaddiisa hooyo, akhriste waxaad ogaataa ummad walbo dunidaan ku nool, waxa ay leedahay qoraa, sidoo kale, hadii larabo in la baabi’iyo bulsho, waxaa laga soo galaa saddex dhinac, 1: diintooda, 2: dhaqan kooda, 3: luqaddooda.Marka luuqadda ay bulsho leedahay , hadii la hor mariyo waxey ka dhigan tahay jiritaanka bulshada, haddaba akhriste, waa in aad diiradda saarto, qorista buugaagta, maxaa yeelay, marka aad wax qorto bulshada waad ka duwan tahay, xitaa goob walbo, waxaad la kul meysaa dad ku jecel, tusaalle, marka aad ilmo dhasho, waxaa la leeyahay, waa wareey ka leexda waa ilmihii qoraaga!, haddaba akhriste, haddii saas laguu wanaajinaayo waa in aad noqotaa qoraa, faafiya luqaddiisa hooyo, noqo mid kusoo kor- dhiyo bulshadiisa buugaag wax tar leh sida.Buugaagta kobciya maskaxda aadanaha. Buugaagta dhiira gellinta nolosha."},{"question":"Gabaygii Baaq ee Abwaan Maxamed Ibraahim Warsame (Hadraawi)","answer":"Adigoon cirka u bixinAma boodin leexadaAma badaha waaweynNafta aan ku biimaynBaariis adaan teginAma Boon ka sheekaynBarashada dalkaagaaHorta laga bogtaayooBeryo laysku hawlaaDhulku baaxad sooriyoBanan miidhan weeyaanAma waa bus iyo oonNinka buug ku haystowBeentaada weeyaanBalcad Jawhar ShalanboodBarakada QoryooleyWaxa canab bislaadeeBaydhabi u gaar tahayBoosaaso iyo BeerBixin-Duule LaaleysBiyo Guure KalabaydhBeeraha WajaaleeLagu reebay baahidaBaardheere iyo JilibWaa boqol kun oo maylDhulka lagu badhaadheeBeeyadu ku taalleeBadar lagu abuureeLagu ridey bariiskeeBalka lagu tallaaleeMuuskiyo babaygiiBarkadeen xareeddooWaxa taa ka sii badanDhulka bari samaadkeeBeeshaannu daaqdeeBarta aynu dhaqannaaBarqo dhereg ka joogteeIyadoo barwaaqo ahBalliyada xareeddiiKu bariisanaysooBidix midig dhan loo dayoBarigiyo galbeedkabaWaaberi cadceediiSoo saartey baallahaBilcilkiyo maraagiiShinbiruhu bulxamayaanIndhihii basaasowBoorame ma aragteen?Ma ogtahay barbaareeyHeesaha Barawn tumoAdigaan bogga u lulinBeerrey KabeebeyBismillaahi SayliciHana-haybsantii bariBatar iyo WareegtaaKuu baadi soocee.Ma ogtahay barbaarreeyQalabkana bud dhumucliyoWaran iyo billaawaaKuu baadi sooceeMa ogtahay barbaarreeyBarshin iyo darfooleyBayluuli xaradhlaaKuu baadi sooceeMa ogtahay barbaarreeyWaxa loo buseelaaAma qurux ku caan baxayAma laysku baantaaAma lagu bogsoodaaKal bugtaa ku faydaaKugu deeqa baashaalGuri bila ku magac dheerHablaheenna bilicdiyoBiligiyo il-waadka lehBilcantii shisheeya ahNinka beegsanaayowWaxaan kaaga baqayaaInaad baadi noqoteeCidla baylah keligaaYaanu bahalku kaa helinIsu buri geyaankaaBarta gogoshu kuu taalBahda lagama maarmaanBud-dhiggaaga koowaadBaaqaygu waa kaas."},{"question":"Apakah maksud \\"barang siapa menggali lubang, dia juga akan terperesuk ke dalamnya\\"?","answer":"Ianya bermaksud barang siapa yang berniat jahat terhadap orang lain, dia sendiri akan mendapat kecelakaan."},{"question":"لومړۍ جمله: مینه وال د هغه په زړه پورې تنوع ، تخنیکي جمالیات ، تاکتیک او ځواک څخه متاثره شوي وو. دویمه جمله: مینه وال د هغه په زړه پورې تنوع ، تخنیکي جمالیات ، تاکتیک او ځواک څخه متاثره شوي وو. پوښتنه: ایا لومړۍ او دویمه جمله یو شان معنی لري؟ هو یا نه؟","answer":"هو"},{"question":"Májẹ̀mú Láíláí ","answer":"Májẹ̀mú Láéláé je apa kinni ninu Bibeli Mimo, tí ó ní ìwé ọkàn dín logoji, tí wón kó ni èdè Hébérù. Apá kejì Bíbélì mímọ́ ni májẹ̀mú tuntun, èyí tí a ko ni èdè Griki, tí ó sì jẹ́ àkójọ ìwé metadinlogbon.Májẹ̀mú láéláé jẹ́ akojopo orísi àwọn ìwé tí orisi àwọn ènìyàn mímọ́ ko ni ọpọlọpọ ọdún sẹ́yìn.Àwọn Kristẹni pín majẹmu Láéláé sí merin: àkókò ni ìwé marun àkókò; àwọn ìwé tí ó sọ nípa ìtàn àwọn ọmọ Israeli, láti ìṣẹ́gun wọn ní Canani sí ìgbà tí a kọ Bábílónì lẹ́ru; àwọn ìwé ọgbọ́n àti ewì àti àwọn ìwé nípa àwọn wòlíì májẹ̀mú Láéláé.Májẹ̀mú láéláé jẹ́ àkójọ ìwé ọkàn dín logoji, bí ó tilè jẹ́ wípé ìwé Májẹ̀mú Láéláé tí àwọn ìjọ míràn bí ìjọ Kátólíìkì ń lò ní ìwé tí ó tó merindinladota."},{"question":"ਚਾਬੀਆਂ ਵਾਲਾ ਮੋਰਚਾ ਕਿਉਂ ਲੱਗਾ ?","answer":"ਅੰਗਰੇਜ਼ ਸਰਕਾਰ ਨੇ ਦਰਬਾਰ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਅੰਮ੍ਰਿਤਸਰ ਦੀ ਗੋਲਕ ਦੀਆਂ ਚਾਬੀਆਂ ਆਪਣੇ ਕੋਲ ਦਬਾ ਰੱਖੀਆਂ ਸਨ ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਪ੍ਰਾਪਤ ਕਰਨ ਲਈ ਸਿੱਖਾਂ ਨੇ ਚਾਬੀਆਂ ਵਾਲਾ ਮੋਰਚਾ ਲਗਾਇਆ ।"},{"question":"Martha Karua","answer":"Martha Karua (bi ni odun 1957)je oloselu ni ilu Kenya. o je a tele gun-duro egbe ti asofin fun awon gichu constituency ati awon eya alagbawi ti awon ga ejo ti orile-ede kenya.o je iranse ti ododo titi fiwasile lati pe si ipo ninu kerin 2009. Kaura ti aiyese ja fun aabo ti awon obirin ka otun ati idarasi si ijoba tiwatiwa ilana.Omobirin jackson karua ati iyawo re, Martha karua a bi on 22 Kẹsán 1957 ni kirinyaga DISTRICT ni aringbungbun ekun ti Kenya. mu soke ni abule ti Kimunye ni Gichugu loôdun, o ni keji ọmọ ni a ebi ti mẹjọ, mẹrin omobirin ati mẹrin omokunrin.O lọ Kabare Girls School wiwọ ati Kiburia Girls Secondary School ṣaaju ki o to ran rẹ East African School Certificate ni Karoti Girls High School ni Kirinyaga County. O iwadi ofin ni University of Nairobi lati 1977 to 1980. Laarin 1980 ati 1981 o ti oruko ni Kenya School of Law fun awọn amofin post mewa ofin dajudaju ti o ni kan pataki ṣaaju to gbigbani ti o ga si awọn orile eerun ti onigbawi ati iwe-ašẹ lati niwa ofin ni Kenya.Lẹhin ti se yanju, lati 1981 to 1987 Karua sise bi a Adajoô ni orisirisi ile ejo pẹlu awon ni Makadara, Nakuru ati Kibera, gbigba gbese fun ṣọra ìfòyemọ. Ni 1987, o sosi lati bẹrẹ ara rẹ ofin duro, Martha Karua & Co. onigbawi, ti o si sare titi 2002. Igba to wa ni ọtẹ iwadii ti Koigi Wamwere ati awọn ti o ti orile egbe ti asofin Mirugi Kariuki. Ni awọn ewu ti a blacklisted nipasẹ awọn Moi ijoba, o gbà orisirisi eto eda eniyan ajafitafita. Iṣẹ rẹ contributed si ebi ofin, paapa ni iyi si asopo-ini.Karua je kan egbe ti awọn alatako oselu agbeka ti o ni ifijišẹ agitated fun awọn reintroduction ti olona-kẹta ijoba tiwantiwa ni Kenya ni awọn tete 1990s. Kenya wà ni akoko labẹ awọn authoritarian ofin ti awọn Kenya African National Union (Kanu), awọn nikan ofin mọ oselu kẹta ni Kenya ati eyi ti a ti mu nipasẹ Aare Daniel arap Moi.Martha Karua darapo Kenneth Matiba ká Ford-Asili keta sugbon nu awọn kẹta yiyan tiketi si awọn ọlọrọ ati gbajugbaja tele Ori ti Public Service Geoffrey Kareithi. O ti a ki o si nṣe a tiketi ati support nipasẹ awọn Democratic Party of Kenya (DP) àgba ti o fe a mọ Bireki lati awọn Kareithi - Nahashon Njuno noir. Karua gba awọn 1992 gbogbo idibo lati di awọn MP fun Gichugu constituency ati obirin akọkọ agbẹjọro to wa ni popularly dibo to Asofin. O ti a pẹlu si ti yan bi awọn kẹta ká ofin àlámọrí akọwé laarin 1992 ati 1997.Ni odun 1998, Karua sile awọn ipo ti Shadow Minisita fun asa ati Social Iṣẹ eyi ti conflicted pẹlu rẹ ipo ti National Akowe fun orileede Affairs (ohun dibo ọfiisi) ti o ṣe rẹ awọn osise spokesperson on ofin ọrọ ti awọn kẹta. O ti yọ kuro lati resign rẹ si ipo bi awọn National Akowe.Ni 2001, nigbati awọn orileede Review Bill a ti gbe ṣaaju ki o to Ile, gbogbo atako pẹlu awọn sile ti Karua rin jade ti Asofin. The Bill ti a ti kọ nipa awọn alatako bi daradara bi Civil Society ṣugbọn Karua wà ninu awọn ti wo ti bi dibo asoju, dipo ti nrin jade, o yoo wa ni diẹ amoye lati wa ni Asofin ki o si fi awọn atako on gba. O nitorina yàn lati duro ni awọn asofin ati awọn rẹ atako si Bill won duly gba silẹ ninu awọn Hansard.Lẹyìn o wà laarin awon ti o akoso awọn oselu Iṣọkan NARC ti o gba 2003 Gbogbogbo idibo ni Kenya o si pari Kanu ká fere merin ewadun ti olori ni Kenya ká iseluTiti 6 April 2009 o je Minisita ti Idajo, National isomọra & orileede Affairs. O tun tẹlẹ yoo wa bi Minisita fun Omi Resources Management & Development, o si wà lẹhin imuse ti awọn Omi Ìṣirò 2002, eyi ti o ni niwon ki o si onikiakia awọn Pace ti omi atunṣe ati iṣẹ ipese ni Kenya.Karua duro Justice ati orileede Affairs Minisita ni Minisita lesa nipasẹ Kibaki on 8 January 2008, awọn wọnyi ni ariyanjiyan December 2007 idibo. Ninu ohun lodo BBC ká HARDtalk ni January 2008, Karua si wipe, nipa awọn iwa idaamu ti o ti ni idagbasoke lori awọn idibo esi, pe nigba ti ijoba ti ifojusọna ti awọn alatako Orange Democratic Movement (ODM) ti Raila Odinga le jẹ \\"igbogun mayhem ti o ba ti won padanu \\", ti o ti ya nipasẹ\\" bii \\"ti o, pipe awọn iwa-ipa\\" eya ṣiṣe itọju \\". Beere lati salaye, Karua so wipe o ti siso \\"categorically\\" ti awọn ODM ngbero eya ṣiṣe itọju. Odinga ti paradà ti a npe ni Karua ká ẹsùn \\"outrageous\\". Karua ni ṣiṣi ijoba egbe ni idunadura pẹlu awọn alatako nipa awọn oselu ifarakanra ti yorisi lati idibo. Awọn oselu idaamu bajẹ yori si awọn fawabale ti a agbara-pínpín adehun laarin Kibaki ati Odinga. Ni awọn sayin Iṣọkan Minisita ti a ti kede lori 13 April 2008, Karua joko ninu rẹ post bi Minisita ti Idajo, National isomọra ati orileede Affairs.O ti ofi bi awọn orilẹ-Alaga ti NARC-Kenya oselu keta lori 15 November 2008. Nibẹ wà fere ko si ifigagbaga idibo nigba ti kẹta ká orilẹ-asoju 'Adehun ni Bomas of Kenya ni ilu Nairobi bi gbogbo awọn ijoye pẹlu Ms Karua wọn ń ofi. Lẹhin rẹ rii o lẹsẹkẹsẹ polongo o yoo wa ni gunning fun awọn ga oselu ijoko ti jije Aare ni Kenya ká 2012 idibo.Martha Karua kosesile bi Minisita fun Idajo ati ofin orileede Affairs on 6 April 2009, so frustrations ni batiri rẹ ojuse. A ko o apẹẹrẹ ti rẹ frustrations je nigba ti Aare Mwai Kibaki yàn Onidajọ lai rẹ ìmọ kan diẹ ọjọ ṣaaju ki rẹ denu. O si wà ni igba akọkọ ti Minisita to resign atinuwa niwon 2003.Martha Karua oludije fun awọn Ọdọmọbìnrin ni 2013 labẹ awọn NARC kẹta tiketi ibi ti o ti padanu.Karua ni o ni awọn aworan ti jije combative ati obinrin kan ti unbending pari. Ni akoko kan ninu rẹ Kirinyaga District nigba ti Kanu wà si tun ni agbara, Karua bosipo rin jade lori Aare Moi ti a ki o si sọrọ a enia ni DISTRICT papa. Yi je ohun dani àpapọ ìmọ defiance lodi si Moi, ti a ki o si bẹru o si jọba awọn orilẹ-ede pẹlu ohun irin ikunku.O ti a asiwaju alapon fun awọn siterio ti tiwantiwa aaye ati iwa oran ni Kenya. O ti a ti lowo ninu kaleô obirin awọn ẹtọ nipasẹ àkọsílẹ anfani ẹjọ, nparowa ati agbawi fun awọn ofin ti o mu ki o si dabobo ẹtọ awọn obirin ni nipasẹ rẹ iṣẹ pẹlu orisirisi obirin ajo, paapa ni International Federation of Women Lawyers (FIDA-Kenya) ati awọn League of Kenya Women oludibo.Ni February 2009 nigba rẹ akoko bi Minisita ti Idajo, o ni kete ti ní a kikan ariyanjiyan pẹlu awọn Minisita fun Ise-ogbin William Ruto ni a minisita ipade bi Aare joko laiparuwo, wiwo awọn sparring iranṣẹ, a orisun ni ipade sọ pé: \\"The Aare ṣe ko sọ tabi ṣe ohunkohun. O si o kan joko nibẹ laiparuwo wiwo bi awọn iranṣẹ si mu lori kọọkan miiran. O je ni rudurudu, gbona ati eruptive. \\" Awọn meji minisita ti a ti sparring ni gbangba lori akoko kan ti ọsẹ mẹta, pẹlu Ms Karua demanding Mr Ruto ká denu lori a agbado sikandali.O ti a tọka si bi \\"awọn nikan eniyan\\" ni PNU Minisita, pelu awọn ti o daju wipe gbogbo awọn miiran Minisita omo wà ọkunrin.Martha Karua ni ibe akiyesi lẹhin ti o ati ki o kan Catholic alufa, kn Dominic Wamugunda, ni won carjacked ati ja lori 6 December 2003 pẹ ni alẹ nigba ti enroute si ile rẹ ni Wamugunda ká ọkọ ayọkẹlẹ. Awọn bata wà nikan. O si wi ni Asofin lori ni bi nipa MPS ti o wà abẹ ide lati pese eyikeyi alaye fun idi ti o wà ni Wamugunda ká ọkọ ayọkẹlẹ tabi ohun ti o ti ṣe ni akoko ti awọn carjacking. Rẹ aabo olusona wà ko bayi nigbati awọn ilufin lodo; Karua si wi pe nigba ti o ko lero o nilo awọn ẹṣọ, o ko lo wọn. Martha Karua ni a ikọsilẹ, pẹlu ni akoko ti rẹ royin sepo pẹlu Wamugunda.Martha Karua contested ni nṣiṣẹ fun awọn Ọdọmọbìnrin ni 2013. New lati siwo ofin ti kilo ajodun contenders lati nigbakannaa koni asofin ijoko ki o ní lati fun soke rẹ anfani ninu rẹ ni itumo ailewu Gichugu ijoko pẹlu o pọju ewu ti a jade iselu patapata ti o ba ti o padanu rẹ ajodun idu) ó wá ni kẹfa pẹlu 43.881 votes, nipa gbogbo iroyin a dismal afihan, ibi ti si iyalenu ti ọpọlọpọ awọn fun u ka o ani trailed Mohammed Abduba Dida, a pipe aimọ ki o si decidedly a lightweight, ti o polled 0.43% lodi si rẹ ara 0,38 % ti lapapọ ajodun ibo.Wọnyi yi ati lẹhin igba pipẹ ni ojulumo obscurity ati itakete ninu awọn oselu si nmu, o ti reappeared ni gbangba aye laipe, hinting on lotun oselu okanjuwa ninu awọn bọ 2017 ajodun idibo ninu eyi ti Aare Uhuru Kenyatta ti wa ni o ti ṣe yẹ lati wá tun-idibo. O je ninu awọn atako olori ti o Aare oba pade nigbati o ti gbalejo nipa Uhuru ni 2015 ni oba ma ká nikan ajodun ibewo si Kenya. Akoso, o dabi lati ti tẹ si okun, awọn ifilelẹ ti awọn atako oselu aṣọ mu nipa Raila Odinga, ani bi o ati Raila ti ti gun-duro oselu ọta ati fun igba pipẹ dabi enipe julọ išẹlẹ ti ti oselu ore. Karua nigbamii abandoned rẹ oselu ibasepo pelu Raila.Ni December 2015 Karua gba eleyi si gbigba a multimillion-iwon \\"ẹbun\\" si rẹ ajodun ipolongo owo lati British American Tobacco. Karua so wipe o ro wipe awọn ilowosi nipa Paul Hopkins, a adan abáni, je kan ti ara ẹni ẹbun. Awọn owo ti a ti san nipasẹ Mary M'Mukindia ti o ti nṣiṣẹ Karua ká ipolongo. Šaaju si yi, Martha Karua ti gun gbadun ni rere ninu kikopa untainted nipa ibaje nipa ọpọlọpọ sugbon yi bribery Iroyin han lati lé iyemeji lori yi. Ko si culpability ti a ti fihan tabi owo lepa rẹ. Karua ti muduro wipe o le wa ko le ibajeNi 1991 Karua ti a mọ nipa Human Rights Watch bi a eto eda eniyan atẹle.Ni December 1995 o ti fun un nipa awọn Federation of Kenya Women Lawyers (FIDA) fun imutesiwaju awọn fa ti awọn obirin. Ni 1999 ni Kenya Abala ti awọn International Commission of jurists fun un rẹ ni 1999 Kenya teletele ti Odun ati ni odun kanna kanna oṣu, ofin awujọ ti Kenya (LSK) fun un rẹ ni ofin awọn oṣiṣẹ nitori tokantokan Eye."},{"question":"Мындай үлгү берилди: күйгүзүү : өчүрүүУшуну карап туруп, төмөнкү варианттардын кайсынысы туура келээрин аныктап бер:(А) маанилүү : көңүл буруу(Б) маалкатуу : тездетүү(В) камыгуу : чалыгуу(Г) сүйлөө : токтоо","answer":"Үлгүдө берилген \\"күйгүзүү\\" жана \\"өчүрүү\\" сөздөрү бири-бирине карата толук антонимдер. Аларга окшоп толук антонимдерди издеп тапканга аракет кылалы. (А) вариантындагы \\"маанилүү\\" жана \\"көңүл буруу\\" сөздөрү антонимдер эмес. (Б) вариантындагы \\"маалкатуу\\" (убакыт чоюу) жана \\"тездетүү\\" бири-бирине карата толук антонимдер. (В) вариантындагы \\"камыгуу\\" (ысуу, тердөө) жана \\"чалыгуу\\" (чарчоо) антонимдер эмес. (Г) вариантындагы \\"сүйлөө\\" жана \\"токтоо\\" толук эмес, контексттик антонимдер болушу мүмкүн.Ошентип, туура жооп төмөнкү болду: (Б) маалкатуу : тездетүү"},{"question":"Apakah maksud \\"air dalam terenang\\"?","answer":"Hidup yang aman dan tenteram"},{"question":" Maxay kala yihiin tiirarka uuiimaanku ku taaganyahay (arkaanul-iimaan)?","answer":"Tiirarka iimaanku waa lix tiir oo kalalah:1) In Ilaahey la rumeeyo.2) In Malaa igtiisa la rumeeyo.3) In Kutub-tiisa la rumeeyo.4) In Rasuulladiisa la rumeeyo.5) In Maalinta qiyaame la rumeeyo.6) Iyo in Qaddarka Alle  shar iyokhayrba la rumeeyo."},{"question":"विरुध्दार्थी शब्दांची अयोग्य जोड़ी ओळखा?गुण × दोषआवक × जावकअतिवृष्टि × दूरदृष्टिइहलोक × परलोक","answer":" अतिवृष्टि × दूरदृष्टिअतिवृष्टीचा विरुध्दार्थी शब्द \\"दुष्काळ\\" हा आहे. म्हणून अतिवृष्टि × दूरदृष्टि ही अयोग्य जोडी आहे. इतर तीन पर्याय योग्य आहेत."},{"question":"صحابية قتلت تسعه من الروم بعمود قسطاطها؟","answer":"أسماء بنت يزيد بنت السكن الأنصارية."},{"question":"Qual é a capital da Tonga?","answer":"Nucualofa."},{"question":"Apakah maksud 'bahasa pasar'?","answer":"Ia bermaksud bahasa yang tidak mengikut tatabahasa untuk bahasa asal. Salah satu punca bahasa pasar adalah hasil kacukan antara bahasa Melayu dengan bahasa-bahasa lain. Bahasa pasar juga disebabkan oleh kewujudan kelompok sosial yang hendak mencipta identiti mereka yang tersendiri. Contoh bahasa pasar ialah penggunaan perkataan dari bahasa lain (contohnya \\"I\\", \\"You\\") ataupun penggunaan perkataan yang tidak wujud dalam kamus rasmi (contohnya \\"kacang je\\")."},{"question":"Продолжите следующую фразу: Паркс представлял Англию...","answer":"и завоевал серебряную медаль в среднем весе (-75 кг) в Играх Содружества 1978 года в Эдмонтоне, Альберта, Канада."},{"question":"كم يبلغ طول الأمعاء الدقيقة ؟","answer":"6 أمتار"},{"question":"வினா: ஓசோன் படலம் எதிலிருந்து நம்மைப் பாதுகாக்கிறது?","answer":"விடை: புற ஊதா கதிர்கள்"},{"question":"Saan ang \\"Strawberry Capital of the Philippines\\"?","answer":"Ang bayan ng La Trinidad sa lalawigan ng Benguet ay ang \\"Strawberry Capital of the Philippines\\". Dahil sa lamig ng klima roon buong taon, nakapagtatanim ng sapat na dami ng presa o strawberry para ipangnegosyo. "},{"question":"Боору катуу дегенде кандай түшүнөсүз?","answer":"Боору катууТаш боор, бирөөгө жан тартпаган, ырайымсыз;Аябай күлүү, ыкшып күлкүсүн тыя албоо;Чоңоюу, бойго жетүү, баралына келүү, толуу."},{"question":"Apakah maksud \\"bagai belalang di atas kacang\\"?","answer":"Usaha yang mustahil berhasil"},{"question":"வினா:உன்னைப்போல் ஒருவன் என்ற நாவலை இயற்றியவர்?","answer":"விடை: ஜெயகாந்தன்"},{"question":"آسام ریاست کے بارے میں بتایں","answer":"آسام بھارت کی ریاستوں میں ایک ریاست سے۔ یہ ریاست، بھارت کے شمال مشرق میں واقع ہے۔ اس کا دار الحکومت دسپور۔ یہ ریاست قومی پارکوں کے لیے مشہور ہے۔قومی پارکبھارت کا مشہور جانور گینڈا (“رائنوسیراس“) کازی رنگا قومی پارک، آسام میں۔آسام اور نباتیاتریاست آسام گھنے جنگلوں سے، بالخصوص سرسبز باغیوں سے بھری ریاست۔آسام میں آرکڈز بکثرت پائے جاتے ہیں۔ ایک قسم - بھاتو پھول یا وانڈا کویرولیا، 'بلیو آرکڈ'۔یہ اصلی وانڈا کورولیا ہے، 'بلیو آرکڈ۔آسام میں بہت سارے قومی پارک، پرندوں کے سنکچوری۔ جو سیاحوں کے کشش کا مرکز۔"},{"question":"ما هي السورة التي تسمى القتال؟","answer":"– سورة محمد."},{"question":"දේදුන්නක වර්ණ පහක් ඇත. මෙය නිවැරදිද?","answer":"නැත, දේදුන්නක වර්ණ පහක් ඇත ප්‍රකාශය අසත්‍යය. දේදුන්නට වර්ණ 7ක් ඇත. (VIBGYOR)"},{"question":"Ibọn ati ọta rẹpẹtẹ ni wọn ba lapo Adigun atọrẹ ẹ ni Badagry","answer":"Awọn afurasi ọdaran meji kan, Adigun Jeremiah, ẹni ọdun mẹtadinlọgbọn ati Okorocha Covenant, ẹni ọdun mejidinlọgbọn, ti wa lakata awọn ọlọpaa ọtẹlẹmuyẹ ni Panti, Yaba, bayii. Ibẹ ni wọn ti n ṣalaye ohun ti wọn fẹẹ fi ibọn ti wọn ka mọ wọn lọwọ ṣe.Irọlẹ ọjọ Abamẹta, Satide yii, ni Alukoro ọlọpaa Eko, Olumuyiwa Adejọbi, sọ f’ALAROYE pe ọwọ tẹ awọn mejeeji. Wọn ni mẹta ni wọn, ọkada Bajaj kan ni wọn n gun lọ tawọn ọlọpaa teṣan Ilasan fi da wọn duro lori titi marosẹ to lọ lati Lẹkki si Ẹpẹ ni nnkan bii aago mẹsan-an aabọ alẹ.Yatọ si pe awọn ti ọkada naa ko ju iye ero to yẹ ko gbe lọ, wọn ni ere asapajude ti wọn ba kọja lori titi naa mu ifura lọwọ, lawọn ọlọpaa ba gba tẹle wọn, ko si pẹ ti wọn fi le wọn ba.Amọ bi wọn ṣe fẹẹ duro, niṣe ni ẹni kẹta ti wọn loun lo n wa ọkada naa ja awọn meji to gbe sẹyin silẹ, lo ba fi ọkada ẹ si jia, o sa lọ bẹẹ ni.Nigba ti wọn maa yẹ ara awọn mejeeji ti ọkada ja ju silẹ wo, ibọn oyinbo alawọ goolu kan ni wọn ba lapo wọn, wọn ti loodu ọta sinu ẹ temu, wọn si tun ko awọn ọta rẹpẹtẹ sinu apo ṣokoto wọn.Wọn lawọn ọlọpaa naa beere pe nibo ni wọn ti ri ibọn, ki si ni wọn fẹẹ fi i ṣe, iṣẹ wo ni wọn n ṣe, lọrọ ba di wo-mi-n-wo-ẹ, awọn afurasi ọdaran naa ko ri alaye gidi ṣe, wọn o si jẹwọ iṣẹ buruku ti wọn n tori ẹ mu ibọn kiri.Bi wọn ṣe fọrọ naa to Kọmiṣanna ọlọpaa Eko, Hakeem Odumosu, leti lo ni ki wọn tete maa ko awọn mejeeji lọ si Panti, wọn ni ọrọ wọn maa wulo lati tete ri ẹkẹta wọn mu, ki iwadii ti wọn maa ṣe lori ọrọ wọn le tete pari, tori ati gbe igbesẹ to kan."},{"question":"Uzman araştırmacı nedir?","answer":"Başlıca hizmet dalı araştırma olup bütün enerjisini takip ve analize ayıran personellere araştırma uzmanı denir. İnceleme yapmakla görevli çalışanlar, dönemsel planların veya devamlı işlerin merkezinde bulunur. Hizmeti iyileştirerek kazancı artırmak ancak profesyonel araştırmalarla sağlanabilir."},{"question":"පහත ගීතය රචනා  කලේ කව්ද ?බෝ පතක් වැටෙන සේනුඹ වැටී ලෙඩ ඇඳේනිසොල්මනේ ඇයි අම්මේපෙරහැරක් වගේ සිටිකොඩි වැලක් වගේ නැගිදූ පුතුන් කොහේ අම්මේමුතු පබළු අතේ නැතසවි බලද හිතේ නැතතනිකමද හිතින් දැරුවේකිරි සුවඳ හමා ගියමහ ගෙදර පාළු බවමව් සුවඳ වසා පැතිරේසිල් සුවඳ පිරූ සිතගුණ සුවඳ දැනේ මටපන්සලක් වගේ අම්මේසා දුකින් පෙලෙන සඳකිරි පොවා කඳුළු හෙලුනුඹ නිවන් දකින් අම්මේ","answer":"රඹුකන සිද්ධාර්ථ හිමි"},{"question":"Dame un ejemplo de trivia en está categoría : deporte. ","answer":"Pregunta:  ¿Cuántos Supertazones ganó Sonny Jurgensen? "},{"question":"राजाराम या पराक्रमी छत्रपतीचा वयाच्या तिसाव्या वर्षी मृत्यू कोठे झाला ?","answer":"राजाराम या पराक्रमी छत्रपतीचा वयाच्या तिसाव्या वर्षी मृत्यू सिंहगडावर झाला."},{"question":"Мага кызыктуу факты жазып берчи ?","answer":"Албетте , мына сизге кызыктуу факты :Эгерде сиз дагы деле паспорттогу сүрөтүңүзгө тынчсызданып жатсаңыз, анда Рамсес IIнин паспортуна карап коюңуз.Легендарлуу Фараон Рамзес IIге анын 3000 жаштагы мумиясын зарыл калыбына келтирүү үчүн Парижге жеткирүүгө жарактуу Египеттин паспорту берилген."},{"question":"Question: విజయపురం మండలంలో 1992 నాటికి మొత్తం ఎన్ని చేపల చెరువులు ఉన్నాయి?Answer the question with Yes or No. If it is not possible then answer None.Hint: విజయపురం, ఆంధ్ర ప్రదేశ్ రాష్ట్రములోని చిత్తూరు జిల్లా, విజయపురం మండలం లోని గ్రామం..[1]విజయపురం చిత్తూరు జిల్లా, ఇదే పేరుతో ఉన్న మండలం యొక్క కేంద్రము. ఇది సమీప పట్టణమైన నగరి నుండి 25 కి. మీ. దూరంలో ఉంది. 2011 భారత జనగణన గణాంకాల ప్రకారం ఈ గ్రామం 1058 ఇళ్లతో, 3750 జనాభాతో 1561 హెక్టార్లలో విస్తరించి ఉంది. గ్రామంలో మగవారి సంఖ్య 1890, ఆడవారి సంఖ్య 1860. షెడ్యూల్డ్ కులాల సంఖ్య 1242 కాగా షెడ్యూల్డ్ తెగల సంఖ్య 206. గ్రామం యొక్క జనగణన లొకేషన్ కోడ్ 596377[2].పిన్ కోడ్: 517586.విజయపురం చిత్తూరు జిల్లా, ఇదే పేరుతో ఉన్న మండలం యొక్క కేంద్రము. ఇది సమీప పట్టణమైన నగరి నుండి 25 కి. మీ. దూరంలో ఉంది. 2011 భారత జనగణన గణాంకాల ప్రకారం ఈ గ్రామం 1058 ఇళ్లతో, 3750 జనాభాతో 1561 హెక్టార్లలో విస్తరించి ఉంది. గ్రామంలో మగవారి సంఖ్య 1890, ఆడవారి సంఖ్య 1860. షెడ్యూల్డ్ కులాల సంఖ్య 1242 కాగా షెడ్యూల్డ్ తెగల సంఖ్య 206. గ్రామం యొక్క జనగణన లొకేషన్ కోడ్ 596377[3].పిన్ కోడ్: 517586.విద్యా సౌకర్యాలుగ్రామంలో ప్రభుత్వ ప్రాథమిక పాఠశాలలు నాలుగు, ప్రభుత్వ ప్రాథమికోన్నత పాఠశాల ఒకటి , ప్రభుత్వ మాధ్యమిక పాఠశాల ఒకటి ఉన్నాయి. ఒక ప్రైవేటు జూనియర్ కళాశాల  ఉంది.ఒక ప్రభుత్వ అనియత విద్యా కేంద్రం ఉంది. సమీప బాలబడి పన్నూరులో ఉంది.సమీప ప్రభుత్వ ఆర్ట్స్ / సైన్స్ డిగ్రీ కళాశాల, ఇంజనీరింగ్ కళాశాల , సమీప వైద్య కళాశాల, దివ్యాంగుల ప్రత్యేక పాఠశాల తిరుపతి లోనూ, మేనేజిమెంటు కళాశాల, పాలీటెక్నిక్‌లు సమీప వృత్తి విద్యా శిక్షణ పాఠశాల నగరిలోను ఉన్నాయి.వైద్య సౌకర్యంప్రభుత్వ వైద్య సౌకర్యంవిజయపురంలో ఉన్న ఒకప్రాథమిక ఆరోగ్య కేంద్రంలో ఇద్దరు డాక్టర్లు , 8 మంది పారామెడికల్ సిబ్బందీ ఉన్నారు. ఒక ప్రాథమిక ఆరోగ్య ఉప కేంద్రంలో డాక్టర్లు లేరు. ఇద్దరు పారామెడికల్ సిబ్బంది ఉన్నారు. ఒక అలోపతి ఆసుపత్రిలో ఒక డాక్టరు, ఏడుగురు పారామెడికల్ సిబ్బందీ ఉన్నారు. ఒక పశు వైద్యశాలలో ఒక డాక్టరు, ఇద్దరు పారామెడికల్ సిబ్బందీ ఉన్నారు. ఒక సంచార వైద్య శాలలో డాక్టర్లు లేరు. ముగ్గురు పారామెడికల్ సిబ్బంది ఉన్నారు. సమీప సామాజిక ఆరోగ్య కేంద్రం, మాతా శిశు సంరక్షణ కేంద్రం, టి. బి వైద్యశాల గ్రామం నుండి 10 కి.మీ. కంటే ఎక్కువ దూరంలో ఉన్నాయి. ప్రత్యామ్నాయ ఔషధ ఆసుపత్రి, డిస్పెన్సరీ, కుటుంబ సంక్షేమ కేంద్రం గ్రామం నుండి 10 కి.మీ. కంటే ఎక్కువ దూరంలో ఉన్నాయి. ప్రైవేటు వైద్య సౌకర్యంతాగు నీరుగ్రామంలో కుళాయిల ద్వారా...నీటి సరపర. ","answer":"None"},{"question":"Бухарест жөнүндө кыскача эмне айта аласың ?","answer":"Бухарест - Румыниянын борбору жана эң чоң шаары .Бухарест - бай тарыхы жана ар түрдүү архитектурасы бар шаар, аны мурда көбүнчө \\"Кичи Париж\\" деп аташкан. Бул жерде көптөгөн кооз парктар жана сонун музейлер бар, кызыктуу маданий иш-чаралар өткөрүлөт."},{"question":"பெரியாரின் எழுத்துகளிலிருந்து  மேற்கோள் ஒன்றை தரவும்.","answer":"மனிதனுக்கு நாளைக்கு வேண்டுமே என்கிற வேலையும், தன்னம்பிக்கை அற்ற தன்மையும், திருப்தியடையாத ஆசையும் அதிகம் இருக்கிறது."},{"question":"Wọn ba oku ololufẹ meji ninu yara, wọn ni Sniper ni wọn mu","answer":"Ki i ṣe ayẹwo dokita lo fidi ẹ mulẹ pe awọn ololufẹ meji, Emmanuel Oshiotu, ẹni ọdun mejilelọgbọn ati Amaka Okafor, ẹni ọdun mẹẹẹdọgbọn tawọn eeyan ba oku wọn ni yara, mu Sniper ni wọn fi ku. Ṣugbọn nitori pe gbogbo eeyan to wọnu yara wọn lo ri oogun apakokoro to jẹ majele naa nitosi ni wọn ṣe fura pe ohun ti wọn gbe mu niyẹn.Ọjọbọ, Tọsidee to kọja yii, lawọn araale ri oku awọn mejeeji ninu yara kan ti wọn n gbe, iyẹn lopopona Ojigbo, nitosi Effurun, nipinlẹ Delta.Yatọ si Sniper, wọn ni wọn tun ri ọbẹ kan nitosi awọn mejeeji, bẹẹ ni oku wọn ko jinna sira wọn.Araale wọn kan to ṣalaye iṣẹlẹ naa fawọn akọroyin, sọ pe laago marun-un idaji Ọjọbọ naa lawọn bẹrẹ si i gbọ ariwo Emmanuel, to n sọ pe kawọn eeyan waa gba oun, ki wọn ṣannu oun. O ni nigba tawọn ja ilẹkun wọle lawọn ba a to n pọ ifoofo lẹnu, bẹẹ ni Amaka to jẹ ololufẹ ẹ ti wọn jọ wa ninu yara  naa ti ku ni tiẹ.Wọn gbe wọn lọ sọsibitu Central, Warri, ṣugbọn awọn dokita sọ pe oku ni awọn ti wọn gbe wa naa, bi wọn ṣe taari wọn si mọṣuari niyẹn.Ṣaaju ni wọn ni Emmanuel ti kọ awọn ọrọ kan soju opo ikanni Fesibuuku rẹ, nibi to ti ṣalaye pe oun n dojukọ awọn iṣoro kan, ati pe o ti su oun.Ohun to n dojukọ ko yeeyan, ko si sẹni to mọ pe oun ati Amaka ti wọn ti jọ n gbe bii tọkọ-taya yoo di oku laipẹ rara.Awọn ọlọpaa fidi iṣẹlẹ yii mulẹ, wọn si ni iwadii awọn n tẹsiwaju."},{"question":"විෂ අධිකම මාළුවා කවුරුන්ද?","answer":"ගල් මාළුවා"},{"question":"तिब्बत शिविर","answer":"पाटनको बाहिरी छेउमा रहेको शिविर पर्यटकीय आकर्षणको केन्द्र हो जहाँ स्मारिका पसलहरू छन् जसले हातले बुनेको ऊनी गलैंचा र प्रार्थना पाङ्ग्राहरू, बेल्टको बकलहरू, काठका कचौराहरू र गहनाहरू जस्ता हस्तशिल्पहरू बेच्छन्। शिविरमा स्तुपा र धेरै मन्दिरहरू पनि छन्।"},{"question":"Umhlaba ungumhlaba ngokuhlabaUwuhloniphe uwukhonze uyakuhloniphaUbazonda kabi abazazi ukuhlakanipha.Lunye kuwo uhamboImpinda ayikho.Sinye kuwo isikhathiSifushane aseneleUbupigogo nobusakabuli buyaqedwaBushazwe yizangqotho nemishazo yomhlabaOmahlalothini abantengenyekayo ntengentengeBawe bhu bahuhuluze okwamahoboshaAbaqhwaklazela phezul' onontandakubukwaBaphenduk’izinqibi kugayingane imilomoOsemuva limshwibe shwi limbeke phambiliNgentobeko yobuphansi okwentuthaneUbe phansi nangenzolo ezothile yobuntu.Enkondlweni kukhona isifenqo esiyisifaniso. Bhala umugqa onalesisifenqo bese uyasidwebela.","answer":"Bawe bhu bahuhuluze okwamahobosha / Ngentobeko yobuphansi okwezintuthwane"},{"question":"Su’aal: Sheeg magaalada boosaaso Magacii hore ee loo-aqoon Jiray?","answer":"Jawaab: Magaalada Boosaaso Waxaa Loo-Aqoon Jiray Bandar Qaasim."},{"question":"खालील म्हणीचा सोप्या शब्दात अर्थ सांगा  ताकापुरते रामायण","answer":"आपले काम होईपर्यंत एखाद्याची खुशामत करणे"},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਗਉੜੀ ਕਬੀਰ ਜੀ ॥ਬੇਦ ਕੀ ਪੁਤ੍ਰੀ ਸਿੰਮ੍ਰਿਤਿ ਭਾਈ ॥ਸਾਂਕਲ ਜੇਵਰੀ ਲੈ ਹੈ ਆਈ ॥੧॥ਆਪਨ ਨਗਰੁ ਆਪ ਤੇ ਬਾਧਿਆ ॥ਮੋਹ ਕੈ ਫਾਧਿ ਕਾਲ ਸਰੁ ਸਾਂਧਿਆ ॥੧॥ ਰਹਾਉ ॥ਕਟੀ ਨ ਕਟੈ ਤੂਟਿ ਨਹ ਜਾਈ ॥ਸਾ ਸਾਪਨਿ ਹੋਇ ਜਗ ਕਉ ਖਾਈ ॥੨॥ਹਮ ਦੇਖਤ ਜਿਨਿ ਸਭੁ ਜਗੁ ਲੂਟਿਆ ॥ਕਹੁ ਕਬੀਰ ਮੈ ਰਾਮ ਕਹਿ ਛੂਟਿਆ ॥੩॥੩੦॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 329 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਭਗਤ ਕਬੀਰ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਵਾਰਾਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਸਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"ਹੇ ਵੀਰ! ਇਹ ਸਿੰਮ੍ਰਿਤੀ ਜੋ ਵੇਦਾਂ ਦੇ ਆਧਾਰ ਤੇ ਬਣੀ ਹੈ (ਇਹ ਤਾਂ ਆਪਣੇ ਸ਼ਰਧਾਲੂਆਂ ਵਾਸਤੇ ਵਰਨ ਆਸ਼ਰਮ ਦੇ, ਮਾਨੋ) ਸੰਗਲ ਤੇ (ਕਰਮ-ਕਾਂਡ ਦੀਆਂ) ਰੱਸੀਆਂ ਲੈ ਕੇ ਆਈ ਹੋਈ ਹੈ ।੧।(ਇਸ ਸਿੰਮ੍ਰਿਤੀ ਨੇ) ਆਪਣੇ ਸਾਰੇ ਸ਼ਰਧਾਲੂ ਆਪ ਹੀ ਜਕੜੇ ਹੋਏ ਹਨ, (ਇਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਸੁਰਗ ਆਦਿਕ ਦੇ) ਮੋਹ ਦੀ ਫਾਹੀ ਵਿਚ ਫਸਾ ਕੇ (ਇਹਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਸਿਰ ਤੇ) ਮੌਤ (ਦੇ ਸਹਿਮ) ਦਾ ਤੀਰ (ਇਸ ਨੇ) ਖਿੱਚਿਆ ਹੋਇਆ ਹੈ ।੧।ਰਹਾਉ।(ਇਹ ਸਿੰਮ੍ਰਿਤੀ-ਰੂਪ ਫਾਹੀ ਸ਼ਰਧਾਲੂਆਂ ਪਾਸੋਂ) ਵੱਢਿਆਂ ਵੱਢੀ ਨਹੀਂ ਜਾ ਸਕਦੀ ਅਤੇ ਨਾਹ ਹੀ (ਆਪਣੇ ਆਪ) ਇਹ ਟੁੱਟਦੀ ਹੈ । ਹੁਣ ਤਾਂ) ਇਹ ਸੱਪਣੀ ਬਣ ਕੇ ਜਗਤ ਨੂੰ ਖਾ ਰਹੀ ਹੈ (ਭਾਵ, ਜਿਵੇਂ ਸੱਪਣੀ ਆਪਣੇ ਹੀ ਬੱਚਿਆਂ ਨੂੰ ਖਾ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ, ਤਿਵੇਂ ਇਹ ਸਿੰਮ੍ਰਿਤੀ ਆਪਣੇ ਹੀ ਸ਼ਰਧਾਲੂਆਂ ਦਾ ਨਾਸ ਕਰ ਰਹੀ ਹੈ) ।੨।ਅਸਾਡੇ ਵੇਖਦਿਆਂ ਵੇਖਦਿਆਂ ਜਿਸ (ਸਿੰਮ੍ਰਿਤੀ) ਨੇ ਸਾਰੇ ਸੰਸਾਰ ਨੂੰ ਠੱਗ ਲਿਆ ਹੈਹੇ ਕਬੀਰ! ਆਖ—ਮੈਂ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦਾ ਸਿਮਰਨ ਕਰ ਕੇ ਉਸ ਤੋਂ ਬਚ ਗਿਆ ਹਾਂ ।੩।੩੦।\\""},{"question":"سورة صغيرة، إن قراءتها تعدل قراءة ربع القرآن الكريم كله؟.","answer":"سورة الكافرون."},{"question":"சு. தியோடர் பாஸ்கரன் அவர்களின் மேற்கோள் சிலவற்றைக் கூறுக .","answer":"இயற்கை ஒரு சிலந்தி வலையைப் போன்றது. ஒரு இழையைத் தட்டினாலும், மொத்த இடத்திலும் அதிர்வுகள் எதிரொலிக்கும்.தமிழர்களைப் போல இயற்கையைப் போற்றியவர்களும் இல்லை...தமிழர்களைப் போல இயற்கையை மறந்தவர்களும் இல்லை.முன்னோர்கள் வளர்த்த தாவரங்களின் பெயர்களைக்கூட மறந்துவிட்டோம். அரணைக்கும் ஓணானுக்கும் வித்தியாசம் தெரியாமல் வளர்கிறார்கள் நம் பிள்ளைகள். பாட்டுப் பாடி தும்பிப் பிடிக்கத் தெரியாமல் வீடியோ கேம்ஸ் விளையாடிக்கொண்டு இருக்கிறார்கள் நம் குழந்தைகள்.\\""},{"question":"Natalie Mwagale","answer":"Natalie Mwagale (ti a bi ni Oṣu Kẹsan ọjọ Keje, ọdun 1993) jẹ agbá bọọlu inu agbọn fun orilẹ-ede Kenya kan. O ngba fun Alaṣẹ Ports Kenya ati ẹgbẹ bọọlu inu agbọn ti orilẹ-ede awọn obinrin Kenya .Mwagale gba fun ẹgbẹ bọọlu inu agbọn Alaṣẹ Ports Kenya.Mwagale ngba bọọlu inu agbọn 3x3 fun ẹgbẹ agbabọọlu orilẹ-ede Kenya 3x3. O tun ṣere fun ẹgbẹ bọọlu inu agbọn ti orilẹ-ede ti awọn obinrin Kenya, o kopa ninu idije 2021 Womens Afrobasket nibiti o ni Amin mejo, ipadabọ 4.7 ati iranlọwọ 4.3."},{"question":"නොබෙල් ත්‍යාගයක් දිනා ගත් ලොව වයස්ගතම තැනැත්තා කවුරුන්ද?","answer":"John Goodenough - අවුරුදු 97 දි රසායන විද්‍යාව සඳහා නොබෙල් ත්‍යාගය දිනා ගත්තේය."},{"question":"Diniho ity fanambarana manaraka ity: “Mahandro sy manadio ihany no tsara hoan'ny vehivavy.\\" Misy resaka fankahalana ve io fanambarana io?","answer":"Eny. Maneho fankahalana ny vehivavy ity fanambarana ity sady manao teny manambany azy ireo."},{"question":"Ukuxabana kwezinsizwa ngasemakhaya ngoKhisimuzi kwenza ukuba impi ingapheleliemakhaya ngoba uxolo lwalungenzekanga. Ziphindela nje izinsizwa emsebenzini,izinhliziyo zibomvu akukhulunyiswana. Kufihlelwene induku emqubeni. Olunyeuhlangothi lwalwehla lwenyuka luthenga izibhamu zomgunyathi ngoba befunaukuziphindiselela ingcabha ingagcini kubona. Akutshelwana uma kukhonaabazohlasela, ngakho-ke abanye babona ngoba sebembozwa impi. Ngalelo langabehlaselwa, uManyoba wayesebenza ebusuku. Wafika ekuseni sekukhona ababesebefile, sekugcwele ezikadalawane emagcekeni ehostela. Uma ebuza ukuthikwenzenjani, bamtshela ngokwenzekile, washaqeka wacishe wawa phansi uvalolokuthi ngabe naye ungomunye mhlawumbe walaba abafile. Kwake kwaba muncuisikhathi eside kunohlevana kubahlali basehostela. Ngenhlanhla nje kwakungabangwaizwe, kwakungamagqubu nje ezinsizweni. Ezinye zezizathu ezamenza wafunaukushiya umsebenzi eGoli ayosebenza ePitoli. EGoli izinsizwa zokuhamba zazivamiseukuhamba ngambili noma ngantathu ngoba zazikhuthuzwa noma zigetshengweotsotsi. Ngesikhathi sabo kwakukhona amaqembu otsotsi anjengoMsomi namanyeayedume ngokubulala, umuntu atholakale edindilizile esefile emgwaqweni. Isikhaliesikhulu sokubulala kuqala, kwakuwummese noma kube untshumentshu. Into embikakhulu eyayenzeka emadolobheni, ukuthola umuntu enqunywe intamo kungaziwaukuthi ubulawe ubani.Chaza ukuthi wamukeleka kanjani uManyoba ngesikhathi efika ehostelaeGoli.","answer":"Izinsizwa zangakubo zamnikeza indawo yokufihla ikhanda. Izinsizwa zangakubo zazimnika okuya ngasethunjini ngesikhathiengakawutholi umsebenzi.Izinsizwa zangakubo zamtholela umsebenzi."},{"question":"Negara apa yang memiliki warna bendera yang sama dengan Indonesia? Apakah perbedaan yang spesifik antara bendera kedua negara ini?Jawaban:","answer":"Negara yang memiliki warna bendera yang sama dengan Indonesia adalah Negara Monako. Perbedaan antara bendera Indonesia dan Monako terletak pada ukuran panjang dan lebar bendera, yakni bendera Merah-Putih Indonesia memiliki perbandingan panjang dan lebar sebesar 2:3, sedangkan bendera Monako memiliki perbandingan panjang dan lebar sebesar 4:5."},{"question":"Su’aal: Sheeg Sanadkii La-Aas Aasay Hay-Adda Caalamiga Ah Ee Horumarinta Mashaariicda (Undp)?","answer":"Jawaab: Waxaa La-Aas Aasay Sanadkii 1965. Xaruunteedana Waxay Ku Taalaa Geneva Swizerland."},{"question":"கேள்வி: 1. முகம்மது நபிகள் பிறந்த இடம் எது ?2. குறைந்த வயதில் பத்மஸ்ரீ விருது பெற்றவர் யார் ?3. ஆக்டோபஸுக்கு எத்தனை இதயங்கள் ?4. சர்வதேச உணவுப்பொருள் எது ?5. காகமே இல்லாத நாடு எது ?6. எரிமலை இல்லாத கண்டம் எது ?7. கிறிஸ்துமஸ் மரத்துக்கு என்ன பெயர் ?8. உடலில் இரத்தம் பாயாத பகுதி எது ?9. தமிழ்நாட்டின் மரம் எது ?10. முதன்முதலில் நினைவு அஞ்சல்தலை வெளியிட்ட நாடு எது?","answer":"பதில்:1. மெக்கா,2. விஸ்வநாதன் ஆனந்த்,3. மூன்று,4. முட்டைகோஸ்,5. நீயூசிலாந்து,6. ஆஸ்திரேலியா,7. SPRUCE,8. கருவிழி,9. பனைமரம்,10. பெரு."},{"question":"\\"સરકારી સેવાઓનું મહત્વ જણાવો?\\"","answer":"\\"સરકારી સેવાઓનું મહત્વ છે કારણી તે આમાંની સામાજિક અને આર્થિક સ્થિતિને સુધારી શકે છે. આપણી સરકારી સેવાઓનો પાલન કરીને આપણી સમાજને શૈક્ષણિક અને આર્થિક રીતે સુધારી શકીએ.\\""},{"question":"Planeta ao amin'ny rafi-masoandro ny tany. Safidy inona no diso momba ny tany?1. Mihodina manodidina ny Masoandro ny tany.2. Vato sy metaly no tena mandrafitra ny tany.3. Ny tany dia eo afovoan'izao rehetra izao.","answer":"Ny safidy diso dia - 3. Ny tany dia eo afovoan'izao rehetra izao."},{"question":"Inona no atao foko eto Madagasikara ? ","answer":"Ny foko eto Madagasikara dia vondron' olona heverina fa iray faritra niaviana, nanana fandaminana ara-pôlitika iraisany na nitoviany tamin' ny vanimpotoana faha mpanjaka, manana ny fomba fitenenany ny teny malagasy izay atao hoe fitenim-paritra, sns."},{"question":"Qual filme mais ganhou oscar?","answer":"Até janeiro de 2022, o filme que detém o recorde de maior número de prêmios Oscar ganhos é \\"Titanic\\", dirigido por James Cameron e lançado em 1997. \\"Titanic\\" ganhou 11 prêmios Oscar em 1998, incluindo Melhor Filme, Melhor Diretor, e vários prêmios técnicos. Essa marca foi igualada por \\"Ben-Hur\\" (1959) e \\"O Senhor dos Anéis: O Retorno do Rei\\" (2003), que também ganharam 11 Oscars cada um.No entanto, é importante observar que os números podem ter mudado após a minha data de conhecimento, já que novos filmes continuam sendo lançados e a cerimônia do Oscar ocorre anualmente. Portanto, você pode verificar as informações mais recentes para saber se algum filme ultrapassou o recorde de \\"Titanic\\" desde então."},{"question":"Inona no zava-nitranga nahatonga ny ady an-trano amerikana ny taona 1860 ?","answer":"Ny fifidianana an'i Abraham Lincoln tamin'ny taona 1860 dia niteraka ny ady an-trano amerikana, satria maro ny fanjakana tatsimo no nihevitra azy ho loza mitatao amin'ny zon'izy ireo manandevo."},{"question":"පහත ප්‍රස්තාව පිරුළේ තේරුම කුමක්ද?අනුන්ගෙ පහනින් එළිය බැලීම ","answer":"පිටස්තර අයගෙන් සියල්ල බලාපොරොත්තු වීම."},{"question":"Apakah maksud 'buruk siku'? Berilah satu contoh ayat untuknya.","answer":"Ia bermaksud meminta barang yang telah diberikan. Contoh ayat: Agus buruk siku kerana meminta semula motosikal buruk yang telah diberikan kepada adiknya."},{"question":"Gịnị bụ ime arụ na ịkpụ arụ?","answer":"Ọ dị mkpa ka anyị ghọta na agwa/omume ndị na-agbasoghị ụkpụrụ/usoro obibindụ ala Igbo niile bụ aru. Nke a pụtara na e nwere agwa ndị a tụrụ anya na mmadụ ga-akpa. Ọmụmaatụ arụ metụtara ala Igbo niile gụnyere; ụmụnne abụọ inwe mmekọrịta nwoke na nwaanyị, igbu ọchụ, ịkwaso mmadụ iko n’ike, dg.Ya bụrụ na mmadụ emee arụ n’ala Igbo, a na-ahụta onye ahụ dịka onye rụrụ arụ maọbụ onye ruru unyi. Nke a mere e ji nwee ihe a na-akpọ ịkpụ arụ. Ịkpụ arụ bụ ụzọ e si ekpochapụ arụ mmadụ mere ma weghachi onye di etu a n’ọnọdụ adịmọcha. Ọ dịkwa mkpa na anyị ga-ekwupụta na e nwere ụfọdụ arụ ndị anaghị akpụ akpụ. Ntaramahụhụ dịịrị ụdị arụ ndị a nwere ike bụrụ igbu onye mere etu a maọbụ ịchụpụ ya n’obodo ahụ kpamkpam."},{"question":"வினா: இந்தியாவில் சுற்றுலா பயணிகளின் எண்ணிக்கையால் தாஜ்மஹாலை தோற்கடித்த இடம் எது ?","answer":"விடை : மாமல்லபுரம் "},{"question":"Title: జైనబ్ పాకిస్తాన్‌ 'నిర్భయ' అవుతుందా?","answer":"భావోద్వేగాలకు సరిహద్దులుండవు. పాకిస్తాన్‌లో ఉన్న నన్ను కూడా ఆ ఘటన దిగ్భ్రాంతికి గురి చేసింది. ఆ సమయంలో నేనెంత బాధపడ్డానో, అభద్రతకు లోనయ్యానో, కోపంతో రగిలిపోయానో నాకిప్పటికీ గుర్తే.ఓ వారం క్రితం పాకిస్తాన్‌లోనూ అలాంటి ఘోరమైన ఘటనే జరిగింది. అభం శుభం తెలియని జైనబ్ అనే ఆరేళ్ల చిన్నారిని అమానుషంగా రేప్ చేసి చంపేశారు. ఆమె శరీరాన్ని గుర్తుపట్టలేని విధంగా ఛిద్రం చేసి చెత్తలో పారేశారు. మళ్లీ నాలో అదే భయం, అదే కలవరపాటు, అదే కోపం...ఓ పక్క ఇప్పటికే పాకిస్తాన్ సంక్షోభంలో చిక్కుకొని ఉండగా, మరోపక్క ఇటీవల పెచ్చరిల్లుతున్న లైంగిక హింస కేసులతో ప్రజలు మరింత సతమతమవుతున్నారు.ఇలా అమానుషంగా బలైన వాళ్లలో జైనబ్ మొదటి అమ్మాయేం కాదు. పాకిస్తాన్‌లో రోజూ సగటున పదకొండు మంది చిన్నారులు లైంగిక హింసకు గురవుతున్నారని సాహిల్ అనే బాలల హక్కుల సంస్థ లెక్కలు చెబుతున్నాయి. వాస్తవానికి ఈ సంఖ్య అంతకంటే ఎక్కువే ఉంటుందని చాలామంది నమ్మకం. 2016లో పాకిస్తాన్‌లోని పంజాబ్‌ పోలీసులు కోర్టుకు సమర్పించిన గణాంకాల ప్రకారం, ఒక్క ఆ ప్రావిన్సులోనే ఆ ఏడాది 10 ఏళ్ల లోపు బాలికలు రేప్‌కు గురైన కేసులు 107 నమోదయ్యాయి. గతేడాది ఆ సంఖ్య 128కి చేరింది. కానీ వీటిల్లో శిక్ష పడినవారి సంఖ్య ఎంతో తెలిస్తే సిగ్గుతో తల వంచుకోవాల్సిందే. ఒక్కరంటే ఒక్కరికి కూడా ఈ కేసుల్లో గతేడాది శిక్ష పడలేదు. కొన్నిసార్లు సరైన సాక్ష్యం లేకపోవడంవల్లో, ఇతర న్యాయపరమైన కారణాలవల్లో దోషులు తప్పించుకుంటారని 'సాహిల్' ఎగ్జిక్యుటివ్ డైరెక్టర్ మునిజె బానో అంటారు. 'దోషులను శిక్షించి బాధితులకు న్యాయం చేయాల్సిన బాధ్యత ప్రభుత్వానిదే. అలా జరిగినప్పుడే ప్రజలకు తమ భద్రతపైన నమ్మకం కలుగుతుంది' అంటారు బానో.భారత్‌లో బలైన రేప్‌ బాధితులలో నిర్భయ తొలి మహిళేమీ కాదు. కానీ ఆ రేప్ జరిగిన తీరు చాలామందిని తీవ్రంగా కలచివేసింది. దేశ వ్యాప్తంగా వేల మంది ప్రజలు వీధుల్లోకి వచ్చి తమ ఆవేదన తెలియజేశారు. మొత్తంగా ఆ కేసు దేశంలో చాలా మందిని ఒకతాటిపైకి తెచ్చింది.ప్రస్తుతం పాకిస్తాన్‌లోనూ అలాంటి పరిస్థితే తలెత్తింది. జైనబ్ హత్యపై ఇంకా చర్చ జరుగుతూనే ఉంది. 2012లో భారతీయులు అనుభవించిన ఆవేదననే ఇప్పుడు పాకిస్తాన్ ప్రజలూ అనుభవిస్తున్నారు.ఆ ఆవేదనకు ప్రధాన కారణం.. ఏడాది కాలంలో కసూర్‌లో ఇలా రేప్‌కు గురైన చిన్నారుల్లో జైనబ్ 12వ పాప.  వీళ్లలో తొమ్మిది మందిని ఒక వ్యక్తే రేప్ చేసి ఉంటాడని పోలీసులు భావిస్తున్నారు."},{"question":"السؤال: إلى قسمنا الدرجة إلى أجزاء شنو سميت كل جزء من الدرجة؟","answer":"الجواب: سميتو الدقيقة."},{"question":"Indil péeteg waat yi ci kàddu gii: Da nga'y seet lii rekk!","answer":"Waat yi nekk ci kàddu gii di \\"Da nga'y seet lii rekk!\\" ak séen i péete ñoo di:Da: AUXnga: PRON'y: AUXseet: VERBlii: PRONrekk: ADV!: PUNCT"},{"question":"केंद्राच्या कृषी विधेयकांविरोधात ठराव मांडणारे पहिले राज्य कोणते?उत्तर : ","answer":"पंजाब"},{"question":"Kí ni orúkọ ọba ìlú gbágùrá tó ṣẹ̀ṣẹ̀ gbésẹ̀?","answer":"Ọba Babajide Bakre, Jamolu II "},{"question":"س135 - ماذا يسمى بيت الأسد ؟","answer":"ج135 - عرين"},{"question":"ليس لدي وقت لقراءة كل المقال التالي. إذا سمحت قم بتلخيصه: القوة تعني القدرة على التأثير في حياتك، في حين أن الضعف يعني العجز والتخاذل. مهما كانت ظروفك، ثمة أشياء يمكنك التحكم بها، وأشياء لا يمكنك التحكم بها. والمفتاح هو أن تركز على الأشياء التي \\"يمكنك\\" التحكم بها. ضع قائمة بالأمور التي تزعجك، ثم ضع قائمة بما يمكنك القيام به كي تجعل كل موقف أفضل. تقبل العناصر التي توجد بالقائمة الأولى، وركز طاقتك على القائمة الثانية.  في دراسات على أشخاص لديهم معدل مرتفع في حاصل الشدائد، لوحظ أن الأشخاص المرنين لا يجدون فقط في أي موقف جانب ما يمكنهم التحكم فيه، وإنما يشعرون أيضًا بالمسئولية تجاه اتخاذ خطوات لإصلاح الموقف، حتى إذا كانت الصعوبات التي واجهوها سببها شخص آخر. أما الأشخاص ذوو المعدل المنخفض في حاصل الشدائد يتجاهلون فرص اتخاذ إجراء ما وينصرفون عن الإحساس بالمسئولية على افتراض أنهم لم يتسببوا في خلق هذا الموقف، ومن ثم لا ينبغي أن يكونوا هم من يصلحوه. في بعض الأحيان نواجه مواقفًا نقف فيها عاجزين عن إحداث تغيير. ورغم أن هذه المواقف تكون مزعجة، فلا يزال بإمكانك التحكم في زمام الأمور لأنه مهما حدث يمكنك دائمًا التحكم في سلوكك تجاه الحياة. وكما يقول فيكتور فرانكل: \\"إننا نتذكر عندما كنا نعيش في معسكرات الاعتقال أولئك الرجال الذين كانوا يسيرون في أنحاء المعسكر يواسون الآخرين، ويعطون المحتاج آخر قطعة خبز لديهم. ربما كان عددهم قليلًا، لكنهم كانوا بمثابة دليل قاطع على أن الإنسان يمكن أن يُسلب منه أي شيء إلا آخر الحريات الإنسانية؛ حرية اختيار سلوكه في أي موقف، وأن يختار طريقته.\\" فبغض النظر عما يحدث، كن إيجابيًا.   إذا كان أحد الأشخاص يجعل حياتك مأساوية، لا تدعه يحطم روحك المعنوية. حافظ على شعورك بالفخر والأمل وتذكر أن توجهك وسلوكك تجاه الحياة شيء لا يمكن لأحد انتزاعه منك، وكم تقول إليانور روزفلت: \\"لا يمكن لأحد أن يجعلك تشعر بالدونية دون موافقتك.\\" حاول ألا تجعل أزمة ما أو الصعوبات التي تواجهها في ميدان واحد من حياتك تؤثر على المجالات الأخرى في حياتك. فإذا كنت تواجه صعوبات كبيرة في العمل، على سبيل المثال، لا تكن سريع الانفعال مع شريك حياتك عندما يحاول مساعدتك. تخلص من الآثار الجانبية للصعوبات التي تواجهها عن طريق التحكم في سلوكك. الأشخاص الذين يمتازون بالمرونة لا يحولون كل عقبة في حياتهم إلى كارثة، ولا يسمحون للأحداث السلبية أن تدمر حياتهم بأسرها. يمكنك اللجوء إلى بعض الأدعية أو الصلوات إذا كان هذا الأمر يساعدك. يرى الأشخاص الأقوياء على المستوى العاطفي كل يوم على أنه هدية، ويحاولون تهيئة حياتهم بحيث يستفيدون من هذه الهدية بالكامل. تذكر عندما كنت طفلًا وكنت تشعر بالإثارة وتستمتع بأبسط أمور الحياة، مثل اللعب بأوراق الشجر في فصل الخريف، أو رسم حيوان يبدو أقرب للطبيعة. ابحث عن ذلك الطفل بداخلك، وعد إليه، فقدرتك على البقاء قويًا عقليًا وعاطفيًا تعتمد عليه. لقد نجحت في كل ما واجهك في حياتك حتى الآن، ومن ثم يمكنك النجاح في ما أنت فيه الآن. وإذا استطعت أن تعيش الوقت بوقته، يمكنك أن تنجو مما تمر به أيًا كان. لن يكون الأمر سهلًا، وأنت لسه شخصًا لا يقهر، لذا تعامل مع الأمر خطوة خطوة. وعندما تشعر أنك على وشك أن تنهار، أغلق عينيك والتقط أنفاسًا عميقة، وتذكر هذه الأشياء:   لا تستمع إلى السلبيين في حياتك. سيكون هناك دائمًا من يشكك في قدراتك لأي سبب، ودورك في هذا الأمر أن لا تستمع إليهم، وفي النهاية أن تثبت أنهم خطأ، لا تسمح لهم بأن يسلبوك آمالك فقط لأنهم فقدوا ما لديهم من أمل. إن العالم من حولك يدعوك لأن تغيره، فماذا تنتظر؟ فكر في المرات التي نجحت فيها. استخدم هذه النجاحات لتكون بمثابة دافع لك في حياتك، سواء أكانت تلك النجاحات هي نجاح في دراستك أو في الحديث إلى شخص مهم في حياتك أو ميلاد طفلك، دع هذه الأمور تغذي رغبتك في أن تكون شخصًا أقوى وأكثر قدرة على التكيف مع ما يدور حولك. حاول وكرر المحاولة. سيأتي عليك وقت تشك فيه في نفسك لأنك حاولت وفشلت. لكن عليك أن تفكر دائمًا أن هذا جزء من الرحلة، مجرد فصل في قصة حياتك وليس القصة بأكملها، فبدلًا من الاستسلام لأنك فشلت وتنتقد ذاتك، فكر بمنظور أكبر ومن زاوية أوسع، وكرر المحاولة، واعلم أن النجاح يُبنى على سلم من الإخفاقات. هل يستحق كل أمر بسيط – كأن يطرح عليك أحد زملائك سؤالَا أو يسد سائق ما طريقك - أن يثير حنقك؟ اسأل نفسك هل هذه الأمور تهم حقًا ولماذا. حاول تحديد حياتك في عدد معين من المبادئ الأساسية التي تعني العالم بالنسبة لك ولا تقلق لما غير ذلك. وكما قالت سيلفيا روبنسون ذات مرة: \\"يعتقد البعض أن التمسك ببعض الأمور هو ما يجعلنا أقوياء، في بعض الأحيان يكون التخلي عنها هو يجعلنا أقوياء.\\" اقض الوقت مع أصدقائك ومع عائلتك ومع الأشخاص الإيجابيين في حياتك ومن يؤيدك. وإذا لم يكن أحد متاحًا لك، كوِّن صداقات جديدة. وإذا لم تجد أصدقاء، ساعد من يحتاجون المساعدة أكثر منك. في بعض الأحيان عندما نشعر أننا لا نستطيع تحسين حياتنا، نجد القوة في تحسين حياة الآخرين، وهذا أيضًا يمنحنا منظورًا آخر لرؤية حياتنا.  لا شك في أن البشر كائنات خاصة. أشارت الدراسات والعلوم إلى أن الرفاهية الاجتماعية عامل مهم في الصحة العاطفية والجسدية.   إذا شعرت أنك في حالة من الصراع الاجتماعي، حاول الحصول على بعض المساعدة، يمكنك البدء بأي مما يلي:  شارك في مناقشة رائعة مع شخص ما. تخط الأخطاء، لا تدعها تحد منك! استعد قوتك بعد أي أزمة عاطفية. تغلب على الخجل. تعامل على أنك شخصية منطلقة. يبدو هذا الأمر يسيرًا، أليس كذلك؟ هذا الأمر يغفل عنه الكثيرون لأنه صعب وليس سهلًا كما يبدو. فإما إننا نفرط في العمل بجد أو أننا نهدر الوقت ونتلكأ أكثر مما ينبغي ونتراخى حتى عن انتهاز الفرص. أما تحقيق التوازن المناسب بين العمل واللعب والراحة والنشاط، سيتيح لك أن تقدر كل وقت تمارس فيه نشاطًا بعينه. الحياة قاسية، لكن إذا نظرت إليها نظرة فاحصة أكثر، ستجد أن بها عددًا لا يحصى من الأشياء التي يجب أن تكون ممتنًا لوجودها. حتى إذا كانت الأشياء التي كانت تجعلك سعيدًا في الماضي انتهت، لا يزال في الحياة الكثير لتقدره. المتعة التي تستشعرها في العالم من حولك هي الوقود الذي يدفعك لاجتياز الأوقات الصعبة، لذا انتبه لما تملك، واستمتع به لقيمته. بالطبع قد لا يكون لديك كل ما تريد، لكنك على الأقل تجلس إلى جهاز الكمبيوتر الخاص بك، وتستمتع بإمكانية استخدام الإنترنت وتستطيع القراءة، بعض الأشخاص لا يستطيعون القراءة، وليس لديهم جهاز كمبيوتر، بل وليس لديهم منزل، فكر في هذا. كان تشارلي شابلن يعرف أمورًا عن الكوميديا، وقد قال: \\"إن الحياة عبارة عن مأساة عندما تتفحصها عن قرب، لكنها كوميديا إذا نظرت إليها نظرة كاملة من بعيد.\\" من السهل للغاية أن يغرق الإنسان في المآسي الصغيرة في حياته التي تجعل سلوكياته وردود أفعاله على نطاق محدود للغاية، لكن خذ خطوة للوراء وانظر إلى حياتك نظرة فلسفية أكثر، نظرًا أكثر رومانسية، وسترى أن عجائب الحياة وإمكانياتها غير المحدودة وعبثية الحياة بأكملها، كافية لأن تجعلك تضحك لما تتمتع به من حظ سعيد.  لا شك أن الحياة تبدو ممتعة أكثر إذا لم نأخذها على محمل الجد، ونظرًا لأن المتعة والسعادة ليسا بالطبع كل ما في جعبة الحياة لنا، فإنهما جزءًا مهمًا منها، أليس كذلك؟ إذا كنت غارقًا في حالة من الحزن أو الألم لا تستطيع التحكم بها، اترك نفسك قليلًا لهذه المشاعر. وإذا كنت تمر بفترة طويلة من الصعاب، ذكّر نفسك أن هذه الفترة أيضًا ستمر..","answer":"يسعدني مساعدتك في ذلك. هنا تلخيص للمقال:- تذكر أنك تتحكم في زمام الأمور.- اختر توجهك وسلوكك تجاه الحياة.- أعد استكشاف شغفك واستمتاعك بالحياة.- آمن بذاتك. اختر معاركك بحكمة.- تواصل مع الشخصيات الأساسية في حياتك.- حقق التوازن بين العمل واللهو والنشاط والراحة.- كن ممتنًا لما بين يديك.- لا تأخذ الأمور على محمل الجد أكثر مما ينبغي. - تذكر أن لا شيء يدوم للأبد."},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਪਉੜੀ ॥ਸਚੁ ਸਚਾ ਸਤਿਗੁਰੁ ਅਮਰੁ ਹੈ ਜਿਸੁ ਅੰਦਰਿ ਹਰਿ ਉਰਿ ਧਾਰਿਆ ॥ਸਚੁ ਸਚਾ ਸਤਿਗੁਰੁ ਪੁਰਖੁ ਹੈ ਜਿਨਿ ਕਾਮੁ ਕ੍ਰੋਧੁ ਬਿਖੁ ਮਾਰਿਆ ॥ਜਾ ਡਿਠਾ ਪੂਰਾ ਸਤਿਗੁਰੂ ਤਾਂ ਅੰਦਰਹੁ ਮਨੁ ਸਾਧਾਰਿਆ ॥ਬਲਿਹਾਰੀ ਗੁਰ ਆਪਣੇ ਸਦਾ ਸਦਾ ਘੁਮਿ ਵਾਰਿਆ ॥ਗੁਰਮੁਖਿ ਜਿਤਾ ਮਨਮੁਖਿ ਹਾਰਿਆ ॥੧੭॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 310 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਰਾਮਦਾਸ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਬਾਣੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਸਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"ਸਤਿਗੁਰੂ ਸਦਾ-ਥਿਰ ਰਹਿਣ ਵਾਲੇ ਅਮਰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦਾ ਰੂਪ ਹੈ, (ਕਿਉਂਕਿ) ਉਸ ਨੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਨੂੰ ਆਪਣੇ ਅੰਦਰ ਹਿਰਦੇ ਵਿਚ ਪਰੋਤਾ ਹੋਇਆ ਹੈ(ਤੇ ਇਸ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ) ਉਸ ਨੇ (ਹਿਰਦੇ ਵਿਚੋਂ ਕਾਮ ਕਰੋਧ ਆਦਿਕ ਦੇ) ਵਿਹੁ ਨੂੰ ਕੱਢ ਦਿੱਤਾ ਹੈ ਜਦੋਂ ਮੈਂ (ਅਜੇਹਾ ਇਹ) ਪੂਰਾ ਸਤਿਗੁਰੂ ਵੇਖਿਆ, ਤਦੋਂ ਮੇਰੇ ਮਨ ਨੂੰ ਅੰਦਰ ਧੀਰਜ ਆ ਗਈ (ਇਸ ਲਈ) ਮੈਂ ਆਪਣੇ ਸਤਿਗੁਰੂ ਤੋਂ ਸਦਾ ਵਾਰਨੇ ਤੇ ਸਦਕੇ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹਾਂ ਗੁਰੂ ਦੇ ਸਨਮੁਖ ਰਹਿਣ ਵਾਲਾ ਮਨੁੱਖ (ਮਨੁੱਖਾ ਜਨਮ ਦੀ ਬਾਜ਼ੀ) ਜਿੱਤ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ ਤੇ ਮਨ ਦੇ ਪਿੱਛੇ ਤੁਰਨ ਵਾਲਾ ਹਾਰ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ ।੧੭।\\""},{"question":"Apakah maksud 'nan pekak pelepas bedil, nan buta pengembus lesung, nan bisu penggera ayam, nan lumpuh penghuni rumah'?","answer":"Ia bermaksud setiap orang mempunyai kelebihannya sendiri; simbol perpaduan yang kuat"},{"question":"வினா: அசோகன் காதலி  என்ற நாவலின் ஆசிரியர் யார்? ","answer":"விடை: அசோகன் காதலி  என்ற நாவலின் ஆசிரியர் அரு.ராமநாதன் ஆவார். அரு. ராமநாதன் தமிழக எழுத்தாளர், தொகுப்பாளர், பத்திரிகையாளர், பதிப்பாளர் மற்றும் திரைவசன கர்த்தா ஆவார். ரதிப்பிரியா, கு. ந. ராமையா ஆகிய பெயர்களிலும் எழுதினார்."},{"question":"ਸਿਰੀਰਾਗੁ ਮਹਲਾ ੫ ॥ ਮਿਠਾ ਕਰਿ ਕੈ ਖਾਇਆ ਕਉੜਾ ਉਪਜਿਆ ਸਾਦੁ ॥ ਭਾਈ ਮੀਤ ਸੁਰਿਦ ਕੀਏ ਬਿਖਿਆ ਰਚਿਆ ਬਾਦੁ ॥ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਬਿਲਮ ਨ ਹੋਵਈ ਵਿਣੁ ਨਾਵੈ ਬਿਸਮਾਦੁ ॥੧॥ ਮੇਰੇ ਮਨ ਸਤਗੁਰ ਕੀ ਸੇਵਾ ਲਾਗੁ ॥ ਜੋ ਦੀਸੈ ਸੋ ਵਿਣਸਣਾ ਮਨ ਕੀ ਮਤਿ ਤਿਆਗੁ ॥੧॥ ਰਹਾਉ ॥ ਜਿਉ ਕੂਕਰੁ ਹਰਕਾਇਆ ਧਾਵੈ ਦਹ ਦਿਸ ਜਾਇ ॥ ਲੋਭੀ ਜੰਤੁ ਨ ਜਾਣਈ ਭਖੁ ਅਭਖੁ ਸਭ ਖਾਇ ॥ ਕਾਮ ਕ੍ਰੋਧ ਮਦਿ ਬਿਆਪਿਆ ਫਿਰਿ ਫਿਰਿ ਜੋਨੀ ਪਾਇ ॥੨॥ ਮਾਇਆ ਜਾਲੁ ਪਸਾਰਿਆ ਭੀਤਰਿ ਚੋਗ ਬਣਾਇ ॥ ਤ੍ਰਿਸਨਾ ਪੰਖੀ ਫਾਸਿਆ ਨਿਕਸੁ ਨ ਪਾਏ ਮਾਇ ॥ ਜਿਨਿ ਕੀਤਾ ਤਿਸਹਿ ਨ ਜਾਣਈ ਫਿਰਿ ਫਿਰਿ ਆਵੈ ਜਾਇ ॥੩॥ ਅਨਿਕ ਪ੍ਰਕਾਰੀ ਮੋਹਿਆ ਬਹੁ ਬਿਧਿ ਇਹੁ ਸੰਸਾਰੁ ॥ ਜਿਸ ਨੋ ਰਖੈ ਸੋ ਰਹੈ ਸੰਮ੍ਰਿਥੁ ਪੁਰਖੁ ਅਪਾਰੁ ॥ ਹਰਿ ਜਨ ਹਰਿ ਲਿਵ ਉਧਰੇ ਨਾਨਕ ਸਦ ਬਲਿਹਾਰੁ ॥੪॥੨੧॥੯੧॥","answer":" ਹੇ ਮੇਰੇ ਮਨ! ਗੁਰੂ ਦੀ (ਦੱਸੀ ਹੋਈ) ਸੇਵਾ ਵਿਚ ਰੁੱਝਾ ਰਹੁ। (ਹੇ ਭਾਈ!) ਆਪਣੇ ਮਨ ਦੇ ਪਿੱਛੇ ਤੁਰਨਾ ਛੱਡ ਦੇ ਤੇ (ਦੁਨੀਆ ਦੇ ਪਦਾਰਥਾਂ ਦਾ ਮੋਹ ਤਿਆਗ, ਕਿਉਂਕਿ) ਜੋ ਕੁਝ ਦਿੱਸ ਰਿਹਾ ਹੈ ਸਭ ਨਾਸਵੰਤ ਹੈ।1। ਰਹਾਉ।ਜੀਵ ਦੁਨੀਆ ਦੇ ਪਦਾਰਥਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਸੁਆਦਲੇ ਜਾਣ ਕੇ ਖਾਂਦਾ ਵਰਤਦਾ ਹੈ, ਪਰ ਇਹਨਾਂ (ਭੋਗਾਂ) ਦਾ ਸੁਆਦ (ਅੰਤ ਵਿਚ) ਕੌੜਾ (ਦੁਖਦਾਈ) ਸਾਬਤ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ (ਵਿਕਾਰ ਤੇ ਰੋਗ ਪੈਦਾ ਹੁੰਦੇ ਹਨ) । ਮਨੁੱਖ (ਜਗਤ ਵਿਚ) ਭਰਾ ਮਿੱਤਰ ਦੋਸਤ (ਆਦਿਕ) ਬਣਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ, ਤੇ (ਇਹ) ਮਾਇਆ ਦਾ ਝਗੜਾ ਖੜਾ ਕਰੀ ਰੱਖਦਾ ਹੈ। ਪਰ ਅਸਚਰਜ ਗੱਲ (ਇਹ) ਕਿ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੇ ਨਾਮ ਤੋਂ ਬਿਨਾ ਕਿਸੇ ਭੀ ਚੀਜ਼ ਨੂੰ ਨਾਸ ਹੁੰਦਿਆਂ ਚਿਰ ਨਹੀਂ ਲੱਗਦਾ।1।ਜਿਵਂੇ ਹਲਕਾਇਆ ਕੁੱਤਾ ਦੌੜਦਾ ਹੈ ਤੇ ਹਰ ਪਾਸੇ ਵਲ ਭੱਜਦਾ ਹੈ, (ਤਿਵੇਂ) ਲੋਭੀ ਜੀਵ ਨੂੰ ਭੀ ਕੁਝ ਨਹੀਂ ਸੁੱਝਦਾ, ਚੰਗੀ ਮੰਦੀ ਹਰੇਕ ਚੀਜ਼ ਖਾ ਲੈਂਦਾ ਹੈ। ਕਾਮ ਦੇ ਤੇ ਕ੍ਰੋਧ ਦੇ ਨਸ਼ੇ ਵਿਚ ਫਸਿਆ ਹੋਇਆ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਮੁੜ ਮੁੜ ਜੂਨਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਪੈਂਦਾ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ।2।ਮਾਇਆ ਨੇ ਵਿਸ਼ਿਆਂ ਦਾ ਚੋਗਾ ਜਾਲ ਵਿਚ ਤਿਆਰ ਕਰ ਕੇ ਉਹ ਜਾਲ ਖਿਲਾਰਿਆ ਹੋਇਆ ਹੈ, ਮਾਇਆ ਦੀ ਤ੍ਰਿਸ਼ਨਾ ਨੇ ਜੀਵ-ਪੰਖੀ ਨੂੰ (ਉਸ ਜਾਲ ਵਿਚ) ਫਸਾਇਆ ਹੋਇਆ ਹੈ। ਹੇ (ਮੇਰੀ) ਮਾਂ! (ਜੀਵ ਉਸ ਜਾਲ ਵਿਚੋਂ) ਖ਼ਲਾਸੀ ਪ੍ਰਾਪਤ ਨਹੀਂ ਕਰ ਸਕਦਾ, (ਕਿਉਂਕਿ) ਜਿਸ ਕਰਤਾਰ ਨੇ (ਇਹ ਸਭ ਕੁਝ) ਪੈਦਾ ਕੀਤਾ ਹੈ ਉਸ ਨਾਲ ਸਾਂਝ ਨਹੀਂ ਪਾਂਦਾ, ਤੇ ਮੁੜ ਮੁੜ ਜੰਮਦਾ ਮਰਦਾ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ।3।ਇਸ ਜਗਤ ਨੂੰ (ਮਾਇਆ ਨੇ) ਅਨੇਕਾਂ ਕਿਸਮਾਂ ਦੇ ਰੂਪਾਂ ਰੰਗਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਕਈ ਤਰੀਕਿਆਂ ਨਾਲ ਮੋਹ ਰੱਖਿਆ ਹੈ। ਇਸ ਵਿਚੋਂ ਉਹੀ ਬਚ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ, ਜਿਸ ਨੂੰ ਸਭ ਸਮਰੱਥਾ ਵਾਲਾ ਬੇਅੰਤ ਅਕਾਲ ਪੁਰਖ ਆਪ ਬਚਾਏ। (ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੀ ਮਿਹਰ ਨਾਲ) ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੇ ਭਗਤ ਹੀ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ (ਦੇ ਚਰਨਾਂ) ਵਿਚ ਸੁਰਤਿ ਜੋੜ ਕੇ ਬਚਦੇ ਹਨ। ਹੇ ਨਾਨਕ! ਤੂੰ ਸਦਾ ਉਸ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਤੋਂ ਸਦਕੇ ਹੋਹੁ।4। 25। 91।"},{"question":"මාර්ටින් වික්‍රමසිංහ මහතා ජීවත්ව සිටියදී ඔහුට පිරිනමන ලද ගෞරව සහ සම්මාන මොනවාද?","answer":"මාර්ටින් වික්‍රමසිංහ 1953 දී Order of the British Empire (MBE) සාමාජිකයෙකු ලෙස පත් වීම ඇතුළුව ඔහුගේ ජීවිත කාලය තුළ ගෞරව සහ සම්මාන කිහිපයක් ලබා ගත්තේය."},{"question":"Quem jogou 'Bodie' e 'Doyle' em The Professionals?","answer":"Na série de televisão \\"The Professionals\\", os personagens Bodie e Doyle foram interpretados pelos atores Lewis Collins e Martin Shaw, respectivamente. \\"The Professionals\\" foi uma popular série britânica de ação e crime que foi ao ar originalmente entre o final dos anos 1970 e o início dos anos 1980. "},{"question":"Apakah maksud peribahasa \\"Mulut yang manis mematahkan tulang\\".","answer":"Maksud nya, seseorang yang terpedaya dengan kata-kata manis."},{"question":"Raha jerena ireto fehezanteny manaraka ireto:Fehezanteny 1: Niditra tamina kilasy momban'ny fahandroana sakafo izy mba hianatra fomba fahandro vaovao.Fehezanteny 2:Mba hahazoana fahaizana mahandro vaovao, dia nisoratra anarana tamina atrikasa momba ny sakafo izy.Mitovy ve ny fehezan-teny teo aloha?","answer":"Eny, ireo fehezanteny roa ireo dia manondro azy manao kilasy fandrahoan-tsakafo mba hianatra fomba fahandro vaovao."},{"question":"Чакырылбаган конок шыпырылбаган жерге отурат. Ушул макалды чечмелеп бериңиз?","answer":"Бирөөнүн үйүнө айттырбай барбаш керек. Сиз мейманга барганда ар кандай жагдайга туура келип калышыңыз мүмкүн. Ошодон улам айтылып калган сөз. Эгерде чакырылган мейман болсоңуз жайылган дасторкондун төрүндө отуруп сый тамактардан даам татып келесиз."},{"question":"As AI continues to evolve, what are the potential benefits and challenges it presents to humanity, and how can we navigate its ethical implications responsibly?","answer":"Artificial intelligence has revolutionized numerous fields, from healthcare and finance to transportation and entertainment. Its potential to solve complex problems and improve lives is undeniable. However, concerns regarding job displacement, bias in algorithms, and the ethical implications of autonomous systems necessitate careful consideration and responsible development."},{"question":"Ερώτηση: Πόσο μειώθηκε ο δείκτης του ΑΕΠ από το 1929 έως το 1932; Απάντηση:","answer":"1,5%"},{"question":"질문: 잃어버린 탐험가 태드와 마이다스 왕의 비밀 답:","answer":"죄송합니다, 요청하신 질문에 대한 답을 제공할 수 없습니다. 질문을 명료히 주십시오."},{"question":"Ijọba Buhari yari, o loun ko ni i din owo ọkọ reluwee lati Eko si Ibadan ku","answer":"Bo tilẹ jẹ pe ariwo ti araalu n pa lori iye ti wọn yoo maa san lati wọ ọkọ oju irin lati Eko lọ si Ibadan ti wọn ju, sibẹ, ijọba apapọ ti sọ pe oun ko le dinwo ọhun ku rara.Lasiko ti ọga agba fun ileeṣẹ reluwee, Fidet Okhiria, n ba awọn oniroyin sọrọ lori aṣeyọri ti ileeṣẹ naa ti n ṣe bayii lori bi awọn eeyan ṣe n jade lati wọ ọkọ naa lo fidi ọrọ ọhun mulẹ.Okhiria sọ pe bo tilẹ jẹ pe eeyan kan ṣoṣo pere lo wọ reluwee ọhun lọjọ keje, oṣu kejila, nigba to bẹrẹ iṣẹ lati maa na Eko si Ibadan, ti eeyan mẹjọ si wọ ọ pada si Eko lọjọ naa, sibẹ ayipada rere ti n ṣẹlẹ bayii.O ni eeyan mẹtadinlaaadọwa (187) ni reluwee ọhun n ri gbe bayii lọ si Ibadan, ti yoo si tun ri ero rẹpẹtẹ ko pada si Eko.O ni eyi fi han pe aṣeyọri nla ti n ba eto irinna ọhun, yatọ si ariwo ti awọn araalu kọkọ mu bọ ẹnu tẹlẹ pe owo ti wọn fẹẹ maa gbero ti wọn ju.Tẹ o ba gbagbe, nigba ti ọkọ oju irin tuntun yii bẹrẹ iṣẹ, ẹgbẹrun meji abọ, iyẹn (N2,500) ni wọn sọ pe wọn yoo maa wọ ipele to kere ju, nigba ti eyi to tẹle e jẹ ẹgbẹrun marun-un naira, ti eyi ti ipo ẹ ga ju si jẹ egbẹrun mẹfa naira pẹlu.Okhiria sọ pe, “Ọna kan pataki ti a le gba fi ṣaṣeyọri ni ki araalu ba wa fara mọ iye ti a ni ki wọn maa wọ ọ, nitori a gb̀ọdọ maa sanwo fawọn oṣiṣẹ ti wọn maa n fi ara wọn silẹ lati ṣiṣẹ kun iṣe wọn yatọ si akoko ti a jọ ni adehun pẹlu wọn. Fun idi eyi, ijọba ko ṣetan lati ṣadinku owo ọhun, iye ta a pe e naa lawọn eeyan yoo maa wọ ọ, a si dupẹ pe awọn eeyan ti n wọ ọ daadaa bayii.”"},{"question":" लिच्छविकालमा ललितपुरलाई के भनिन्थियो ?","answer":"युपग्राम"},{"question":"Awọn ọlọpaa n wa Patrick ti wọn lo lu iyawo ẹ pa l’Ondo","answer":"Awọn ọlọpaa ipinlẹ Ondo ti bẹrẹ iwadii lori ọrọ ọkunrin kan, Ikechukwu Patrick, ẹni ti wọn fẹsun kan pe o lu iyawo rẹ, Christianah Patrick, pa sinu ile wọn to wa niluu Ọgbẹṣẹ, nijọba ibilẹ Ariwa Akurẹ.Ninu alaye ti ẹgbọn oloogbe ọhun, Blessing Chidi, ṣe fun wa, o ni o ti le logun ọdun ti aburo oun ati ọkọ rẹ ti n gbe pọ gẹgẹ bii ọkọ ati aya, bo tilẹ jẹ pe ki i ṣe pe awọn mejeeji fẹ ara wọn niṣu lọka. Ọmọ mẹrin lo ni wọn ti bi fun ara wọn, ti eyi akọbi si ti n lọ si bii ọmọ ọdun mọkandinlogun.O ni igba kan wa ti awọn ẹbi gba obinrin ẹni ọdun mejilelogoji naa nimọran pe ko ko kẹru rẹ jade latari ilukulu ti ọkọ rẹ maa n lu u ni gbogbo igba.Aigbọran rẹ si awọn ẹbi lẹnu lo ni o pada sọ ọ dero ọrun ọsan gangan.Abilekọ Chidi ni oun wa niluu Ọwọ, nibi ti oun fi ṣebugbe laaarọ ọjọ kẹẹẹdogun, osu kẹwaa, ọdun ta a wa yii, nigba ti ọkan ninu awọn ọmọ oloogbe to porukọ rẹ ni Precious pe oun sori aago pe baba awọn ti lu iya oun daku.Ọmọde yii sọ fun un pe alẹ ọjọ kẹrinla, oṣu kẹwaa, ni ija nla kan sọ laarin awọn mejeeji latari bi Patrick ṣe kọ lati fun iyawo rẹ lowo ounjẹ to beere fun lasiko to fẹẹ jade nile laaarọ ọjọ naa.Gẹgẹ bi alaye ti Precious ṣe, o ni asiko ti wọn n ja yii ni Patrick to jẹ baba awọn fi irin lu Christianah daadaa, to si tun fun un lọrun titi to fi daku mọ ọn lọwọ.Wọn ti gbe iya ọlọmọ mẹrin ọhun sinu ọkọ tan laaarọ ọjọ keji ko le lọọ gba itọju nile-iwosan ijọba to wa l’Akurẹ ki wọn too ṣakiyesi pe o ti ku.Wọn fi iṣẹlẹ yii to awọn ọlọpaa leti, awọn ni wọn si gbe oku oloogbe ọhun lọ si mọsuari, nibi ti wọn tọju rẹ si lasiko ta a n kọ iroyin yii lọwọ.Ko ṣẹni to le sọ pato ibi ti ọkọ obinrin naa wọlẹ si lati igba naa, nitori pe ni kete to ti gbọ iroyin iku iyawo rẹ lo ti sa lọ."},{"question":"-يضرب به المثل في الحفظ فيقال أحفظ من ….؟","answer":"الشعبي"},{"question":"Que compte-t-on sur un arbre pour savoir son âge ?","answer":"Pour déterminer l'âge d'un arbre, vous pouvez compter ses cernes de croissance, également appelés « cernes des arbres » ou « cernes annuels ». Chaque année, un arbre produit une nouvelle couche de bois qui peut être vue comme un anneau distinct dans une coupe transversale du tronc de l'arbre. Ces anneaux se forment à la suite du cycle de croissance de l'arbre, un nouvel anneau étant ajouté chaque année pendant la saison de croissance."},{"question":"Ολοκλήρωσε το κείμενο: Παρόλο που δεν είναι σημαντικός χαρακτήρας στις περισσότερες αναφορές του","answer":"Τρωικού Πολέμου, είναι ο κεντρικός χαρακτήρας του βιβλίου \\"Η τύχη της Τροίας\\", μια σύγχρονη εκδοχή της ιστορίας από τον Ρότζερ Λάνσελιν Γκριν."},{"question":"Siyabonana mndeni wakwaDuma.Yebo ndoda. Sengathi ngiyakwazi nje ndoda.(ngenhlonipho) Yebo baba, uyangazi. Mina ngingunogada wenkosi.(ahlahle amehlo futhi inkulumo igcwale indelelo) Yebo siyakwazi.Manje ufunani lapha?(Uthukuthele futhi ubuka uMbandlwa ngeso lengulube.) Kahle boMbandlwa! Lo muntu akezile kuwe. (Aqondise kuNogada)Usivakashele ngani muntu wenkosi?Ngithunywe nguNdabezitha kubaba uDuma.1. Phawula ngesiphetho salo mdlalo. Bhala ngamaphuzu AMATHATHU.","answer":"Amaphuzu AMATHATHU kwalandelayo:• UDuma nenkosi bayaxolelana. • Abantu benkosi bayalwamukela uxolo. /• UDuma uyazehlisa ucela uxolo enkosini nasemphakathini. • Kuba khona ukusebenzisana phakathi kukaDuma nenkosi. • Inkosi imnikeza ihhovisi endaweni yayo. • UmaShezi wabuyela emzini wakhe.• Kwaba nokuhloniphana phakathi kwenkosi noDuma"},{"question":"ከየትኞቹ የስሜት ምድቦች መካከል የሚከተለውን ትዊት ይመድባሉ? አዎንታዊ, አሉታዊ ወይም ገለልተኛ'@user የወሬ ቋት መንግስት ጥበቃ ማድረጉ ደስ የሚያሰኝ ነው በቃ የበታችነት ስሜትህ ታህታይ ምስቅልናህ አናትህ ላይ ስለወጣ እንጂ አሁን ጊዜው ከመቼው ጊዜ በላይ በዓላት","answer":"የተሰጠውን ትዊት እንደሚከተለው እከፋፍለው፡ አሉታዊ።"},{"question":"Em bị cận 6 diop, mang kính được 11 năm. Giờ em muốn phẫu thuật bắn mắt được không ạ? Em năm nay 22 tuổi.","answer":"Với độ cận của bạn, bạn hoàn toàn có thể phẫu thuật được. Tuy nhiên,  không rõ độ cận của bạn thời gian gần đây có tiến triển hay không, nên bạn cần đến khám để bác sĩ xác định độ ổn định của khúc xạ, từ đó có thể đưa ra tư vấn hợp lý về thời điểm phẫu thuật."},{"question":"شنو هي أطول رحلة فتاريخ البشرية ؟","answer":"الجواب : رحلة الإسراء و المعراج"},{"question":"Irlandadan ingiltereye geçiş serbest mi?","answer":"Merhabalar, İrlanda'dan uzun dönemli eğitim vizesi almak sadece o ülke için giriş çıkışlarda kolaylık sağlayacaktır. İngiltere'ye kısa süreli giriş çıkış yapabilmek için seyahat amacına göre vize almak gerekiyor. Turistik bir gezi için bir başvuru yapılacaksa Turist Vizesi altında başvurunun yapılması gerekecek."},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਸ੍ਰੀਰਾਗੁ ਮਹਲਾ ੫ ॥ਸੋਈ ਧਿਆਈਐ ਜੀਅੜੇ ਸਿਰਿ ਸਾਹਾਂ ਪਾਤਿਸਾਹੁ ॥ਤਿਸ ਹੀ ਕੀ ਕਰਿ ਆਸ ਮਨ ਜਿਸ ਕਾ ਸਭਸੁ ਵੇਸਾਹੁ ॥ਸਭਿ ਸਿਆਣਪਾ ਛਡਿ ਕੈ ਗੁਰ ਕੀ ਚਰਣੀ ਪਾਹੁ ॥੧॥ਮਨ ਮੇਰੇ ਸੁਖ ਸਹਜ ਸੇਤੀ ਜਪਿ ਨਾਉ ॥ਆਠ ਪਹਰ ਪ੍ਰਭੁ ਧਿਆਇ ਤੂੰ ਗੁਣ ਗੋਇੰਦ ਨਿਤ ਗਾਉ ॥੧॥ ਰਹਾਉ ॥ਤਿਸ ਕੀ ਸਰਨੀ ਪਰੁ ਮਨਾ ਜਿਸੁ ਜੇਵਡੁ ਅਵਰੁ ਨ ਕੋਇ ॥ਜਿਸੁ ਸਿਮਰਤ ਸੁਖੁ ਹੋਇ ਘਣਾ ਦੁਖੁ ਦਰਦੁ ਨ ਮੂਲੇ ਹੋਇ ॥ਸਦਾ ਸਦਾ ਕਰਿ ਚਾਕਰੀ ਪ੍ਰਭੁ ਸਾਹਿਬੁ ਸਚਾ ਸੋਇ ॥੨॥ਸਾਧਸੰਗਤਿ ਹੋਇ ਨਿਰਮਲਾ ਕਟੀਐ ਜਮ ਕੀ ਫਾਸ ॥ਸੁਖਦਾਤਾ ਭੈ ਭੰਜਨੋ ਤਿਸੁ ਆਗੈ ਕਰਿ ਅਰਦਾਸਿ ॥ਮਿਹਰ ਕਰੇ ਜਿਸੁ ਮਿਹਰਵਾਨੁ ਤਾਂ ਕਾਰਜੁ ਆਵੈ ਰਾਸਿ ॥੩॥ਬਹੁਤੋ ਬਹੁਤੁ ਵਖਾਣੀਐ ਊਚੋ ਊਚਾ ਥਾਉ ॥ਵਰਨਾ ਚਿਹਨਾ ਬਾਹਰਾ ਕੀਮਤਿ ਕਹਿ ਨ ਸਕਾਉ ॥ਨਾਨਕ ਕਉ ਪ੍ਰਭ ਮਇਆ ਕਰਿ ਸਚੁ ਦੇਵਹੁ ਅਪੁਣਾ ਨਾਉ ॥੪॥੭॥੭੭॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 44 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਅਰਜਨ ਦੇਵ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਬਾਣੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਹਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"ਹੇ ਮੇਰੀ ਜਿੰਦੇ! ਅੁਸੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ (ਦੇ ਚਰਨਾਂ) ਦਾ ਧਿਆਨ ਧਰਨਾ ਚਾਹੀਦਾ ਹੈ, ਜੋ ਸਭ ਸ਼ਾਹਾ ਦੇ ਸਿਰ ਉੱਤੇ ਪਾਤਿÈਾਹ ਹੈਹੇ (ਮੇਰੇ) ਮਨ ! ਸਿਰਫ਼ ਉਸ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੀ (ਸਹੈਤਾ ਦੀ) ਆਸ ਬਣਾ, ਜਿਸ ਦਾ ਸਭ ਜੀਵਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਭਰੋਸਾ ਹੈ(ਹੇ ਮਨ !) ਸਾਰੀਆਂ ਚਤੁਰਾਈਆਂ ਛੱਡ ਕੇ ਗੁਰੂ ਦੇ ਚਰਨੀਂ ਪਉ (ਗੁਰੂ ਦੀ ਸਰਨ ਪਿਆਂ ਹੀ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਮਿਲਾਪ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ) ।੧।ਹੇ ਮੇਰੇ ਮਨ ! ਆਨੰਦ ਨਾਲ ਤੇ ਆਤਮਕ ਅਡੋਲਤਾ ਨਾਲ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਸਿਮਰ  ਅੱਠੇ ਪਹਰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਨੂੰ ਸਿਮਰਦਾ ਰਹੁ, ਸਦਾ ਗੋਬਿੰਦ ਦੇ ਗੁਣ ਗਾਂਦਾ ਰਹੁ ।੧।ਰਹਾਉ।ਹੇ (ਮੇਰੇ) ਮਨ ! ਉਸ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੀ ਸਰਨ ਪਉ, ਜਿਸ ਦੇ ਬਰਾਬਰ ਦਾ ਹੋਰ ਕੋਈ ਨਹੀਂ ਹੈਜਿਸ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਸਿਮਰਿਆਂ ਬਹੁਤ ਆਤਮਕ ਆਨੰਦ ਮਿਲਦਾ ਹੈ, ਤੇ ਕੋਈ ਭੀ ਦੱੁਖ ਕਲੇਸ਼ ਉੱੱਕਾ ਹੀ ਪੋਹ ਨਹੀਂ ਸਕਦਾ(ਹੇ ਮਨ !) ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਹੀ ਸਦਾ ਕਾਇਮ ਰਹਿਣ ਵਾਲਾ ਮਾਲਕ ਹੈ, ਸਦਾ ਉਸੇ ਦੀ ਹੀ ਸੇਵਾ ਭਗਤੀ ਕਰਦਾ ਰਹੁ ।੨।ਸਾਧ ਸੰਗਤਿ ਵਿਚ ਰਿਹਾਂ (ਆਚਰਨ) ਪਵਿਤ੍ਰ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ, ਤੇ ਜਮਾਂ ਦੀ ਫਾਹੀ ਕੱਟੀ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ (ਹੇ ਮਨ ! ਸਾਧ ਸੰਗਤਿ ਦਾ ਆਸਰਾ ਲੈ ਕੇ) ਉਸ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਅੱਗੇ ਅਰਦਾਸ ਕਰਦਾ ਰਹੁ, ਜੋ ਸਾਰੇ ਸੁਖ ਦੇਣ ਵਾਲਾ ਹੈ ਤੇ ਸਾਰੇ ਡਰ-ਸਹਮ ਨਾਸ ਕਰਨ ਵਾਲਾ ਹਮਿਹਰ ਕਰਨ ਵਾਲਾ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਜਿਸ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਉੱਤੇ ਜਦੋਂ ਮਿਹਰ (ਦੀ ਨਿਗਾਹ) ਕਰਦਾ ਹੈ, ਤਦੋਂ ਉਸ ਦੀ ਮਨੁੱਖਾ ਜੀਵਨ ਦੀ ਭਾਰੀ ਜ਼ਿੰਮੇਵਾਰੀ ਸਿਰੇ ਚੜ੍ਹ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ ।੩।ਹਰ ਕੋਈ ਆਖਦਾ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਬਹੁਤ ਉੱਚਾ ਹੈ, ਬਹੁਤ ਉੱਚਾ ਹੈ, ਉਸ ਦਾ ਟਿਕਾਣਾ ਬਹੁਤ ਉੱਚਾ ਹੈਉਸ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦਾ ਕੋਈ ਖ਼ਾਸ ਰੰਗ ਨਹੀਂ ਹੈ ਕੋਈ ਖ਼ਾਸ ਰੂਪ-ਰੇਖਾ ਨਹੀਂ ਹੈ । ਮੈਂ ਉਸ ਦੀ ਕੋਈ ਕੀਮਤ ਨਹੀਂ ਦੱਸ ਸਕਦਾ (ਭਾਵ, ਦੁਨੀਆ ਦੇ ਕਿਸੇ ਭੀ ਪਦਾਰਥ ਦੇ ਵੱਟੇ ਉਸ ਦੀ ਪ੍ਰਾਪਤੀ ਨਹੀਂ ਹੋ ਸਕਦੀ) ਹੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੁੂ ! ਮਿਹਰ ਕਰ ਤੇ ਮੈਨੂੰ ਨਾਨਕ ਨੂੰ ਆਪਣਾ ਸਦਾ ਕਾਇਮ ਰਹਿਣ ਵਾਲਾ ਨਾਮ ਬਖ਼ਸ਼ (ਕਿਉਂਕਿ ਜਿਸ ਨੂੰ ਤੇਰਾ ਨਾਮ ਮਿਲ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਤੇਰਾ ਮੇਲ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ) ।੪।੭।੭੭।\\""},{"question":"Nola deitzen da euskal mitologiako sorginak gidatzen zituen izaki beltza?","answer":"Euskal mitologiako izaki beltza \\"Akerbeltz\\" da. Akerbeltza, askotan aker moduan irudikatua, sorginen biltzarretan, akelarreetan, gidari izan ohi zen. Sinbolo honek, besteak beste, bereizmena eta babesa adierazten ditu, eta zenbait herriko ohituretan garrantzitsua izan da."},{"question":"Awọn adigunjale yinbọn pa oniṣowo n’Ibadan","answer":"Awọn adigunjale ẹlẹni meji kan ti ran gbajumọ oniṣowo bàtà nigboro Ibadan lọ sọrun apapandodo.Ọkunrin naa, Ọgbẹni Afuyẹ, lo n ti ṣọọbu to ti n taja bọ lọjà Ogunpa, n’Ibadan, ti awọn adigunjale ẹlẹni meji ọhún fi dá a lọna nigba to ku diẹ ko délé nirọlẹ ọjọ Iṣẹgun, Tusidee ijẹta.Gẹgẹ b’ALAROYE ṣe gbọ, ọkada lawọn adigunjale naa gun ti wọn fi já ọkada gba mọ ọkunrin oniṣowo náà lọwọ laduugbo ti wọn n pe ni Baba Sala, ni Sango, n’Ibadan.Olugbe adugbo ọhún kan ti iṣẹlẹ yii ṣoju ẹ ṣalaye f’ALAROYE pe “Lẹyin ti ọkan ninu awọn ole yẹn gba ọkada lọwọ ẹ (Afuyẹ) lo bẹrẹ si i sare tẹle wọn, to sí n pariwo ole le wọn lori.“Nigba yẹn lọkan ninu awọn ole yẹn fa ibọn yọ, to sí yín in mọ ọ nigbaaya.“Ariwo ti baba yẹn n pa le awọn adigunjale yẹn lori ni ko jẹ ki wọn le gbé ọkada rẹ lọ. Ẹ̀gbẹ́ maṣíìnì ẹ naa lo ṣubu si to fi kú nitori loju ẹsẹ naa nibọn ti wọn yín mọ ọn ti pa a.”ALAROYE gbọ pe inu oyun ni iyawo baba ti wọn yinbọn pa ọhun wa, asiko to yẹ ko bímọ sì ti fẹrẹ pe. Idi ree ti awọn alabaagbe ẹ ko fi ti i mọ bi wọn ṣe le tufọ iku ọkọ ẹ fún un titi ta a fi pari akojọ iroyin yii.Agbẹnusọ fún ileeṣẹ ọlọpaa ipinlẹ Ọyọ, CSP Olugbenga Fadeyi, fidi ẹ mulẹ pe ni kete ti wọn fi iṣẹlẹ idigunjale yii to awọn leti lawọn ọlọpaa lati teṣan ti yara lọ sibẹ lati dẹkun iṣẹlẹ ọhun, ṣugbọn o ṣe ni laaanu pe wọn yi yinbọn pa ọkunrin naa bo tilẹ jẹ pé wọn kò rí ọkada rẹ gbe lọ.O ni awọn agbofinro ni wọn palẹ oku ọkunrin naa mọ pẹlu ọkada ẹ, ti wọn gbé alupupu lọ sí teṣan wọn, ti wọn sì lọọ tọju oku ọkunrin oniṣowo yii pamọ sì yara ti wọn n ṣe oku lọjọ sí l’Adeọyọ Maternity ti i ṣe ileewosan ijọba ipinlẹ Ọyọ."},{"question":"Awọn agbebọn ji ọmọ Fulani gbe l’Ọṣun","answer":"Awọn ikọ alaabo atawọn ọlọdẹ ti fọn sinu igbo to yi ilu Ora-Igbomina, nijọba ibilẹ Ifẹdayọ, nipinlẹ Ọṣun, ka lati ṣawari ọmọdebinrin kan tawọn agbebọn ji gbe nibẹ lalẹ ọjọ Aiku, Sannde.Nnkan bii aago meje alẹ la gbọ pe awọn agbebọn naa lọ si ile baba ọmọdebinrin naa, Alhaji Bayọ ninu Gaa Fulani ti wọn n gbe.A gbọ pe lẹyin ti wọn yinbọn fun un, ṣugbọn ti ko wọle si i lara, ni wọn fibinu gbe ọkan lara awọn ọmọbinrin rẹ lọ sinu igbo.Nigba ti wọn lọ tan ni baba yii atawọn araale rẹ figbe ta, latigba naa si ni awọn ọlọpaa, OPC, ọlọdẹ, figilante ati bẹẹ bẹẹ lọ ti wa ninu igbo lati dọdẹ awọn agbebọn ọhun.Alukoro ileeṣẹ ọlọpaa l’Ọṣun, Yẹmisi Ọpalọla, sọ pe awọn ti gbọ nipa iṣẹlẹ naa, ati pe awọn agbofinro ti wa ninu igbo lati gba ọmọbinrin ọhun silẹ lai fara pa."},{"question":"application -தமிழில் மொழிபெயர்க்கவும்","answer":"application (1) : மனு , கோரிக்கை , விண்ணப்பம் .  (Application -- petition)application (2) : பயன்பாடு . (Application -- to use)application (3) : தடவுதல் , அப்புதல் , ஒற்றல் . (Application -- to apply)"},{"question":"日本人はよく助詞を飛ばして話しているけど、全部の助詞を飛ばしても大丈夫 ？","answer":"基本的に「は」「が」「を」は飛ばしても意味がわかるのですが、「で」や「に」は飛ばすと変です。〇　私、ごはん　食べます　（私は　ごはんを　食べます）×　  私、レストラン　食べます　（私は、レストランを食べます？？）〇   私　映画の時間　調べるね　（私は映画の時間を調べるね）×　 私　映画の時間　スマホ　調べるね　（私はスマホと映画の時間を調べます？？)「に」は、グレーゾーン〇　よく渋谷　行く？　(よく渋谷に行く)〇　いす、座る？×　友だち　会う？×　12時　ごはん食べる"},{"question":"Inona no manana maso iray nefa tsy mahita?","answer":"Fanjaitra no manana maso iray nefa tsy mahita"},{"question":"Varsovie mooy gëblag man réew?","answer":"Varsovie mooy gëblag réewum Pologne."},{"question":"Bacalah teks di bawah ini dan jawablah pertanyaan di bawahnyaTeks: Selama ratusan tahun, luka tembak di perut berarti kematian akibat gangren atau infeksi lainnya, dan dokter hanya dapat meringankan rasa sakit. Hanya tujuh belas tahun sebelumnya, Dr. Emil Kocher, seorang ahli bedah dari Swiss, adalah orang pertama yang berhasil mengoperasi seorang pasien yang mengalami luka seperti itu. Untuk meningkatkan pencahayaan, sinar matahari dipantulkan ke luka oleh dokter lain; menjelang akhir operasi, cahaya yang lebih baik diperbaiki. Rumah sakit tidak memiliki peralatan bedah dasar seperti retractor. Dengan McKinley dalam kondisi lemah, Mann dapat melakukan sedikit penggalian luka untuk mencoba menemukan peluru; pekerjaannya rumit oleh fakta bahwa Presiden mengalami obesitas. Dokter bedah membuat sayatan di kulit Presiden, dan menemukan dan mengeluarkan sepotong kain kecil yang tertanam dalam daging. Dia mengamati dengan jari dan tangannya, menemukan kerusakan pada sistem pencernaan, perut menunjukkan luka masuk dan keluar. Mann menjahit kedua lubang di organ, tetapi tidak dapat menemukan peluru itu sendiri; ia menyimpulkan bahwa peluru itu tertanam di otot punggung Presiden. Ia kemudian menulis, \\"Sebuah peluru setelah berhenti bergerak tidak banyak membahayakan\\". Sebuah mesin sinar-X primitif dipamerkan di pameran tetapi tidak digunakan pada McKinley; Mann kemudian menyatakan bahwa penggunaannya mungkin telah mengganggu pasien dan tidak banyak membantu. Dia menggunakan benang sutra hitam untuk menjahit luka dan luka, tanpa drainase, dan menutupi daerah dengan perban. Saat operasi selesai, Dr. Park tiba dari Niagara Falls; ia tidak mau ikut campur dan pada pukul 5:20, McKinley diberi suntikan obat penghilang rasa sakit lagi dan diizinkan untuk bangun. Dia dibawa ke Rumah Milburn oleh ambulans listrik. Wanita Pertama tidak diberitahu tentang penembakan Presiden; setelah operasi selesai, dokter presiden, Presley M. Rixey, dengan lembut memberitahunya apa yang telah terjadi. Ida McKinley menerima berita itu dengan tenang; dia menulis dalam buku hariannya, \\"Pergi ke Niagra [sic] Falls pagi ini. My Dearest menerima di ruang publik pada saat kami kembali, ketika dia ditembak oleh...Pertanyaan: Apa contoh peralatan yang tidak dimiliki rumah sakit?","answer":"Retractor."},{"question":"રીંગણનું ભરતું બનાવાની રીત .","answer":"રીંગણનું ભરતુંસામગ્રી:રીંગણ - ૨લસણ - ૫-૬ કળીઆદુ - ૧ ઈંચમીઠું - ૧ ચમચીહળદર - ૧/૨ ચમચીલીંબુનો રસ - ૧ ચમચીખાંડ - ૧/૨ ચમચીગરમ મસાલો - ૧/૨ ચમચીધાણાજીરું પાવડર - ૧/૨ ચમચીગરમ તેલ - ૧/૨ કપરીત:૧. રીંગણને સાફ કરીને ઉપર છિદ્રો કરી લો.૨. એક કડાઈમાં તેલ ગરમ કરો અને તેમાં લસણ અને આદુને વાટીને નાખો.૩. તેને થોડીવાર સાંતળી લો અને પછી તેમાં રીંગણ નાખી દો.૪. તેને ઉપરથી મીઠું, હળદર, લીંબુનો રસ, ખાંડ અને ગરમ મસાલો નાખી દો.૫. રીંગણને ઢાંકીને ધીમા તાપે ૧૫-૨૦ મિનિટ માટે રાંધો.૬. રીંગણ ગરમ ગરમ પીરસો.ટીપ્સ:રીંગણને ઉપરથી ઘણી છિદ્રો કરવાથી તેમાંની પાણી નીકળી જાય છે અને રીંગણ ઝડપથી રાંધાય છે.રીંગણને ધીમા તાપે રાંધવાથી તેનો રસ જાળવી રાખી શકાય છે.તમે રીંગણના ભરણમાં ટામેટાં, ડુંગળી, મરચું વગેરે પણ ઉમેરી શકો છો."},{"question":"Na nasiona chryzantemy wielkokwiatowej działano promieniowaniem jonizującym (gamma), dzięki czemu otrzymano nowe odmiany tej rośliny o niespotykanych wcześniej barwach i kształtach kwiatostanów.Dokończ zdanie. Wybierz właściwą odpowiedź spośród podanych.Promieniowanie jonizujące spowodowało w komórkach chryzantem mutacje polegające na zmianachA. w budowie komórek tworzących tkanki.B. w materiale genetycznym (w DNA).C. w sposobie dziedziczenia cech.D. w kodzie genetycznym.","answer":"Poprawna opowiedź to B, gdyż promieniowanie jonizujące powoduje mutacje w strukturze DNA."},{"question":"Ca bhfuil an tír Asarbaiseáin? ","answer":"Tá sí suite idir an Iaráin, an Rúis, an Airméin agus an tSeoirsia. Tá cuid den Asarbaiseáin, mar atá, Nakhchivan nó Naxçıvan, dealaithe ón gcuid eile den phoblacht ag an Airméin. Tá Naxçıvan ag críochantacht go díreach leis an Tuirc."},{"question":"Địa phương duy nhất nào giáp với 8 tỉnh?A. Hà NộiB. TP HCMD. Bình Dương","answer":"A. Hà NộiHà Nội giáp 8 tỉnh, trong đó Thái Nguyên, Vĩnh Phúc ở phía Bắc; Hà Nam, Hòa Bình phía Nam; Bắc Giang, Bắc Ninh và Hưng Yên phía Đông; Hòa Bình, Phú Thọ phía Tây.Địa hình Hà Nội vừa có núi, đồi (tập trung ở phía Bắc và Tây), thấp dần từ Bắc xuống Nam và từ Tây sang Đông, trong đó, đồng bằng chiếm 3/4 diện tích tự nhiên của thành phố. Các đỉnh cao nhất là Ba Vì 1.281 m, Gia Dê 707 m, Chân Chim 462 m, Thanh Lanh 427 m và Thiên Trù 378 m... Khu vực nội đô có một số gò đồi thấp, như gò Đống Đa, núi Nùng."},{"question":"\\"મેરી પોપિન્સ 1964 ની મ્યુઝિકલ ફિલ્મ છે, જેમાં જુલી એન્ડ્રુઝ, ડિક વેન ડાઇક, ડેવિડ ટોમલિનસન અને ગ્લીનિસ જોન્સ અભિનય કરે છે, વોલ્ટ ડિઝની દ્વારા ઉત્પાદિત છે, અને પી. એલ. ટ્રેવર્સ દ્વારા મેરી પોપિન્સ પુસ્તકોની શ્રેણી પર આધારિત છે. \\"?","answer":"\\"મેરી પોપિન્સ નું પાત્ર ફિલ્મમાં કોણ ભજવે છે?"},{"question":"You have the following word:“amazing”","answer":"The stem of the word “amazing” is “amaz”"},{"question":"Inona ny teny mifanohitra hevitra amin'ny \\"Mamelona\\"?","answer":"Ny teny mifanohitra hevitra amin'ny \\"Mamelona\\" dia \\"Mamono\\"."},{"question":"KG Манас эпосу 📚Сейтек эпосунун канча варианты бар?а) 12 б) 15в) 17 г) 19","answer":"KG Манас эпосу 📚а) 12"},{"question":"Манас биринчи болуп кимдер менен жоолашат?а) Алтайлык калмактар менен б) кытайларв) казактар г) Шорук хан менен","answer":"а) Алтайлык калмактар менен "},{"question":"wane Sahabi ne yayi fice a fagen yabon Annabi Sallallahu Alaihi Wa Sallama da bashi kariya da wakokin sa ","answer":"(a) Usman Bin Affan(b) Khalid bin Walid (c) Hassanu bin Sabit"},{"question":"இந்தியாவின் தேசிய பாடல் என்ன?இயற்றியவர் யார் ?","answer":"வந்தே மாதரம்                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        வந்தே மாதரம்வந்தே மாதரம்சுஜலாம் சுபலாம் மலயஜஸீதலாம்சஸ்யஷ்யாமலாம் மாதரம் வந்தே மாதரம்கோடி கோடி கண்ட கலகல நினாத கராலேகோடி கோடி புஜைர் த்ருத கர கரவாலேஅபலா கெனோ மா நமாமி தாரிணீம்பஹுபல தாரிணீம் நமாமி தாரிணீம்ரிபுதல வாரிணீம் மாதரம் வந்தே மாதரம்துமி வித்யா திமி தர்மதுமி ருதி துமி மர்ம த்வம் ஹி ப்ராணா சரீரேபாஹுதே துமி மா சக்திருதயே துமி மா பக்திதோமாரயி ப்ரதிமா கடி மந்திரே மாதரம் வந்தே மாதரம்த்வம் ஹி துர்கா தசப்ரஹண தாரிணீம்கமலாம் கமலதல விஹாரிணீம்வாணீ வித்யா தாயினீம்நமாமி த்வாம் நமாமி கமலாம் அமலாம் அதுலாம்சுஜலாம் சுபலாம் மாதரம் வந்தே மாதரம்ச்யாமளாம் சரளாம்ஸுஸ்மிதாம் புஷிதாம்தரணீம் பரணீம் மாதரம் வந்தே மாதரம்பாரத மாதா கீ ஜெய்இந்திய தேசிய பாடலான 'வந்தே மாதரம்' சமஸ்கிருதத்தில் பங்கிம்சந்திர சாட்டர்ஜியால் இயற்றப்பட்டது.         பங்கிம் சந்திர சட்டர்ஜி , (பிறப்பு ஜூன் 26/27, 1838, வங்காளத்தின் நைஹாட்டிக்கு அருகில், இந்தியா - ஏப்ரல் 8, 1894, கல்கத்தா), இந்திய எழுத்தாளர், அவரது நாவல்கள் வங்காள மொழிக்கான இலக்கிய வாகனமாக உரைநடையை உறுதியாக நிறுவி, இந்தியாவில் உருவாக்க உதவியது. ஐரோப்பிய மாதிரியில் ஒரு புனைகதை பள்ளி.பங்கிம் சந்திரா ஒரு மரபுவழி பிராமண குடும்பத்தைச் சேர்ந்தவர் மற்றும் ஹூக்ளி கல்லூரி, கல்கத்தாவில் உள்ள பிரசிடென்சி கல்லூரி மற்றும் கல்கத்தா பல்கலைக்கழகத்தில் கல்வி கற்றார் , அதில் அவர் முதல் பட்டதாரிகளில் ஒருவர். 1858 முதல், 1891 இல் ஓய்வு பெறும் வரை, இந்திய சிவில் சர்வீஸில் துணை மாஜிஸ்திரேட்டாகப் பணியாற்றினார் .4:043 டிக்கின்சன், எமிலி: எ லைஃப் ஆஃப் லெட்டர்ஸ், இது உலகத்திற்கான எனது கடிதம்/இது எனக்கு ஒருபோதும் எழுதவில்லை;  ஒரு நேரத்தில் சன் ரோஸ்/எ ரிப்பன் எப்படி என்று நான் உங்களுக்கு சொல்கிறேன்;  நம்பிக்கை என்பது இறகுகளைக் கொண்ட விஷயம்/ஆன்மாவில் நிலைத்திருப்பதுபிரிட்டானிகா வினாடி வினாபுகழ்பெற்ற கவிஞர்கள் மற்றும் கவிதை வடிவம்பங்கிம் சந்திராவின் சில இளமைப் பாடல்கள் சம்பத் பிரபாகர் செய்தித்தாளில் வெளிவந்தன , மேலும் 1858 இல் அவர் லலிதா ஓ மனஸ் என்ற தலைப்பில் ஒரு கவிதைத் தொகுதியை வெளியிட்டார் . சிறிது காலத்திற்கு அவர் ஆங்கிலத்தில் எழுதினார், மேலும் அவரது நாவலான ராஜ்மோகனின் மனைவி 1864 இல் இந்தியத் துறையில் தொடராக வெளிவந்தது. அவரது முதல் குறிப்பிடத்தக்க பெங்காலி படைப்பு நாவல் ஆகும்.துர்கேஷ் நந்தினி, இதில் ராஜபுத்திர நாயகன் மற்றும் பெங்காலி கதாநாயகி. அதுவே அலட்சிய தரம் வாய்ந்தது, ஆனால் தத்துவஞானி தேபேந்திரநாத் தாகூரின் வார்த்தைகளில், அது “வங்காளத்தின் இதயத்தை புயலால் தாக்கியது”, அதனுடன் பெங்காலி நாவல் முழுவதுமாக பிறந்தது. கபால்குண்ட ஆலா, தாந்த்ரீக சடங்குகளின் கொடூரமான பின்னணிக்கு எதிரான காதல் கதை, 1866 இல் வெளியிடப்பட்டது; மற்றும் 1869 இல் வங்காளத்தின் முதல் முஸ்லீம் படையெடுப்பின் போது அமைக்கப்பட்ட ம்ருண் ஆலினி .பங்கிம் சந்திராவின் சகாப்தமான செய்தித்தாள் பாங்கதர்ஸ் 1872 இல் வெளியிடப்பட்டது, மேலும் அதில் அவரது சில பிற்கால நாவல்கள் தொடராக வெளியிடப்பட்டன. விதவை மறுமணப் பிரச்சனையை முன்வைக்கும் Biṣ abṛ ksa மற்றும் இந்திரா 1873 இல் வெளியிடப்பட்டன; 1874 இல் யுகலங்குரியா ; 1875 இல் ராதாராணி மற்றும் கான்ட்ராஷேகர் ; 1877 இல் ரஜனி ; கிருஷ்ணன் அகந்தர் உயில், 1878 இல் ஆசிரியர் தனது மிகப் பெரிய நாவலாகக் கருதினார்; ராஜ்சிஹா , 1881 இல் ராஜபுத்திர வீரம் மற்றும் முஸ்லீம் ஒடுக்குமுறை பற்றிய கதை;Ā nandamaṭh , 1882 இல் கிழக்கிந்திய கம்பெனியின் முஸ்லீம் படைகளுக்கு எதிராக சன்னியாசிகளின் கிளர்ச்சியின் தேசபக்தி கதை; டெபி கௌதுராணி, 1884 இல், கொள்ளையடிக்கும் பின்னணியைக் கொண்ட உள்நாட்டு நாவல்; இறுதியாக, 1886 இல், சீதாரம், ஒரு திருமணச் சிக்கல் மற்றும் முஸ்லீம் கொடுங்கோன்மைக்கு எதிரான இந்துக்களின் போராட்டம் .பங்கிம் சந்திராவின் நாவல்கள் படிக்க உற்சாகமூட்டுவதாகக் கருதப்படுகின்றன, ஆனால் அவை கட்டமைப்பு ரீதியாகப் பழுதடைந்தன. தொடர் வெளியீடு பல்வேறு அத்தியாயங்களின் முழுமையற்ற ஒருங்கிணைப்புக்கு ஓரளவு காரணமாகும் . சதித்திட்டத்தின் பரிணாமம் பெரும்பாலும் வாய்ப்பு அல்லது இயற்கைக்கு அப்பாற்பட்ட தலையீட்டைப் பொறுத்தது, மேலும் குணாதிசயம் பெரும்பாலும் ஒரு மேலோட்டமான செயற்கையான நோக்கத்திற்கு கீழ்ப்படுத்தப்படுகிறது. இருப்பினும், அவரது சாதனைகள் இந்த தொழில்நுட்ப குறைபாடுகளை விட அதிகமாக உள்ளன. அவரது சமகாலத்தவர்களுக்கு அவருடைய குரல் ஒரு தீர்க்கதரிசியின் குரல்; அவரது வீரம் மிக்க இந்து மாவீரர்கள் தங்கள் தேசபக்தியையும் இனத்தின் பெருமையையும் தூண்டினர். அவரிடம் தேசியமும் இந்து மதமும் ஒன்றாக இணைந்தன; மேலும் அவனது மதம் பாடலில் உருவகப்படுத்தப்பட்டது \\"பந்தே மாதரம்\\" (\\"உங்களுக்கு வணக்கம், அம்மா\\")-அவரது நாவலான ஆனந்தமாத் - இது பின்னர் சுதந்திரத்திற்கான போராட்டத்தில் இந்து இந்தியாவின் மந்திரமாகவும் (\\"பாடல்\\") முழக்கமாகவும் மாறியது.தொடர் , ஒரு நாவல் அல்லது பிற படைப்புகள் (பத்திரிக்கையில் இருப்பது போல்) இடைவெளியில் பகுதிகளாகத் தோன்றும். 19 ஆம் நூற்றாண்டில் எழுதப்பட்ட நாவல்கள் பொதுவாக தொடர்களாக வெளியிடப்பட்டன. சார்லஸ் டிக்கன்ஸ் , ஜார்ஜ் எலியட் , வில்லியம் மேக்பீஸ் தாக்கரே , அந்தோனி ட்ரோலோப் மற்றும் பிறரின் பல படைப்புகள் முதலில் டிக்கன்ஸின் வீட்டு வார்த்தைகள் மற்றும் தாக்கரேயின் தி கார்ன்ஹில் இதழ் போன்ற இதழ்களில் தொடர்ச்சியாக வெளிவந்தன .பெங்காலி இலக்கியம் , இந்திய துணைக்கண்டத்தின் வங்காள மொழியில் எழுதப்பட்ட தொகுப்பு . சஹாஜியா மதப் பிரிவின் நம்பிக்கைகள் மற்றும் நடைமுறைகளைப் பிரதிபலிக்கும் 12 ஆம் நூற்றாண்டுக்கு முந்தைய பாடல் வரிகளின் தொகுப்பே அதன் ஆரம்பகால படைப்பு ஆகும் . 1199 ஆம் ஆண்டின் முஸ்லீம் படையெடுப்பின் கவிஞர்களின் சிதறல் 14 ஆம் நூற்றாண்டின் நடுப்பகுதி வரை அனைத்து கவிதை நடவடிக்கைகளையும் உடைத்தது. அதன்பிறகு, இலக்கியம் இடைக்காலம் (1360-1800) மற்றும் நவீனம் (1800க்குப் பிறகு) எனப் பிரிக்கப்பட்டது .பாடல் வரிகள் , ஒரு வசனம் அல்லது கவிதை, ஒரு இசைக்கருவியின் துணையுடன் (பண்டைய காலங்களில், பொதுவாக ஒரு பாடல்) பாடப்படுவதற்கு வாய்ப்புள்ளது அல்லது ஒரு பாடலைக் குறிக்கும் விதத்தில் தீவிரமான தனிப்பட்ட உணர்ச்சிகளை வெளிப்படுத்துகிறது . பாடல் கவிதைகள் கவிஞரின் எண்ணங்கள் மற்றும் உணர்வுகளை வெளிப்படுத்துகிறது மற்றும் சில சமயங்களில் கதை வடிவில் நிகழ்வுகளை தொடர்புபடுத்தும் கதை கவிதை மற்றும் வசன நாடகம் ஆகியவற்றுடன் முரண்படுகிறது. எலிஜிஸ், ஓட்ஸ் மற்றும் சொனெட்டுகள் அனைத்தும் முக்கியமான பாடல் கவிதைகள்.இல்பண்டைய கிரீஸ் பாடகர்களின் பாடகர்களால் பாடப்பட்ட கவிதைகளுக்கு இடையில் ஒரு ஆரம்ப வேறுபாடு காட்டப்பட்டது (பாடல் வரிகள் ) மற்றும் ஒரு கவிஞரின் உணர்வுகளை வெளிப்படுத்தும் பாடல் . பிந்தையது, திமெலோஸ் , அல்லது சரியான பாடல், \\"கிரீஸ் தீவுகளில், எரியும் இடத்தில் தொழில்நுட்ப பரிபூரணத்தின் உச்சத்தை எட்டியது.சப்போ நேசித்தார் மற்றும் பாடினார், \\" கிமு 7 ஆம் நூற்றாண்டின் முற்பகுதியில் . அந்தக் கவிஞர், அவரது சமகாலத்தவரான அல்கேயஸுடன் சேர்ந்து , தூய கிரேக்கப் பாடலின் முக்கிய டோரிக் கவிஞர்கள். அவர்களின் பக்கத்திலும், பின்னர், பாடகர்களுக்கு இசையமைத்த சிறந்த கவிஞர்கள், அல்க்மேன், ஏரியன், ஸ்டெசிகோரஸ், சிமோனிடிஸ் மற்றும் ஐபிகஸ் ஆகியோர் வளர்ந்தனர், அவர்கள் 5 ஆம் நூற்றாண்டின் இறுதியில் பாக்கிலைட்ஸ் மற்றும் பிண்டார் ஆகியோரால் பின்பற்றப்பட்டனர் . டைதிராம்பிக் ஓட்ஸ் அதன் மிக உயர்ந்த வளர்ச்சியை அடைந்தது.வில்லியம் பிளேக்கின் \\"சாங்ஸ் ஆஃப் இன்னசென்ஸ்\\" இலிருந்து \\"தி லாம்ப்\\" இன் விளக்கப்படம், 1879. கவிதை;  கவிதைபிரிட்டானிகா வினாடி வினாகவிதை பற்றிய ஒரு ஆய்வுலத்தீன் பாடல் வரிகள் கிமு 1 ஆம் நூற்றாண்டில் கேடல்லஸ் மற்றும் ஹோரேஸ் ஆகியோரால் எழுதப்பட்டது மற்றும் இடைக்கால ஐரோப்பாவில் ட்ரூபடோர்களின் பாடல்களிலும், கிறிஸ்தவப் பாடல்களிலும், பல்வேறு பாலாட்களிலும் பாடல் வடிவத்தைக் காணலாம். மறுமலர்ச்சியில் மிகவும் முடிக்கப்பட்ட பாடல் வரிகள், திசொனட் , பெட்ராக் , ஷேக்ஸ்பியர், எட்மண்ட் ஸ்பென்சர் மற்றும் ஜான் மில்டன் ஆகியோரால் அற்புதமாக உருவாக்கப்பட்டது . 18 ஆம் மற்றும் 19 ஆம் நூற்றாண்டின் பிற்பகுதியில் கவிதையின் பாடல் வடிவங்களுடன் குறிப்பாக அடையாளம் காணப்பட்ட காதல் கவிஞர்கள் , ராபர்ட் பர்ன்ஸ் , வில்லியம் பிளேக் , வில்லியம் வேர்ட்ஸ்வொர்த் , ஜான் கீட்ஸ் , பெர்சி பைஷே ஷெல்லி , லாமார்டின், கோரிச் , விக்டர் ஹுச் மற்றும் ஹெய்ன் . சில வியத்தகு வசனங்களைத் தவிர, 19 ஆம் நூற்றாண்டின் பிற்பகுதி மற்றும் 20 ஆம் நூற்றாண்டின் பெரும்பாலான மேற்கத்திய கவிதைகள் பாடல் வரிகளாக வகைப்படுத்தப்படலாம்.தேசிய கீதம் , பாடல் அல்லது தேசபக்தி உணர்வை வெளிப்படுத்தும் பாடல் மற்றும் அதிகாரப்பூர்வ தேசிய கீதமாக அரசாங்கத்தால் அங்கீகரிக்கப்பட்டது அல்லது மக்கள் உணர்வில் அந்த பதவியை வகிக்கிறது. பழமையான தேசிய கீதம் கிரேட்பிரிட்டனின் \\"காட் சேவ் தி குயின் ”, இது 1825 இல் தேசிய கீதமாக விவரிக்கப்பட்டது, இருப்பினும் இது ஒரு தேசபக்தி பாடலாக பிரபலமானது மற்றும் 18 ஆம் நூற்றாண்டின் நடுப்பகுதியில் இருந்து அரச சடங்கு நிகழ்வுகளில் பயன்படுத்தப்பட்டது.19 ஆம் மற்றும் 20 ஆம் நூற்றாண்டின் முற்பகுதியில், பெரும்பாலான ஐரோப்பிய நாடுகள் பிரிட்டனின் முன்மாதிரியைப் பின்பற்றின, சில தேசிய கீதங்கள் குறிப்பாக நோக்கத்திற்காக எழுதப்பட்டன, மற்றவை ஏற்கனவே இருக்கும் ட்யூன்களிலிருந்து தழுவின. தேசிய கீதங்களின் உணர்வுகள் , மன்னருக்கான பிரார்த்தனைகள் முதல் தேசிய முக்கியத்துவம் வாய்ந்த போர்கள் அல்லது எழுச்சிகள் (\\"தி ஸ்டார்-ஸ்பாங்கிள்ட் பேனர், யுனைடெட் ஸ்டேட்ஸ்; \\"லா மார்சேய்ஸ்,\\" பிரான்ஸ்) தேசபக்தி உணர்வின் வெளிப்பாடுகள் (\\"ஓ கனடா\\") வரை வேறுபடுகின்றன. .தேசிய கீதங்கள் இசைத் தகுதியில் பெரிதும் வேறுபடுகின்றன, மேலும் இசையைப் போன்ற வசனம் அல்லது உரை, ஒவ்வொரு சந்தர்ப்பத்திலும் சம்பந்தப்பட்ட நாட்டின் நாட்டவரால் எழுதப்படவில்லை. அரசியல் அல்லது சர்வதேச உறவுகளில் ஏற்படும் மாற்றங்கள் பெரும்பாலும் நூல்களை மாற்றியமைக்க அல்லது ஒரு புதிய கீதம் ஏற்றுக்கொள்ளப்படுவதற்கு காரணமாகின்றன. உதாரணமாக, திசோவியத் ஒன்றியம் 1944 ஆம் ஆண்டில் அதன் தேசிய கீதமாக \\"கிம்ன் சோவெட்ஸ்கோகோ சோயுசா\\" (\\"சோவியத் ஒன்றியத்தின் பாடல்\\") ஏற்றுக்கொண்டது, கம்யூனிஸ்ட் பாடலான \\"எல்'இன்டர்நேஷனல்\\" க்கு பதிலாக, 19 ஆம் நூற்றாண்டின் பிற்பகுதியில் இரண்டு பிரெஞ்சு தொழிலாளர்களால் எழுதப்பட்ட வார்த்தைகளும் இசையும்.புகழ்பெற்ற கவிஞர்கள் அல்லது இசையமைப்பாளர்களால் சில தேசிய கீதங்கள் எழுதப்பட்டுள்ளன, இது முதல் விதிவிலக்குஆஸ்திரிய தேசிய கீதம், \\"காட் எர்ஹால்ட் ஃபிரான்ஸ் டென் கைசர்\\" (\\"காட் சேவ் எம்பரர் பிரான்சிஸ்\\"), இயற்றியவர்ஜோசப் ஹெய்டன் 1797 மற்றும் பின்னர் (1929) \\"Sei gesegnet ohne Ende\\" (\\"என்றென்றும் ஆசீர்வதிக்கப்படு\\") என்ற உரைக்கு பாடினார். 1922 இல் ஏற்றுக்கொள்ளப்பட்ட ஜெர்மன் தேசிய கீதமான “Deutschland, Deutschland über Alles” (“Germany, Germany Above All”)க்கும் ஹெய்டனின் மெல்லிசை பயன்படுத்தப்பட்டது. அதன் மூன்றாவது வசனமான “Einigkeit und Recht und Freiheit” (“ஒற்றுமை மற்றும் உரிமைகள் மற்றும் சுதந்திரம்”), இது தேசிய கீதமாக தொடர்ந்து பயன்பாட்டில் உள்ளதுஜெர்மனி , \\"Deutschlandlied\\" என மறுபெயரிடப்பட்டது. 1922 ஆம் ஆண்டுக்கு முன் ஜெர்மானிய தேசிய கீதம் \\"Heil dir im Siegerkranz\\" (\\"Wictor's Garlands இல் உங்களுக்கு வணக்கம்\\"), \\"God Save the Queen\\" என்ற மெல்லிசையில் பாடப்பட்டது. இத்தாலியின் Goffredo Mameli போன்ற தேசிய கீதங்களின் சில ஆசிரியர்கள் , அவர்களின் இசையமைப்பின் தேசிய பிரபலத்தின் விளைவாக மட்டுமே புகழ் பெற்றார்கள். ( \\" அட்வான்ஸ் ஆஸ்திரேலியா ஃபேர் \\"; \\" Deutschlandlied \\"; \\" God Save the Queen \\"; \\" L ' International \\"; \\" La Marseillaise \\"; \\" O Canada \\"; \\" The Star-Spangled Banner .\\""},{"question":"உங்கள் ஊரிலுள்ள சிறப்பு வாய்ந்த இடங்களைப் பற்றி, உமது கருத்துகளை எடுத்துக் கூறுக.","answer":"எங்கள் ஊர் திருவண்ணாமலை. இங்கு சிறப்பு வாய்ந்த இடங்களில் முதலிடம் பெறுவது அருணாச்சலேஸ்வரர் கோயில்தான். கார்த்திகை தீபம், கிரிவலம் இவையிரண்டும் திருவண்ணாமலையுடன் பிணைந்தது. இது சிவனின் பஞ்சபூத தலங்களில் ஒன்று இது அக்னி தலமாகும். கார்த்திகை மாதத்தில் இங்குள்ள மலை உச்சியில் நெய் தீபம் ஏற்றப்படும். ஒவ்வொரு பௌர்ணமியன்றும் மலையைச் சுற்றிவருவர். அவ்வாறு சுற்றும்போது மூலிகைக் காற்றைச் சுவாசிக்க முடியும் என்று கூறுவர்.அடுத்தது சாத்தனூர் அணை. பெண்ணையாற்றின் குறுக்கே கட்டப்பட்டது. இங்கு தொங்குபாலம் ஒன்று உள்ளது. சிறுவர்களுக்கான படகு சவாரியும் இரயில் வண்டியும் உள்ளன. ஸ்ரீசேஷாத்திரி சுவாமிகள் ஆசிரமம், செஞ்சிக்கோட்டை இவையெல்லாம் திருவண்ணாமலைக்குப் பெருமை சேர்ப்பவை. திருவண்ணாமலை அண்ணாமலையார் கோவில் அருணகிரிநாதரால் பாடப்பெற்ற வரலாற்றுச் சிறப்புடையது. செஞ்சிக்கோட்டையும் வரலாற்றுச் சிறப்புடைய கோட்டையாகும். விடுமுறை நாட்களில் இங்கு சுற்றுலாவாசிகளால் அலங்கரிக்கப்படும்.வட இந்திய பாணியில் நாரக அமைப்பில் அமைக்கப்பட்டுள்ள ரகுமாயி சமேத பாண்டுரங்கன் கோயில் தென்னாங்கூர் கிராமத்தில் அமைந்துள்ளது. இந்து புராணங்களின்படி இது லட்சுமி தேவி அவதாரத் தலம். இந்தக் கோயில் வளாகத்தில் பூந்தோட்டங்களுடன் மிகவும் சிறப்பாக பராமரிக்கப்பட்டு வருகிறது. நுழைவாயிலில் பெரிய கோபுரமும் உள்ளே அமைந்துள்ள விமானம் நாகர பாணியில் அமைந்துள்ளது. இங்கு ஓவியங்கள் நிறைந்த பெரிய மண்டபம் ஒன்று உள்ளத. இந்த மண்டபத்தில் இருந்தே 10.5 அடி உயர பாண்டுரங்கன் திருவுருவச்சிலையும் 8.5 அடி உயர ரகுமாயி திருவுருவச்சிலையும் கண்டு சேவிக்கலாம். வாரத்தின் ஆறு நாட்களுக்கு பல வகை ஆடை அணிகலன்களாலும் அலங்கரிக்கப்படுகின்றன. இவ்வூர் வந்தவாசி – காஞ்சிபுரம் நெடுஞ்சாலையில் வந்தவாசியிலிருந்து 5 கி.மீ. தொலைவில் அமைந்துள்ளது.திருவண்ணாமலை மாவட்டத்தில் திருவண்ணாமலைக்கு அடுத்த பெரிய கோயிலாகவும் விஜயநகர கட்ட்டக்கலைக்கு சிறந்த சான்றாகவும் அமைந்துள்ளது பெரியநாயகி அம்மன் ஆலயமும் மலைமீதுள்ள பொன்மலைநாதர் ஆலயமும் ஆகும். இக்கோயில்களில் சுமார் 10000 க்கும் மேற்பட்ட சிற்பங்களும், 60 கல்வெட்டுகளும் உள்ளன. விஜயநகர பேரரசர் காலத்தில் புகழ்பெற்ற வணிக நகராகவும், ஆன்மிக தலமாகவும் விலங்கி வந்தது. இக்கோயில் அக்காலத்தில் ஊரின் நிர்வாக அமைப்பாக செயல்பட்டுள்ளது.பெரியநாயகி அம்மன் கோயில் மதில் சுவர் , கல்யாணமண்டபம், மகாமண்டபம், கருவறை ஆகிய இடங்களில் சைவ, வைணவச் கதைச் சிற்பங்கள் எழிலுற அமைந்துள்ளன. தேவராக் கதைச்சிற்பங்கள், விஷ்ணுவின் அவதாரச்சிற்பங்கள், தலவரலாற்றுச்சிற்பங்கள் போன்றவை காணத்தகுந்தவை ஆகும். இக்கோயிலுக்கு பின்புறம் அமைந்துள்ள திருகாமேஸ்வரர் சம்மே கோகிலாம்பாள் ஆலயமும் அதன் அருகில் சுமார் 500 அடி உயர மலையில் அமைந்துள்ள பொன்மலைநாதர் திருக்கோயிலும் சிற்ப எழில் கொண்ட கோயில்களாகும்."},{"question":"Ithini indlela yosindiso? impendulo ibenonxulumelano ne-bhayibhile.","answer":"Ulambile? Andilambanga ngokwasenyameni,ngaba ulambele enye into yasebomini? Ingaba ikhona into phakathi kuwe engonelisekanga? Ukuba kunjalo, uYesu sisisombululo! UYesu whathi, “Ndisisonka sobomi. Ozileyo kum akasayi kuphinde alambe, kwaye okholelwa kum akasayi kuphinde anxanwe” (UYohane 6:35).Undidekile? Zange ufumane indlela okanye injongo ngobomi? Ibonakala ngathi umntu ucime isibane kwaye awukwazi kufumana iswitshi? Ukuba kunjalo, UYesu sisisombululo! UYesu wamemeza, “Ndilukhaniselo lwehlabathi. Nabani ondilandelayo akasoze ahambe ebumnyameni, koko ubomi bakhe buza kukhanya” (UYohane 8:12).Whakhe waziva ngathi uvaleleke ngaphandle kobomi bakho? Wakhe wazama yonke iminyango,waza wafumanisa ukuba emva kwayo akukho nto kwaye akukho ntsingiselo? Ingaba ufuna isango lokungena ebomini obonelisayo? Ukuba kunjalo, UYesu sisisombululo ! UYesu waxela, “Ndilisango; ukuba umntu uthe wangena ngam wosindiswa, uyakungena ephuma, afumane utyani” (UYohane 10:9).Ingaba abanye abantu bayakuphoxa? Ingaba ubudlelwane bakho abunzulwanga yaye buyalambatha? Ingaba kubonakala ngathi wonke umntu ufuna ukudlala ngawe? Ukuba kunjalo, UYesu sisisombululo ! UYesu wathi, “Ndim umalusi olungileyo. Umalusi olungileyo ubomi bakhe ubuncamela izimvu. Ndim umalusi olungileyo; Ndiyazazi izimvu zam, nezimvu zam ziyandazi” ( UYohane 10:11, 14).Ingaba ufuna ukwazi ukuba kwenzeka ntoni emva kobu bomi? Ingaba udiniwe ukuphila ubomi bakho kwizinto ezibolayo okanye ezirusayo? Ingaba ngamanye amaxesha ukhe uthandabuze ingaba ubomi bunayo intsingiselo? Ingaba uyafuna ukuphila emva kokuba ufile? Ukuba kunjalo, uYesu sisisombululo! UYesu uyaxela, “Ndiluvuko kwanobomi. Okholwa kum uyakudla ubomi, nakubeni efile; bonke abadla ubomi bekholwa kum abasayi kufa naphakade” (UYohane 11:25-26).Yintoni indlela? Yintoni ukunyaniseka? Yintoni ubomi? UYesu waphendula, “Ndiyindlela ndiyinyaniso ndibubomi.Akukho namnye oya kubawo engezi ngam” (UYohane 14:6).Indlala oyivayo yindlala yomoya, kwaye unokuhluthiswa kuphela nguYesu. UYesu kuphela komntu onokususa ubumnyama. UYesu ulisango eliya kubomi obukholisayo. UYesu usisihlobo kwaye ungumalusi okudala efunana nawe. UYesu ububomi—kobu bomi nakobuzayo. UYesu uyindlela yosindiso!Unobangela wokuziva ulambile, imbangi yokuba ngathi ulahleke ebumnyameni, imbangi yokuba ungayifumani intsingiselo yobomi, yeyokuba uzahlulile kuThixo. IBhayibhile iyasixelela ukuba sonke sonile, into ethi sizohlulile kuThixo (INtsumayelo 7:20; KwabaseRoma 3:23). Ubuze obuvayo entliziyweni yakho kungokuba uThixo akekho ebomini bakho. Sadalwa ukuba sibenonxibelelwano noThixo. Ngenxa yezono zethu, silohlule unxibelelwano. Ede ixhalise yeyoba izono zethu zizakusenza sohlukane noThixo nako konke okungunaphakade ebomini nakobuzayo (KwabaseRoma 6:23; UYohane 3:36).Ingasonjululwa njani lengxaki? UYesu sisisombululo! UYesu wazithathela kuye izono zethu (KwabaseKorinte besibini 5:21). UYesu wafa endaweni yethu (KwabaseRoma 5:8), wathabatha isohlwayo sethu. Emva kweentsuku ezintathu, uYesu wavuka ekufeni, waluqinisekisa uloyiso lwakhe ekufeni nasezonweni (KwabaseRoma 6:4-5). Kwakutheni ukuze enze lontot? UYesu wawuphendula loo mbuzo ngokwakhe: “Akukho namnye unalo uthando olungaphezu kolu, lokuba ubomi bakhe abuncamele izihlobo zakhe (Yohane 15:13). UYesu wafa ukwenzela siphile. Ukuba sibeka ukholo lwethu kuYesu, sithemba ukuba ukufa kwakhe kwabayintlawulo yezono zethu, zonke izono zethu zixolelwe kwaye zihlanjiwe. Ukulamba kwemiphefumo yethu kuzakwaneliswa. Izibane zakukhanyiswa. Sizakufikelela ebomini obanelisayo. Sizakumazi owona mhlobo wethu kunye nomalusi olungileyo. Sizakuyazi ukuba sizakuba nobomi emva kokufa—ubomi bovuko obungunaphakade noYesu emazulwini!“Kuba wenjenje uThixo ukulithanda kwakhe ihlabathi ude wancama uNyana wakhe ekuphela kwamzeleyo, ukuze bonke abakholwa kuye bangatshabalali, koko babeomi obungunaphakade” (UYohane 3:16).Sele usenzile isigqibo ngoKristu ngenxa yoku okufunde apha? Ukuba kunjalo, nceda ucofe kwiqhosha elingezantsi elithi “Ndiyamamkela uKristu namhlanje”."},{"question":"ఇచ్చిన పదానికి పర్యాయ పదాలని ఇవ్వండి: పావురము","answer":"కపోతము, పావురాయి, పారావతము"},{"question":"请给以下的文言文它的译文：(唐) 德宗问陆贽以当今切务。贽以乡日致乱，由上下之情不通，劝上接下从谏，乃上疏，其略曰：“臣谓当今急务，在于审察群情，若群情之所甚欲者，陛下先行之；所甚恶者，陛下先去之。欲恶与天下同而天下不归者，自古及今，未之有也。未理乱之本，系于人心，况乎当变故动摇之时，在危疑向背之际，人之所归则植，人之所在则倾，陛下安可不审察群情，同其欲恶，使亿兆归趣，以靖邦家乎！此诚当今之所急也。”","answer":"德宗向陆贽询问当今最为急切的事务。陆贽认为，往日导致变乱，是由于上下之情不相通。劝说德宗接触下情，听从谏诤。于是他进上章疏，大略是说：“我认为当今最为急切的事务，在于详细察明众人的心志，如果是众人非常喜欢的，那么陛下先去施行它；如果是众人非常憎恶的，那么陛下先去除掉它。陛下所喜欢和憎恶的与天下人相同，而天下人不肯归向陛下的事情，从古到今，都是没有的。一般说来，治与乱的根本，与人心密切相关，何况正当变故发生、人心动摇时，处于危险疑虑、人心向背的关头！人心归向，就会万事振兴；人心离异，就会万事倾危。陛下怎么能不审察众人的心志，与他们同好同恶，使民众向往归附，以安定国家呢！这一点就是当前所最为急切的啊。”"},{"question":"අධි ජවය සහිත විදුලි කෝෂ සදහා ලංකාවේ සම්මත වර්ණය කුමක්ද?","answer":"අධි ජවය සහිත විදුලි කෝෂ සදහා ලංකාවේ සම්මත වර්ණය කළු වර්ණයයි."},{"question":"नेपालका प्रमुख हिमाल चुचुराहरूबारे छलफल गर्नुहोस्।","answer":"नेपालमा सगरमाथा, कञ्चनजङ्घा र ल्होत्से लगायतका धेरै प्रमुख हिमाल चुचुराहरू छन्।"},{"question":"අභ්‍යවකාශයට ගිය පළමු කාන්තාව කවුද?","answer":"අභ්‍යවකාශයට ගිය පළමු කාන්තාව වන්නේ වැලන්ටිනා ටෙරෙෂ්කෝවා මහත්මිය."},{"question":"ਮੁੰਬਈ, 14 ਮਾਰਚਮੁੰਬਈ ਇੰਡੀਅਨਜ਼ ਵਿਰੁੱਧ ਆਈ.ਪੀ.ਐਲ. ਦਾ ਸਭ ਤੋਂ ਤੇਜ਼ ਸੈਂਕੜਾ ਜੜਨ ਵਾਲੇ ਯੂਸਫ ਪਠਾਨ ਨੇ ਆਪਣੀ ਇਸ ਪਾਰੀ ਨੂੰ ਵਿਸ਼ੇਸ਼ ਕਰਾਰ ਦਿੱਤਾ ਹੈ ਅਤੇ ਕਿਹਾ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਉਹ ਭਵਿੱਖ ਵਿਚ ਵੀ ਅਜਿਹੀਆਂ ਪਾਰੀਆਂ ਖੇਡਣੀਆਂ ਚਾਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ। ਪਠਾਨ ਨੇ ਅੱਜ ਪੱਤਰਕਾਰਾਂ ਨਾਲ ਗੱਲਬਾਤ ਕਰਦਿਆਂ ਕਿਹਾ, ”ਇਹ ਪਾਰੀ ਇਸ ਲਈ ਵਿਸ਼ੇਸ਼ ਸੀ ਕਿਉਂਕਿ ਇਹ ਮੇਰਾ ਪਹਿਲਾ ਸੈਂਕੜਾ ਸੀ। ਮੈਂ ਅਜਿਹੀਆਂ ਹੋਰ ਪਾਰੀਆਂ ਖੇਡਣਾ ਚਾਹੁੰਦਾ  ਹਾਂ, ਜਿਸ ਨਾਲ ਜਦੋਂ ਮੈਂ ਸੰਨਿਆਸ ਲਵਾਂ ਤਾਂ ਮੇਰੇ ਕੋਲ ਅਜਿਹੀਆਂ ਪਾਰੀਆਂ ਦੀਆਂ ਡੀ.ਵੀ.ਡੀਜ਼ ਦਾ ਬੈਗ ਭਰਿਆ ਹੋਵੇ। ਉਸ ਨੇ ਕਿਹਾ, ”ਮੈਂ ਚੰਗਾ ਖੇਡ ਰਿਹਾ ਹਾਂ। ਮੈਂ ਘਰੇਲੂ ਕ੍ਰਿਕਟ ਵਿਚ ਚੰਗਾ ਪ੍ਰਦਰਸ਼ਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਹੈ। ਮੈਂ ਇਸ ਲੈਅ ਨੂੰ ਜਾਰੀ ਰੱਖਣਾ ਚਾਹੁੰਦਾ ਹਾਂ। ਮੈਂ ਆਪਣੀ ਟੀਮ ਲਈ ਵੱਧ ਤੋਂ ਵੱਧ ਮੈਚ ਜਿੱਤਣਾ ਚਾਹੁੰਦਾ ਹਾਂ।”ਯੂਸਫ ਦੀ 37 ਗੇਂਦਾਂ ਵਿਚ 100 ਦੌੜਾਂ ਦੀ ਪਾਰੀ ਦੇ ਬਾਵਜੂਦ ਰਾਜਸਥਾਨ ਰਾਇਲਜ਼ ਨੂੰ ਚਾਰ ਦੌੜਾਂ ਦੀ ਹਾਰ ਝੱਲਣੀ ਪਈ। ਉਸ ਨੇ ਕਿਹਾ ਕਿ ਉਹ ਇਸ ਹਮਲਾਵਰ ਅੰਦਾਜ਼ ਨੂੰ ਜਾਰੀ ਰੱਖੇਗਾ। ਉਹ ਇਸ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਹੀ ਖੇਡਣਾ ਚਾਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ। ਇਸ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਖੇਡ ਕੇ ਹੀ ਉਹ ਕਾਮਯਾਬ ਹੋਇਆ ਹੈ। ਭਾਵੇਂ ਕਿ ਇਸ ਵਿਚ ਸੁਧਾਰ ਦੀ ਗੁੰਜਾਇਸ਼ ਹੈ, ਪਰ ਉਹ ਆਪਣੀ ਕ੍ਰਿਕਟ ਇਸੇ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਹੀ ਖੇਡਣੀ ਚਾਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ। ਪਠਾਨ ਨੇ ਕਿਹਾ ਕਿ ਚੰਗੇ ਗੇਂਦਬਾਜ਼ੀ ਹਮਲੇ ਵਿਰੁੱਧ ਇਸ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਦੀ ਪਾਰੀ ਖੇਡ ਕੇ ਉਸ ਦਾ ਆਤਮ-ਵਿਸ਼ਵਾਸ ਵਧਿਆ ਹੈ। ਉਸ ਨੇ ਕਿਹਾ ਕਿ ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਖੁਦ ਦੇ ਆਊਟ ਹੋਣ ਦੀ ਆਸ ਨਹੀਂ ਸੀ, ਪਰ ਫਿਰ ਵੀ ਵਿਸ਼ਵਾਸ ਸੀ ਕਿ ਟੀਮ ਟੀਚਾ ਹਾਸਲ ਕਰਨ ਦੀ ਸਮਰੱਥਾ ਰੱਖਦੀ ਹੈ। ਬੜੌਦਾ ਦੇ ਇਸ ਹਰਫਨਮੌਲਾ ਨੂੰ ਇਸ ਗੱਲ ਦੀ ਖੁਸ਼ੀ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਰਾਜਸਥਾਨ ਰਾਇਲਜ਼ ਦੇ ਕਪਤਾਨ ਸ਼ੇਨ ਵਾਰਨ ਤੇ ਸਚਿਨ ਤੇਂਦੁਲਕਰ ਨੇ ਉਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਦੀ ਪਾਰੀ ਦੀ ਤਾਰੀਫ ਕੀਤੀ ਹੈ। ਉਸ ਨੇ ਕਿਹਾ, ”ਮੇਰੇ ਪਰਤਣ ਬਾਅਦ ਵਾਰਨ ਨੇ ਕਿਹਾ ਕਿ ਉਸ ਨੇ ਆਪਣੇ 21 ਸਾਲ ਦੇ ਖੇਡ ਜੀਵਨ ਵਿਚ ਅਜਿਹੀ ਪਾਰੀ ਨਹੀਂ ਦੇਖੀ। ਸਚਿਨ ਨੇ ਮੈਨੂੰ ਵਧਾਈ ਦਿੱਤੀ ਅਤੇ ਇਸ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਖੇਡਣ ਦੀ ਤਾਕੀਦ ਕੀਤੀ। ਇਹ ਪੁੱਛਣ ‘ਤੇ ਕਿ ਉਸ ਨੇ ਇਸ ਪਾਰੀ ਦਾ ਜਸ਼ਨ ਕਿਵੇਂ ਮਨਾਇਆ ਤਾਂ ਉਸ ਨੇ ਕਿਹਾ ਕਿ ਇਹ ਅਜਿਹੀ ਪਾਰੀ ਸੀ ਜਿਸ ਨੂੰ ਕੋਈ ਖਿਡਾਰੀ ਕਦੇ-ਕਦੇ ਖੇਡਦਾ ਹੈ। ਉਂਜ ਇਸ ਪਾਰੀ ਲਈ ਉਸ ਨੇ ਅੱਲਾ ਦਾ ਧੰਨਵਾਦ ਕੀਤਾ ਤੇ ਬਾਅਦ ਵਿਚ ਨਮਾਜ਼ ਅਦਾ ਕੀਤੀ। ਉਸ ਨੇ ਆਪਣੇ ਪਰਿਵਾਰਕ ਮੈਂਬਰਾਂ ਨਾਲ ਗੱਲਬਾਤ ਕੀਤੀ। ਇਸ ਤੋਂ ਬਾਅਦ ਉਸ ਨੇ ਆਪਣੇ ਸਾਥੀ ਖਿਡਾਰੀਆਂ ਨਾਲ ਛੋਟਾ ਜਿਹਾ ਜਸ਼ਨ ਮਨਾਇਆ।ਯੂਸਫ਼ ਪਠਾਨ ਕਿਸ ਆਈਪੀਐਲ ਟੀਮ ਦਾ ਖਿਡਾਰੀ ਹੈ?","answer":"ਯੂਸਫ਼ ਪਠਾਨ ਰਾਜਸਥਾਨ ਰਾਇਲ ਆਈਪੀਐਲ ਟੀਮ ਦਾ ਖਿਡਾਰੀ ਹੈ।"},{"question":"Ayat 1: Ia terletak di selatan Sungai Solomon, antara Minneapolis dan Salt Creek. Ayat 2: Ia terletak di selatan Sungai Solomon, antara Salt Creek dan Minneapolis. Soalan: Adakah ayat 1 dan ayat 2 menyatakan makna yang sama?","answer":"Ya."},{"question":"काठमाडौं उपत्यकाका मध्ययुगीन राज्यहरूले छिमेकी क्षेत्रहरूसँग कसरी कूटनीतिक सम्बन्ध राखे?","answer":"काठमाडौं उपत्यकाका मध्यकालीन राज्यहरूले व्यापार र गठबन्धनको माध्यमबाट छिमेकी क्षेत्रहरूसँग कूटनीतिक सम्बन्धमा संलग्न थिए। यस कूटनीतिक गतिविधिले यस क्षेत्रको सांस्कृतिक आदानप्रदान र आर्थिक समृद्धिमा योगदान पुर्‍यायो।"},{"question":"问题：三星公司何时开始涉足电子产品领域？","answer":"答案：三星公司在1960年代开始涉足电子产品领域。"},{"question":"What positive role does the Sri Lankan Elephant play as a symbol in the country's cultural and religious traditions?","answer":"The Sri Lankan Elephant holds immense positive symbolism in the country's cultural and religious traditions. Considered a symbol of prosperity, wisdom, and power, elephants are revered in religious processions and festivals. The presence of elephants in cultural events showcases the nation's commitment to wildlife conservation and the preservation of this majestic species, contributing to both cultural heritage and environmental awareness."},{"question":"එකොළොස යන්නෙන් කුමන ඉලක්කමක් හැදින්වේද?","answer":" එකොළොස = 11"},{"question":"Amfice unina. Babingelelane.'Kanti lo mfelokazi wakho usebenzaphi?''Kade umbona yini?''Ngimbonela ukwenzani, ngimfunani nje?''Ngifuna ukwazi ukuthi usebenza msebenzi muni. Ngeke uthi unguthisha ushadenomuntu osebenza emajalidini.''Akasebenzi khona ejalidini?''Usebenza kuphi pho?''Sengathi usebenza efemini ethile.''Kufanele ngabe wambuza phela. Ngeke sivume thina ushade nomuntu ongafundile,ufunde kangaka.'1. Le ndaba yenzeka esikhathini samanje. Bhala amaphuzu AMATHATHUukusekela lesi sitatimende.","answer":"Amaphuzu AMATHATHU kwalandelayo:• Ukwanda kwezidakamizwa. • Abelungu sebekwazi ukuya ezindaweni zabantu ngokukhululeka. • Ukwanda kwemijondolo. • Ukuthandana kwabantu bobulili obufanayo. • ULindiwe ukwazi ukuzovakasha kubo kamfana athandana naye. • ULindiwe wathi uzoyolala nomama kaBhekani. "},{"question":"Parametric Methods","answer":"Parametric methods involve a two-step model-based approach.1. First, we make an assumption about the functional form, or shape, of f. For example, one very simple assumption is that f is linear in X: f(X) = β0 + β1X1 + β2X2 + ... + βpXp.This is a linear model. Once we have assumed that f is linear, the problem of estimating f is greatly simplified. Instead of having to estimate an entirely arbitrary p-dimensional function f(X), one only needs to estimate the p + 1 coefficients β0, β1,...,βp.2. After a model has been selected, we need a procedure that uses the training data to fit or train the model. In the case of the linear model fit train, we need to estimate the parameters β0, β1,...,βp. That is, we want to find values of these parameters such that Y ≈ β0 + β1X1 + β2X2 + ... + βpXp. The most common approach to fitting the model is referred to as (ordinary) least squares. "},{"question":"y = x + 2 రేఖా చిత్రం X – అక్షాన్ని A వద్ద, y = x – 2 రేఖా చిత్రం B వద్ద ఖండించినచో A, B బిందువుల మధ్య దూరంను కనుగొనుము.","answer":"y = x + 2, X – అక్షాన్ని ఖండించే బిందువు A = (-2, 0) y = x – 2,X – అక్షాన్ని ఖండించే బిందువు B = (2, 0)(-2, 0), (2, 0) బిందువుల మధ్య దూరం= |x2 – x1| = 4"},{"question":"In postmodern art theory, how does it challenge the traditional interpretation and criticism of art, and what effect does it have on the creative process of today's artists?","answer":"Postmodern art challenges the traditional interpretation of art by accepting multiple meanings and different perspectives. This transforms the creative process of artists, overcoming aesthetic boundaries and renewing medium, form and content."},{"question":"Firy ny isan'ny riran'ny vola ariary folo?\\ta- 6\\tb- 9\\td- 7\\te- 8","answer":"Valiny: d.Miisa fito ny isan'ny riran'ny vola ariary folo ariary."},{"question":"لدي هذا السؤال ما هي عاصمة المغرب ؟ ، أجب عليه بطريقة مبسطة.","answer":"الرِّبَاطُ (بالأمازيغية: ⵔⴱⴰⵟ) هي العاصمة الإدارية الرسمية للمملكة المغربية. وجماعة ذات طابع حضري تقع بجهة الرباط سلا القنيطرة. يبلغ عدد سكانها 572 717 نسمة حسب إحصاء 2014."},{"question":"*كم دولة تشترك بحدودها مع السودان ؟","answer":"9 دول"},{"question":"أنت بتدرس أي يا ابني؟","answer":"هندسة يا عمو"},{"question":"Inona no vokatry ny loto?","answer":"Ny vokatry ny loto dia aretina."},{"question":"Firy no karazana baobab tsy hita raha tsy eto Madagasikara ?","answer":"Enina amin’ireo sivy maneran-tany no karazana baobab tsy hita raha tsy eto Madagasikara ihany."},{"question":"aiza avy no toerana mety hanaovana ny joro?","answer":"miovaova, arakarak ny anton-javatra ny toerana anaovana ny joro: mety ho any an-tanàna, mety ho eo anoloan'ny toerana anorenan-javatra, mety ho eny anoloan'ny fasana."},{"question":"अंधविश्वास | अंधश्रद्धा","answer":"आज चे युग हे सर्वात आधुनिक युग आहे, हे तर आपण कितीक वेळा ऐकले असेल, आज बघावे त्या गोष्टीचे तंत्रज्ञान आहे. प्रतेक गोष्ट जेव्हा घडते किंव्हा घडवली जाते त्या मागे एक वैज्ञानिक कारण असते हे आपल्यांना शाळेत शिकवले जाते.पण सकाळी जेव्हा वृत्तांत पत्र वाचायला घेतला कि एक न एक बातमी असतेच अंधविश्वासा मुळे हे झाले ते झाले. ह्या अंधविश्वासाच्या नादात कितेक लोक रोज मरण पावतात. मला माहित नाही का आणि कसे पण जेव्हा टी.वी वर बातम्या लागतात आणि जेव्हा काही अंधविश्वासा बदल दाखवतात तेव्हा मोठी शिकलेली माणसे ह्या अंधविश्वासाला बळी पडतात माहित नाही का.पण मला तर टी.वी वर जेव्हा अंधविश्वास पसरव नारे डोंगी दाखवले कि त्यांचे कृत्य बगूनच हसायला येते कोणी कुंकू काय उडवते राख काय फेकतात, झाडू ने झपाटतात आणि वेड्या सारखे ओरडतात. माझे तर हे सगळे बगून हसून-हसून पोट दुखते.आपल्या घरचे आपल्यांना नेहमी चांगल्या गोष्टी सांगतात पण माहित नाही का ? ह्या अंधविश्वासाच्या गोष्टी आपल्या घरा मधूनच सुरु होतात घरी काही आणल कि नजर काढतात, रस्त्यावर मांजर गेली तर रस्ता अलोंडून जात नाही, कावला घरा वरून गेला आणि ओरडला कि घरी कोणी तर येणार असे अंधविश्वास आपण ऐकले असतील आणि नकळत आपण ते मानतो.एक गोष्ट मी ऐकली होती ती म्हणजे एका गाव मदे लग्न होत आणि साहजिक आहे जिथे लग्न असणार त्या घरा मदे लोकांचा गोंधळ असतो, ज्या घरा मदे लग्न होते त्यांनी एक मांजर पाळली होती. जेव्हा ब्राम्हण पूजा करत असताना ती मांजर तिथे फिरत होती, त्या मांजरीने तिथे असलेल्या वस्तूचे काही नुकसान करू नये म्हणून त्या ब्राम्हणणे मांजरीला बांधायला सांगितले. मग काय लोकांनी हे पाहिले आणि मांजरीला का बांधले हे कारण न समजता त्यांनी आपल्या मनात घेतले कि लगनाच्या वेळेस मांजरीला बांधणे गरजेचे असते आणि आपण सुद्धा अश्या गेर समजुतीची शिकार बनतो आणि अंधविश्वासाला बळी पडतो.काही माणसे अगदी साधी भोळी असतात आणि ह्याचा फयदा डोंगी पाखंडी बाबा लोक घेतात आणि त्याच लोकांना ह्याच अंधविश्वासाच्या सहायाने घाबरवतात आणि त्यांना काही हि करून फसवतात आणि भोले-भाबडे लोक त्यांच्या डोंग चाळीत सापडतात.प्रत्येक गोष्ट हि खोटी नसते, आणि प्रत्येक गोष्ट खरी हि नसते. म्हणूनच योग गोष्टींवर विश्वास दाखवा आणि अंधविश्वास पाळू हि नका आणि कोणाला पाळू हि देऊ नका."},{"question":"Ai là nhạc sĩ, ca sĩ đầu tiên được trao Nobel Văn học?a. Bob Dylanb. John Lennonc. Elton John","answer":"đáp án là Bob DylanNhạc sĩ, ca sĩ Bob Dylan được Viện Hàn lâm Thụy Điển xướng tên trao giải thưởng Nobel Văn học 2016 vì đã \\"tạo ra những biểu đạt thi ca mới bên trong truyền thống âm nhạc vĩ đại của Mỹ\\". Giải Nobel Văn học lần đầu được trao một nhạc sĩ, nhạc sĩ khiến nhiều người ngạc nhiên, tranh cãi."},{"question":"Cé hé David Trezeguet? ","answer":"Iar-imreoir sacair Francach is é David Sergio Trezeguet. Rugadh ar an 15 Deireadh Fómhair 1977 i Rouen, An Fhrainc, é.Scóráíl sé aon chúl amháin ag Corn FIFA an Domhain 1998. "},{"question":"Dê um exemplo de uma pergunta trivia da categoria: videogames","answer":"Qual é o nome do principal policial de Resident Evil 4? Leon S. Kennedy"},{"question":"文章からキーワードを選び、その解釈を述べなさい。 8月15日、太平洋戦争が終わってから78年になりました。東京の日本武道館では、戦争で亡くなった約310万人のために祈る式がありました。台風のため、出席した人は予定より少ない1855人でした。式では、昼12時から1分、みんなで静かに祈りました。天皇陛下は「過去のことを深く反省して、戦争がまた起こらないことを強く願います。国民のみなさんと一緒に、戦争で亡くなった人のことを思って祈ります。世界の平和と日本の発展を祈ります」と話しました。戦争が終わってから78年が過ぎて、亡くなった人の家族で式に出席した人の75%以上が70歳以上になりました。式には、曽祖父が戦争で亡くなった7歳の小学生も出席しました。小学生は「戦争は人の命だけではなくて、人の心も奪います。悲しくなるので絶対にしてほしくないです。戦争がない日がずっと続いてほしいです」と話していました。","answer":"この文章に含まれるキーワードとその解釈は以下です。- 太平洋戦争: 1）第二次世界大戦のうち、1941年から1945年まで、アジア・太平洋地域で行われた戦争。日本と、アメリカ・イギリスなどの国々との戦いで、日本が敗れて終わった。- 約: 1）ちかう。取り決める。2）縮める。省く。簡単にする。3）おおよそ。ほぼ。だいたい。- 天皇: 1）日本国憲法によって、日本の国の象徴としてあおがれている人。- 陛下: 1）天皇や皇后などを敬って呼ぶ言葉。- 過去: 1）過ぎ去った時。今よりも前。昔。- 反省: 1）自分の行いをふり返って、よく考えてみること。- 起こら: 1）始まる。2）生じる。起きる。- 願い: 1）（神や仏や他の人に）こうしてほしいと思う。たのむ。望む。- 国民: 1）その国の国籍を持つ人々。- 平和: 1）おだやかで、無事なこと。2）戦争がなく、世の中が無事に治まっていること。- 発展: 1）栄えていくこと。勢いが、のび広がること。2）次の段階に進むこと。- 曽祖父: 1）その人の父や母の祖父。ひいおじいさん。- 小学生: 1）小学校に通っている子ども。- 命: 1）生き物が生きているもとになる力。生命。2）生きている間。3）いちばん大切なもの。- 奪い: 1）無理やりに取り上げる。2）心を引きつける。- 絶対: 1）他に比べるものがないこと。2）まちがいなく。必ず。3）けっして。とうてい。"},{"question":"महाराष्ट्राने भारताचा किती टक्के भाग व्यापलेला आहे?","answer":"९.७ टक्के"},{"question":"Diniho ity fanambarana manaraka ity: “Manao tsinontsinona ireo mpitandro filaminana ireo aho; mpidoroka avokoa. Misy resaka fankahalana ve ilay fanambarana?","answer":"Eny, kabary fankahalana ity fanambarana ity satria tsy ara-drariny no iantsoana ireo mpitandro filaminana ho mpidoroka avokoa. "},{"question":"Qual animal dorme de cabeça para baixo?","answer":"O morcego."},{"question":"Joxeel péeteg waat yi ci kàddu gii: Jële na'ñ lu ëpp ñent fukk (40) i ndaw ca wàrab ya'ñ nekkoon yóbbu léen feneen.","answer":"Waat yi nekk ci kàddu gii di \\"Jële na'ñ lu ëpp ñent fukk (40) i ndaw ca wàrab ya'ñ nekkoon yóbbu léen feneen.\\" ak séen i péete ñoo di:Jële: VERBna: AUX'ñ: PRONlu: PRONëpp: ADJñent: NUMfukk: NUM(: PUNCT40: NUM): PUNCTi: ADPndaw: NOUNca: ADPwàrab: NOUNya: PRON'ñ: PRONnekkoon: VERByóbbu: VERBléen: PRONfeneen: ADV.: PUNCT"},{"question":"గుడ్లకోశ పరాన్నజీవనం గురించి సోదాహరణగా వివరించండి.","answer":"కొన్ని పక్షులు ప్రత్యేకమైన పరాన్నజీవనానికి మంచి ఉదాహరణలుగా ఉంటాయి. పరాన్న జీవ పక్షి వాటి గుడ్లను అతిథేయి పక్షి గూటిలో ఉంచి అతిథేయిచే గుడ్లను పొదిగిస్తాయి. పరిణామ క్రమంలో పరాన్నజీవ పక్షిగుడ్లు, అతిథేయి జీవి గుడ్లు పరిమాణం, వర్ణం ఒకే విధంగా ఉండేటట్లు అభివృద్ధి చెందటం వల్ల, పరాన్నజీవ పక్షి గుడ్లను అతిథేయి గుర్తు పట్టలేకపోవడం వల్ల, గుడ్లు గూటి నుండి వెలికితీయబడకుండా పొదగబడతాయి.ఉదా : కోయిల, కాకి పక్షుల కదలికలను మనం దగ్గర పరిసరాలనుండి పరిశీలిస్తే సంపర్క కాలంలో గర్భకోశ లేదా గుడ్లకోశ పరాన్నజీవ చర్యలను గమనించవచ్చును."},{"question":"Nire familiarekin oporretan joateko planak egin nuen, baina oraindik ez dakigu zein herri edo hiri bisitatuko dugun. Euskal Herriko zein leku gomendatuko zenuke oporretarako, eta zergatik?","answer":"Donostia gomendatuko nuke, hondartza ederrak eta pintxo goxoak direlako! Bestalde, Gaztelugatxe ere aparta da, itsasoarekin eta bere historia naturalarekin harreman berezia duen leku bat delako."},{"question":"Akụkọ ifo a na-akọ banyere otu nwa agbọghọ mara mma nke zutere nnukwu ihe ndabara n'ihi nnupụisi ya na mkpebi ya inupụrụ ndị mụrụ ya isi.N'ime oge mgbe ndị mmụọ ọjọọ na ndị mmụọ na-agbagharị n'ime obodo, nwa agbọghọ ahụ a na-akpọ \\"obaledo\\" gwara nne na nna ya ntụziaka tupu ha abanye na njem ha, ka ha nọrọ n'ime ụlọ ha na-eri naanị ji na eju mgbe agụụ na-agụ ya. Ndị nne na nna rịọrọ ya ka o buru ụzọ rie ji ahụ n'ihu eju, n'ihi na ejula ga-emecha menyụọ ọkụ ahụ. N'ụzọ dị mwute, nwa agbọghọ ahụ, n'ịbụ onye anyaukwu na agụụ anụ siri ike, buru ụzọ rie eju ahụ, ọkụ wee pụọ. N'ịbụ onye agụụ ka nọ na-agụ, ọ pụrụ n'ụlọ ya, n'enupụrụ ndị mụrụ ya isi, iji nweta osisi n'aka ndị agbata obi. Ka ọ na-aga, ọ zutere otu mmụọ ọjọọ nke na-ezu ohi ịma mma ya ma hapụ ya ihe jọrọ njọ nke ya.","answer":"Isiokwu nke paragraf gara aga bụ Akụkọ ifo ana akpụọ Obaledo ."},{"question":"Suaal: Foomalka laga helo degaanka da'yarada waa sidee?","answer":"Jawaab: Foomalka laga helo degaanka da'yarada waa A = πr²."},{"question":"கீழே கொடுக்கப்பட்டுள்ள பொருட்களைவைத்து ரஷ்யன் சாலட் செய்வது எப்படி?தேவையான பொருட்கள்:3 உருளைக்கிழங்கு2 கேரட்¾ அன்னாச்சி பழம்½ கப் பீன்ஸ்½ கப் பச்சை பட்டாணி½ மேஜைக்கரண்டி கருப்பு மிளகு தூள்1 கப் மயோனிஸ்1 துண்டு பிரக்கோலி1 பனிப்பாறை கீரை இதழ்தேவையான அளவு உப்பு","answer":"செய்முறை:1. முதலில் உருளைக்கிழங்கு, கேரட், மற்றும் அன்னாச்சி பழத்தை சதுர வடிவில் நறுக்கி, பீன்ஸ் மற்றும் பச்சை பட்டாணியை தயார் செய்து ஒரு தட்டில் வைத்து கொள்ளவும்.2. அடுத்து ஒரு பாத்திரத்தை மிதமான சூட்டில் அடுப்பில் வைத்து அதில் நாம் நறுக்கி வைத்திருக்கும் கேரட்டை வேக வைப்பதற்கு தேவையான அளவு தண்ணீர் ஊற்றி அதை சுட வைக்கவும்.3. தண்ணீர் சுட்ட பின் அதில் நாம் நறுக்கி வைத்திருக்கும் கேரட்டை போட்டு அதை சுமார் 2 நிமிடம் வரை வேக விடவும்.4. 2 நிமிடத்திற்கு பிறகு அதை ஒரு கரண்டியின் மூலம் எடுத்து ஒரு தட்டில் வைத்து கொள்ளவும்.5. பின்பு அதே பாத்திரத்தில் நாம் நறுக்கி வைத்திருக்கும் பீன்ஸ்ஸை போட்டு அதை சுமார் 2 நிமிடம் வரை வேக விடவும்.6. 2 நிமிடத்திற்கு பிறகு பீன்ஸ்ஸை ஒரு கரண்டியின் மூலம் எடுத்து அதை ஒரு தட்டில் வைத்து கொள்ளவும்.7. பின்பு அதே பாத்திரத்தில் நாம் உரித்து வைத்திருக்கும் பச்சை பட்டாணியை போட்டு அதை சுமார் 3 நிமிடம் வரை வேக விடவும்.8. 3 நிமிடத்திற்கு பிறகு பச்சை பட்டாணியை ஒரு கரண்டியின் மூலம் எடுத்து அதை ஒரு தட்டில் வைத்து கொள்ளவும்.9. பின்பு அதே பாத்திரத்தில் நாம் நறுக்கி வைத்திருக்கும் உருளைக்கிழங்கை போட்டு அதை சுமார் 3 நிமிடம் வரை வேக விடவும்.10. 3 நிமிடத்திற்கு பிறகு அடுப்பை அணைத்து விட்டு உருளைக்கிழங்கை ஒரு கரண்டியின் மூலம் எடுத்து அதை ஒரு தட்டில் வைத்து கொள்ளவும்.11. இப்பொழுது ஒரு கிண்ணத்தை எடுத்து அதில் நாம் வேக வைத்து எடுத்து வைத்திருக்கும் காய்கறிகள் அனைத்தையும் ஒன்றாக போட்டு அதனுடன் நாம் நறுக்கி வைத்திருக்கும் அன்னாச்சி பழத்தையும் போட்டு அதை நன்கு கலந்து விடவும்.12. பின்னர் அந்த கலவையில் சிறிதளவு உப்பு, கருப்பு மிளகு தூள், மற்றும் ஒரு கப் அளவு மயோனிஸ்ஸை சேர்த்து அதை நன்கு கலந்து விடவும்.13. பிறகு ஒரு கிண்ணத்தை எடுத்து அதில் ஒரு பனிப்பாறை கீரை இதனை வைத்து அதன் மேலே நாம் செய்து வைத்திருக்கும் கலவையை வைத்து அதன் மேலே ஒரு பிரக்கோலியை வைத்து அதை ஜில்லென்று பரிமாறவும்.14. இப்பொழுது உங்கள் அருமையான மற்றும் சில்லென்று இருக்கும் ரஷ்யன் சாலட் தயார். இதை கட்டாயம் உங்கள் வீட்டில் செய்து பார்த்து உங்கள் குடும்பத்தாருடன் சேர்ந்து சுவைத்து மகிழுங்கள்."},{"question":"Болот Шамшиев ким болгон?","answer":"Болот Шамшиев(1941-2019) Кыргызстанык белгилүү актёр, кинорежиссёр, ошондой ценарист болгон.\\"Караш-караш окуясы\\", \\"Ысык-Көлдүн кызгалдактары\\", \\"Асма көпүрө\\", \\"Ак кеме\\", \\"Бөрү зындан\\" жана башка тасмаларды тарткан."},{"question":"De categoria é a pergunta a seguir: Para qual prêmio Grammy Post Malone foi indicado em 2020, mas não ganhou?","answer":"A pergunta provavelmente pertence a categoria Música"},{"question":"“స్త్రీలపై జరుగుతున్న అత్యాచారాల్ని ఖండిస్తూ వారిని గౌరవించాలని తెలుపుతూ” ఒక కరపత్రం తయారుచేయండి.","answer":"స్త్రీలను గౌరవిద్దాంసోదర సోదరీ మణులారా !స్త్రీ తల్లిగా, చెల్లిగా, భార్యగా కుటుంబంలో పోషించే పాత్ర కదా ! ఆమె నిస్వార్థంగా సేవచేస్తూ మమతానుబంధాల్ని పంచుతూ జీవిస్తుంది.అందుకే “యత్ర నార్యస్తు పూజ్యంతే, తత్సరమంతే దేవతాః” – అని ఆర్యోక్తి. అనగా ఎక్కడ స్త్రీలు పూజింపబడుతారో అక్కడ దేవతలు ఆనందిస్తారని స్త్రీ యొక్క గొప్పతనాన్ని ఆర్యులు గొప్పగా చెప్పారు.ప్రాచీనకాలం నుంచి విజ్ఞానరంగంలో స్త్రీలు, పురుషునితో పోటీపడుతూనే ఉన్నారు. నేడు స్త్రీలు అన్నిరంగాల్లో రాణిస్తున్నారు. చదువుల్లో పురుషునికంటే ముందంజ వేస్తున్నారు. సమాజంలో క్రియాశీలమైన స్త్రీలపై అత్యాచారాలు జరగడం సిగ్గుచేటు, స్త్రీని గౌరవించడం అనే మంచి సంప్రదాయం ఉన్న మనదేశానికి అవమానకరం.క్షణికమైన ఆవేశంతో స్త్రీలపై అత్యాచారాలు చేయడం వల్ల మన జాతి నిర్మాతలైన సోదరీమణుల ఆత్మగౌరవం దెబ్బ తింటుంది. విలువైన ప్రాణాలు పోతున్నాయి. జాతికి పరువుపోతుంది. కనుక స్త్రీలను గౌరవిద్దాం ! వారి ఆత్మగౌరవానికి ఆటంకం కలిగించకుండా పురుషునితో సమానంగా ఆదరిద్దాం ! మహాకవి చిలకమర్తి లక్ష్మీనరసింహం పంతులు “ముదితల్ నేర్వగలేని విద్య కలదే ముద్దార నేర్పించినన్” అని స్త్రీ యొక్క గొప్పతనాన్ని ఏనాడో విశ్లేషించి చెప్పాడు. స్త్రీల కున్న స్వేచ్ఛను రక్షించుదాం ! వారి హక్కుల్ని కాపాడుదాం !తేది : X X X X,ఇట్లు,తెలంగాణ మహిళాసంఘం,సికింద్రాబాద్."},{"question":"چگونه قانون اتحادیه اروپا بالاتر از قوانین ملی دیده می شود؟ با توجه به سوال قبلی، متنی را بنویسید که شامل پاسخ باشد. این متن می‌تواند ۱ تا ۲۰ جمله باشد. متن:","answer":"از زمان تأسیس آن، قدرت اتحادیه اروپا در میان نظام های حقوقی ملی و جهانی در حال افزایش بوده است. این به این معنی است که هم دادگاه اروپا و هم دادگاه های عالی ملی باید اصول را برای حل تعارض قوانین بین سیستم های مختلف توسعه دهند. در درون اتحادیه اروپا، نظر دادگاه دادگستری این است که اگر قانون اتحادیه اروپا با مقررات قانون ملی در تضاد باشد، پس قانون اتحادیه اروپا برتری دارد. در اولین پرونده بزرگ در سال ۱۹۶۴، کوستا علیه اینل، یک وکیل میلان و سهامدار سابق یک شرکت انرژی به نام آقای کوستا از پرداخت صورتحساب برق خود به اینل، به عنوان اعتراض به ملی سازی شرکت های انرژی ایتالیایی، خودداری کرد. او ادعا کرد که قانون ملی سازی ایتالیایی با معاهده رم در تضاد است و خواستار ارجاع به هر دو دادگاه قانون اساسی ایتالیا و دادگاه دادگستری بر اساس ماده ۲۶۷ پیمان اتحادیه اروپا شد. دادگاه قانون اساسی ایتالیا به این نتیجه رسید که چون قانون ملی شدن از سال ۱۹۶۲ بود و معاهده از سال ۱۹۵۸ به اجرا درآمده بود، کاستا هیچ ادعایی نداشت. در مقابل، دادگاه دادگستری اعلام کرد که در نهایت، معاهده رم به هیچ وجه مانع ملی سازی انرژی نمی شود، و در هر صورت بر اساس مقررات معاهده تنها کمیسیون می تواند ادعایی را مطرح کند، نه آقای کوستا. با این حال، در اصل، آقای کوستا حق داشت به این دلیل که معاهده با قانون ملی در تضاد است، و دادگاه وظیفه دارد که درخواست او را برای ارائه یک مراجعه در نظر بگیرد، اگر هیچ اعتراضی علیه تصمیم آن وجود نداشته باشد. دادگاه دادگستری، با تکرار دیدگاه خود در Van Gend en Loos، گفت که کشورهای عضو \\"اگرچه در حوزه های محدود، حقوق حاکمیت خود را محدود کرده اند و یک مجموعه قانون را برای شهروندان خود و برای خود به صورت \\"بر اساس متقابل\\" ایجاد کرده اند. قانون اتحادیه اروپا نمی تواند \\"به وسیله مقررات حقوقی داخلی، هر چند در چارچوب قرار گرفته باشد... بدون اینکه پایه حقوقی خود جامعه مورد سوال قرار گیرد\\". این بدان معنی بود که هر \\"عمل یکجانبه بعدی\\" از دولت عضو قابل اجرا نیست. "},{"question":"Hãy chọn đáp án đúng nhất cho câu hỏi sau:Kết quả của phép tính (– 15) : 5 là:A. 3B. 5 C. – 3D. – 5 ","answer":"Lời giảiTa có: (– 15) : 5 = – (15 : 5) = – 3.Chọn đáp án C. "},{"question":"Fale sobre o estilo de escrita único de Saramago.","answer":"O estilo distintivo de José Saramago, caracterizado por longas frases e diálogo sem pontuação, cria uma prosa fluida e distintamente reconhecível. Esse \\"fluxo de consciência\\" literário marca as suas obras, conferindo-lhes uma qualidade inovadora."},{"question":"Ноорузда арча түтөтүп айтылчу сөздү билесизби?","answer":" Умай Эне  аластоо жөрөлгөсүн кылат:Алас, алас, алас!Ар балээден калас.Жаңы жыл келди,Нооруз келди!Жер жаңырып, чөп чыкты,Желин жарылып, сүт чыкты!Жер бетине жапжашыл чөп чыкты.Оо, жараткан!Жакшылыгыңды аяба!Кампабызга дан толсун,Дасторконубузга нан толсун.Үлүшүбүзгө мал толсун.Аксакалдарыбыз акылман болсун,Байбичелерибиз мээрман болсун!Келин-кыздар ыймандуу болсун,Жигиттерибиз эр жүрөк баатыр болсун!Өлкөбүздө тынчтык болсун!Айдан аман,Жылдан эсен бололу!Алас, алас,"},{"question":"Noraran-dRadama I ny varotra andevo teto Madagasikara. Marina sa Diso?","answer":"Marina, Noraran-dRadama I ny varotra andevo teto Madagasikara."},{"question":"ファッションブランドの一つ、ハンティングワールドのロゴにデザインされている動物は何でしょう？","answer":"象"},{"question":"Vào một ngày mùa đông ở Sa Pa, nhiệt độ tại Cổng Trời là – 1 °C. Tuy nhiên, nhiệt độ lúc đó tại chợ Sa Pa lại cao hơn 2 °C so với nhiệt độ tại Cổng Trời.Viết phép tính và tính nhiệt độ tại chợ Sa Pa lúc đó. ","answer":"Lời giải:Nhiệt độ tại chợ Sa Pa là (– 1) + 2 (°C).Quan sát nhiệt kế ta thấy nhiệt độ tại chợ Sa Pa là 1°C. Vậy (– 1) + 2 = 1 (°C). "},{"question":"Oluwoo rọ awọn ọba lati ko Fulani to ti pẹ lọdọ wọn mọra, ki wọn si mu wọn bii ọmọ","answer":"Oluwoo ti ilu Iwo, Ọba Abdulrosheed Akanbi, ti sọ pe aisi itọju to peye ati amojuto lo fa a ti awọn Fulani darandaran lorileede Naijiria fi n huwa janduku, ti wọn si sọ ijinigbe di iṣẹ.Lasiko ti Oluwoo lọ sigberiko ti awọn Fulani naa tẹdo si, nibi ti wọn n pe ni Gaa-Fulani to wa ni Odo-Ọba, niluu Iwo, lo ti rọ gbogbo awọn Fulani ti wọn n gbe nigberiko yika ilu Iwo lati ko wa sinu ilu, ki wọn si ni ibaṣepọ pẹlu awọn araalu.O ṣalaye fun wọn pe iwa atijọ ni dida maaluu jẹ kaakiri, asiko si ti to fun awọn eeyan naa lati maa lo ọna igbalode fun bibọ awọn nnkan ọsin wọn.Ọba Akanbi ṣalaye pe oun ti ba Aarẹ Buhari atawọn adari kọọkan lorileede sọrọ pe ki wọn ran awọn Fulani darandaran diẹ lọ si oke-okun lati lọọ kọ bi wọn yoo ṣe maa bọ awọn ẹran wọn lọna igbalode.O ni “Ko si bi a ṣe le pa awọn kan ti sinu igbo, ka si maa reti iwa gidi latọdọ wọn. A fẹ ki ẹ maa bọ wa saarin ilu, ẹ maa gbe laarin awọn eeyan.‘Mo lọ si Aso Rock, mo si ba Aarẹ sọrọ nipa yin, mo sọ fun Aarẹ pe ki wọn ran diẹ lara yin lọ soke-okun lati lọọ kọ bi wọn ṣe n sin nnkan ọsin lọna igbalode. Bawo ni maaluu ti ẹ mu lọọ jẹ bii ogun maili yoo ṣe sanra? Oju kan naa lo yẹ ki awọn maaluu yin wa, ki wọn si maa jẹun nibẹ”Oluwoo tun rọ awọn Fulani naa lati gba awọn ọmọ wọn laaye lati kawe, o ni o ṣee ṣe ki eyi to ba kawe ninu wọn pa iṣẹ darandaran ti awọn obi wọn n ṣe ti.Bakan naa lo rọ awọn ori-ade kaakiri orileede yii lati ko awọn Fulani ti wọn ti pẹ lọdọ wọn mọra, ki wọn si mu wọn bii ọmọ ilu wọn.O waa ke si awọn Fulani ọhun lati fọwọsowọpọ fopin si wahala to n ṣelẹ kaakiri. O si gbadura pe ki Ọlọrun fọwọ tọ gbogbo awọn ti wọn n huwa janduku laaarin wọn."},{"question":"નીચેના ગુજરાતી ઉખાણાં નો જવાબ આપો:પાણીનું અબૂકલું ઢબૂકલું છું, પાણીમાં જ રહીને ફરું છું પાણીના તરંગોમાં નાચું છું, પાણીમાં જ તરવું મારૂ કામ છે","answer":"માછલી"},{"question":"Su'aal: Waa meeqo xarfaha afka Soomaaliga?","answer":"Jawaab: Xarfaha afka Soomaaliga waa 21 xaraf oo shiibane ah iyo 5 xaraf oo shaqal ah, taasi oo guud ahaan ka dhigeysa 26 xaraf."},{"question":"太陽は英語でサン、星はスター、では月はなんと言う？","answer":"ムーンです。"},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਮਾਝ ਮਹਲਾ ੫ ॥ਸਿਫਤਿ ਸਾਲਾਹਣੁ ਤੇਰਾ ਹੁਕਮੁ ਰਜਾਈ ॥ਸੋ ਗਿਆਨੁ ਧਿਆਨੁ ਜੋ ਤੁਧੁ ਭਾਈ ॥ਸੋਈ ਜਪੁ ਜੋ ਪ੍ਰਭ ਜੀਉ ਭਾਵੈ ਭਾਣੈ ਪੂਰ ਗਿਆਨਾ ਜੀਉ ॥੧॥ਅੰਮ੍ਰਿਤੁ ਨਾਮੁ ਤੇਰਾ ਸੋਈ ਗਾਵੈ ॥ ਜੋ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਤੇਰੈ ਮਨਿ ਭਾਵੈ ॥ਤੂੰ ਸੰਤਨ ਕਾ ਸੰਤ ਤੁਮਾਰੇ ਸੰਤ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਮਨੁ ਮਾਨਾ ਜੀਉ ॥੨॥ਤੂੰ ਸੰਤਨ ਕੀ ਕਰਹਿ ਪ੍ਰਤਿਪਾਲਾ ॥ਸੰਤ ਖੇਲਹਿ ਤੁਮ ਸੰਗਿ ਗੋਪਾਲਾ ॥ਅਪੁਨੇ ਸੰਤ ਤੁਧੁ ਖਰੇ ਪਿਆਰੇ ਤੂ ਸੰਤਨ ਕੇ ਪ੍ਰਾਨਾ ਜੀਉ ॥੩॥ਉਨ ਸੰਤਨ ਕੈ ਮੇਰਾ ਮਨੁ ਕੁਰਬਾਨੇ ॥ਜਿਨ ਤੂੰ ਜਾਤਾ ਜੋ ਤੁਧੁ ਮਨਿ ਭਾਨੇ ॥ਤਿਨ ਕੈ ਸੰਗਿ ਸਦਾ ਸੁਖੁ ਪਾਇਆ ਹਰਿ ਰਸ ਨਾਨਕ ਤ੍ਰਿਪਤਿ ਅਘਾਨਾ ਜੀਉ ॥੪॥੧੩॥੨੦॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 100 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਅਰਜਨ ਦੇਵ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਬਾਣੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਹਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"ਹੇ ਰਜ਼ਾ ਦੇ ਮਾਲਕ-ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ! ਤੇਰਾ ਹੁਕਮ (ਸਿਰ-ਮੱਥੇ ਉੱਤੇ ਮੰਨਣਾ) ਤੇਰੀ ਸਿਫ਼ਤਿ-ਸਾਲਾਹ ਹੀ ਹੈ ਜੋ ਤੈਨੂੰ ਚੰਗਾ ਲੱਗਦਾ ਹੈ (ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਭਲਾਈ ਜਾਨਣਾ) ਇਹੀ ਅਸਲ ਗਿਆਨ ਹੈ ਇਹੀ ਅਸਲ ਸਮਾਧੀ ਹੈ ।(ਹੇ ਭਾਈ !) ਜੋ ਕੁਝ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਜੀ ਨੂੰ ਭਾਉਂਦਾ ਹੈ (ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਪਰਵਾਨ ਕਰਨਾ ਹੀ) ਅਸਲ ਜਪ ਹੈ, ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੇ ਭਾਣੇ ਵਿਚ ਤੁਰਨਾ ਹੀ ਪੂਰਨ ਗਿਆਨ ਹੈ ।੧।ਹੇ ਮਾਲਕ-ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ! ਆਤਮਕ ਜੀਵਨ ਦੇਣ ਵਾਲਾ ਤੇਰਾ ਨਾਮ ਉਹੀ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਗਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ, ਜੇਹੜਾ ਤੇਰੇ ਮਨ ਵਿਚ (ਤੈਨੂੰ) ਪਿਆਰਾ ਲੱਗਦਾ ਹੈ ਹੇ ਸਾਹਿਬ ! ਤੂੰ ਹੀ ਸੰਤਾਂ ਦਾ (ਸਹਾਰਾ) ਹੈਂ, ਸੰਤ ਤੇਰੇ ਆਸਰੇ ਜੀਊੁਂਦੇ ਹਨ, ਤੇਰੇ ਸੰਤਾਂ ਦਾ ਮਨ ਸਦਾ ਤੇਰੇ (ਚਰਨਾਂ ਵਿਚ) ਜੁੜਿਆ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ ।੨।ਹੇ ਗੋਪਾਲ-ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ! ਹੇ ਸ੍ਰਿਸ਼ਟੀ ਦੇ ਪਾਲਣਹਾਰ ! ਤੂੰੰ ਆਪਣੇ ਸੰਤਾਂ ਦੀ ਸਦਾ ਰੱਖਿਆ ਕਰਦਾ ਹੈਂਤੇਰੇ ਚਰਨਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਜੁੜੇ ਰਹਿ ਕੇ ਸੰਤ ਆਤਮਕ ਆਨੰਦ ਮਾਣਦੇ ਹਨ  ਤੈਨੂੰ ਆਪਣੇ ਸੰਤ ਬਹੁਤ ਪਿਆਰੇ ਲੱਗਦੇ ਹਨ, ਤੂੰ ਸੰਤਾਂ ਦੀ ਜਿੰਦ-ਜਾਨ ਹੈਂ ।੩।ਮੇਰਾ ਮਨ ਤੇਰੇ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਸੰਤਾਂ ਤੋਂ ਸਦਾ ਸਦਕੇ ਹੈਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਨੇ ਤੈਨੂੰ ਪਛਾਣਿਆ ਹੈ (ਤੇਰੇ ਨਾਲ ਡੂੰਘੀ ਸਾਂਝ ਪਾਈ ਹੈ) ਜੇਹੜੇ ਤੈਨੂੰ ਤੇਰੇ ਮਨ ਵਿਚ ਪਿਆਰੇ ਲੱਗਦੇ ਹਨਹੇ ਨਾਨਕ ! (ਆਖ—ਹੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ !) (ਜੇਹੜੇ ਵਡਭਾਗੀ) ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੀ ਸੰਗਤਿ ਵਿਚ ਰਹਿੰਦੇ ਹਨ, ਉਹ ਸਦਾ ਆਤਮਕ ਆਨੰਦ ਮਾਣਦੇ ਹਨ, ਉਹ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਰਸ ਪੀ ਕੇ (ਮਾਇਆ ਦੀ ਤ੍ਰਿਸ਼ਨਾ ਵਲੋਂ) ਸਦਾ ਰੱਜੇ ਰਹਿੰਦੇ ਹਨ ।੪।੧੩।੨੦।\\""},{"question":"இந்த உரை என்ன முக்கியமான நிகழ்வைப் பற்றியது: எசுப்பானிய தேசிய அணியில் 75 முறை ஆடியுள்ள இவர் யூரோ 2008 மற்றும் யூரோ 2012 போட்டித் தொடர்களில் பங்கெடுத்துள்ளார்; அவ்விரு கோப்பைகளையும் எசுப்பானிய அணி வென்றது. மேலும் எசுப்பானிய 2014 உலகக்கோப்பை காற்பந்து அணியிலும் இடம் பெற்றார்.","answer":"யூரோ 2012"},{"question":"volana inona no manaraka ny volana jona?","answer":"Volana jolay no manaraka ny volana jona"},{"question":"ਬਹੁ-ਪਤਨੀ ਵਿਆਹ ਦਾ ਅਰਥ ‘ਦੱਸੋ ।","answer":"ਜਦੋਂ ਇੱਕ ਵਿਅਕਤੀ ਇੱਕ ਤੋਂ ਜ਼ਿਆਦਾ ਔਰਤਾਂ ਨਾਲ ਵਿਆਹ ਕਰਵਾਏ ਤਾਂ ਉਸਨੂੰ ਬਹੁ-ਪਤਨੀ ਵਿਆਹ ਕਹਿੰਦੇ ਹਨ ।"},{"question":"Ndi zitsanzo za zakumwa ndi zotani?","answer":"Mawu akuti \\"chakumwa\\" salowerera ndale, koma nthawi zambiri amagwiritsidwa ntchito m'njira yosonyeza kuledzera. Zakumwa monga soda pop, madzi onyezimira, tiyi wozizira, mandimu, mowa wa mizu, nkhonya ya zipatso, mkaka, chokoleti yotentha, tiyi, khofi, ma milkshakes, madzi apampopi, madzi a m'botolo, madzi ndi zakumwa zopatsa mphamvu zonse ndi zakumwa zoziziritsa kukhosi."},{"question":"Europosłowie opowiedzieli się za zrównywaniem cen połączeń komórkowych krajowych i zagranicznych w całej Unii. Uznali, że ceny połączeń zagranicznych powinny być takie same jak w kraju.Dokończ zdanie. Wybierz właściwą odpowiedź spośród podanych.W tekście opisano wyniki pracA. Parlamentu Europejskiego.B. Rady Unii Europejskiej.C. Komisji Europejskiej.D. Rady Europejskiej. ","answer":"Poprawna odpowiedź to: A."},{"question":"Dalam sebiji durian itu, hanya lima ____________ isi sahaja yang boleh dimakan. ","answer":"ulas"},{"question":"Quel est l’objectif de l’éducation en France ?","answer":"Le droit à l’éducation est garanti à chacun afin de lui permettre de développer sa personnalité, d’élever son niveau de formation initiale et continue, de s’insérer dans la vie sociale et professionnelle, d’exercer sa citoyenneté. Pour garantir ce droit, la répartition des moyens du service public de l’éducation tient compte des différences de situation objectives, notamment en matière économique et sociale."},{"question":"Beqil ma mbind mii:Sa Jëmmi Boroom doŋŋ fiy des, moom miy boroom màgg gi ak teraanga.","answer":"Mbind mi jub a ngi nii:Sa Jëmmi Boroom doŋŋ a fi'y des, moom mi'y boroom màgg gi ak teraanga."},{"question":"Kinsay nagtuo nga si Jesus mao ang Mesiyas?","answer":"Si Pedro mao ang unang nagtuo nga si Jesus mao ang Mesiyas, ang Anak sa Diyos."},{"question":"Apakah maksud 'bagai akan mengaji suratlah hilang; akan bertanya gurulah mati'?","answer":"Maksud 'bagai akan mengaji suratlah hilang; akan bertanya gurulah mati' ialah masalah tidak dapat diselesaikan kerana puncanya sudah hilang."},{"question":"මෙම පැවරිම්මය ක්‍රියාකාරකමමෙම පැවරුම් මය ක්‍රියාකාරකමමොකක්ද නිවැරදි?","answer":"මෙම පැවරුම නිවැරදිය."},{"question":"Ergoterapi 4 yıllık ne iş yapar?","answer":"Ergoterapi birey odaklı bir sağlık mesleğidir. Ergoterapistler temel olarak kişilerin günlük yaşama ve anlamlı aktivitelere katılımlarını sağlamak için çalışır. Özellikle herhangi bir hastalık sebebiyle hayattan kopmuş ya da kendini kültürel sebeplerle dışlanmış hisseden bireylerin tekrar hayata kazanımı hedeflenir."},{"question":"ලෝකයේ කුඩාම වනාන්තරය කුමක්ද?","answer":"Kakamega වනාන්තරය ලෝකයේ කුඩාම වනාන්තරයයි. එය වර්ග සැතපුම් 90කට අඩු ප්‍රමාණයකි. එය දැන් කුඩා වුවද, එය කලක් ලෝකයේ විශාලතම පැරණි-වර්ධන වනාන්තරය විය. අධික සම්පත් පරිහරණය, ​​යුද්ධය සහ මානව සංවර්ධනය හේතුවෙන් පසුගිය වසර 40 තුළ වනාන්තරයෙන් අඩක් පමණ විනාශ වී ඇති බව ගණන් බලා ඇත."},{"question":"வினா:எந்த வெப்ப நிலையில் நீரின் அடர்த்தி அதிகபட்சமாக இருக்கும்?","answer":"விடை: 4 டிகிரி செல்சியஸ்"},{"question":"¿Cuál es el significado del siguiente refrán? A caballo regalado no se le mira el colmillo.","answer":"Este refrán enseña a los individuos que cuando se recibe un obsequio como regalo, no se debe de buscar defectos, aspectos negativos, ni criticar el mismo. Todo lo contrario, se debe de recibir con buen agrado y agradecer por el gesto."},{"question":"Семетей Коңурбайдан атасы Манастын кунун кууп жолго чыкканда согуш эмне менен аяктайт?а) Семетейдин өлүмү менен аяктайтб) Күлчоронун өлүмү, Семетейдин жарадар болушу менен аяктайтв) Коңурбай жана Семетейдин өлүмү менен аяктайтг) Коңурбайдын өлүмү менен аяктайт","answer":"Семетей Коңурбайдан атасы Манастын кунун кууп жолго чыкканда, согуш Коңурбайдын өлүмү менен аяктайт.Ошентип, туура жообу:г) Коңурбайдын өлүмү менен аяктайт"},{"question":"السؤال: من هو قاتل علي بن أبي طالب كرم الله وجهه؟","answer":"الإجابة: عبد الرحمن بن ملجم"},{"question":"Katolik ve Protestan arasındaki fark nedir?","answer":"Protestanlarsa yalnızca vaftiz ve evharistiyayı kabul eder. Ayrıca Evharistiya'nın anlamı da iki mezhep için farklıdır: Katolikler için ekmek ve şarap İsa'nın etine ve kanına dönüşürken Protestanlar için bu ayin İsa'nın ayindeki temsili varlığıdır ve kendini kurban edişinin anılmasıdır."},{"question":"Hãy viết một bài báo có thể sử dụng tiêu đề sau đây: Long An quy hoạch Cần Giuộc thành đô thị vệ tinh. Nội dung chính của đoạn văn là về quy hoạch phát triển của huyện Cần Giuộc, tỉnh Long An. Được đặt ra với mục tiêu biến huyện này thành một đô thị trọng điểm phía Nam của TP HCM. Kế hoạch bao gồm việc hình thành đô thị loại III vào năm 2025 và trở thành thành phố trực thuộc tỉnh vào năm 2030. Cần Giuộc có lợi thế về vị trí địa lý và hạ tầng giao thông, kết nối trực tiếp với TP HCM qua các con đường quốc lộ và đường tỉnh, cũng như sự phát triển của cảng quốc tế Long An.","answer":"Cần Giuộc được quy hoạch là vùng đô thị hỗ trợ, giảm tải áp lực dân số cho TP HCM, trở thành huyện trọng điểm kinh tế của tỉnh Long An.Nằm ở Đông Nam tỉnh Long An, huyện Cần Giuộc hiện có hai đô thị là thị trấn Cần Giuộc (loại IV) và Long Đức Đông (loại V). Với vị trí giáp TP HCM, tỉnh Long An muốn biến huyện thành đô thị trọng điểm nằm trong vùng kinh tế trọng điểm phía Nam. Kỳ vọng này nhiều lần được chính quyền Long An đề cập trước đây nhưng đến nay mới có kế hoạch cụ thể.Theo đó, tỉnh đặt mục tiêu năm 2025, Cần Giuộc sẽ hình thành đô thị loại III trên phạm vi toàn huyện. Năm 2030, địa phương trở thành thành phố trực thuộc tỉnh với 10 phường, 5 xã. Đồ án quy hoạch đô thị đang được hoàn thiện, dự kiến trình Thủ tướng phê duyệt vào quý IV năm nay.Cần Giuộc có nhiều lợi thế để trở thành thành phố trọng điểm, vệ tinh ở khu vực phía Nam của TP HCM. Địa phương này kết nối trực tiếp với TP HCM qua hệ thống giao thông bộ như quốc lộ 50, đường tỉnh 826, 826C, 835B; giao thông thủy với sông Cần Giuộc kết nối sông Xoài Rạp đổ ra biển. Giai đoạn 2021-2022, huyện huy động trên 679 tỉ đồng xây dựng hạ tầng, trong đó có nhiều dự án nâng cấp, mở rộng hạ tầng giao thông quan trọng. Cảng quốc tế Long An cũng là đầu mối giao thương hàng hóa quan trọng, thúc đẩy sự phát triển."},{"question":"Qu'est-ce que le réchauffement climatique et quelles sont ses causes principales, ainsi que ses impacts sur la planète?","answer":"Le réchauffement climatique est l'augmentation de la température moyenne de la Terre due en grande partie à l'augmentation des émissions de gaz à effet de serre. Ses causes principales incluent la combustion de combustibles fossiles et la déforestation. Ses impacts comprennent la fonte des glaciers, l'élévation du niveau de la mer, les événements climatiques extrêmes et la perte de biodiversité."},{"question":"परिवार भनेको के हो?","answer":"परिवार भनेको एक वा धेरै आमाबाबु र उनीहरूका छोराछोरीहरू एक इकाईको रूपमा सँगै बस्ने समूह हो।"},{"question":"Araba suyu neden dışarı atar?","answer":"Su eksiltme varsa kaçak var, demektir. Kaçak nokta, genellikle üst kapak contasıdır. Bazen de sızdırmanın nedeni, radyatör olabilir. Radyatörde olan sorunun çözümü için radyatör su kaçağı önleyicisi olarak satılan ürün takılarak çözüm sağlanabilir."},{"question":"तलको प्रश्नको उत्तर दिनुहोस् । ७) तलका मध्ये कुन चाहीँ नाम हो ?क) रामख) हामीग) गुलियोघ) कुनै पनि होइन","answer":"माथिका मध्ये \\"क) राम\\" मात्र नाम हो ।  "},{"question":"Apakah maksud \\"batu bulat tak bersanding\\"?","answer":"Ia bermaksud orang yang kelihatan lemah lembut tingkah lakunya dan sebagainya, tetapi sebenarnya keras hatinya (tidak takut menghadapi sesuatu)."},{"question":"Rangarira ndima iri pasi apa uye ipapo pindura mubvunzo gare gare mumutauro mumwe chetewo sechikamu:  Kupfuura: YouTube inobvumira vashandisi kurodha, kuona, chiyero, kugovana, kuwedzera kune zvinyorwa zvekutamba, kuzivisa, kutaura pamavhidhiyo, uye kunyorera kune vamwe vashandisi. Inopa mavhidhiyo akasiyana-siyana anogadzirwa nevashandisi uye emakambani. Zviripo zvinosanganisira mavhidhiyo, mavhidhiyo emitambo yeTV, mavhidhiyo emimhanzi, mafirimu mapfupi nemafirimu, marekodhi, mafirimu emafirimu, mararamiro ehupenyu, uye zvimwe zvinhu zvakadai sevhidhiyo blogging, mavhidhiyo mapfupi mavhidhiyo, uye mavhidhiyo ekudzidzisa. Zvizhinji zvemukati paYouTube zvinoiswa nevanhu, asi makambani enhau anosanganisira CBS, BBC, Vevo, uye Hulu anopa zvimwe zvezvinhu zvavo kuburikidza neYouTube sechikamu chechirongwa chekudyidzana cheYouTube. Vashandisi vasina kunyoreswa vanogona kungotarisa mavhidhiyo panzvimbo iyi, nepo vashandisi vakanyoreswa vachibvumidzwa kuisa mavhidhiyo asingaverengeki uye kuwedzera makomendi kumavhidhiyo. Mavhidhiyo anoonekwa seasingakodzeri anowanikwa chete kuvashandisi vakanyoresa vanozviti vane makore 18 zvichikwira.  Mubvunzo: Zvinhu zvipi zviripo?","answer":"Mavhidhiyo emitambo yeTV, mavhidhiyo emimhanzi, mafirimu mapfupi uye ezvinyorwa, marekodhi ekuteerera, mafirimu emafirimu, mafashama ehupenyu, uye zvimwe zvirimo senge vhidhiyo blogging, mapfupi mavhidhiyo ekutanga, uye mavhidhiyo edzidzo. "},{"question":"Raha jerena ireto fehezanteny roa ireto:Fehezanteny A: \\"Taorian'ny taona maro nanomanana dia nanangana ny trano nofinofiko aho tamin'ny farany.\\"Fehezanteny B: \\"Na dia teo aza ny sakana maro, dia nanamboatra ny tranoko tsara aho.\\"Mitovy ve ny dikany?","answer":"Tsia, samy hafa ny dikany ireo fehezanteny ireo roa."},{"question":"Ερώτηση: Τι είναι η απάντηση στην αξία της ανάγνωσης βιβλίων;","answer":"Απάντηση: Η ανάγνωση βιβλίων έχει πολλαπλά οφέλη. Εμπλουτίζει τη γνώση, ενισχύει τη φαντασία, βοηθά στην ανάπτυξη της γλωσσικής ικανότητας και προσφέρει ψυχαγωγία και ευεξία."},{"question":"Write a letter from a time traveler to their past self, warning about the consequences of a specific decision.","answer":"एक समय यात्री के द्वारा उनके अतीत आत्मा को एक विशिष्ट निर्णय के परिणामों के बारे में चेतावनी देने वाला पत्र लिखें।"},{"question":"ทุเรียนหมอนทองเป็นผลไม้ที่พบได้ในประเทศอะไร","answer":"ทุเรียนพันธุ์หมอนทอง สามารถพบได้ในประเทศไทย"},{"question":"Кыргыз аялдары ийикти кантип, эмнеге колдонушкан?","answer":"Ийик — жүн, кебез, жибектен жип ийрүүчү аспап. Аны кыргыздын кыз-келиндери жип ийрип килем, таар, шалча, атка жабуу сыяктуу чарбалык керектүү буюмдарды жасоодо кеңири колдонуп келген. Ошондой эле төө, топоз, койдун жүнүнөн, эчкинин тыбытынан ийрилген жүндөн кийим-кече даярдалган.Ийик сабы, башы, буйладан турат. Ийиктин сабынын узундугу 30-35 сантиметр, жоондугу 7-10 миллиметр болуп, катуу жыгачтан (табылгыдан) жасалат. Башы таш, жыгач, мүйүздөн көзөлүп же коргошундан куюлуп тагылат.Ийиктин башы канчалык оор болсо, жиби ошончо бышык, катуу, калың ийрилет. Ал эми сабынын башы көзөлүп катуу чий, жыгач же темир буйласы өткөрүлүп тагылат.Кыргыз энелери эзелтеден үйдүн босогосун жаңы аттаган келинге ийик менен бир түйдөк аппак кебез беришкен. Муну менен алар жаңы бүлө ак кебездей таза болуп, ийиктей айланып, үй-бүлөдөгү кепти сыртка чыгарбаган жар болсун деп тилек кылышкан. Ошондой эле бул жөрөлгө келин менен кайнененин таанышуусу, аны жаңы бүлөгө кабыл алуу катары эсептелген."},{"question":"ਲਹੂ ਕਿਸ ਨੂੰ ਕਹਿੰਦੇ ਹਨ ?","answer":"ਲਹੁ ਇਕ ਕਿਸਮ ਦਾ ਤਰਲ ਪਦਾਰਥ ਹੈ । ਇਹ ਸਰੀਰ ਵਿਚ ਸ਼ਿਰਾਵਾਂ  ਅਤੇ ਧਮਨੀਆਂ ਵਿਚ ਦਿਨ-ਰਾਤ ਚੱਲਦਾ ਹੈ । ਇਹ ਗਾੜੇ ਰੰਗ ਦਾ ਨਮਕੀਨ ਪਦਾਰਥ ਹੈ । ਇਹ ਵਿਅਕਤੀ ਵਿਚ ਉਸ ਦੇ ਸਰੀਰ ਦੇ ਜਾਂ 5 ਭਾਗ ਦੇ ਬਰਾਬਰ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ ।"},{"question":"¿Qué es la fuerza de flotación?","answer":"La fuerza de flotación es una fuerza que actúa sobre un objeto sumergido en un fluido, como el agua o el aire. La fuerza de flotación es igual al peso del fluido que el objeto desplaza.La fuerza de flotación actúa en sentido contrario al peso del objeto. Esto significa que un objeto que flota en un fluido tendrá un peso aparente menor que su peso real."},{"question":"Ileeṣẹ ti wọn ti n ṣe ọda jona ni Kwara, ọpọ dukia lo ṣofo ","answer":"Ọjọruu, Wẹsidee, ọṣẹ yii, ni ina sẹ yọ nileesẹ ti wọn ti n pese ọda (Paint Chemical Company) to wa ni opopona ileesẹ Lubcon, nijọba ibilẹ Iwọ Oorun Ilọrin (West), niluu Ilọrin, nipinlẹ Kwara, to si ba dukia olowo iyebiye jẹ.ALAROYE gbọ pe ni nnkan bii aago mẹwaa alẹ Ọjọruu ni ina ọhun sẹ yọ, ti wọn o si mọ ohun to fa a titi di akoko ta a n ko iroyin yii jọ.Alukoro lẹka iroyin ileeṣẹ ajọ panapana nipinlẹ Kwara, Ọgbẹni Hassan Hakeem Adekunle, lo fidi iṣẹlẹ naa mulẹ, o ni ki ajọ awọn too de ibi ijamba ina naa, nnkan ti bajẹ jinna, sugbọn ni kete tawọn debẹ lawọn pana ọhun to ku patapata. O tẹsiwaju pe awọn eroja kẹmika to wa nileesẹ ọhun lo jẹ ki nnkan bajẹ kọja afẹnu sọ, tori pe o yara ran mọ ina.O waa parọwa is gbogbo olugbe ipinlẹ Kwara lati maa ṣọra ṣe fun gbogbo ohun to le sokunfa ijamba ina, ki wọn si maa ran ara wọn lọwọ lasiko pajawiri."},{"question":"Táíwò Ajai-Lycett","answer":"Taiwo Ajai-Lycett (bíi ọjọ́ Keta oṣù kejì ọdún 1941) ni òṣeré, oníròyìn àti atọ́kùn ará ilẹ̀ Nàìjíríà. Ajai-Lycett ni obìnrin àkọ́kọ́ tí ó ṣe iṣẹ́ olóòtú ìwé-ìròyìn Africa Woman ni ọdún 1970.Wọn bí Lycett ni ọjọ́ Keta oṣù kejì ọdún 1941 ni ìpínlè Èkó, bàbà rẹ jẹ ọmọ ìran Àwórì. Ó lọ sí ilé ẹ̀kọ́ Mt Carmel Convent School àti Methodist Girl's High School ni ìpínlè Èkó.Ó lọ sí ìlú London láti ka ìwé ímo Business and administration. Ó lọ sí ilé ẹ̀kọ́ gíga tí Hendon College of Technology nibẹ ni ó ti gba HND nínú Business Studies ni ọdún 1969. Ní Igba tí ó wà ní ilẹ̀ ẹ̀kọ́ gíga, ó ń ṣíṣe ni Lyson tea shop, ilé ifiwe ranse ati ilé iṣẹ́ ìpolówó.O bẹ̀rẹ̀ rẹ̀ sì ní ṣe ère ni ọdún 1966 ni gba ti o kópa nínú eré The lion and the jewel. Kò lérò láti kópa nínú eré na tẹ́lẹ̀, ṣùgbọ́n olùdarí eré náà, William Gaskill sọ fún pé kí ó wà kópa nínú eré náà. Lẹ́yìn eré náà ni ó wà lọ sí ilé ẹ̀kọ́ orin àti eré tí \\"Guildhall School of Music and Drama\\".O kópa nínú àwọn ère orí ìtàgé bíi Life everlasting , The national health àti Parcel post. O tí kópa nínú àwọn eré tí Nàìjíríà bíi Tinsel àti Olibiri.Ní ọdún 1975, Lycett darapọ̀ mọ àwọn òṣìṣẹ́ ní ilé iṣẹ́ Africa Magazine.O jẹ ọmọ ẹgbẹ́ Society of Nigerian Theatre Artists (SONTA).Ni ọjọ́ kìíní oṣù kẹwàá ọdún 2006, Lycett gba ebun Officer of the Order of Niger láti ọwọ́ Chief Olusegun Obasanjo. Ní oṣù kejì ọdún 2008, wọn fi ṣe olórí British-African theatre, pelu Dotun Adebayo àti Yemi Ajíbádé."},{"question":"10 LESSONS FROM RICH DAD, POOR DAD","answer":"10 LESSONS FROM RICH DAD, POOR DAD 1. Manage your money:Many people are able to make money, but not everyone learns how to manage it properly.Financial intelligence starts with learning the difference between assets and liabilities.ensure that you have more money coming in than going out, which is what will make you richer.2. Pay yourself first.Most people earn and spend their salary paying bills.A rich person always pays himself.Invest in- Courses- Books- Experiences 3. Saving and investing are different.Saving is considered a must and a good habit.You need to invest your money instead, where it grows at a higher rate than inflation.Savings weaken your purchasing power, while investments increase the value of your money.4. Learn taxes:If you are rich and lack financial literacy, you will end up paying a lot of taxes.The rich often invest in learning, so they have to pay fewer taxes.You need to have financial IQ in different areas like accounting, investing, market forces, and the law.5. Do not rely on a single source of income.Most people rely on a single source of income.You can never become rich and financially secure if you are one of them.You should have 2 to 3 streams from which you earn money.You will be in a better position even if you face a financial crisis if you have multiple income streams.6. You become smarter by taking risks.Unless you take a risk, you cannot grow—as in, grow really big.You should take a risk because some opportunities in life have the potential to change the course of your life.7. Everyone needs to be financially literate.Intelligence solves problems and produces money.Money without financial intelligence is soon gone.The sad part about the education system around the world is that it teaches people to work for money.The system never teaches how to make, manage, and keep money.You should learn how to create wealth and make a plan to achieve it."},{"question":"请解释“卑卑不足道”的意思。","answer":"这句话形容一个人卑微藐小,不值得一谈。"},{"question":"Liste 3 músicas populares do Zeca Pagodinho.","answer":"\\"Deixa a Vida Me Levar\\", \\"Caviar\\", \\"Verdade\\"."},{"question":"Опишіть оскорочено, про що йде наступна стаття:  Багато ранніх форм захисту від копіювання фактично встановлювали інвазивне програмне забезпечення на вашому комп'ютері, не знаючи про це. Тому потрібно відключити Autorun, перш ніж вставити компакт-диск, який ви хочете скопіювати, щоб переконатися, що інвазивне програмне забезпечення не буде встановлено. Вам потрібно буде відкрити реєстр Windows, щоб відключити Autorun. Детальніше ознайомтесь з цим посібником. Існує цілий ряд програм, які можуть видаляти аудіо з захищених компакт-дисков. Якщо вам потрібно скопіювати весь зміст даних CD-диска, дивіться наступний метод. Деякі з найбільш популярних програм включають dBpoweramp, EAC та ISOBuster. dBpoweramp надають перевагу, тому що він має різні варіанти обходу захисту від копірайтингу. Вам потрібна придбана версія, щоб отримати доступ до всіх функцій. ISOBuster можна отримати безкоштовно, але він поставляється з значною кількістю рекламних вставок. Вставляйте компакт-диск у комп'ютер. Автозапуск повинен бути відключений, але якщо він не відключений, тримайте клавішу Shift приблизно п'ять секунд, коли ви закриваєте поднос диска. Це не дозволить запустити автозавантаження. Метод варіюється залежно від програми, яку ви використовуєте. Можливо, вам доведеться спробувати кілька методів, поки не знайдете спосіб, який вам підходить. Якщо ви використовуєте dBpoweramp, натисніть кнопку \\"Options\\" в верхній частині вікна і виберіть \\"Secure\\" для методу Ripping. Натисніть на посилання \\"Безопасні налаштування\\" і включіть \\"Ультра-безпечне розривання\\". Це може зайняти набагато більше часу, але може виправити помилки, викликані захистом від копіювання. Якщо цей перший метод не працює, спробуйте вибрати \\"Дефектний за проектом\\" з меню Опції. Це для компакт-дисков, які були навмисно пошкоджені для захисту від копіювання. Вибравши налаштування, виберіть треки, які ви хочете скопіювати, і натисніть кнопку Rip. Якщо ви використовуєте ISOBuster, виділіть всі треки, які ви хочете скопіювати, натисніть на них правою кнопкою миші і виберіть \\"Витягти об'єкти\\". Виберіть місце для збереження і почекайте, поки процес розриву завершиться. Як тільки пісні були скопійовані на ваш комп'ютер, вони більше не захищені від копіювання. Ви можете записати їх на компакт-диск, використовуючи улюблене програмне забезпечення для запису, або додати їх до вашої цифрової музичної бібліотеки. Дивіться цей посібник для подробиць про запис аудіо CD.  Резюме:","answer":"Щоб скопіювати CD-диск треба відключити автозапуск, завантажити програму для копіювання компакт-дисков. Вставити свій компакт-диск. Скопіювати пісні, а потім записати пісні на порожній компакт-диск."},{"question":"Noufissa Benchehida","answer":"Noufissa Benchehida (tí wọ́n bí ní 23 Oṣù Kẹẹ̀wá Ọdún 1975) jẹ́ òṣèrébìnrin ọmọ orílẹ̀-èdè Mòrókò.Wọ́n bí Benchehida ní Mòrókò ní ọdún 1975. Ó fẹ́ràn eré sinimá láti ìgbà èwe rẹ̀. Ó kẹ́kọ̀ọ́ ní ilé-ìwé Cours Florent tí ó wà ní ìlú Paris. Benchehida gba oyè-ẹ̀kọ́ nínu ìmọ́ eré-ìtàgé láti ilé-ẹ̀kọ́ gíga Conservatory of Casablanca, bẹ́ẹ̀ ló sì tún lọ sí ilé-ẹ̀kọ́ Ecole supérieure d'hôtellerie et de tourisme à Montpellier.Benchehida kó àkọ́kọ́ ipa fíìmù rẹ̀ ní ọdún 2004 nínu eré tí àkọ́lé rẹ̀ jẹ́ Syriana tí olùdarí rẹ̀ síì n ṣe Stephane Cagan. Ó di gbajúmọ̀ lẹ́hìn tí ó kó ipa Zineb Hejjami gẹ́gẹ́ bi ọlọ́pàá nínu eré tẹlifíṣọ̀nù tí àkọ́lé rẹ̀ jẹ́ El kadia ní ọdún 2006. Ó sọ di mímọ̀ wípé òun gbádùn kíkó ipa náà ṣùgbọ́n òun kò fẹ́ láti máa ṣe irúfẹ̀ ipa bẹ́ẹ̀ ní gbogbo ìgbà, àti pé òun fẹ́ láti kópa nínu àwọn eré oníjà. Bákan náà ní ọdún 2006, ó kópa nínu eré tẹlifíṣọ̀nù tí àkọ́lé rẹ̀ jẹ́ Moulouk Attawaif. Ní ọdún 2011, Benchehida kó ipa olú-ẹ̀dá-ìtàn nínu eré Agadir Bombay, gẹ́gẹ́ bi obìnrin kan tí ó n ṣe àgbàwí fún àwọn obìnrin ẹgbẹ́ rẹ̀. Myriam Bakir ló darí eré náà. Ní ọdún 2015, ó kópa nínu fíìmù Aida.Ní ọdún 2016, Benchehida kópa nínu eré tí àkólẹ́ rẹ̀ jẹ́ A la recherche du pouvoir perdu (\\"Ṣíṣe àwárí agbára tí ó sọnù\\"), èyí tí Mohammed Ahed Bensouda darí. Iṣé takuntakun rẹ̀ nínu eré náà ló fun ńi àmì-ẹ̀yẹ ti Golden Sotigui níbi ayẹyẹ Sotigui Awards ti ọdún 2017. Benchehida tún gba àmì-ẹ̀yẹ òṣèrébìnrin tí ó dára jùlọ níbi ayẹyẹ Panafrican Film and Television Festival of Ouagadougou.Benchehida maá n sọ èdè Faransé, èdè Lárúbáwá àti èdè Gẹ̀ẹ́sì."},{"question":"Voltooi de volgende zin: Katrina is nog steeds aan de gang,","answer":"orkaan Ophelia heeft nu de stroom afgesneden voor bijna 81.000 huizen en bedrijven aan de oostkust van North Carolina."},{"question":"Ndi zipatso ziti zomwe zimaletsa malungo?","answer":"Zipatso ndi ndiwo zamasamba zimagwira ntchito modabwitsa kwa odwala malungo. Malinga ndi kafukufuku, vitamini A ndi vitamini C zipatso ndi ndiwo zamasamba monga beetroot, karoti, papaya, laimu wotsekemera, mphesa, zipatso, mandimu, lalanje zimathandiza kuchotsa poizoni ndi kulimbikitsa chitetezo cha mthupi cha wodwala malungo."},{"question":"问：如何在YouTube上创建自己的频道？","answer":"答：你可以在YouTube网站或应用上注册账号，并在账号设置中创建自己的频道。创建频道后，你就可以上传视频并管理你的频道了。"},{"question":"Qual cantor da MPB brasileira tem família com origem em Vitória da Conquista, cidade da Bahia? ","answer":"Gilberto Gil."},{"question":"ਰਜਿੰਦਰ ਕੌਰ ਤੇ ਸੁਹਰੇ ਪਰਿਵਾਰ ਵੱਲੋਂ ਗਰਭਪਾਤ ਕਰਨ ਦਾ ਦਬਾਅ ਸੀ। ਉਸ ਦਿਨ ਉਹ ਭਲਵਾਨ ਪੁਲਿਸ ਚੌਕੀ ਵਿੱਚ ਪੇਕਿਆਂ, ਸਹੁਰਿਆਂ ਅਤੇ ਪਤਵੰਤੇ ਸੱਜਣਾਂ ਦੀ ਹਾਜ਼ਰੀ ਵਿੱਚ ਆਪਣੇ ਪਤੀ ਨਾਲ ਦਸ ਮਹੀਨਿਆਂ ਬਾਅਦ ਸਹੁਰੇ ਪਿੰਡ ਜਾ ਰਹੀ ਸੀ। ਤਕਰੀਬਨ ਚਾਰ ਵਜੇ ਸ਼ਾਮ ਨੂੰ ਉਹ ਪੁਲਿਸ ਚੌਕੀ ਵਿੱਚੋਂ ਆਪਣੇ ਪਤੀ ਅਤੇ ਬੱਚੀ ਨਾਲ ਸਹੁਰੇ ਪਿੰਡ ਲਈ ਰਵਾਨਾ ਹੋਈ ਸੀ ਅਤੇ ਪੰਜ ਘੰਟਿਆਂ ਬਾਅਦ ਮਾਂ-ਧੀ ਦੀਆਂ ਲਾਸ਼ਾਂ ਨਹਿਰ ਵਿੱਚੋਂ ਮਿਲੀਆਂ ਸਨ। ਪੁਲਿਸ ਨੇ ਪਤੀ ਅਤੇ ਸਹੁਰੇ ਪਰਿਵਾਰ ਦੇ ਹੋਰ ਜੀਆਂ ਖ਼ਿਲਾਫ਼ ਕਤਲ ਦਾ ਪਰਚਾ ਦਰਜ ਕੀਤਾ ਸੀ।ਜਦੋਂ ਪਿੰਡ ਭੁੱਲਰਹੇੜੀ ਦੇ ਬਾਹਰ ਇੱਕ ਦੁਕਾਨ ਉੱਤੇ ਖੜ੍ਹੇ ਨੌਜਵਾਨ ਨੂੰ ਰਜਿੰਦਰ ਕੌਰ ਦੇ ਘਰ ਦਾ ਰਾਹ ਪੁੱਛਿਆ ਤਾਂ ਦੋ ਜਣੇ ਬਿਨਾ ਕੁਝ ਕਹੇ ਬੀਬੀਸੀ ਦੀ ਟੀਮ ਨੂੰ ਮ੍ਰਿਤਕ ਲੜਕੀ ਦੇ ਘਰ ਤੱਕ ਛੱਡ ਕੇ ਆਉਣ ਲਈ ਤਿਆਰ ਹੋ ਗਏ। ਗਰਭਪਾਤ ਕਰਵਾਉਣ ਲਈ ਕਰਦੇ ਸੀ ਮਜਬੂਰ। ਇਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਦੋਹਾਂ ਗਰਾਈਆਂ ਦੇ ਚਿਹਰੇ ਉੱਤੇ ਪਰਿਵਾਰ ਨਾਲ ਹਮਦਰਦੀ ਦੇ ਭਾਵ ਸਾਫ਼ ਪੜ੍ਹੇ ਜਾ ਸਕਦੇ ਸਨ।ਘਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਪਰਿਵਾਰ ਤੋਂ ਇਲਾਵਾ ਇੱਕ ਦੋ ਵਿਅਕਤੀ ਹੋਰ ਮੌਜੂਦ ਹਨ, ਜੋ ਪਰਿਵਾਰ ਨਾਲ ਗੱਲਬਾਤ ਕਰਨ ਤੋਂ ਪਹਿਲਾਂ ਪਿੰਡ ਦੇ ਕੁਝ ਮੋਹਤਬਰਾਂ ਨਾਲ ਗੱਲ ਕਰਨ ਲਈ ਕਹਿੰਦੇ ਹੋਏ ਤਰਕ ਦਿੰਦੇ ਹਨ, \\"ਇਹ ਤਾਂ ਵਿਚਾਰੇ ਅਨਪੜ੍ਹ ਨੇ ਜੀ, ਉਹ ਥੋਨੂੰ ਜ਼ਿਆਦਾ ਦੱਸ ਸਕਦੇ ਹਨ।\\"ਰਜਿੰਦਰ ਕੌਰ ਦਾ ਵਿਆਹ ਨੇੜਲੇ ਪਿੰਡ ਮੀਰਹੇੜੀ ਦੇ ਰਹਿਣ ਵਾਲੇ ਗੁਰਪ੍ਰੀਤ ਸਿੰਘ ਨਾਲ 18 ਮਹੀਨੇ ਪਹਿਲਾਂ ਹੋਇਆ ਸੀ। ਰਜਿੰਦਰ ਜਦੋਂ ਦੋ ਮਹੀਨੇ ਦੀ ਗਰਭਵਤੀ ਸੀ ਤਾਂ ਪਤੀ ਪਤਨੀ ਵਿੱਚ ਝਗੜਾ ਰਹਿਣ ਲੱਗ ਪਿਆ। ਰਜਿੰਦਰ ਦੇ ਪਿਤਾ ਰਣਜੀਤ ਸਿੰਘ ਮੁਤਾਬਕ, \\"ਉਹ ਸਾਡੀ ਕੁੜੀ ਨੂੰ ਗਰਭਪਾਤ ਕਰਵਾਉਣ ਲਈ ਦਬਾਅ ਪਾ ਰਿਹਾ ਸੀ। ਜਦੋਂ ਇਹ ਨਾ ਮੰਨੀ ਤਾਂ ਉਸ ਨੇ ਇਸਦਾ ਦੋ ਵਾਰ ਗਲਾ ਘੁੱਟਣ ਦੀ ਕੋਸ਼ਿਸ਼ ਵੀ ਕੀਤੀ। ਫਿਰ ਅਸੀਂ ਆਪਣੀ ਧੀ ਨੂੰ ਪਿੰਡ ਲੈ ਆਏ।'' \\"ਇਥੇ ਹੀ ਉਸ ਨੇ ਕੁੜੀ ਨੂੰ ਜਨਮ ਦਿੱਤਾ। ਹੁਣ ਸਾਲ ਬਾਅਦ ਪੁਲਿਸ ਚੌਕੀ ਵਿੱਚ ਹੋਏ ਸਮਝੌਤੇ ਮਗਰੋਂ ਸਾਡਾ ਜਵਾਈ ਸਹਿਮਤੀ ਨਾਲ ਕੁੜੀ ਨੂੰ ਨਾਲ ਲੈ ਕੇ ਗਿਆ ਸੀ। ਸਾਨੂੰ ਕੀ ਪਤਾ ਸੀ ਕਿ ਉਹ ਇਹ ਕਾਰਾ ਕਰਨਗੇ।\\"ਪਿੰਡ ਦੇ ਸਾਬਕਾ ਪੰਚਾਇਤ ਮੈਂਬਰ ਕਰਮ ਸਿੰਘ ਦੱਸਦੇ ਹਨ, \\"ਅਸੀਂ ਪੁੱਛਿਆ ਤਾਂ ਕੁੜੀ ਆਪਣੇ ਸਹੁਰੇ ਘਰ ਵੱਸਣਾ ਚਾਹੁੰਦੀ ਸੀ।  ਜੇ ਕੁੜੀ ਭੋਰਾ ਵੀ ਨਾਂਹ ਨੁੱਕਰ ਕਰਦੀ ਤਾਂ ਅਸੀਂ ਕੁੜੀ ਤੋਰਨ ਲਈ ਸਹਿਮਤ ਨਾ ਹੁੰਦੇ।\\"23 ਅਪ੍ਰੈਲ ਨੂੰ ਇਸ ਮਾਮਲੇ ਵਿੱਚ ਤੀਜਾ ਪੰਚਾਇਤੀ ਇਕੱਠ ਹੋਇਆ ਸੀ।ਰਜਿੰਦਰ ਕੌਰ ਦੇ ਸਹੁਰੇ ਪਿੰਡ ਵਿੱਚ ਕੋਈ ਵੀ ਉਸ ਦੇ ਸਹੁਰਿਆਂ ਦੇ ਘਰ ਦਾ ਪਤਾ ਦੱਸਣ ਲਈ ਰਾਜ਼ੀ ਨਹੀਂ ਸੀ।","answer":"ਸੰਗਰੂਰ ਜ਼ਿਲ੍ਹੇ ਦੇ ਪਿੰਡ ਭੁੱਲਰਹੇੜੀ ਦੀ ਰਜਿੰਦਰ ਕੌਰ ਅਤੇ ਉਸ ਦੀ ਸਾਢੇ ਤਿੰਨ ਮਹੀਨਿਆਂ ਦੀ ਬੱਚੀ ਦੀਆਂ ਲਾਸ਼ਾਂ 23 ਅਪ੍ਰੈਲ ਨੂੰ ਬੱਬਨਪੁਰ ਪਿੰਡ ਕੋਲੋਂ ਲੰਘਦੀ ਨਹਿਰ ਵਿੱਚੋਂ ਮਿਲੀਆਂ ਸਨ।"},{"question":"da'","answer":"1.da' : Inta sano, bilo, maalmo iwm ee nafley jirto laga bilaabo maalintii uu dhashay, cumri.2. Da’ ah: qof sanado badan jira, duq. 3. Dad hal casri wada nool."},{"question":"ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਰਾਮਦਾਸ ਜੀ ਨੇ ਗੁਰਗੱਦੀ ਕਿਸਨੂੰ ਅਤੇ ਕਦੋਂ ਸੌਂਪੀ ?","answer":"ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਰਾਮਦਾਸ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਤਿੰਨ ਪੁੱਤਰ ਸਨ ! ਸਭ ਤੋਂ ਵੱਡਾ ਪੁੱਤਰ ਪ੍ਰਿਥੀ ਚੰਦ ਬੜਾ ਬੇਈਮਾਨ ਤੇ ਸੁਆਰਥੀ ਸੀ । ਦੂਜਾ ਪੁੱਤਰ ਮਹਾਂਦੇਵ ਬੈਰਾਗੀ ਸੁਭਾਅ ਦਾ ਸੀ। ਉਸ ਦੀ ਸੰਸਾਰਿਕ ਕੰਮਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਕੋਈ ਰੁਚੀ ਨਹੀਂ ਸੀ । ਤੀਜੇ ਅਤੇ ਸਭ ਤੋਂ ਛੋਟੇ ਪੁੱਤਰ ਅਰਜਨ ਦੇਵ ਜੀ ਸਨ । ਉਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਗੁਰੂ ਭਗਤੀ, ਸੇਵਾ ਅਤੇ ਨਿਮਰਤਾ, ਆਦਿ ਗੁਣ ਪ੍ਰਮੁੱਖ ਸਨ । ਇਸੇ ਕਾਰਨ ਗੁਰੂ ਰਾਮਦਾਸ ਜੀ ਨੇ ਅਰਜਨ ਦੇਵ ਜੀ ਨੂੰ 1581 ਈ: ਵਿਚ ਗੁਰਗੱਦੀ ਸੌਂਪੀ । ਇਸ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਅਰਜਨ ਦੇਵ ਜੀ ਸਿੱਖਾਂ ਦੇ ਪੰਜਵੇਂ ਗੁਰੂ ਬਣੇ ।"},{"question":"Generate a headline for the following text: nIroyin to n tẹ wa lọwọ lati aafin Awujale ti ilẹ Ijebu, Ọba Sikiru Adetona sọ pe Kabiesi ko tii waja gẹgẹ bi iroyin ti awọn eeyan ka n gbe kiri lori ayelujara. Ọkan lara awọn eeyan to sumọ ori ade naa, Alhaji Alaga Kamorudeen, to jẹ adari eto ọdun Ojude Oba ti ilẹ Ijebu ṣalaye fun BBC Yoruba pe alaafia ni baba wa ni aafin rẹ. Gẹgẹ bii ohun to sọ, o ni oun ṣi foju ganni Kabiesi ni nnkan bi ọjọ meji sẹyin. Kamorudeen ni \\"Ẹ ma naani iroyin ti awọn kan n gbe kiri lori ayelujara, ko si nnkankan to ṣe baba o.\\" \\"Mo ṣi wa lọdọ Kabiesi lọjọ Aiku lati nnkan bii aago mejila ọsan titi di alẹ ni aafin wọn ko sì sí nnkankan to ṣe wọn.\\" \\"Ipade meji ni wọn ṣe lọjọ naa, lẹyin ti mo ba wọn ṣe ipade tan, wọn tun ba awọn ọba meji miran ṣe ipade.\\" Kamorudeen sọ siwaju si pe oun naa ti gbọ iroyin ọhun pe kabiesi ti waja, irọ patapata ni iroyin naa jẹ. Alaga tun ṣalaye pe ko ni si ọdun Ojude Ọba lọdun yii bi wọn ṣe maa n ṣe tẹlẹ latẹyinwa. Ọjọ keji, oṣu Kẹrin, ọdun 1960 ni Ọba Sikiru Kayode Adetona gori itẹ gẹgẹ bii Awujale ilẹ Ijebu.","answer":"Sure, here's a headline for the given text - Awujale: Àlàáfíà ni Ọba Síkírù Adétònà  wà ní ààfin rẹ̀- Alága Kamorudeen tí Ìjẹ̀bú Òde tó jẹ́ adarí ètò Ojúde Ọba."},{"question":"Amaka Igwe","answer":"Amaka Igwe (tí a bí ní ọjọ́ kejì oṣù Ṣéẹ́rẹ́ ọdún 1963 - ó di olóògbé ní ọjọ́ kejìdínlọ́gbọ̀n oṣù Igbe, ọdún 2014). Amaka Igwe jẹ́ òṣèré ọmọ orílẹ̀èdè Nàìjíríà àti ọ̀gá sọ̀rọ̀sọ̀rọ̀. Òun ni aláṣẹ iléeṣẹ́ rédíò Top 90.8 Èkó àti iléeṣẹ́ Amaka Igwe Studio. Ipa rẹ̀ lásìkò ìgbédìde fíìmù àgbéléwò láyé sinimá ní Nàìjíríà kò ṣé é fọwọ́ rọ́ sẹ́yìn. Èèkàn ní ni agbo òṣèré nígbà ayé rẹ̀ kí ó tó di wí pé àìsàn ikọ́ sémìísémìí mú ẹ̀mí rẹ̀ lọ.Ní ọjọ́ kejì, Oṣù Ṣéẹ́rẹ́ wọ́n dá ṣe ìrántí ọjọ́ọ̀bí rẹ̀, wọ́n sì fi Google Doodle da lọ́la.Uzomaka Audrey \\"Amaka\\" Igwe jẹ́ ọmọ Isaac àti Patience Ene ní ìlú Port-Harcourt. Ipo karùn-ún ni Igwe nínú àwọn ọmọ méje, ó sì jẹ́ ọmọbìnrin kẹrìn nínú obìnrin mẹ́fà. \\"GCO\\" Ọ̀gá Apàṣẹ̀ ni bàbá rẹ̀ máa  ń pè é, tí ìyà rẹ̀ sì ń pè é ni \\"ìjì\\" (storm) torí pé ọwọ́ rẹ̀ kì í dilẹ̀. Ó lọ sí ilé ẹ̀kọ́ All Saints àti Iléẹ̀kọ́ Gíga Awkunanaw àwọn obìnrin ní Enugu.Ó ja ẹ̀ṣẹ́, ó gba bọ́ọ̀lù àfọwọ́gbá, òun sì ni olórí ikọ̀ agbábọ́ọ́lù àwọn obìnrin. Nígbà tí ó ń ṣe A-level ní Kọ́lẹ́jì Idia, ó bẹ̀rẹ̀ sí ní ṣe àwárí ẹ̀bùn rẹ̀. Ó kọ́ àwọn èèyàn ní ijó Atilogwu,ó sì díjé orílẹ̀èdè. Ó bẹ̀rẹ̀ sí ní kọ eré-onítàn àti orin. Ẹ̀kọ́ Ìmọ̀ òfin ló wu Amaka Igwe láti ṣe ṣùgbọ́n àwọn òṣìṣẹ́ Ajọ́ JAMB fún ní *Ìmọ̀ Ẹ̀kọ́ àti Ẹ̀sìn (Theology). Fún ìdí èyí, ó kẹ́kọ̀ọ́ Ìmọ̀ Ẹ̀kọ́ àti Ẹ̀sìn náà ní Yunifásítì Ifẹ̀ (Yunifásítì Ọbáfẹ́mi Awólọ́wọ̀ báyìí)Láti OAU, Igwe darapọ̀ mọ́ MNET short celluloid film \\"Barbers Wisdom\\" gẹ́gẹ́ bíi olùdarí, ó tẹ̀síwájú láti lọ sí Yunifásítì Ìjọba Àpapọ̀ tí ìlú Ìbàdàn, níbi tí ó ti gba òye EM-EE (MA) nínú Ìmọ̀ Library and Information Sciences. Lásìkò tí ó jẹ́ àgùnbánirọ̀ ó jẹ́ akọ̀wé arìnrìn-àjò fún Scripture Union. Ó sì ṣíṣe gẹ́gẹ́ bíi Aláṣẹ olùdarí ní Iléẹ̀kọ́ Yunifásítì Ìmọ̀ Èrọ Anambra ni Eida Information Systems kí ó tó fi àdàgbà ètò rọ̀ sí agbo àwọn alátinúdáà. Ó fẹ́ ọkọ rẹ̀ Charles Igwe ní Oṣù Igbe ni ọdún 1993, wọ́n sì bí ọmọ mẹ́ta.Aláṣeyorí òǹkọ̀wé, olótùú, olùdarí, oníṣòwò àti olùkọ́ ni Igwe. Aṣáájú Fíìmù àti Dirama ayé òde òní tí Nàìjíríà ni. Ó di gbajúgbajà gẹ́gẹ́ bí òǹkọ̀tàn àti olótùú eré \\"Checkmate\\" àti *Fuji House of Commotion\\". Lára àwọn iṣẹ́ rẹ̀ ni Nollywood ni Rattle snake àti Violated tí ó ya iléeṣẹ́ Amaka Igwe Studio sọ́tọ̀ lásìkò fíìmù àgbéléwò láyé sinimá ní Nàìjíríà. Òun ló dá BOBTV Exp sílẹ̀, Òun sì ni olùdásílẹ̀ àti Aláṣẹ Rédíò TOP 90.9Fam tó wà ní ìgboro Èkó, The quality content production House, Amaka Igwe Studios àti Q Entertainment Networks and ìkànnì DSTV.Àwùjọ kò ní gbàgbé ipa ribiribi tí Igwe kò láti mú ìgbéga bá fíìmù ṣíṣe, bí ó tilẹ̀ jẹ́ pé wọ́n kò ka agbo òṣèré sí pàtàkì nígbà kan, síbẹ̀ Iléeṣẹ́ Amaka Studio gbìyànjú púpọ̀ láti mú ìdàgbàsókè ba, àti àṣeyọrí kí wọ́n sì jẹ́ ìwúrí fún ọ̀pọ̀lọpọ̀ nínú àwọn òṣèré nílẹ̀ Nàìjíríà, àwọn ọmọ orílẹ̀èdè Nàìjíríà àti àgbáyé lápapọ̀.Ìbẹ̀rù àti ìbọ̀wọ̀ fún Ọlọ́run, àwọn ẹbì rẹ̀, àṣeyege, iṣẹ́ gidi rẹ̀, àti àṣà lákòótán jẹ́ àbùdá pàtàkì Amaka. Ó fẹ́ràn àwọn ẹ̀bí rẹ̀, ó sì pinnu láti má fi wọ́n sílẹ̀ nígbà kankan. Amaka Igwe mú ìdàgbàsókè ba awon èèyàn, àwọn sì ni ẹ̀rí rẹ̀ dòní. Ó sábà máa ń sọ fún àwọn tí ó ń kọ́ níṣẹ́ tààrà pé òun yóò fi ohunkóhun tí òun bá ní ṣe àlékún òun ti o wà lọ́wọ́ tiwọn kí wọ́n lè dára ju òun lọ. Kò hùwà àfèmi-àfèmi, ó sì farajìn fún ìdàgbàsókè àti ìsọlọ́jọ agbo àwọn alátinúdá.Igwe gba àwọn àmì-ẹ̀yẹ nígbà ayé rẹ̀. Ní ọdún 2011, Orílẹ̀èdè Nàìjíríà fi oyè MFR - Ọmọ Ẹgbẹ́ Orílẹ̀èdè Nàìjíríà (Member of the Federal Republic of Nigeria) da lọ́lá fún ìmọrírì akitiyan àti ipa pàtàkì rẹ̀ sí àwùjọ àwọn alátinúdá.Ni ọjọ́ kejì, Oṣù Ṣéẹ́rẹ́, Google fi Google Doddle ṣe àjọyọ ọjọ́ọ̀bí Kẹtàdínlọ́gọ́ta fún-un.Igwe kú ní Enugu ní ọjọ́ kẹtàdínlọ́gbọ̀n, Oṣù Igbe ọdún 2014, ni alẹ́ aago mẹ́jọ àbọ̀. Gbogbo ìgbìyànjú láti dóòlà ẹmí rẹ̀ lọ́wọ́ pípeléke ikọ́-sèmìí-sèmìí tí ó ń bá fínra ló já sí pàbó. Gómìnà Ìpínlẹ̀ Imo nígbà náà Rochas Okorocha lọ sí ètò ìsìnkú rẹ̀, bákan náà ni àwọn èèkàn ní agbo àwọn òṣèré."},{"question":"Oviana no nisy ny repoblika faharoa teto Madagasikara?","answer":"Ny taona 1973 hatramin'ny taona 1991 no nisy ny repoblika faharoa teto Madagasikara."},{"question":"ਸਮਾਜ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰ ਦੀ ਉਤਪੱਤੀ ਦੇ ਵੱਖ-ਵੱਖ ਚਰਣਾਂ ਦਾ ਵਰਣਨ ਕਰੋ ।","answer":"ਮਨੁੱਖ ਇੱਕ ਚਿੰਤਨ ਕਰਨ ਵਾਲਾ ਪ੍ਰਾਣੀ ਹੈ । ਆਪਣੇ ਜੀਵਨ ਦੇ ਸ਼ੁਰੂਆਤੀ ਪੱਧਰ ਤੋਂ ਹੀ ਉਸ ਵਿਚ ਆਪਣੇ ਆਲੇ-ਦੁਆਲੇ ਬਾਰੇ ਪਤਾ ਕਰਨ ਦੀ ਇੱਛਾ ਹੁੰਦੀ ਹੈ । ਉਸਨੇ ਸਮੇਂ-ਸਮੇਂ ਉੱਤੇ ਪੈਦਾ ਹੋਈਆਂ ਮੁਸ਼ਕਿਲਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਦੂਰ ਕਰਨ ਲਈ ਇਕੱਠੇ ਮਿਲ ਕੇ ਕੋਸ਼ਿਸ਼ਾਂ ਕੀਤੀਆਂ । ਵਿਅਕਤੀਆਂ ਵਿਚ ਹੋਈਆਂ ਅੰਤਰਕ੍ਰਿਆਵਾਂ ਨਾਲ ਸਮਾਜਿਕ ਸੰਬੰਧ ਵਿਕਸਿਤ ਹੋਏ ਜਿਸ ਨਾਲ ਨਵੇਂ-ਨਵੇਂ ਸਮੂਹ ਸਾਡੇ ਸਾਹਮਣੇ ਆਏ । ਮਨੁੱਖੀ ਵਿਵਹਾਰ ਨੂੰ ਵੱਖ-ਵੱਖ ਪਰੰਪਰਾਵਾਂ ਅਤੇ ਪ੍ਰਭਾਵਾਂ ਨਾਲ ਨਿਯੰਤਰਨ ਵਿਚ ਰੱਖਿਆ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਰਿਹਾ ਹੈ । ਇਸ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਸਮਾਜ ਦੇ ਵੱਖ-ਵੱਖ ਪੱਖਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਸਮਝਣ ਦੀ ਕੋਸ਼ਿਸ਼ ਕਰਦਾ ਰਿਹਾ ਹੈ ।ਸਮਾਜ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰ ਦੀ ਉਤਪੱਤੀ ਦੇ ਵਿਕਾਸ ਦੇ ਚਰਣ (Stages of Origin and Development of Sociology) ਸਮਾਜ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰ ਦੀ ਉਤਪੱਤੀ ਅਤੇ ਵਿਕਾਸ ਨੂੰ ਮੁੱਖ ਤੌਰ ਉੱਤੇ ਚਾਰ ਭਾਗਾਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਵੰਡਿਆ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ-1. ਪਹਿਲਾ ਚਰਣ (First Stage) – ਸਮਾਜ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰ ਦੇ ਵਿਕਾਸ ਦੇ ਪਹਿਲੇ ਚਰਣ ਨੂੰ ਦੋ ਭਾਗਾਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਵੰਡ ਕੇ ਬੇਹਤਰ ਢੰਗ ਨਾਲ ਸਮਝਿਆ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ-(i) ਵੈਦਿਕ ਅਤੇ ਮਹਾਂਕਾਵ ਕਾਲ (Vedic and Epic Era) – ਚਾਹੇ ਸਮਾਜ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰ ਦੇ ਵਿਕਾਸ ਦੀ ਸ਼ੁਰੂਆਤੀ ਅਵਸਥਾ ਦੀ ਸ਼ੁਰੁਆਤ ਨੂੰ ਆਮ ਤੌਰ ਉੱਤੇ ਯੂਰਪ ਤੋਂ ਮੰਨਿਆ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ । ਪਰ ਇਤਿਹਾਸ ਇਸ ਗੱਲ ਦਾ ਗਵਾਹ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਭਾਰਤ ਦੇ ਰਿਸ਼ੀਆਂ-ਮੁਨੀਆਂ ਨੇ ਪੂਰੇ ਭਾਰਤ ਦਾ ਵਿਚਰਣ ਕੀਤਾ ਅਤੇ ਇੱਥੋਂ ਦੇ ਲੋਕਾਂ ਦੀਆਂ ਸਮੱਸਿਆਵਾਂ ਜਾਂ ਜ਼ਰੂਰਤਾਂ ਦਾ ਡੂੰਘਾ ਅਧਿਐਨ, ਚਿੰਤਨ ਅਤੇ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦਾ ਮੰਥਨ ਕੀਤਾ । ਉਹਨਾਂ ਨੇ ਭਾਰਤੀ ਸਮਾਜ ਵਿੱਚ ਵਰਣ ਵਿਵਸਥਾ ਨੂੰ ਵਿਕਸਿਤ ਕੀਤਾ । ਇਸ ਗੱਲ ਦਾ ਉੱਲੇਖ ਦੁਨੀਆ ਦੇ ਸਭ ਤੋਂ ਪੁਰਾਣੇ ਪਰ ਭਾਰਤ ਵਿੱਚ ਲਿਖੇ ਮਹਾਨ ਪ੍ਰਾਚੀਨ ਗੰਥ ਰਿਗਵੇਦ (Rigveda) ਵਿੱਚ ਮਿਲਦਾ ਹੈ । ਵੇਦ, ਉਪਨਿਸ਼ਦ, ਪੁਰਾਣ, ਮਹਾਂਭਾਰਤ, ਰਾਮਾਇਣ, ਗੀਤਾ ਆਦਿ ਵਰਗੇ ਗ੍ਰੰਥਾਂ ਨਾਲ ਭਾਰਤ ਵਿਚ ਸਮਾਜ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰ ਦੀ ਸ਼ੁਰੁਆਤ ਹੋਈ । ਵਰਣ ਵਿਵਸਥਾ ਤੋਂ ਇਲਾਵਾ ਆਸ਼ਰਮ ਵਿਵਸਥਾ, ਚਾਰ ਪੁਰੂਸ਼ਾਰਥ, ਰਿਣਾਂ ਦੀ ਧਾਰਨਾ, ਸੰਯੁਕਤ ਪਰਿਵਾਰ ਆਦਿ ਭਾਰਤ ਸਮਾਜ ਵਿੱਚ ਵਿਕਸਿਤ ਪ੍ਰਾਚੀਨ ਸੰਸਥਾਵਾਂ ਵਿੱਚੋਂ ਪ੍ਰਮੁੱਖ ਹਨ । ਇਹਨਾਂ ਧਾਰਮਿਕ ਗ੍ਰੰਥਾਂ ਤੋਂ ਇਲਾਵਾ ਕੌਟਿਲਯ ਦੇ ਅਰਥ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਭਾਰਤ ਦੀਆਂ ਉਸ ਸਮੇਂ ਦੀਆਂ ਸਮੱਸਿਆਵਾਂ ਦਾ ਸਮਾਜ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰੀ ਵਿਸ਼ਲੇਸ਼ਣ ਦੇਖਣ ਨੂੰ ਮਿਲਦਾ ਹੈ ।(ii) ਯੂਨਾਨੀ ਵਿਚਾਰਕਾਂ ਦੇ ਅਧਿਐਨ (Studies of Greek Scholars) – ਸੁਕਰਾਤ ਤੋਂ ਬਾਅਦ ਪਲੈਟੋ (Plato) (427-347 B.C.) ਅਤੇ ਅਰਸਤੂ (Aristotle) (384-322B.C.) ਯੂਨਾਨੀ ਵਿਚਾਰਕ ਹੋਏ ਹਨ | ਪਲੈਟੋ ਨੇ ‘ਰਿਪਬਲਿਕ ਅਤੇ ਅਰਸਤੂ ਨੇ Ethics and Politics ਵਿੱਚ ਉਸ ਸਮੇਂ ਦੇ ਪਰਿਵਾਰਿਕ ਜੀਵਨ, ਜਨਰੀਤੀਆਂ, ਪਰੰਪਰਾਵਾਂ, ਔਰਤਾਂ ਦੀ ਸਥਿਤੀ ਆਦਿ ਦਾ ਵਿਸਤਾਰ ਨਾਲ ਵਰਣਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਹੈ | ਪਲੈਟੋ ਨੇ 50 ਤੋਂ ਵੱਧ ਅਤੇ ਅਰਸਤੂ ਨੇ 150 ਤੋਂ ਵੱਧ ਛੋਟੇ-ਵੱਡੇ ਰਾਜਾਂ ਦੇ ਰਾਜਨੀਤਿਕ, ਸਮਾਜਿਕ, ਧਾਰਮਿਕ, ਆਰਥਿਕ, ਵਿਵਸਥਾ ਦਾ ਅਧਿਐਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਅਤੇ ਆਪਣੀਆਂ ਕਿਤਾਬਾਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਵਿਚਾਰ ਦਿੱਤੇ ।2. ਦੂਜਾ ਚਰਣ (Second Stage) – ਕਿਤਾਬਾਂ ਸਮਾਜ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰ ਦੇ ਵਿਕਾਸ ਦੇ ਦੂਜੇ ਚਰਣ ਵਿੱਚ 6ਵੀਂ ਸਦੀ ਤੋਂ ਲੈ ਕੇ 14ਵੀਂ ਸਦੀ ਤੱਕ ਦਾ ਕਾਲ ਮੰਨਿਆ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ । ਇਸ ਕਾਲ ਦੇ ਸ਼ੁਰੂਆਤੀ ਚਰਣ ਵਿੱਚ ਸਮਾਜਿਕ ਸਮੱਸਿਆਵਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਸਮਝਣ ਦੇ ਲਈ ਧਰਮ ਅਤੇ ਦਰਸ਼ਨ ਦੀ ਮਦਦ ਲਈ ਗਈ । ਪਰ 13ਵੀਂ ਸਦੀ ਵਿੱਚ ਸਮੱਸਿਆਵਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਤਾਰਕਿਕ ਢੰਗ ਨਾਲ ਸਮਝਣ ਦੀ ਕੋਸ਼ਿਸ਼ ਕੀਤੀ ਗਈ । ਬਾਮਸੇ ਏਕਯੂਸ (Thomas Acquines) ਅਤੇ ਦਾਂਤੇ (Dante) ਨੇ ਸਮਾਜਿਕ ਘਟਨਾਵਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਸਮਝਣ ਦੇ ਲਈ ਕਾਰਜ-ਕਾਰਣ ਦੇ ਸੰਬੰਧ ਨੂੰ ਸਪੱਸ਼ਟ ਕੀਤਾ । ਇਸ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਸਮਾਜ ਦੇ ਵਿਗਿਆਨ ਦੀ ਰੂਪ ਰੇਖਾ ਬਣਨ ਲੱਗ ਗਈ ।3. ਤੀਜੀ ਅਵਸਥਾ (Third Stage) – ਸਮਾਜ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰ ਦੇ ਵਿਕਾਸ ਦੇ ਤੀਜੇ ਚਰਣ ਦੀ ਸ਼ੁਰੂਆਤ 13ਵੀਂ ਸਦੀ ਵਿੱਚ ਹੋਈ । ਇਸ ਸਮੇਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਕਈ ਅਜਿਹੇ ਮਹਾਨ ਵਿਚਾਰਕ ਹੋਏ ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਨੇ ਸਮਾਜਿਕ ਘਟਨਾਵਾਂ ਦੇ ਅਧਿਐਨ ਦੇ ਲਈ ਵਿਗਿਆਨ ਵਿਧੀ ਦਾ ਪ੍ਰਯੋਗ ਕੀਤਾ । ਹਾਂਬਸ, ਲਾਂਕ, ਰੂਸੋ (Hobbes, Locke and Rousseau) ਨੇ ਸਮਾਜਿਕ ਸਮਝੌਤੇ ਦਾ ਸਿਧਾਂਤ (Social Contract Theory) ਦਿੱਤਾ । ਥਾਮਸ ਮੂਰੇ (Thomas Moore) ਨੇ ਆਪਣੀ ਕਿਤਾਬ ਦਾ ਸਪਿਰਿਟ ਆਫ਼ ਲਾਂਜ਼ (The Spirit of Laws), ਮਾਲਥਸ (Malthus) ਨੇ ਆਪਣੇ ‘ਜਨਸੰਖਿਆ ਦੇ ਸਿਧਾਂਤ’ ਦੀ ਮਦਦ ਨਾਲ ਸਮਾਜਿਕ ਘਟਨਾਵਾਂ ਦਾ ਅਧਿਐਨ ਕਰਕੇ ਸਮਾਜ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰ ਦੇ ਵਿਕਾਸ ਵਿੱਚ ਆਪਣਾ ਯੋਗਦਾਨ ਦਿੱਤਾ ।4. ਚੌਥਾ ਚਰਣ Fourth Stage) – ਮਹਾਨ ਫ਼ਰਾਂਸੀਸੀ ਵਿਚਾਰਕ ਅਗਸਤੇ ਕਾਮਤੇ (Auguste Comte) ਨੇ 19ਵੀਂ ਸਦੀ ਦੀ ਸ਼ੁਰੂਆਤ ਵਿੱਚ ਸਮਾਜ ਦੇ ਵਿਗਿਆਨ ਨੂੰ ਸਮਾਜਿਕ ਭੌਤਿਕੀ (Social Physics) ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਦਿੱਤਾ । 1839 ਵਿੱਚ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਨੇ ਇਸਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਬਦਲ ਕੇ ਸਮਾਜ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰ (Sociology) ਰੱਖ ਦਿੱਤਾ । ਉਹਨਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਸਮਾਜ ਵਿਗਿਆਨ ਦਾ ਪਿਤਾ (Father of Sociology) ਕਿਹਾ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ ।1843 ਵਿੱਚ ਜੇ.ਐੱਸ. ਮਿਲ (J.S.Mill) ਨੇ ਇੰਗਲੈਂਡ ਵਿੱਚ ਸਮਾਜ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰ ਨੂੰ ਸ਼ੁਰੂ ਕੀਤਾ । ਹਰਬਰਟ ਸਪੈਂਸਰ ਨੇ ਆਪਣੀ ਕਿਤਾਬ Principles of Sociology ਅਤੇ Theory of Organism ਨਾਲ ਸਮਾਜ ਦਾ ਵਿਗਿਆਨ ਵਿਧੀ ਨਾਲ ਵਿਸ਼ਲੇਸ਼ਣ ਕੀਤਾ । ਸਭ ਤੋਂ ਪਹਿਲਾਂ ਅਮਰੀਕਾ ਦੀ Yale University ਵਿੱਚ 1876 ਵਿੱਚ ਸਮਾਜ ਵਿਗਿਆਨ ਦਾ ਅਧਿਐਨ ਸੁਤੰਤਰ ਵਿਸ਼ੇ ਦੇ ਰੂਪ ਵਿੱਚ ਹੋਇਆ । ਦੁਰਖੀਮ ਨੇ ਆਪਣੀਆਂ ਕਿਤਾਬਾਂ ਦੀ ਮਦਦ ਨਾਲ ਸਮਾਜ ਵਿਗਿਆਨ ਨੂੰ ਸੁਤੰਤਰ ਵਿਗਿਆਨ ਦੇ ਰੂਪ ਵਿੱਚ ਵਿਕਸਿਤ ਕਰਨ ਲਈ ਯੋਗਦਾਨ ਦਿੱਤਾ । ਮੈਕਸ ਵੈਬਰ ਤੇ ਹੋਰ ਸਮਾਜ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰੀਆਂ ਨੇ ਵੀ ਬਹੁਤ ਸਾਰੇ ਸਮਾਜ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰੀ ਸਿਧਾਂਤ ਦਿੱਤੇ । ਵਰਤਮਾਨ ਸਮੇਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੁਨੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਲਗਭਗ ਸਾਰੇ ਦੇਸ਼ਾਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਇਹ ਵਿਸ਼ਾ ਸੁਤੰਤਰ ਰੂਪ ਵਿੱਚ ਨਵਾਂ ਗਿਆਨ ਇਕੱਠਾ ਕਰਨ ਦੀ ਕੋਸ਼ਿਸ਼ ਕਰ ਰਿਹਾ ਹੈ ।                                           ਭਾਰਤ ਵਿੱਚ ਸਮਾਜ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰ ਦਾ ਵਿਕਾਸ (Development of Sociology in India)ਭਾਰਤ ਵਿੱਚ ਸਮਾਜ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰ ਦੇ ਵਿਕਾਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਕਈ ਭਾਗਾਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਵੰਡਿਆ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ-1. ਪਾਚੀਨ ਭਾਰਤ ਵਿੱਚ ਸਮਾਜ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰ ਦਾ ਵਿਕਾਸ (Development of Sociology in Ancient India) – ਭਾਰਤ ਵਿੱਚ ਸਮਾਜ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰ ਦੀ ਉੱਤਪਤੀ ਪ੍ਰਾਚੀਨ ਕਾਲ ਤੋਂ ਹੀ ਸ਼ੁਰੂ ਹੋ ਗਈ ਸੀ । ਮਹਾਂਰਿਸ਼ੀ ਵੇਦ ਵਿਆਸ ਨੇ ਚਾਰਾਂ ਵੇਦਾਂ ਦਾ ਸੰਕਲਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਅਤੇ ਮਹਾਂਭਾਰਤ ਵਰਗੇ ਮਹਾਂਕਾਵਿ ਦੀ ਰਚਨਾ ਕੀਤੀ । ਰਾਮਾਇਣ ਦੀ ਰਚਨਾ ਕੀਤੀ ਗਈ । ਇਹਨਾਂ ਤੋਂ ਇਲਾਵਾ ਉਪਨਿਸ਼ਦਾਂ, ਪੁਰਾਣਾਂ ਅਤੇ ਸਮਰਿਤੀਆਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਪ੍ਰਾਚੀਨ ਭਾਰਤੀ ਦਰਸ਼ਨ ਦੀ ਵਿਸਤਾਰ ਨਾਲ ਵਿਆਖਿਆ ਕੀਤੀ ਗਈ ਹੈ । ਇਹਨਾਂ ਸਾਰੀਆਂ ਲਿਖਤਾਂ ਤੋਂ ਪਤਾ ਚਲਦਾ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਪ੍ਰਾਚੀਨ ਭਾਰਤ ਵਿੱਚ ਵਿਚਾਰਧਾਰਾ ਉੱਚ ਪੱਧਰ ਦੀ ਸੀ । ਇਹਨਾਂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥਾਂ ਤੋਂ ਪਤਾ ਚਲਦਾ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਪ੍ਰਾਚੀਨ ਭਾਰਤ ਦੀਆਂ ਸਮੱਸਿਆਵਾਂ, ਜ਼ਰੂਰਤਾਂ, ਘਟਨਾਵਾਂ, ਤੱਥਾਂ, ਮੁੱਲਾਂ, ਆਦਰਸ਼ਾਂ, ਵਿਸ਼ਵਾਸਾਂ ਆਦਿ ਦਾ ਡੂੰਘਾ ਅਧਿਐਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ । ਵਰਤਮਾਨ ਸਮੇਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਭਾਰਤੀ ਸਮਾਜ ਵਿੱਚ ਮਿਲਣ ਵਾਲੀਆਂ ਕਈ ਸੰਸਥਾਵਾਂ ਦੀ ਸ਼ੁਰੂਆਤ ਪ੍ਰਾਚੀਨ ਸਮੇਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਹੀ ਹੋਈ ਸੀ । ਇਹਨਾਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਵਰਣ, ਆਸ਼ਰਮ, ਪੁਰੂਸ਼ਾਰਥ, ਧਰਮ, ਸੰਸਕਾਰ, ਸੰਯੁਕਤ ਪਰਿਵਾਰ ਆਦਿ ਪ੍ਰਮੁੱਖ ਹਨ ।ਚਾਣਕਯ ਦਾ ਅਰਥ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰ, ਮਨੁਸਮਿਤੀ ਅਤੇ ਸ਼ੁਕਰਾਚਾਰਯ ਦਾ ਨੀਤੀ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰ ਵਰਗੇ ਰੀਥ ਪ੍ਰਾਚੀਨ ਕਾਲ ਦੀਆਂ ਪਰੰਪਰਾਵਾਂ, ਥਾਵਾਂ, ਮੁੱਲਾਂ, ਆਦਰਸ਼ਾਂ, ਕਾਨੂੰਨਾਂ ਉੱਤੇ ਕਾਫ਼ੀ ਰੋਸ਼ਨੀ ਪਾਉਂਦੇ ਹਨ । ਇਸ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਸਪੱਸ਼ਟ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਵੈਦਿਕ ਕਾਲ ਤੋਂ ਹੀ ਭਾਰਤ ਵਿੱਚ ਸਮਾਜ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰ ਦੀ ਸ਼ੁਰੂਆਤ ਹੋ ਗਈ ਸੀ ।ਮੱਧਕਾਲ ਵਿੱਚ ਆ ਕੇ ਭਾਰਤ ਵਿੱਚ ਮੁਸਲਮਾਨਾਂ ਅਤੇ ਮੁਗਲਾਂ ਦਾ ਰਾਜ ਰਿਹਾ, ਉਸ ਸਮੇਂ ਦੀਆਂ ਲਿਖਤਾਂ ਤੋਂ ਭਾਰਤ ਦੀ ਉਸ ਸਮੇਂ ਦੀ ਵਿਚਾਰਧਾਰਾ, ਸੰਸਥਾਵਾਂ, ਸਮਾਜਿਕ ਵਿਵਸਥਾ, ਸੰਸਕ੍ਰਿਤੀ ਦਾ ਗਿਆਨ ਪ੍ਰਾਪਤ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ ।2. ਸਮਾਜ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰ ਦਾ ਰਸਮੀ ਸਥਾਪਨਾ ਯੁੱਗ (Formal Establishment Era of Sociology) – 1914 ਤੋਂ 1947 ਤੱਕ ਦਾ ਸਮਾਂ ਭਾਰਤ ਵਿੱਚ ਸਮਾਜ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰ ਦੀ ਸਥਾਪਨਾ ਦਾ ਕਾਲ ਮੰਨਿਆ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ । ਭਾਰਤ ਵਿੱਚ ਸਭ ਤੋਂ ਪਹਿਲਾਂ ਬੰਬਈ ਯੂਨੀਵਰਸਿਟੀ ਵਿੱਚ 1914 ਵਿੱਚ ਗੈਜੂਏਟ ਪੱਧਰ ਉੱਤੇ ਸਮਾਜ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰ ਪੜ੍ਹਾਉਣ ਦਾ ਕੰਮ ਸ਼ੁਰੂ ਹੋਇਆ । 1919 ਤੋਂ ਅੰਗਰੇਜ਼ ਸਮਾਜ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰੀ ਪੈਟਿਕ ਗਿੱਡਸ (Patric Geddes) ਨੇ ਇੱਥੇ ਐੱਮ.ਏ. ਪੱਧਰ ਉੱਤੇ ਸਮਾਜ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰ ਪੜ੍ਹਾਉਣ ਦਾ ਕੰਮ ਸ਼ੁਰੂ ਕੀਤਾ । ਜੀ.ਐੱਸ. ਘੁਰੀਏ (G.S. Ghurye) ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਹੀ ਵਿਦਿਆਰਥੀ ਸਨ । ਪ੍ਰੋਫ਼ੈਸਰ ਵੀਰਜੇਂਦਰਨਾਥਸ਼ੀਲ ਦੀਆਂ ਕੋਸ਼ਿਸ਼ਾਂ ਨਾਲ 1917 ਵਿੱਚ ਕਲਕੱਤਾ ਯੂਨੀਵਰਸਿਟੀ ਵਿੱਚ ਸਮਾਜ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰ ਪੜ੍ਹਾਉਣ ਦਾ ਕੰਮ ਸ਼ੁਰੂ ਹੋਇਆ । ਪ੍ਰਸਿੱਧ ਸਮਾਜ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰੀ ਡਾ: ਰਾਧਾ ਕਮਲ ਮੁਖਰਜੀ ਅਤੇ ਡਾ: ਡੀ.ਐੱਨ. ਮਜੂਮਦਾਰ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਹੀ ਵਿਦਿਆਰਥੀ ਸਨ । ਚਾਹੇ 1947 ਤੱਕ ਭਾਰਤ ਵਿੱਚ ਸਮਾਜ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰ ਦੇ ਵਿਕਾਸ ਦੀ ਗਤੀ ਘੱਟ ਸੀ ਪਰ ਉਸ ਸਮੇਂ ਤੱਕ ਦੇਸ਼ ਦੀਆਂ ਬਹੁਤ ਸਾਰੀਆਂ ਯੂਨੀਵਰਸਿਟੀਆਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਪੜ੍ਹਾਉਣ ਦਾ ਕੰਮ ਸ਼ੁਰੂ ਹੋ ਚੁੱਕਾ ਸੀ ।3. ਸਮਾਜ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰ ਦਾ ਪਸਾਰ ਯੁੱਗ (Expansion Era of Sociology) – 1947 ਵਿੱਚ ਆਜ਼ਾਦੀ ਤੋਂ ਬਾਅਦ ਦੇਸ਼ ਦੀਆਂ ਬਹੁਤ ਸਾਰੀਆਂ ਯੂਨੀਵਰਸਿਟੀਆਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਸਮਾਜ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰ ਨੂੰ ਸੁਤੰਤਰ ਵਿਸ਼ੇ ਦੇ ਰੂਪ ਵਿੱਚ ਮਾਣਤਾ ਪ੍ਰਾਪਤ ਹੋਈ । ਵਰਤਮਾਨ ਸਮੇਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੇਸ਼ ਦੇ ਲਗਪਗ ਸਾਰੇ ਕਾਲਜਾਂ ਤੇ ਯੂਨੀਵਰਸਿਟੀਆਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਇਸ ਵਿਸ਼ੇ ਨੂੰ ਪੜ੍ਹਾਇਆ ਜਾ ਰਿਹਾ ਹੈ । ਯੂਨੀਵਰਸਿਟੀਆਂ ਤੋਂ ਇਲਾਵਾ ਕਈ ਸੰਸਥਾਵਾਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਖੋਜ ਦੇ ਕੰਮ ਚੱਲ ਰਹੇ ਹਨ । Tata Institute of Social Sciences, Mumbai, Institute of Social Sciences Agra, Institute of Sociology and Social work, Lucknow, I.I.T. Kanpur and I.I.T Delhi. ਕੁੱਝ ਦੇਸ਼ ਦੇ ਅਜਿਹੇ ਪ੍ਰਮੁੱਖ ਸੰਸਥਾਨ ਹਨ ਜਿੱਥੇ ਸਮਾਜ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰੀ ਖੋਜਾਂ ਦੇ ਕੰਮ ਕੀਤੇ ਜਾ ਰਹੇ ਹਨ । ਇਹਨਾਂ ਨਾਲ ਸਮਾਜ ਸ਼ਾਸਤਰੀ ਵਿਧੀਆਂ ਅਤੇ ਇਸਦੇ ਗਿਆਨ ਵਿੱਚ ਲਗਾਤਾਰ ਵਾਧਾ ਹੋ ਰਿਹਾ ਹੈ ।"},{"question":"Hãy trả lời câu hỏi sau đây. Người đóng vai chính trong bộ phim Whatever Happened to Baby Jane là ai?","answer":"Người đóng vai chính trong bộ phim \\"Whatever Happened to Baby Jane?\\" là Bette Davis."},{"question":"家庭暴力对孩子的抚养权有影响吗？","answer":"抚养权方面，要按照那一方的抚养对孩子成长有利原则，法院确定抚养权时会综合考虑孩子现在的生活状态、夫妻双方的工作收入及道德方面及孩子是否一直由一方父母在抚养等因素来判断。在我国，根据婚姻家庭方面的法律规定及相关司法解释，对未成年子女直接抚养权的确立主要有以下原则：1、以有利于子女身心健康，保障子女的合法权益为原则;2、哺乳期内的子女，以随哺乳的母亲抚养为原则;3、哺乳期后的子女，以双方协商优先，不能达成协议时，以子女的权益和双方的具体情况进行判决为补充为原则;4、对十周岁以上的未成年子女随父或随母生活发生争执的，以适当考虑未成年子女的意见为原则没有扶养孩子一方应支付抚养费，抚养费一般是未抚养孩子一方收入的20-30%。抚养费包括生活费、教育费、医疗费等。具体抚养费的确定要根据当地生活水平及孩子可能的实际生活花费来确定。《中华人民共和国民法典》第一千零八十四条父母与子女间的关系，不因父母离婚而消除。离婚后，子女无论由父或者母直接抚养，仍是父母双方的子女。离婚后，父母对于子女仍有抚养、教育、保护的权利和义务。离婚后，不满两周岁的子女，以由母亲直接抚养为原则。已满两周岁的子女，父母双方对抚养问题协议不成的，由人民法院根据双方的具体情况，按照最有利于未成年子女的原则判决。子女已满八周岁的，应当尊重其真实意愿。"},{"question":"కింది ప్రశ్నకు సమాధానం ఇవ్వండివిక్షిప్త ప్రావస్థ, విక్షేపణ యానకం వీటి మధ్య గల అన్యోన్య చర్యల ఆధారంగా కొల్లాయిడ్లను ఎలా వర్గీకరిస్తారు?","answer":"విక్షిప్త ప్రావస్థ(ద్రావితం) కణ పరిమాణం 1mµ – lµ వరకు ఉండే ద్విగుణాత్మక విజాతి వ్యవస్థను కొల్లాయిడ్లు అంటారు.కొల్లాయిడ్ల వర్గీకరణ :విక్షిప్త ప్రావస్థ మరియు విక్షేపక యానకం మధ్యగల సంబంధం ఆధారంగా వర్గీకరణ జరిగింది.ఎ) లయోఫిలిక్ కొల్లాయిడ్లు (ద్రవ ప్రియ కొల్లాయిడ్లు) :వీటిలో విక్షేపక యానకంకూ,, విక్షిప్త ప్రావస్థకీ మధ్య ఎక్కువ ఆపేక్ష ఉంటుంది.ఉదా : స్టార్చ్ కొల్లాయిడ్ ద్రావణం లయోఫిలిక్.బి) లయోఫోబిక్ కొల్లాయిడ్లు (ద్రవ విరోధి కొల్లాయిడ్లు) :వీటిలో విక్షిప్త ప్రావస్థకూ, విక్షేపక యానకానికీ మధ్య ఆపేక్ష ఉండదు.ఉదా : గోల్డ్ కొల్లాయిడ్ ద్రావణం లయోఫోబిక్.."},{"question":"Wanene sarki na farko a Kano?","answer":"Sarki na farko a Kano shi ne Bagauda, Masarautar Hausa ta Kano ta kasance a kan wani tsohon mazaunin Tudun Dala. Yayin da a baya akwai kananan masarautu a yankin, kamar yadda littafin tarihin Kano ya nuna, Bagauda, ​​jikan jarumin tatsuniyar Bayajidda, ya zama sarkin Kano na farko a shekarar 999, ya yi sarauta har zuwa 1063."},{"question":"Inona avy ireo vokatra ratsy amin'ny finonana ny anjara?","answer":"Ireto avy no vokatra ratsy amin'ny finonana ny anjara:- Mahatonga fisarahana.-Fialonan’ny fiarahamonina ireo manana lafim-piainana tsaratsara- Mitarika finoanoam-poana- Fanomezan-tsiny ny Razana- Fanararaotam-pahefana ataon’ny tsara fari-piainana- Miteraka tsy fandraisana andraikitra- Miteraka famoizam-po- Mahatonga fanilikilihana"},{"question":"సమతల దర్పణాన్ని కుంభాకార దర్పణంగా ఉపయోగించవచ్చా? కాకపోతే ఎందుకు?","answer":"లేదు, మనం సమతల దర్పణాన్ని వెనుక వాహనాలను చూడటానికి ఉపయోగించలేము. ఎందుకంటే సాదా అద్దం వాహనం వెనుక ఉన్న అన్ని వస్తువులను చూపించలేదు. కుంభాకార దర్పణం వస్తువులను చిన్నదిగా చూపటం వలన దూరపు వాహనాలు కూడా కనిపిస్తాయి. కాబట్టి మనం కుంభాకార దర్పణాన్ని వెనుక వాహనాలను చూడటానికి ఉపయోగిస్తాము."},{"question":"“冰淇淋”是從哪國傳進的外來語？","answer":"第一次有冰淇淋記載是出現在1769年的英格蘭。"},{"question":"Qual é a capital de Mónaco?","answer":"Mónaco."},{"question":"Aiza no ahitana an'ny Antakarana ? ","answer":"Ao amin' ny tendro avaratr' i Madagasikara no ahitana ny Antankarana, ao amin' ny faritanin' Antsiranana."},{"question":"பெரிய நகாங்களுக்கு அழகு சேர்ப்பவை ………………அ) மாடங்கள்ஆ) நகரங்கள்இ) வண்ணங்கள்ஈ) கோபுரங்கள்","answer":"கோபுரங்கள்"},{"question":"ਨਵੀਂ ਦਿੱਲੀ, 27 ਫਰਵਰੀਲੰਘੀ 14 ਫਰਵਰੀ ਨੂੰ ਸੀਆਰਪੀਐਫ ਦੇ ਕਾਫ਼ਲੇ ’ਤੇ ਹੋਏ ਹਮਲੇ ਅਤੇ ਵੱਖਵਾਦੀਆਂ ਅਤੇ ਦਹਿਸ਼ਤਪਸੰਦ ਗੁਰਪਾਂ ਦੀ ਫੰਡਿੰਗ ਨਾਲ ਸਬੰਧਤ ਕੇਸਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਦੱਖਣੀ ਕਸ਼ਮੀਰ ਵਿਚ ਐਨਆਈਏ ਨੇ 11 ਥਾਵਾਂ ’ਤੇ ਤਲਾਸ਼ੀਆਂ ਲਈਆਂ ਹਨ। ਜਾਂਚ ਏਜੰਸੀ ਵਲੋਂ ਜਾਰੀ ਕੀਤੇ ਗਏ ਇਕ ਬਿਆਨ ਵਿਚ ਕਿਹਾ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਮੁੱਦਸਰ ਅਹਿਮਦ ਖ਼ਾਨ ਅਤੇ ਸੱਜਾਦ ਭੱਟ ਦੇ ਘਰਾਂ ਦੀ ਤਲਾਸ਼ੀ ਲਈ ਗਈ ਜੋ ਕਿ ਜੈਸ਼-ਏ-ਮੁਹੰਮਦ ਦੇ ਸਰਗਰਮ ਦਹਿਸ਼ਤਪਸੰਦ ਅਤੇ ਪੁਲਵਾਮਾ ਹਮਲੇ ਦੇ ਪ੍ਰਮੁੱਖ ਮੁਲਜ਼ਮ ਮੰਨੇ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ।ਐਨਆਈਏ ਨੇ ਦੱਸਿਆ ਕਿ ਦੱਖਣੀ ਕਸ਼ਮੀਰ ਦੇ ਤਰਾਲ, ਅਵੰਤੀਪੋਰਾ ਅਤੇ ਪੁਲਵਾਮਾ ਖੇਤਰਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਸਰਗਰਮ ਜੈਸ਼-ਏ-ਮੁਹੰਮਦ ਦੇ ਕਾਰਕੁਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਘਰਾਂ ਦੀਆਂ ਤਲਾਸ਼ੀਆਂ ਲਈਆਂ ਗਈਆਂ ਹਨ।ਏਜੰਸੀ ਦਾ ਕਹਿਣਾ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਤਲਾਸ਼ੀਆਂ ਦੌਰਾਨ ਡਾਇਰੀਆਂ, ਗੁੱਝੀ ਭਾਸ਼ਾ ਵਿਚ ਲਿਖੇ ਸੰਦੇਸ਼ਾਂ ਸਮੇਤ ਅਹਿਮ ਦਸਤਾਵੇਜ਼ ਬਰਾਮਦ ਕੀਤੇ ਗਏ ਹਨ। ਜਾਂਚ ਏਜੰਸੀ ਨੇ ਦੱਸਿਆ ਕਿ ਦੱਖਣੀ ਕਸ਼ਮੀਰ ਵਿਚ ਤਿੰਨ ਵੱਖਵਾਦੀ ਆਗੂਆਂ ਮੁਹੰਮਦ ਸ਼ਬਾਨ ਡਾਰ, ਸ਼ੌਕਤ ਮੌਲਵੀ ਅਤੇ ਯਾਸਮੀਨ ਰਜ਼ਾ ਦੇ ਘਰਾਂ ਦੀ ਤਲਾਸ਼ੀ ਲਈ ਗਈ। ਇਸ ਦੌਰਾਨ ਐਨਆਈਏ ਟੀਮਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਵੱਡੀ ਤਾਦਾਦ ਵਿਚ ਦਸਤਾਵੇਜ਼ ਮਿਲੇ ਹਨ ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਸੰਪਤੀ ਦੇ ਵੇਰਵੇ, ਵਿੱਤੀ ਲੈਣ ਦੇਣ, ਮੋਬਾਈਲ ਫੋਨ ਅਤੇ ਸਿਮ ਕਾਰਡ ਸ਼ਾਮਲ ਹਨ।ਸਬੰਧਤ ਕੇਸਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਦੱਖਣੀ ਕਸ਼ਮੀਰ ਵਿਚ ਕਿਹੜੀ ਏਜੰਸੀ ਖੋਜ ਕਰ ਰਹੀ ਹੈ?","answer":"ਸਬੰਧਤ ਕੇਸਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਦੱਖਣੀ ਕਸ਼ਮੀਰ ਵਿਚ ਐਨਆਈਏ ਨੇ 11 ਥਾਵਾਂ ’ਤੇ ਤਲਾਸ਼ੀਆਂ ਲਈਆਂ ਹਨ।"},{"question":"Waxaad  Sheegtaa Nabigii laga soo saaray waddan afrikaan ah?","answer":" Wuxuu ahaa Nabi Muuse (cs) Wadanka  Laga soo saaray Waa Dalka Masar.    "},{"question":"Với chủ đề là BMC Software, đặt câu hỏi cho câu trả lời tương ứng như sau: \\"Trong năm 2011, công ty đã ghi nhận doanh thu hàng năm là 2,1 tỷ đô la, khiến nó trở thành công ty phần mềm lớn thứ 20 về doanh thu trong năm đó\\"","answer":"Công ty BMC Software đạt doanh thu hàng năm bao nhiêu trong năm 2011 và vị trí của nó trong danh sách các công ty phần mềm có doanh thu lớn nhất trong năm đó là gì?"},{"question":"Waa Tumey aheed gabadhii ugu horeysay ee hees soomaliya qaado?","answer":" waxey aheyd guduudo carwo"},{"question":"ጥያቄ:-ብዙውን ጊዜ በዓለም የመጀመሪያ መኪና እንደፈጠረ የሚነገርለት ማን ነው? ","answer":"መልስ:- ካርል ቤንዝ"},{"question":"Що сталося з замком Радзивілів в Олиці? ","answer":"З початку XVI століття і до 1939 року волинське містечко Олика було одним з родових гнізд династії Радзивілів, найдавнішого князівського роду в Європі. До наших днів збереглися князівський палац і величний колегіальний костел, архітектурна перлина Волині. Олика, що перейшла до Радзивілів на початку XV1 століття, 1586 року стала майоратним володінням, тобто її не можна було продати або роз­ділити, а успадковували її старші сини роду. З 1547 року Радзивіли мали титул князів Олики і Несвіжа. У 1558-1564 роках Микола Радзивіл Чорний побудував Олицький за­мок, перший замок бастіонного типу в Україні. 1640 року Альбрехт Ста­ніслав Радзивіл перетворив фортецю на палацовий комплекс. Замість фортечних стін виросли палацові корпуси, що утворили квадратний двір. В'їзд до двору вінчала висока вежа у стилі бароко. Замок, як і раніше, за­хищали бастіони, які обслуговували 202 гармати і великий гарнізон. Нині в корпусах колишнього замку розміщена психіатрична лікарня, проте туристам доступ на територію відкритий. "},{"question":"Inis dom faoin bhanna \\"The Beatles\\". ","answer":"Banna popcheoil ó Learpholl i Sasana ab ea The Beatles. An Fab Four a thugtar ar cheithre bhall rialta an bhanna amannta. Tá siad i measc na ngrúpaí is mó cáil agus is rathúla i stair an rac-cheoil.Tá níos mó ceirníní díolta ag The Beatles ná ag aon bhanna eile riamh i Stáit Aontaithe Mheiriceá, dar leis an Recording Industry Association of America. Sa Ríocht Aontaithe, scaoil siad níos mó ná 40 singil, albam agus EP a chuaigh go dtí barr na gcairteacha. Bhí an rath céanna acu i dtíortha eile, agus measann an comhlacht ceoil EMI go raibh níos mó ná aon bhilliún cheirnín díolta acu timpeall na cruinne faoin mbliain 1985. Sa bhliain 2004, roghnaigh an iris Rolling Stone iad mar uimhir a haon ar an liosta den 100 Ealaíontóir Ceoil is Fearr Riamh. De réir na hirise chéanna, bhí baint lárnach ag ceol an bhanna le cultúr na 1960idí, agus tá an tionchar a bhí acu ar an gcultúr pop le feiceáil fós sa lá atá inniu ann."},{"question":"A grande cidade mais ocidental da África é","answer":"Dakar. Dakar é a capital e a maior cidade do Senegal, na península do Cabo Verde. Fundada pelos franceses em 1857, é uma das quatro cidades históricas do Senegal e a antiga capital da África Ocidental Francesa (AOF). A sua localização na borda ocidental da África, na estreita península de Cabo Verde, favoreceu os primeiros colonos e o comércio com o Novo Mundo, e lhe dá uma posição privilegiada para intersecção das culturas africanas e europeias."},{"question":"Write a continuation for this paragraph - Dıbenko Mart 1921'de Mihail Tuhaçevski komutasındaki birliklerle Kronstadt Ayaklanmasının bastırılmasında yer alır. Ayrıca bu dönemde çıkan Tambov Ayaklanması","answer":"'nın bastırılmasında da görev yapar. Başarılarından dolayı Kızıl Bayrak Nişanı ile üç kez ödüllendirilir. Dıbenko devrim öncesinde ve sırasında yaşadıklarına dair çok sayıda eser yazar. Kitaplarındaki yüksek kalite onun gibi eğitim seviyesi düşük birisinin gerçek yazar olmadığına dair şüphelere yol açmıştır. 1922 yılında Genelkurmay Askerî Akademisini bitirir. Bu dönemde Kollontay ile ayrılacaklardır. Dıbenko ayrılık yüzünden intihara kalkışır, Kollontay ise ondan uzaklaşabilmek için yurtdışı elçilik görevi talep ederek ülke dışına çıkar. Dıbenko, Kollontay'dan sonra iki kez daha evlenecektir. Dıbenko Akademiden mezun olduktan sonra yeniden komutanlık görevi alır ve partiye yeniden kabul edilir. 1925 – 1928 yılları arasında Kızılordu Genelkurmay Başkanlığı Topçu ve İstihkam Komutanlığında görev alır. 1928 yılından sonra Orta Asya'da görevlendirilir. Burada sınır birliklerine komuta eder. 1930 yılında görevli olarak diğer subaylarla beraber Almanya'ya gönderilir."},{"question":"Ahoana no hanatsarana ny kalitaon'ny torimasoko?","answer":"Azonao atao ny manatsara ny kalitaon'ny torimaso amin'ny fitazonana ny fandaharam-potoana matory tsy tapaka, ny famoronana fahazarana matory alohan'ny hatoriana, ny fisorohana ny kafeinina sy ny efijery elektronika alohan'ny hatory, ary ny fiantohana fa ny tontolo iainanao dia milamina sy maizina."},{"question":"Please continue to write the following paragraph: Jupiter, often referred to as a gas giant is primarily composed of hydrogen and helium.","answer":" Its massive size, more than 300 times the mass of Earth, gives it a strong gravitational pull, influencing the orbits of other bodies in the solar system. Beneath its thick clouds lies a vast atmosphere, turbulent storms, and possibly a solid core. The planet's iconic Great Red Spot, a colossal storm larger than Earth, has raged for centuries. Jupiter's diverse moons, from icy Europa to volcanic Io, add to its intrigue, making it a focal point of planetary exploration and study."},{"question":"Asho maqede azigubuzele ngengubo.USithole wazikhuza sekuthi akamyabule,amsonge kanye nezingubo, amjikijele phandle umkakhe. Wacabangela umntwanawakhe ukuthi uzosuke abe yintandane kanti usemncane. Wathula isikhashana esadlaamathambo ekhanda, wangena embhedeni. Kwathi ngesikade bafika ubuthongo.Walala zwi kwaze kwasa.Ukusa kwabonwa nguye uMaNzimande. Igwebu lemfezi lalisalokhu lithe ciki entanyenikuyena. Wazithola ephoqelekile ukuba akhiphe ingonyuluka yakhe.'Yise kaMpisendlini, vuka uhambise uDumazile. Angisamdingi nje lapha kwami.Angisamdingi nje.' Athi ukuthula kancane uSithole, bese ethi:'Ngimhambise ngimyise kuphi?'1. Fingqa ngamaphuzu AMATHATHU izehlakalo ezaholela esigamekwenisokuhamba kukaSithole emzini wakhe.","answer":"UMaNzimande umqulisa icala lokuthi kungani uDumazile aqhubekeahlale kwakhe esitolo.• UMaNzimande wenqaba ukumenzela enye inkomishi yetiye umbuzaukuthi kanti uDumazile akamenzelanga yini.• USithole uthenga umuzi, uhambisa uDumazile kuwo.UMaNzimandeuphinda uyamdelela uma ethi ulambile umtshela ukuba uphethweyingculazi. Wanquma ukuhamba unomphela kwakhe, wafakaisehlukaniso enkantolo"},{"question":"නැපෝලියන් බොනපාට් , ප්‍රංශයේ අධිරාජයා ලෙස පත්වූයේ කුමන වසරේද ?","answer":"1804 වසරේදී"},{"question":"ਕੱਪੜੇ ਧੋਣ ਲਈ ਪਾਣੀ ਤੋਂ ਇਲਾਵਾ ਕੀ-ਕੀ ਸਮਾਨ ਚਾਹੀਦਾ ਹੈ ?","answer":"ਕੱਪੜੇ ਧੋਣ ਲਈ ਪਾਣੀ ਤੋਂ ਇਲਾਵਾ ਸਾਬਣ, ਟੱਬ, ਬਾਲਟੀਆਂ, ਚਿਲਮਚੀਆਂ, ਮੱਗ, ਰਗੜਨ ਵਾਲਾ ਬੁਰਸ਼ ਅਤੇ ਫੱਟਾ, ਪਾਣੀ ਗਰਮ ਕਰਨ ਵਾਲੀ ਦੇਗ, ਕੱਪੜੇ ਧੋਣ ਵਾਲੀ ਮਸ਼ੀਨ, ਸਕਸ਼ਨ ਵਾਸ਼ਰ ਆਦਿ ਦੀ ਲੋੜ ਹੁੰਦੀ ਹੈ ।"},{"question":"アメリカの作家でノーベル文学賞も受賞した、代表作が「エデンの東」といえばその作者は誰でしょう？","answer":"（ジョン・）スタインベックです。"},{"question":"சென்னைப் பல்கலைக்கழகத்தின் முதல் தமிழிப்பேராசிரியர் யார் ?","answer":"சென்னைப் பல்கலைக்கழகத்தின் முதல் தமிழிப்பேராசிரியர் ரா.பி. சேதுப்பிள்ளை.சென்னைப் பல்கலைக்கழகம் தமிழ்நாட்டுப் பல்கலைக்கழகங்களுள் ஒன்றாகும். இது 1851-ஆம் ஆண்டு சென்னையில் தொடங்கப்பட்டது. இஃது இந்தியாவின் பழமையான பல்கலைக்கழகங்களில் ஒன்றாகும். லண்டன் பல்கலைக்கழகத்தின் அடிப்படையில் உருவாக்கப்பட்ட இது, 5 செப்டம்பர் 1857-இல் இந்திய சட்டமன்றத்தின் கீழ் இணைக்கப்பட்டது. எனினும் இப்பல்கலைக்கழகம், நடுவண் அரசின் பல்கலைக்கழக மானிய ஆணைக்குழு அமைக்கும் வழிமுறைகளுக்கு உட்பட்டது. மருத்துவம், பொறியியல், சட்டம், அறிவியல், கலை முதலிய அனைத்துத் துறைகளும் இருந்தன. நீண்ட காலம் தமிழகத்தின் ஒரே பல்கலைக்கழகமாக விளங்கியது. இப்பொழுது சட்டம், பொறியியல், மருத்துவம் ஆகிய பிரிவுகள் பிற பல்கலைக்கழகங்களுடன் இணைக்கப்பட்டு விட்டன."},{"question":"Fan moy péeyum réwum Samoa","answer":"Péeyum réwum Samoa mu ngi tudu Apia"},{"question":"ઉમાશંકર જોશી ની \\"અમે ગીત ગગનનાં ગાશું\\" કવિતા લખો.","answer":"અમે ગીત ગગનનાં ગાશું રે,અમે ગીત મગનમાં ગાશું,કલ-કલ પૂજન સુણી પૂછશો તમે,અરે છે આ શું?અમે ગીત ગગનનાં ગાશું રે..સૂર્ય ચંદ્ર ને દીયો ઓલવી,ઠારો નવલખ તારા,હથેળી આડી રાખી રોકો,વરસંતી જલધારા,અમે સૂર સરિતમાં ન્હાશું રે..પંખી માત્રને મુનિવ્રત આપો,ચૂપ કરી દો ઝરણા,પૂરો બેડીમાં હૃદય હૃદય પર,નરતંતા પ્રભુ ચરણા,પૂર મૂકી મોકળાં ગાશું રે..બાળક હાલરડા માગે ને,યૌવન રસભર પ્યાલા,પ્રૌઢ ભજન ભણકાર ચહે,આપે કોઈ મતવાલા,અમે દિલ દિલ ને કંઈ પાશું રે.."},{"question":"يوجد ساعاتان على الحائط، ساعة منهم تدق أجراسها كل ثلاث ساعات، والثانية تدق أجراسها كل أربع ساعات، بعد كم ساعة يمكن لأجراس الساعتين أن تدقا معاً؟","answer":"بعد 12 ساعة تدق الساعاتان معاً."},{"question":"*إلى أي بلد يرجع أصل السيدة هاجر؟","answer":"مصر"},{"question":"السؤال: ما هي الحواميم السبعة المبدوءة ب(حم)؟","answer":"جابة: سور غافر، فصلت، الشورى، الزخرف، الدخان، الجاثية، الأحقاف."},{"question":"A Ki Sọ Pé Ki Wèrè Ṣe Òkú Ìyá Rẹ̀ Bi Ó Bá Ṣe Ri, Bi Ó Bá Ni Òhun Fẹ́ Sún Jẹ Nkọ́? – Never Trust An Unstable/Unpredictable Person With Life And Death Decision Making","answer":"Oriṣiriṣi wèrè ló wà, nitori pé ki ṣe wèrè ti ó wọ àkísà ni ìgboro tàbi já sita nikan ni wèrè.  Ẹnikẹni ti o nhu ìwà burúkú tàbi ṣe ìpinnu burúkú ni Yorùbá npè ni “wèrè”.Ìpinnu ṣi ṣe, ṣe pàtàki ni ayé àtijọ́ àti òde òní.  Òwe Yorùbá sọ wi pé “Bi ará ilé ẹni bá njẹ kòkòrò búburú, hẹ̀rẹ̀-huru rẹ̀ kò ni jẹ́ ki a sùn ni òru”.  Àbáyọrí ìpinnu tàbi èrò burúkú kò pin si ọ̀dọ̀ ẹbi àwọn ti ó wà ni àyíká elérò burúkú, ó lè kan gbogbo àgbáyé. Fún àpẹrẹ, kò si ìyàtọ̀ laarin wèrè tó já sita nitori wèrè ni Yorùbá npe ọkọ tàbi ìyàwó ti ó ni ìwà burúkú, ẹbi burúkú, ọba ti ó nlo ipò rẹ lati rẹ́ àwọn ènìyàn rẹ̀ jẹ àti òṣèlu ti ó nja ilú ni olè lati kó owó ti wọn ji lọ si òkè òkun nibiti ohun amáyédẹrùn ti ilú wọn kò ni wà.Gẹ́gẹ́ bi òwe Yoruba ti ó sọ wi pé “A ki sọ pé ki Wèrè ṣe òkú ìyá rẹ̀ bi ó bá ṣe ri, bi ó bá ni òhun fẹ́ sún jẹ nkọ́?” Ìtumọ̀ òwe yi ni wi pé ìpinnu pàtàki bi ìyè àti ikú kò ṣe é gbé lé wèrè lọ́wọ́. Ó yẹ ki àwọn ènìyàn gidi ti ori rẹ pé dásí ọkọ tàbi ìyàwó, ọba tàbi àwọn ti ó wà ni ipò agbára, òṣèlu ti o nfi ipò wọn jalè àti àwọn ti ó nhu ìwà burúkú yi lati din àbáyọrí ìwà burúkú lóri ẹbí, alá-dúgbò àti àgbáyé kù."},{"question":"Fenoy ny banga _\\"Izay to fo _\\"","answer":"Izay to fo mpamosavy."},{"question":"व्यक्तिच्या जीवनातील आवश्यक संस्कारापैकी शेवटचे संस्कार कोणते ?","answer":"व्यक्तिच्या जीवनातील आवश्यक संस्कारापैकी शेवटचे संस्कार अंतिम संस्कार आहे. याचा मतलब त्यात्रुप्ति असते की आदमीच्या मृत्युनंतर मृतदेहाची देखरेख आणि अंतिम संस्कार कसे केले जाते. इसे 'अंत्येष्टि' किंवा 'अंत्यक्रिया' आणि 'अंतिम संस्कार' म्हणतात.अंतिम संस्काराची प्रक्रिया भिन्न धर्मांनी विविधपणे केलीत, परंतु आपल्या समाजातील, आपल्या धर्मातील किंवा आपल्या क्षेत्रिय आणि सांस्कृतिक विशेषतेताने यात्रुप्तिच्या उपायांची अनुसरण केलीत. याचे मतलब असे असू शकते की मृत्युनंतर मृतदेह अग्निदेवाच्या समीप या दहनालयात येतो, किंवा इतर स्थानिक प्रक्रियेच्या अनुसरणात असू शकतो.यात्रुप्तिच्या अंतिम संस्काराची प्रक्रिया व्यक्तींच्या आणि त्याच्या कुटुंबाच्या धार्मिक आणि सांस्कृतिक प्राथमिकतांच्या आधारावर ठरवली जाते."},{"question":"将棋で、最初に動かすことの出来ない駒は角行と何でしょう？","answer":"桂馬"},{"question":"ලෝකය වටා යාමට හේතුව කුමක්ද?","answer":"සමහරු පවසන්නේ මුදල් ලෝකය වටා ගමන් කරන බවයි, තවත් සමහරු පවසන්නේ එය ආදරය බවයි. ලෝකය වටා ගමන් කරන ඉන්ධනය සංගීතය බව පවා යෝජනා කර ඇත. කෙසේ වෙතත් මෙම පැහැදිලි කිරීම් මානව අධ්‍යාත්මිකත්වය සහ අවශ්‍යතා මත පදනම් වේ. අනෙකුත් ජීවීන් සම්බන්ධයෙන් ගත් කල, ජීවත් වීමට ඇති ආශාව ලෝකය වටා ගමන් කරයි. යථාර්ථයේ දී ලෝකය භෞතිකව තමා වටා යාමට පටන් ගත්තේය, එහි අක්ෂය වටා භ්‍රමණය විය, එය සෑදී ඇති ආකාරය නිසාය."},{"question":"What does \\"no crust, no rice\\" mean?","answer":"This phrase means that every incident has its scars."},{"question":"පහත වචනයට අදාළ විරුද්ධ පද කුමක්ද?සමගි  ","answer":"අසමගි"},{"question":"Sukurkite atsakymą į šį sudėtingą klausimą: kokia kita mokykla yra tame pačiame priemiestyje kaip ir Ganos policijos koledžas?","answer":"Ganos Technologijų universiteto kolegija"},{"question":"અહીં એક ગુજરાતી પ્રાર્થના ની શરૂઆત ની પંક્તિઓ નીચે આપેલી છે: \\"એક જ દે ચિનગારી, મહાનલ!એક જ દે ચિનગારી.ચકમક લોઢું ઘસતાં ઘસતાં ખરચી જિંદગી સારી,જામગરીમાં તણખો ન પડ્યો, ન ફળી મહેનત મારી.મહાનલ! એક જ દે ચિનગારી..\\"આ પ્રાર્થના ની આગળની પંક્તિઓ લખો.","answer":"એક જ દે ચિનગારી, મહાનલ!એક જ દે ચિનગારી.ચકમક લોઢું ઘસતાં ઘસતાં ખરચી જિંદગી સારી,જામગરીમાં તણખો ન પડ્યો, ન ફળી મહેનત મારી.મહાનલ! એક જ દે ચિનગારી..ચાંદો સળગ્યો, સૂરજ સળગ્યો, સળગી આભઅટારી,ના સળગી એક સગડી મારી, વાત વિપતની ભારી.મહાનલ! એક જ દે ચિનગારી..ઠંડીમાં મુજ કાયા થથરે, ખૂટી ધીરજ મારી,વિશ્વાનલ હું અધીક ન માગું, માગું એક ચિનગારી.મહાનલ! એક જ દે ચિનગારી.."},{"question":"the average amount of customers yearly income: 151551.35the most common marital status of the customers is marriedmost common educational level is graduateand the average age is 50.9, maximum age is 80 and the minimum age is -64 so I'll assume it is 0, and households tend to have teensBased on your understanding of the customer data, how would you describe the typical customer for your company?","answer":"Your typical customer appears to be a relatively affluent, well-educated individual, often married, and potentially in the later stages of their career or retirement. They are likely part of households that include teenagers, which may have implications for the types of products or services your company offers or markets to this customer base."},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਆਸਾ ਮਹਲਾ ੫ ॥ਪ੍ਰਥਮੇ ਮਤਾ ਜਿ ਪਤ੍ਰੀ ਚਲਾਵਉ ॥ਦੁਤੀਏ ਮਤਾ ਦੁਇ ਮਾਨੁਖ ਪਹੁਚਾਵਉ ॥ਤ੍ਰਿਤੀਏ ਮਤਾ ਕਿਛੁ ਕਰਉ ਉਪਾਇਆ ॥ਮੈ ਸਭੁ ਕਿਛੁ ਛੋਡਿ ਪ੍ਰਭ ਤੁਹੀ ਧਿਆਇਆ ॥੧॥ਮਹਾ ਅਨੰਦ ਅਚਿੰਤ ਸਹਜਾਇਆ ॥ਦੁਸਮਨ ਦੂਤ ਮੁਏ ਸੁਖੁ ਪਾਇਆ ॥੧॥ ਰਹਾਉ ॥ਸਤਿਗੁਰਿ ਮੋ ਕਉ ਦੀਆ ਉਪਦੇਸੁ ॥ਜੀਉ ਪਿੰਡੁ ਸਭੁ ਹਰਿ ਕਾ ਦੇਸੁ ॥ਜੋ ਕਿਛੁ ਕਰੀ ਸੁ ਤੇਰਾ ਤਾਣੁ ॥ਤੂੰ ਮੇਰੀ ਓਟ ਤੂੰਹੈ ਦੀਬਾਣੁ ॥੨॥ਤੁਧਨੋ ਛੋਡਿ ਜਾਈਐ ਪ੍ਰਭ ਕੈਂ ਧਰਿ ॥ਆਨ ਨ ਬੀਆ ਤੇਰੀ ਸਮਸਰਿ ॥ਤੇਰੇ ਸੇਵਕ ਕਉ ਕਿਸ ਕੀ ਕਾਣਿ ॥ਸਾਕਤੁ ਭੂਲਾ ਫਿਰੈ ਬੇਬਾਣਿ ॥੩॥ਤੇਰੀ ਵਡਿਆਈ ਕਹੀ ਨ ਜਾਇ ॥ਜਹ ਕਹ ਰਾਖਿ ਲੈਹਿ ਗਲਿ ਲਾਇ ॥ਨਾਨਕ ਦਾਸ ਤੇਰੀ ਸਰਣਾਈ ॥ਪ੍ਰਭਿ ਰਾਖੀ ਪੈਜ ਵਜੀ ਵਾਧਾਈ ॥੪॥੫॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 371 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਅਰਜਨ ਦੇਵ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਬਾਣੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਹਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"ਪਹਿਲਾਂ ਮੈਨੂੰ ਸਲਾਹ ਦਿੱਤੀ ਗਈ ਕਿ (ਵੈਰੀ ਬਣ ਕੇ ਆ ਰਹੇ ਨੂੰ) ਚਿੱਠੀ ਲਿਖ ਭੇਜਾਂ,ਫਿਰ ਸਲਾਹ ਮਿਲੀ ਕਿ ਮੈਂ (ਉਸ ਪਾਸ) ਦੋ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਅਪੜਾਵਾਂ, ਤੀਜੀ ਸਲਾਹ ਮਿਲੀ ਕਿ ਮੈਂ ਕੋਈ ਨ ਕੋਈ ਉਪਾਉ ਜ਼ਰੂਰ ਕਰਾਂ,ਪਰ ਹੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ! ਹੋਰ ਸਾਰੇ ਜਤਨ ਛੱਡ ਕੇ ਮੈਂ ਸਿਰਫ਼ ਤੈਨੂੰ ਹੀ ਸਿਮਰਿਆ ।੧।(ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਆਸਰਾ ਲਿਆਂ) ਬੜਾ ਆਤਮਕ ਆਨੰਦ ਮਿਲਦਾ ਹੈ, ਨਿਸਚਿੰਤਤਾ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ, ਆਤਮਕ ਅਡੋਲਤਾ ਪੈਦਾ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ, ਸਾਰੇ ਵੈਰੀ ਦੁਸ਼ਮਨ ਮੁੱਕ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ (ਕੋਈ ਦੁਸ਼ਮਨ ਨਹੀਂ ਜਾਪਦਾ, ਕੋਈ ਵੈਰੀ ਨਹੀਂ ਜਾਪਦਾ), (ਇਸ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ) ਅੰਤਰ ਆਤਮੇ ਸੁਖ ਮਿਲਦਾ ਹੈ ।੧।ਰਹਾਉ।ਸਤਿਗੁਰੂ ਨੇ ਮੈਨੂੰ ਸਿੱਖਿਆ ਦਿੱਤੀ ਕਿਇਹ ਜਿੰਦ ਤੇ ਇਹ ਸਰੀਰ ਸਭ ਕੁਝ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੇ ਰਹਿਣ ਲਈ ਥਾਂ ਹੈ । (ਇਸ ਵਾਸਤੇ) ਮੈਂ ਜੋ ਕੁਝ ਭੀ ਕਰਦਾ ਹਾਂ ਤੇਰਾ ਸਹਾਰਾ ਲੈ ਕੇ ਕਰਦਾ ਹਾਂ,ਤੂੰ ਹੀ ਮੇਰੀ ਓਟ ਹੈਂ ਤੂੰ ਹੀ ਆਸਰਾ ਹੈਂ ।੨।ਹੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ! ਤੈਨੂੰ ਛੱਡ ਕੇ ਹੋਰ ਜਾਈਏ ਭੀ ਕਿਹੜੇ ਪਾਸੇ? (ਕਿਉਂਕਿ) ਤੇਰੇ ਬਰਾਬਰ ਦਾ ਦੂਜਾ ਕੋਈ ਹੈ ਹੀ ਨਹੀਂ (ਜਿਸ ਨੂੰ ਨਿਸ਼ਚਾ ਹੋਵੇ ਉਸ) ਤੇਰੇ ਸੇਵਕ ਨੂੰ ਹੋਰ ਕਿਸ ਦੀ ਮੁਥਾਜੀ ਹੋ ਸਕਦੀ ਹੈ? (ਪਰ ਹੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ!) ਤੈਥੋਂ ਟੁੱਟਾ ਹੋਇਆ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਕੁਰਾਹੇ ਪੈ ਕੇ (ਮਾਨੋ) ਉਜਾੜ ਵਿਚ ਭਟਕਦਾ ਫਿਰਦਾ ਹੈ ।੩।ਹੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ! ਤੂੰ ਕੇਡਾ ਵੱਡਾ ਹੈਂ ਇਹ ਗੱਲ ਮੈਥੋਂ ਬਿਆਨ ਨਹੀਂ ਕੀਤੀ ਜਾ ਸਕਦੀ, ਤੂੰ ਹਰ ਥਾਂ (ਮੈਨੂੰ ਆਪਣੇ) ਗਲ ਨਾਲ ਲਾ ਕੇ ਬਚਾ ਲੈਂਦਾ ਹੈਂ । ਹੇ ਦਾਸ ਨਾਨਕ! (ਆਖ—ਹੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ!) ਮੈਂ ਤੇਰੀ ਸਰਨ ਹੀ ਪਿਆ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹਾਂ ।(ਹੇ ਭਾਈ!) ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਨੇ ਮੇਰੀ ਇੱਜ਼ਤ ਰੱਖ ਲਈ ਹੈ (ਮੁਸੀਬਤਾਂ ਦੇ ਵੇਲੇ ਭੀ ਉਸ ਦੀ ਮੇਹਰ ਨਾਲ) ਮੇਰੇ ਅੰਦਰ ਚੜ੍ਹਦੀ ਕਲਾ ਪ੍ਰਬਲ ਰਹਿੰਦੀ ਹੈ ।੪।੫।\\""},{"question":"问题：苏州有哪些著名的旅游景点？","answer":"答案：苏州有许多世界著名的旅游景点，如拙政园、留园、狮子林、寒山寺、周庄古镇等。"},{"question":"Viết bài báo có tiêu đề sau: Châu Âu đau đầu với bài toán an ninh năng lượng","answer":"Châu Âu tránh được kịch bản tồi tệ nhất khi quay lưng với khí đốt Nga, song bài toán an ninh năng lượng dài hạn vẫn chưa có lời giải.Từ khi xung đột Ukraine bùng phát, châu Âu biết họ sẽ sớm phải đối mặt nhiều vấn đề phức tạp liên quan đến khí đốt giá rẻ của Nga, nguồn năng lượng mà họ đã phụ thuộc trong nhiều thập kỷ để sưởi ấm và sản xuất.Đối với châu Âu, an ninh năng lượng luôn là sự đánh đổi. Năng lượng nhập khẩu giá rẻ luôn đi kèm nguy cơ khiến họ phải phụ thuộc vào bên cung cấp.Các quan chức châu Âu từng dự đoán rằng một mùa đông dài và lạnh giá năm 2022-2023 sẽ buộc họ phải cắt giảm các biện pháp trừng phạt với Nga, bởi các thành viên trong Liên minh châu Âu (EU) không thể để người dân nước mình chịu lạnh vì lợi ích của Ukraine.Tuy nhiên, mùa đông ấm áp vừa qua cùng các nỗ lực tiết kiệm khí đốt đã giúp châu Âu tránh được kịch bản này, đồng thời thúc đẩy họ từ bỏ chính sách Wandel durch Handel (Thay đổi bằng Thương mại) đã áp dụng hàng chục năm qua. Các nhà hoạch định chính sách Wandel durch Handel từng tin rằng nước Nga sẽ dần thay đổi và ngả về các giá trị phương Tây sau quá trình làm ăn lâu dài với châu Âu."},{"question":"અહીં નરસિંહ મહેતા રચિત કૃતિ એક \\"આ શો ચતુરાના ચિત્તનો ચાળો રે\\" ના શરૂઆતની પંકતિઓ આપેલ છે:\\"આ શો ચતુરાના ચિત્તનો ચાળો રે, એને કોઈ ન્યાળોરે. ટેક.બ્રહ્માએ નથી ઘડી ભામિની, એ તો આપે બનીને આવીરે\\"આ કૃતિની આગળની પંકતિઓ લખો.","answer":"આ શો ચતુરાના ચિત્તનો ચાળો રે, એને કોઈ ન્યાળોરે. ટેક.બ્રહ્માએ નથી ઘડી ભામિની, એ તો આપે બનીને આવીરે,ત્રણ લોકનું તેજ તારુણી, એ તો છબિ છબિલે બનાવીરે. એને.ઘડ્યું ઘરેણું એને રે હાથે, હાથે ભરી છે ચોળી રે;સાળુડે ભાત નારી કુંજરની, કસુંબાના રંગમાં બોળી રે. એને.વાસ પુર્યો એણે વૃન્દાવન માં, ગોવરધન થકી આવેરે;એ નારીની જાત કોઈ જાણે, તેનો ફેરો ફાવે રે. એને.કહીએ છીએ પણ કહ્યું ન માને, એ નારી નહીં ગીધારી રે,બ્રહ્મા ઈન્દ્ર શેષ શારદા એના ચરણ તણા અધિકારી રે. એને.અંતર હેત પોતાનું જાણી, એ તો આવે છે અંતરજામીરે.વ્યભિચાર મૂકી જુઓ વિચારી, એતો નરસૈંતાચો સ્વામીરે. એને."},{"question":"ඉතිහාසයේ සඳහන්වන පරිදි ලෝකයේ පළමුවරට \\"මාඝාත නීතිය\\" පැනවූ රජතුමා කවුද ?","answer":"ඉතිහාසයේ සඳහන්වන පරිදි ලෝකයේ පළමුවරට \\"මාඝාත නීතිය\\" පැනවූ රජතුමා ධර්මාශෝක අධිරාජයා ය."},{"question":"కింద ఇచ్చిన పదాలని విడదీసి సంధి పేరు మరియు దాని సూత్రం క్లుప్తంగా రాయండి:1. ముత్యము2. సూకరంబునకేల3. అదెట్లు4. ముద్దుసేయగ","answer":"1. ముత్యముముత్యము + అట్లు = ఉకారసంధిసూత్రము :- అత్తునకు సంధి బహుళమగును.2. సూకరంబునకేలసూకరంబునకు + ఏల = ఉకరా సంధిసూత్రము :- అత్తునకు సంధి బహుళమగును.3. అదెట్లుఅదెట్లు = అది + ఎట్లు = ఇకారసంధిసూత్రము :- ఏమ్యాదుల యిత్తునకు సంధి వైకల్పకముగాను.4. ముద్దుసేయగముద్దు + చేయగ = గసడదవాదేశసూత్రము :- కళలైన క్రియా పదములపై పరుషములకు గసడడవలు వైకల్పికముగానగు."},{"question":"Cuál es el tema principal de esta pregunta: ¿Qué fruta/vegetal es muy popular en Italia y está asociada de manera cercana con su cocina pero no es nativa de allí?","answer":"El tema principal es: Alimentos."},{"question":"Onde foram realizados os Jogos da Commonwealth em 1930?","answer":"Foram realizado em Hamilton, Canadá."},{"question":"నేను స్టెర్లింగు బాయిలరు అనే అంశం గురించి నా తరగతికి బోధించాలనుకుంటున్నాను. నేను వారికి హోంవర్క్‌గా చదవడానికి ఇవ్వగల కథనాన్ని మీరు నాకు వ్రాయగలరా? స్టెర్లింగు బాయిలరు యొక్క సామర్థ్యం ఎంత ? అనే ప్రశ్నకి ఇచ్చే కధనం లో సమాధానం ఉండాలి. దయచేసి కధనం తెలుగులో ఉండండి మరియు అధికారికంగా ఉండండి. ","answer":"స్టెర్లింగు బాయిలరు ఒక వాటరు ట్యూబు బాయిలరు.వంపు కలిగిన వాటరు ట్యూబు బాయిలరులో మూల వైవిధ్యం కల్గిన బాయిలరు స్టెర్లింగు బాయిలరు.ఆధునిక థెర్మల్ విద్యుతు ఉత్పాదక కేంద్రాలలో వంపు వాటరు ట్యూబులున్న బాయిలరులకు అధిక ప్రాధాన్యత ఉంది. స్టెర్లింగు బాయిలరు వంపు కల్గిన వాటరు ట్యూబు బాయిలరులలో ఎక్కువ పీడనంతో ఎక్కువ పరిమాణంతో నీటి ఆవిరిని ఉత్పత్తి చెయ్యగల కెపాసిటి ఉంది. స్టెర్లింగు బాయిలరు గంటకు 50 టన్నుల స్టీమును దాదాపు 60 kgf/ cm2 పీడనంతో ఉత్పత్తి చేయు సామర్థ్యం కల్గి ఉంది.ఎక్కువ పీడనంతో ఎక్కువ ఘనపరిమాణంతో స్టీమును ఉత్పత్తి చెయ్య గల్గడం వలన స్టెర్లింగు బాయిలరు సెంట్రల్ పవరు ప్లాంట్లలో ఎక్కువగా ఉపయోగిస్తారు."},{"question":"Qual desses filmes foi baseado na obra de Shakespeare?a) Muito Barulho por Nada (2012)b) Capitães de Areia (2011)c) A Dama das Camélias (1936)d) A Revolução dos Bichos (1954)e) Excalibur (1981)","answer":"Alternativa a: Muito Barulho por Nada (2012).Muitos filmes foram baseados na obra do poeta, ator e dramaturgo William Shakespeare (1564-1616). Muito Barulho por Nada (2012) é uma comédia baseada na peça homônima de Shakespeare. O filme, que retrata a história do casamento entre Hero e Cláudio foi dirigido por Joss Whedon."},{"question":"Tohizo izao ohabolana izao : \\"Mamerina indroa .....................\\" ","answer":"\\"Mamerina indroa manana ny antitra \\" "},{"question":"Дүйнө элдери арасындагы шайлоо тууралуу кызыктуу фактыларды жазып бере аласыңбы?","answer":" Дания- актёр-куудул Якоб Хаугард 1979-жылы өз өлкөсүнө парламентке тамашалуу программасы менен кандидаттыгын койгон. Ал шайлоочуларына күн тартибин:  8-8-8: сегиз саат эркин убакыт, сегиз саат эс алуу маалы жана калган сегиз саат уйку мезгили деп бөлүштүргөн. Дагы башка пункттарында: велосипед жолдорунда көп жүрүү, эң мыкты аба ырайын билдирип туруу, дүкөндөрдөгү эң аз кезектер бар болчу.1994-жылы ал акыры жетиштүү добуштарга ээ болуп, Даниянын парламентинде 4  жыл отурган."},{"question":"பென்சில் தயாரிக்கப்பயன்படும் மூலப்பொருட்கள் எவை ?","answer":"காரியம் , களிமண், மரக்கூழ்"},{"question":"「世界中の女性の首を真珠でしめてご覧に入れます」という言葉を残した、世界で初めて真珠の養殖法を開発した人物は誰でしょう？","answer":"御木本幸吉です。"},{"question":"የሚከተሉትን ነጥቦች በአጭሩ አጠቃልል:- መምህር አንለይ መኩሪያ ለአርባ ዓመታት በመምህርነት ሲያገለግሉ በሕይወት ዘመናቸው አንድ ሚሊዮን ብር የሚጠይቅ ፈተና ገጥሟቸው አያውቅም። በመቶዎች ብር ክፍያ ከጀመሩት የመምህርነት ሙያቸውም በአራት አስርት ዓመታት አገልግሎታቸው ውስጥ በደሞዝ በቀጥታ እጃቸው የገባው ገንዘብ ቢታሰብ አንድ ሚሊዮን ሊደርስ ስለመቻሉም እርግጠኛ አይደሉም። በዚህ ዓመት ሰኔ ወር መጀመሪያ ላይ ግን ባለሰቡት እና ባልጠበቁት ሁኔታ የበኩር ልጃቸውን ሕይወት ለመታደግ አንድ ሚሊዮን ብር ተጠይቀው በጡረታ ዘመናቸው ከማይወጡት ዕዳ ውስጥ ገብተዋል። በአማራ ክልል፣ ምሥራቅ ጎጃም ዞን የአማኑኤል ከተማ ነዋሪ የሆኑት መምህር አንለይ “የልጄን ሕይወት በአንድ ሚሊዮን ብር ከአጋቾች ላይ ገዝቻለሁ” ሲሉ ይናገራሉ።","answer":"አርባ አመታትን ያስቆጠረው መምህር አንለይ መኩሪያ አንድ ሚሊዮን ብር የሚጠይቅ ፈተና ገጥሞት አያውቅም። በመምህርነት ዘመናቸው ሁሉ አንድ ሚሊዮን ብር በቀጥታ ተቀብለው ስለመሆኑ እርግጠኛ አይደሉም። ሆኖም በዚህ አመት ሰኔ ወር ላይ የበኩር ልጃቸውን ህይወት ለማትረፍ አንድ ሚሊዮን ብር እንዲከፍሉ ተጠይቀዋል። መምህር አንለይ ይህንን ቤዛ ለአጋቾች እንደከፈሉ ይናገራል።"},{"question":"Snippet: వలిడిపనస, విశాఖపట్నం జిల్లా, అరకులోయ మండలానికి చెందిన గ్రామము.[1]ఇది మండల కేంద్రమైన అరకులోయ నుండి 36 కి. మీ. దూరం లోను, సమీప పట్టణమైన విశాఖపట్నం నుండి 136 కి. మీ. దూరంలోనూ ఉంది. 2011 భారత జనగణన గణాంకాల ప్రకారం ఈ గ్రామం 19 ఇళ్లతో, 97 జనాభాతో 29 హెక్టార్లలో విస్తరించి ఉంది. గ్రామంలో మగవారి సంఖ్య 44, ఆడవారి సంఖ్య 53. షెడ్యూల్డ్ కులాల సంఖ్య 0 కాగా షెడ్యూల్డ్ తెగల సంఖ్య 96. గ్రామం యొక్క జనగణన లొకేషన్ కోడ్ 583982[2].పిన్ కోడ్: 531149.I know that the answer to \\"వలిడిపనస గ్రామ పిన్ కోడ్ ఏంటి?\\" ","answer":"531149"},{"question":"س263- شكون الرئيس الامريكي اللي تفرض عليه انه يقدم الاستقالة ديال و قبل نهاية الولاية ديالو ؟","answer":"ج263- نيكسون"},{"question":"ஹுரோஷிமா தினம் எப்போது அனுசரிக்கப்படுகிறது?","answer":"ஹுரோஷிமா தினம் ஆகஸ்ட் 6இரண்டாம் உலகப் போரின் போது ஹிரோஷிமா மீது அணுகுண்டு வீசப்பட்டதன் 77வது ஆண்டு நினைவு தினம் ஆகஸ்ட் 6 ஆகும். இந்த குண்டுவெடிப்பில் சுமார் 140,000 பேர் இறந்தனர்; ஒவ்வொரு ஆண்டும் இந்த நாளில், உலகெங்கிலும் உள்ள மக்கள் அணுசக்தி யுத்தத்தின் தாக்கம் மற்றும் அமைதி மற்றும் நிராயுதபாணியை நோக்கிய உலகளாவிய ஒற்றுமைக்கான அழைப்பைப் பிரதிபலிக்கிறார்கள்."},{"question":"මෘදුකාංග  සංවර්ධකයින්ට තම සේවාදායකයින් සමඟ මෘදුකාංග ඉලක්ක ඵලදායී ලෙස සමපාත කරන්නේ කෙසේද?","answer":"ඕනෑම මෘදුකාංග සංවර්ධන ව්‍යාපෘතියක සාර්ථකත්වය සඳහා  ඉතා  වැදගත් වන්නේ සේවාදායක අපේක්ෂාවන් සමඟ මෘදුකාංග ඉලක්ක ඵලදායී ලෙස පෙළගැස්වීමයි. මෘදුකාංග සංවර්ධකයින් සහ ඔවුන්ගේ කණ්ඩායම්වලට   මෙම අරමුණු ඉටුකිරීම සඳහා  භාවිතා  කළ හැකි ප්‍රධාන උපාය මාර්ග මෙන්න:1. පැහැදිලි සන්නිවේදනය: විවෘත හා විධිමත් සන්නිවේදන මාර්ග ඇති කරන්න. තාක්ෂණික නොවන පාර්ශවකරුවන්ට පැහැදිලි සහ තේරුම් ගත හැකි භාෂාවක් භාවිතා කරන්න. නිත්‍ය රැස්වීම් සහ යාවත්කාලීනයන් සියලු දෙනාම එකම පිටුවක තබා ගැනීමට උදවු විය හැක.2. සේවාදායකයාගේ අවශ්‍යතා  සහ අපේක්ෂාවන් තේරුම් ගන්න: සේවාලාභියාගේ ව්‍යාපාරය, ඔවුන්ගේ කර්මාන්තය, අභියෝග සහ මෘදුකාංගය සමඟින් ඔවුන් සාක්ෂාත් කර ගැනීමට බලාපොරොත්තු වන දේ තේරුම් ගැනීමට කාලය ගත කරන්න. මෙම අවබෝධය මෘදුකාංගයේ ක්‍රියාකාරීත්වය සේවාලාභියාගේ අරමුණු සමග පෙළගැස්වීම සඳහා ඉතා වැදගත් වේ.3. යථාර්ථවාදී අපේක්ෂාවන් සකසන්න: දී ඇති කාල රාමුව සහ අයවැය තුළ කළ හැකි දේ පිළිබඳව විනිවිදභාවයෙන් සිටින්න. ව්‍යාපෘතියට බලපාන තාක්ෂණික සීමාවන් හෝ අභියෝග පැහැදිලි කරන්න.4. සැලසුම් ක්‍රියාවලියට සේවාලාභීන් සම්බන්ධ කර ගැනීම: ආරම්භක සැලසුම් අදියරේදී සේවාදායකයින් සම්බන්ධ කර ගන්න. මෙයට ව්‍යාපෘති විෂය පථය, කාල නියමයන්, අයවැය සහ ඕනෑම බාධාවක් සාකච්ඡා කිරීම ඇතුළත් විය හැක. මුල් අදියරවල සහයෝගීතාවය ව්‍යාපෘති ඉලක්ක සහ අවශ්‍යතා පිළිබඳව දෙපාර්ශවයටම අන්‍යෝන්‍ය අවබෝධයක් ඇති බව සහතික කරයි.5. ලේඛනගත කිරීම සහ වාර්තා කිරීම: අවශ්‍යතා, වෙනස්කම් සහ ප්‍රගතිය පිළිබඳ සවිස්තරාත්මක ලියකියවිලි පවත්වාගෙන යාම. මෙය එකඟ වූ ඉලක්ක සහ මඟ දිගේ ඕනෑම වෙනස් කිරීම් නිරීක්ෂණය කිරීමට උපකාරී වේ.7. පරිශීලක කේන්ද්‍රීය නිර්මාණය: සේවාදායකයාගේ ඉලක්කගත ප්‍රේක්ෂකයින් සමඟ සමපාත වන පරිශීලක අත්දැකීමක් නිර්මාණය කිරීම කෙරෙහි අවධානය යොමු කරන්න. අවසාන පරිශීලකයාගේ අවශ්‍යතා අවබෝධ කර ගැනීම සේවාලාභී අරමුණු සැබවින්ම සපුරාලන මෘදුකාංග සංවර්ධනය කිරීමට උපකාරී වේ.7. අවදානම් කළමනාකරණය: ව්‍යාපෘතියේ මුල් අවස්ථාවේදීම ඇති විය හැකි අවදානම් හඳුනාගෙන ඒවා  සේවාදායකයා  සමඟ සාකච්ඡා  කරන්න. මෙම අවදානම් කළමනාකරණය සඳහා සැලැස්මක් සකස් කර ගන්න.8. පුහුණුව සහ සහාය: සේවාලාභීන්ට පශ්චාත් යෙදවීමෙන් පසු පුහුණුව සහ සහාය ලබා දීම. ඔවුන් තේරුම් ගෙන මෘදුකාංගය ඵලදායී ලෙස භාවිතා කළ හැකි බව සහතික කිරීම ඔවුන්ගේ දිගුකාලීන ඉලක්ක සපුරා ගැනීම සඳහා  වැදගත් වේ."},{"question":"Đoạn văn sau đang nói về vấn đề gì? Ngày 31.7, Công ty CP BOT Trung Lương - Mỹ Thuận (doanh nghiệp dự án) đưa ra một thông cáo báo chí để khái quát về tình hình giao thông sau 90 ngày đưa vào vận hành cao tốc Trung Lương – Mỹ Thuận. Trong đó, doanh nghiệp dự án muốn được thu phí cao tốc Trung Lương - Mỹ Thuận để hoàn vốn nhưng phía Cơ quan quản lý nhà nước có thẩm quyền dự án là UBND tỉnh Tiền Giang chưa đưa ra ý kiến. Như vậy, nhiều khả năng doanh nghiệp này sẽ không thể thu phí chính thức vào ngày 1.8 như dự kiến đã tự đưa ra trước đó. Theo Công ty CP BOT Trung Lương - Mỹ Thuận, qua hơn 90 ngày vận hành phục vụ người dân lưu thông không thu phí (từ ngày 30.4.2022), cao tốc Trung Lương - Mỹ Thuận đã phục vụ hơn 2,2 triệu lượt xe (lưu lượng trung bình trong 30 ngày gần đây là 30.512 lượt xe/ngày đêm); hơn 50 vụ va chạm được ngành chức năng xử lý (không tính các trường hợp va chạm mà có sự thỏa thuận giữa chủ các phương tiện); cứu hộ 550 trường hợp xe gặp sự cố và tiếp nhận giải đáp 1.172 cuộc gọi của người tham gia giao thông thông qua tổng đài điện thoại khẩn cấp. Theo chủ đầu tư, trong số các vụ va chạm trên tuyến, nguyên nhân có tới 43% do lái xe chuyển hướng không đúng quy định, 36% chạy quá tốc độ, 6% sử dụng rượu bia,…Chủ đầu tư BOT cao tốc Trung Lương – Mỹ Thuận cũng viện dẫn nhiều lý do để được chấp nhận thu phí. Trong khi đó, phía UBND tỉnh Tiền Giang vẫn chưa đưa ra quan điểm về vấn đề này. Hoạt động mới nhất có liên quan cao tốc Trung Lương – Mỹ Thuận được tỉnh Tiền Giang đưa vào ngày 14.7 vừa qua, tại buổi làm việc với đoàn công tác của Bộ GTVT, ông Trần Văn Bon, Giám đốc, Sở GTVT Tiền Giang, cho biết Sở đã tham mưu trình UBND tỉnh dự thảo đề xuất xây cao tốc Trung Lương – Mỹ Thuận giai đoạn 2. Dự thảo này được trình lên Ban Thường vụ Tỉnh ủy Tiền Giang xem xét, cho ý kiến. Nếu Ban Thường vụ Tỉnh ủy Tiền Giang thông qua, UBND tỉnh sẽ kiến nghị Chính phủ xem xét phê duyệt.","answer":"\\"550 trường hợp xe ô tô phải cứu hộ trên cao tốc Trung Lương - Mỹ Thuận\\"."},{"question":" Өткөн чак деген эмне ?","answer":"Этиштин өткөн чагы кыймыл-аракеттин болуп өткөнүн билдирет. Ага эмне кылыптыр? Эмне кылды? Эмне кылган? Эмне кылган экен? Кантти? деген суроолор берилет. М и с а л ы: иштеди, эс алды, жашаган экен, сүйлөптүр ж. б."},{"question":"झलकमान गन्दर्भको जन्म कहिले भएको थियो ?","answer":"झलकमान गन्दर्भको जन्म  विसं. १९९२ साल बैशाख १२ गते भएको थियो। "},{"question":"كم قاطعا في فم الإنسان ؟","answer":"8 قواطع"},{"question":"冯诺依曼的主要贡献是什么？","answer":"冯诺依曼的主要贡献主要体现在以下几个方面：    计算机科学：冯诺依曼提出了存储程序的概念，奠定了现代计算机的理论基础。他还参与了EDVAC和MANIAC I等计算机的设计和开发。    量子力学：冯诺依曼提出了量子力学基础的数学理论，并对量子力学的发展做出了重要贡献。    博弈论：冯诺依曼与奥斯卡·摩根斯特恩合作，提出了博弈论的数学模型。"},{"question":"சிறுநீரக நோய்களின் அறிகுறிகள் என்னென்ன?","answer":"கீழ்கண்ட அறிகுறிகள் நபருக்கு நபர் மாறும். ஒருவருக்கு அடிப்படையில் இருக்கும் பின்னணி நோய்களும் அவற்றின் தீவிரங்களும் இந்த மாற்றங்களைக் கொண்டு வரும்.பொதுவான அறிகுறிகள்:முகம் வீங்குதல்: முகம் வீங்குதல், அல்லது பாதங்களும் அடிவயிறும் வீங்குதலும் இந்த நோய்களைக் காட்டிக் கொடுத்து விடும். இதில் ஒரு குறிப்பிடத்தக்க அம்சம் என்னவென்றால், வீக்கங்கள் முதலில் முகத்தில் ஆரம்பித்து கண் இமைகளைத் தொட்டு விட்டு முக்கியமாக காலை வேளையில் மிகவும் தெளிவாகத் தெரிய ஆரம்பிக்கும் நிலைகளாகும்சிறுநீரகங்கள் பழுதாவதே முகம் வீங்கும் அறிகுறியால் தெரிவிக்கும் செய்தி. ஆனால் வெறும் வீக்கங்கள் மட்டுமே போதுமான அறிகுறிகள் அல்ல. ஒருசில மாதிரியான சிறுநீரக பழுதுகளில் முறையாக வேலை செய்து கொண்டிருக்கும் சிறுநீரகங்கள் கூட வீக்கங்களைக் கொண்டு வரும். (உதாரணத்திற்கு நெஃப்ராடிக் சின்ட்ரோம் போன்ற நோய் வகைகள்) . ஒரு சிலருக்கு அந்த வீக்கமே காணப்படாமல் போகலாம். ஆனால் சிறுநீரகங்கள் குறிப்பிடப்படும் அளவுக்கு பாழாகி இருக்கும்.பசியின்மை மற்றும் வாந்தி எடுத்தல்: பசியின்மை, அசாதாரண வாய் ருசி, மற்றும் மிகக் குறைவாக உணவில் நாட்டம் போன்றவை பொதுவான அறிகுறிகளாகும். இது மேலும் மேலும் பழுதாகும்பொழுது, -விஷப் பொருட்களின் அளவு இரத்தத்தில் அதிகமாகும்பொழுது, - சம்பந்தப் பட்ட நோயாளிக்கு வாந்தி மற்றும் அடிக்கடி விக்கல்கள் வரும்.உயர்இரத்த அழுத்தம்: சிறுநீரகங்கள் பழுதடைந்தவர்களுக்கு உயர் இரத்த அழுத்தம் வருவது சகஜம். இளம் வயதில் அதாவது 30 வயதிற்குள் இது ஏற்பட்டால் அல்லது மருத்துவர் சோதிக்கும்பொழுது உயர் இரத்த அழுத்தம் உறுதியானால், சிறுநீரகக் கோளாறுகளே அதற்குக் காரணமாக இருக்கலாம்.இரத்தசோகையும் உடல்நலிவாதலும்: உடல்நலிவு, ஆரம்ப வலிகள், கவனக் குறைபாடு ஆகியவை இரத்த சோகை உள்ளவர்களுள் தென்படும் பொதுவான அறிகுறிகளாகும். மிக மிக மோசமாக சிறுநீரக நோய்கள் தாக்கும் பொழுது இது போன்ற அறிகுறிகள் ஆரம்பமாகலாம். பொதுவான சிகிச்சைகள் மூலம் இரத்த சோகையை குணப்படுத்த முடியவில்லையெனில், சிறுநீரக செயலிழப்பு என்பதை உறுதி செய்யலாம்.எதையும் குறிப்பிட்டுச் சொல்ல முடியாத தாக்கங்கள்: கீழ் முதுகில் வலி, உடல் வலி, அரிப்பு மற்றும் கால்களில் பிடிப்பு போன்றவை பொதுவாக சிறுநீரக நோய்களின் பிரதிபலிப்பு ஆகும்.வளர்ச்சி குன்றுதல் மற்றும் உயரம் குறைவாக இருத்தல் மற்றும் கால் எலும்புகள் வளைந்து கொடுத்தல் - இவை எல்லாம் சிறுநீரக நோய்கள் குழந்தைகளைத் தாக்கும்பொழுது வரக் கூடிய அறிகுறிகள்.சிறுநீர் சார்ந்த பொதுவான பிரச்னைகள்:1. சிறுநீரின் கன அளவு குறைதல் சிறுநீரக நோய்களின் பொதுவான அறிகுறியாகும்.2. சிறுநீர் கழிக்கும் பொழுது எரிச்சல் எடுத்தல், அடிக்கடி சிறுநீர் கழிதலும், சிறுநீர் கழிக்கும்பொழுது இரத்தமும் சேர்ந்து போதல் அல்லது சீழும் சேர்ந்து வருதல் என்பன சிறுநீர்ப் பாதையில் தொற்று ஏற்பட்டிருப்பதற்கான அறிகுறி.3. சிறுநீர்ப்பாதையில் ஏற்படும் அடைப்பு வலியை ஏற்படுத்தும் அல்லது சிறுநீர் அளவு மிகவும் குறைந்து துளித்துளியாக வெளி வரும். மிகவும் மோசமான நிலைகளில், சிறுநீர் கழிக்க முடியாத சூழ்நிலையும் உருவாகும்.மேற்கண்ட அறிகுறிகள் காணப்பட்டாலும் சிறுநீரக நோய் என்று முடிவுகட்டி விடக் கூடாது. இவ்வகை அறிகுறிகள் இருந்தாலும், மருத்துவரைக் கலந்து ஆலோசிப்பது அவசியமாகும். சோதனைகளைச் செய்தும் பரிசோதனைகளுக்கு உட்படுத்திக் கொண்டும் முடிவுக்கு வருவது நல்லது. கடுமையான சிறுநீரக நோய்கள் உள்ளிருந்து கொண்டே தொடர்வது கூட சாத்தியம் என்பதை அவசியம் உணர்ந்தாக வேண்டும். இது நெடுநாட்களாகவே கூட நீடித்துக் கொண்டு இருக்கலாம். வெளிப்புறத்தில் எந்தவித அறிகுறியும் இல்லாமல் தொடர்ந்து கொண்டு இருக்கலாம். இளம் வயதிலேயே, இரத்த அழுத்த நோய் இருப்பது கண்டு பிடிக்கப்பட்டால், சிறுநீரக நோய் எதுவும் தாக்கவில்லை என்பதை முதலில் ஊர்ஜிதப் படுத்திக் கொள்ளவும்."},{"question":"साहित्यका पिता को हुन ?","answer":"जेफ्री चौसर (/ˈtʃɔːsər/; c. 1340s - 25 अक्टोबर 1400) एक अंग्रेजी कवि, लेखक, र सिभिल सेवक थिए जो द क्यान्टरबरी टेल्सका लागि परिचित थिए। उहाँलाई \\"अंग्रेजी साहित्यको पिता\\" भनिन्छ, वा वैकल्पिक रूपमा, \\"अंग्रेजी कविताको पिता\\" भनिन्छ।"},{"question":"文章から主要な単語を特定し、それを定義しなさい。 「電動キックボード」は利用する人が増えていて、事故の心配があります。国は、電動キックボードを安全に使うための交通ルールを決めました。新しいルールになる電動キックボードは、いちばん速いスピードが時速20km以下で、スピードがわかるランプがついていることが必要です。運転免許は必要ありませんが、ヘルメットはできるだけかぶるようにします。16歳になっていない人は運転できません。走る場所は車道です。しかし、時速６kmまでの場合は自転車と同じように歩道を走ることができます。運転しながら携帯電話を使ったり、お酒を飲んで運転したりすると、違反になります。新しいルールは7月1日からです。","answer":"この文章の中での主要な単語とその定義は以下のようになっています。"},{"question":"fenoy ny banga :\\"Tsy mitsinjo ny farany ohatra _\\"","answer":"\\"Tsy mitsinjo ny farany ohatra ny andevo mahita fotsim-bary\\""},{"question":"Maak de volgende zin af: Vesting Luxemburg (Luxemburgs: \\"Festung Lëtzebuerg\\", Duits: \\"Festung Luxemburg\\", Frans: \\"Forteresse de Luxembourg\\") was een vesting ter verdediging van de groothertogelijke hoofdstad Luxemburg. Tijdens de Franse veldtocht in de Nederlanden ondervond de vesting een zeven maanden durend beleg van november 1794 tot juni 1795 voordat de stad zich moest overgeven. In 1830 deed het groothertogdom mee met de Belgische Revolutie, maar het Pruisische garnizoen in de citadel voorkwam dat dit ook in de hoofdstad zo was. Uiteindelijk zou het groothertogdom na negen jaar Belgisch bestuur worden opgesplitst langs taalkundige lijnen. Op het","answer":"Congres van Londen (1867) werd bepaald dat de vesting moest worden afgebroken naar aanleiding van de Luxemburgse kwestie. De kazematten zijn echter intact gebleven tot op de dag van vandaag. De restanten van de Vesting Luxemburg zijn door de Unesco erkend als werelderfgoed."},{"question":"applet-தமிழில் மொழிபெயர்க்கவும்","answer":"குறுநிரல்"},{"question":"Em 2021, qual foi o IDH de Zimbabwe?","answer":"0,593."},{"question":"Ko wakatsvaga kupi kukuraramisa?","answer":"Ndakatsvaga kupi kukuraramisa, ndakazofamba kubasa rangu uye ndakazomirira pamusha."},{"question":"Quem foi a primeira pessoa a andar na lua?","answer":"Neil Armstrong. Ele aterrissou em 20 de julho de 1969."},{"question":"为以下的原文给译文：文徵明临写《千字文》，日以十本为率，书遂大进。平生于书，未尝苟且，或答人简札，少不当意，必再三易之不厌，故愈老而愈益精妙。","answer":"文徵明贴写《文字文》，每天以写十本作为标准，书法就迅速进步起来。他平生对于写字，从来也不马虎草率。有时给人回信，稍微有一点不满意，一定三番五次地改写它，不怕麻烦。因此他的书法越到老年，越发精致美好。"},{"question":"Титаник кайсы жылы чөккөн?","answer":"1912"},{"question":"คุณช่วยฉันหยิบของได้ไหมคะ?","answer":"ต่อขอโทษด้วย เราไม่สามารถช่วยได้เพราะเราไม่มีร่างกาย"},{"question":"சிவயோக சுவாமியின் மேற்கோள் ஒன்றினை தரவும்.","answer":"தன்னைத் திருத்தாது யாத்திரைக்குப் போவதனாலாவதென்ன?"},{"question":"Given the below title and summary of an article, generate a short article or the beginning of a long article to go along with them. Title: ఆస్ట్రియా ప్రభుత్వాన్ని కూల్చిన రహస్య వీడియోnSummary: రష్యా యువతితో ఆస్ట్రియా ఫ్రీడం పార్టీ నేత ఉన్నట్టు ఒక వీడియో లీక్ అవడంతో మొదలైన వివాదం ఇప్పట్లో చల్లారేలా లేదు.nArticle (Max 500 characters):","answer":"ఈ కుంభకోణం వల్ల ఆస్ట్రియాలో ప్రస్తుత ప్రభుత్వం కుప్పకూలింది. ఆస్ట్రియా చాన్స్‌లర్ సెబాస్టియన్ ఖర్జ్‌ పదవి కోల్పోయారు. పార్లమెంటు ప్రత్యేక సమావేశాల్లో ప్రవేశ పెట్టిన అవిశ్వాస తీర్మానంలో ఖర్జ్ తగిన మద్దతు పొందలేకపోయారు. ఈ అవిశ్వాస తీర్మానానికి ఫ్రీడం పార్టీ, ప్రతిపక్ష పార్టీ సోషల్ డెమాక్రట్స్ మద్దతు ఇచ్చారు. ఆస్ట్రియా అధ్యక్షుడు అలెగ్జాండర్ వాన్ డెర్ బెలన్, ప్రస్తుత వైస్ చాన్సలర్ హర్ట్‌వింగ్ లాంగర్‌ను తాత్కాలిక నేతగా నియమించారు.అవిశ్వాస తీర్మానంలో మద్దతు పొందలేకపోయిన ఖర్జ్"},{"question":"Andininy voalohany: Nifarana tamin'ny 10 ora alina ny sarimihetsika.Andininy faharoa: Mbola nandeha tamin'ny 10:30 alina ny sarimihetsika.Mifanaraka ve ireo fehezanteny roa ireo?","answer":" Tsia, mifanohitra izy ireo."},{"question":"Sheeg Maxa La Oran Jiray Ninkii Dilay Cali Bin Abii Daalib?","answer":"Waxa La Oran Jiran C/Raxmaan Binu Muljin."},{"question":"Yeey ahaayeen labada nabi ee aan aroosin ama gursan? ","answer":"Waxey ahayeen Nabi Yaxye CS iyo Nabi Ciise CS ."},{"question":"من أكثر الأنبياء ذكراً بالقرآن ؟","answer":"الإجابة: موسى عليه السلام وذكر 236 مرة"},{"question":"Kan ku jecel waa kan ku dardaarma?...","answer":"𝐊𝐚𝐧 𝐤𝐮 𝐣𝐞𝐜𝐞𝐥 𝐰𝐚𝐚 𝐤𝐚𝐧 𝐤𝐮𝐮 𝐝𝐚𝐫𝐝𝐚𝐫𝐦𝐚 𝐤𝐡𝐞𝐲𝐫𝐤𝐚Hadalkii nebiga صلى الله عليه وسلم oo uu kudhahay mucaad:Mucaadow ; Allah baan ku dhaartaye waan ku jeclahay...  Waxaan kuu dardarmaya salaad weliba gadaasheeda inaad tiraahdo:-اللهُمَّ أعِنِّي على ذِكرِك وشُكرِك وحسنِ عبادتِك\\"💕🤍(Allahayow igu caawi xusitankaga , mahdintada , iyo wanaajinta cibaadooyinkaga).#Hadaba salaad weliba gadaasheeda eeynu aqrisano ducadaas gar ahaan kedib markaa atixayatka aqrino kahor inta aan salaama naqsan."},{"question":"Ọchịchịrị ","answer":"Olundi - ikiri"},{"question":"Tani ó kó àrùn Ebola wọ orílẹ̀ èdè Nàìjíríà? ","answer":"Patrick Oliver Sawyer ni ẹni tí ó kó àrùn Ebola wọ orílẹ̀ èdè Nàìjíríà. "},{"question":"కింది ప్రశ్నకు సమాధానం ఇవ్వండిసొంత వ్యాపారానికి, భాగస్వామ్య వ్యాపారానికి మధ్యగల వ్యత్యాసాలను తెలపండి.","answer":"సొంత వ్యాపారానికి, భాగస్వామ్య వ్యాపారానికి మధ్యగల తేడాలు:సొంత వ్యాపార సంస్థ1. వ్యక్తుల సంఖ్య: దీనిలో ఒకే వ్యక్తి ఉండును.2. స్థాపన: దీనిని స్థాపించుట చాలా సులభం.3. ఋణ బాధ్యత: సొంతవ్యాపారి ఋణబాధ్యత అపరిమితము.4. నమోదు: వ్యాపార సంస్థ నమోదు తప్పని సరికాదు.5. మూలధనము: ఒకే వ్యక్తి మూలధనాన్ని సమ కూరుస్తాడు, కాబట్టి మూలధనము తక్కువ.6. ఒప్పందము: ఒప్పందము అవసరము లేదు.7. వ్యాపార రహస్యాలు: ఒకే వ్యక్తి ఉండటం వలన వ్యాపార రహస్యాలు కాపాడుకోవచ్చు.8. శీఘ్ర నిర్ణయాలు: వ్యాపార నిర్ణయాలు త్వరగా తీసుకోవచ్చు.9. శ్రమ విభజన: ఒకే వ్యక్తి ఉండటము వలన శ్రమ విభజనకు అవకాశము లేదు.10. మంచి నిర్ణయాలు: ఒకే వ్యక్తి ఉండటం వలన తప్పుడు నిర్ణయాలు తీసుకోవచ్చు.భాగస్వామ్య వ్యాపార సంస్థ1. కనిష్ట సభ్యుల సంఖ్య 2. గరిష్ట సభ్యుల సంఖ్య బ్యాంకింగ్ వ్యాపారమయితే 10, ఇతర వ్యాపారమైతే 20.2. వ్యాపార స్థాపనకు భాగస్తుల మధ్య అంగీకారముకావలెను.3. భాగస్తుల ఋణ భాధ్యత అపరిమితం, వ్యక్తిగతం, సమిష్టిగతము.4. నమోదు తప్పనిసరి కాకపోయినా అవసరము.5. ఎక్కువ మంది భాగస్తులు ఉండటము వలన ఎక్కువ మూలధనము ఉంటుంది.6. ఒప్పందము లేకుండా భాగస్వామ్యము ఏర్పడదు.7. ఎక్కువ మంది వ్యక్తులు ఉండటము వలన వ్యాపార రహస్యాలు కాపాడలేరు.8. నిర్ణయాలు తీసుకోవడములో ఆలస్యము జరుగుతుంది.9. ఎక్కువ మంది ఉండటము వలన శ్రమ విభజనను ప్రవేశపెట్టవచ్చును.10. భాగస్తులందరూ సమిష్టిగా ఆలోచించి మంచి నిర్ణయాలు తీసుకోవడానికి అవకాశమున్నది."},{"question":"Slutför den här frasen: I Finlands vinter- och","answer":"fortsättningskrig deltog 330 judiska soldater och 20 lottor av vilka 23 stupade. Nästan samtliga som deltog kom från Helsingfors, Åbo, Viborg och Vasa. Vid minnestillställningen för de stupade i Helsingfors synagoga 6 december 1944 deltog sittande president marskalk Mannerheim."},{"question":"Onye bụ Bose Kaffo?","answer":"Bose Kaffo (onye a mụrụ n'ụbọchị nke 14 n'ọnwa Nọvemba nke afọ 1972 na Surulere,na Legos Steeti,nke Naijiria ) bụ onye egwuregwu ị pịa teniisi nke ala Naijiria nke gara asọmpi ise nke Olimpik site n'afọ 1992 ruo n'afọ 2008.Ọ bụ nwanyị Naijiria nke abụọ na-asọmpi n'egwuregwu Olimpik ise, ma a gụchaa onye ọgba ọsọ Mary Onyali . Onye ọzọ ruru ihe ogo a n'afọ 2008 bụ Segun Toriola onye egwuregwu ị pịa teniisi. Ka ọ na-eru ngwụcha nke asọmpi Olimpiki nke afọ 2008, naanị mmadụ iri na atọ na-egwu egwuregwu teniiss gburugburu ụwa pụtarala opekata mpe egwuregwu nke Olimpik ise. Ndi ya na ya gbara abuo n’egwuregwu Olimpik bu Abiola Odumosu n’afo 1992 na Olufunke Oshonaike site n’afo 1996 ruo n'afọ 2004.O nwetala ihe nrite iri na ise (ọla edo asaa) n'asọmpi o mere n’otu n’otu na ndị abụọ abụọ n’egwuregwu isii nke All-Africa Games site n'afọ 1987 rue n'afọ 2007, na-erite opekata mpe otu nrite n’egwuregwu ọbụla. N'asọmpi o mere naanị ya, o ritere ọla edo n'afọ 1995, ọlaọcha n'afọ 1999 ma n'afọ 2007, na ọla nchara n'afọ 2003. N'asọmpi ndị ha dị abụọ abụọ mee, o ritere ọla edo (ya na Olufunke Oshonaike) n’afọ 1995, n'afọ 1999, nakwazị n'afọ 2003, ọla ọcha n’afọ 1991, na ọla nchara n’afọ 2007.  Na Mixed Doubles, ọ ritere ọla edo n'afọ 1991 (ya na Atanda Musa ), n'afọ 1995 (ya na Sule Olayele ), na afọ 1999 (ya na Segun Toriola ) tinyere ọla ọcha n'afọ 1987 n'afọ 2003 yana ọla nchara n’afọ 2007.  Naịjirịa e meriela otu ọla edo na All-Africa Games."},{"question":"Descreva o símbolo do AC Milan.","answer":"O símbolo do AC Milan é um escudo preto com uma figura vermelha diagonalmente inclinada que se assemelha a uma cruz de São Jorge. No topo, há as iniciais \\"ACM,\\" e na parte inferior, as palavras \\"AC Milan.\\""},{"question":"Taariikhda Fanaanka Maxamef Cabdi Warsame.","answer":"Taariikhda Fanaanka Maxamef Cabdi Warsame.Maxamed Cabdi Warsame (Af Ingiriis : Mohamed Abdi Talil; Af Carabi : ar‎) ku magacdheeraa Tahliil, waa fanaan Soomaaliyeed oo aad looga yaqaanno gayiga Soomaalida, kuna caan baxay magaca Cod Wanaagsane sababtoo ah wuxuu ka mid yahay kuwa ugu sareeya fanaaniinta codka fiican dhammaan fanaaniinta ku heesa af-Soomaaliga.Cabdi Tahliil Warsameمحمدعبذ تهليلCabdi Tahliil WarsameKu dhashay: Maajo 21, 1943 ( 80jir) Muqdisho, BanadirDegenaansho: Nayroobi, KiinyaQoomiyada: SoomaaliShaqada: Heesaa, Fanaan, laxamiiste, jilaaSanadaha Shaqada: 1973kii-2000Ka tirsan; Hobolada Waaberi (1970-1998)Shaqooyinka ugu muhiimsan: Heeso wadani, heeso jacayl, qasaa'idMagaalada ka soo jeedo: Xamar, BanadirDiinta: Sunni IslaamTahliil heesihiisa aad ayaa loo jeceyahay waana mid ka mid ah fannaaniinta qiimaha mugga weyn ku dhex leh umadda Soomaaliyeed. Fanaanka Maxamed Cabdi Warsame wuxuu uu ku dhashay gobolada dhexe ee Soomaaliya sanadkii 1953dii taariikhda Miilaadiga.Fanaanka Maxamed Cabdi Warsame wuxuu leeyahay tiro badan oo heeso ah, kuwaasi oo iskugu jira wadani, jacayl, guubaabin, dhiirigelin, haasaawe, amaan, duco, wacyi, wargelin iyo wax-sheeg.Fanaanku waxuu ka tirsanaa Hobolada Waaberi ee hogaanka u ahaa fanka iyo suugaanta Soomaaliyeed.Fanaankani wuxuu heeso badan la qaaday hobolo dumar oo badan, kuwaasi ooy ka mid yihiin fanaanada Xaliimo Khaliif Magool, Hibo Maxamed Hodoon (Hibo Nuura), Maandeeq, Saynab Cige iyo kuwo kale oo badan. Si kastaba ha ahaatee, heesaha Tahliil aad ayay u badan yihiin, kuwa ugu caansan waxaa ka mid ah:Albumka OnkodHeesta OnkodHeesta HoowlahaadiiHeesta WaayahaHeesta Gobanimodoon: waxay si talantaali ah u wada qaadaan fanaanada Hibo NuuraHeesta CasarHeesta Sida Faras BulaaloHeesta Jacayl Aayatiin LehHeesta Maxaan Xabadeed Ku Nacay (shirkii Djibouti)."},{"question":"බටහිර ආසියාතික රටවල් නම් කරන්න.","answer":"බටහිර ආසියාව යනු සිවිල් යුධ, දේශපාලනික අර්බුධ හමුවේ වෙනස් වන දේශසීමා සහිත කලාපයකි. දැනට මෙහි එක්සත් ජාතින් විසින් හඳුනාගත් රටවල් 20 කි. ඒවා මෙසේ ය.1. තුර්කිය2. බහරේනය3. කුවේටය4. ඕමානය5. කටාර්6. සෞදි අරාබිය7. එක්සත් අරාබි එමීර් රාජ්‍යය8. යේමනය9. ආමේනියාව10. අසර්බයිජානය11. ජෝර්ජියාව12. ඉරාකය13. ඉරානය14. ඊශ්‍ර්‍රායලය15. ජෝර්දානය16. ලෙබනනය17. පලස්තීනය (ගාසා තීරය හා බටහිර ඉවුර)18. සිරියාව19. ඊජිප්තුව20. සයිප්‍රසයකෙසේ වෙතත්, භූගෝලීයව බටහිර ආසියාතික වන සයිප්‍රසය එහි සමාජීය, ආර්ථික, සංස්කෘතික හා ආගමික ලක්ෂණ හේතුකොටගෙන යුරෝපීය රාජ්‍යයක් ලෙස සලකනු ලැබේ.එමෙන් ම මෙම කලාපයේ එක්සත් ජාතීන් විසින් පිළිනොගනු ලබන පාලන ප්‍රදේශ ඇති අතර මේවායෙන් බොහෝමය කෝකේසියානු කලාපයේ පිහිටා ඇත. ඒවා මෙසේ ය.1. අබ්කාසියාව2. අර්ත්සක්3. දකුණු ඔසේටියාව4. උතුරු සයිප්‍රසය මෙම කලාපයට අයත් අක්‍රෝතිරි හා ඩෙකේරියාව එකසත් රාජධානියට අයත් වන අතර සීනායි අර්ධද්වීපය ඊජිප්තුවට අයත් වේ. බටහිර ආසියානු කලාපය හා ඊජිප්තුව පොදුවේ \\"මැදපෙරදිග කලාපය\\" ලෙස හඳුන්වනු ලැබේ.  "},{"question":"「石川や 浜の真砂（まさご）は 尽きるとも 世に盗人の 種はつきまじ」という辞世の句を詠んだ、世紀の大泥棒といえば誰でしょう？","answer":"石川五右衛門です。"},{"question":"Me kalmar: \\"night\\" ke nufi a harshen Hausa? ","answer":"Kalmar \\"night\\" na nufin \\"dare\\" a harshen Hausa"},{"question":"もともとは「しんぼる」と「猫塾」という別々のコンビで活動していた、「まぁねー」などの決めゼリフで人気になり２０２０年にブレイクした女性お笑いグループの名前は何？","answer":"ぼる塾です。"},{"question":"வினா :தமிழ்நாட்டில் பன்னிரெண்டாம் வகுப்பு தேர்வு தொடங்கப்பட்ட வருடம்A. 1977B. 1978C. 1979D. 1980","answer":"விடை : C. 1979"},{"question":"Apakah maksud 'indah khabar dari rupa'? Berikan satu contoh ayat bagi peribahasa tersebut.","answer":"Ia bermaksud khabar atau percakapan orang selalunya melebih-lebihkan kecantikan (kesempurnaan dan lain-lain) sesuatu daripada keadaannya yang sebenar. Contoh ayat: Zainab amat kecewa apabila telah sampai ke pantai tersebut kerana pantai tersebut hanyalah indah khabar dari rupa."},{"question":"Kök hücre tedavisi hangi hastalıklara iyi gelir?","answer":"Kök hücre tedavisi sıklıkla şu hastalıkların iyileştirilmesinde kullanılır:Kemik iliği kanserleri.Lenfoma.Hodgkin lenfoma.Lösemi.Anemi.Akdeniz anemisi.Organ kanserleri.Plazma hücre hastalıkları"},{"question":" பின்லாந்தைத் தாக்கியதற்காக பன்னாட்டுச் சங்கத்திலிருந்து வெளியேற்றப்பட்ட நாடு எது?அ ) ஜெர்மனி ஆ) ரஷ்யா இ) இத்தாலி ஈ) பிரான்ஸ்","answer":"பன்னாட்டுச் சங்கத்தின் முக்கிய இரண்டுக் குறிக்கோள்களில் ஒன்று உலகில் அமைதியை நிலைநாட்டுவது. இதற்காக, உறுப்பினர் நாடுகளிடையே போர் உருவாகும்போது சங்கம் போர் நிறுத்த ஆணை ஒன்றை வெளியிடும். அதுமட்டுமல்லாது, போர் தொடங்கிய நாடு இழப்பீடு தருமாறு வற்புறுத்தப்படும். இந்நிலையில், 1939இல் டிசம்பர் திங்களில் ரஷ்யா பின்லாந்தைத் தாக்கியது. அதன் விளைவாக, பன்னாட்டுச் சங்கம் ரஷ்யாவை சங்கத்திலிருந்து வெளியேற்றியது. இதுவே சங்கத்தின் இறுதியான மற்றும் உறுதியான நடவடிக்கையாகும்."},{"question":"Waa maxay Suuqgeyn?","answer":"Suuqgeyn waa habka loo maro ka iibinta alaab ama adeeg laga iibiyo macmiil."},{"question":"Kee ku buuxin karaa codsiga?","answer":"Waxaad ka codsan kartaa qalab ama aalad walba oo internet ku xirmi karta, ay ka mid tahay telefoonka casriga ah (smart phone), ama kombututer-gacmeedka (tablet), waxaad xataa ka heli kartaa kombuyutermaktabadda xaafadaada."},{"question":"အောက်ပါ မေးခွန်းကိုဖြေပါ။ Vikings ပဥ္စမတွဲ ရဲ့ ဒုတိယပိုင်းကို ဘယ်တော့ ထုတ်လွှင့်မှာလဲ။","answer":"၂၀၁၈ မှာ"},{"question":"Explain the reaction of Indian people against the Rowlatt Act passed through the Imperial Legislative Council in 1919.","answer":"Reaction of Indian people against the Rowlatt Act of 1919:Rallies were organized against this act.Railways, workshops, and shops closed down.The procession in Amritsar provoked widespread attacks on buses, post offices, railway stations, telegraphic lines, etc.On April 6, Gandhiji held Hartal against this unjust law (the Rowlatt Act).The peaceful demonstration in Jallianwala Bagh led to a violent movement all across the country."},{"question":"Fenoy ny banga:\\"Raha tanora tsy hilalao dia aleo mody ho antitra, fa raha antitra tsy hampiady karajia dia aleo mody ho _.\\"","answer":"\\"Raha tanora tsy hilalao dia aleo mody ho antitra, fa raha antitra tsy hampiady karajia dia aleo mody ho razana.\\""},{"question":"Wat voor gebeurtenis beschrijft de volgende tekst: Hij was een trouwe bondgenoot van koning Filips VI van Frankrijk. Lodewijk vocht mee in de Honderdjarige Oorlog tegen koning Eduard III van Engeland en nam in 1356 deel aan de voor de Fransen desastreuze Slag bij Poitiers. In 1360 werd het burggraafschap Thouars als onderdeel van het Verdrag van Brétigny onder Engelse heerschappij geplaatst en in november 1361 werd de stad ingenomen door John Chandos. Twee jaar later, in 1363, legde Lodewijk een eed van trouw af aan de Engelse koning.","answer":"Het gaat over de slag bij Poitiers."},{"question":"पुस्तकावर निबंध.","answer":"बगीतले तर पुस्तके म्हणजे केवळ खूप साऱ्या पानाचा असलेला संग्रह आहे. पण ह्या पुस्तकांच्या पाना मधे आपले सर्व आयुष्य बदलण्याची शक्ति असते, पुस्तके म्हणजे ज्ञानाचा भंडार आहे. प्रतेक गोष्ट च्याचा तुम्ही विचार करू शकतात ते सर्व काही आपल्यानं पुस्तका मधे बघायला मिळते. पुस्तकान मधे आपल्या सर्व प्रश्नांची उत्तरे आहेत. पुस्तक आपलये कधीच चुकीचे मार्ग दर्शन करत नाही, आणि ते आपल्याशी कधीच खोटे सुद्धा बोलत नाही. पुस्तक आपल्या गुरु प्रमाणे आहे ते नेहमी आपले हित पाहतात.कोणाला ही कोणत्या ही विषया मधे रुचि असूदे आपल्या साठी प्रतेक प्रकारचे पुस्तक उपलब्ध आहे. पुस्तकांचे वेगवेलगे प्रकार आहेत जसे की काल्पनिक, वरणात्मक आणि खूप सारे. प्रत्यकाला आपल्या विषया मधे रुचि असणाऱ्या पद्धतीची पुस्तके सुद्धा उपलब्ध आहेत. ह्या पुस्तकान मधे आपल्या विषयाची सर्व प्रश्नाचे उतर भेटू शकते.पुस्तक केवळ आपल्याला ज्ञानच देत नाही तर ते आपल्याला कंटाळ येत असणाऱ्या वेळेला एका अनंदिक क्षणा मधे बदलू शकतो. कारण अशी पुस्तके आहेत ज्या मधे काही जागेंचे अशे वर्णन केले आहे की आपल्याला ते वाचून असे वाटते जसे आपण त्या जागेत राहून, त्या जागेतील क्षण अनुभवत आहेत. आनंदा बरोबरच अश्या पुस्तकातून आपल्याला नवीन गोष्टींची माहिती सुद्धा मिळते.पुस्तकांची आपल्या जीवना मधे एक महत्त्वपूर्ण भूमिका असते. पुस्तक आपले गुरू आहे ते नेहमी आपले योग्य मार्गदर्शन करतात. पुस्तके वाचण्याचे खूप सारे लाभ आहेत. नियमित पुस्तके वाचली तर त्याने आपले शब्दसंग्रह आणि संप्रेषण कौशल्ये वाढते. आत्मचरित्रावर आधारित पुस्तके वाचल्याने आपल्या वक्तीमहत्वा मधे चांगले बदल घडून येतात. पुस्तका मधून घेतलेले ज्ञान अपल्यांना आपल्या आयुष्यात कधी न कधी कमी येतेच.यशस्वी लोकांचे आत्मचरित्र वाचण्याणे आपल्याला प्रेरणा तर मिळतेच त्या बरोबरच आपल्याला माहीत पडते त्यांनी कश्या परिस्तिथी मधून यश मीळवले. पुस्तके आपले ज्ञान त्यांन मधे साचून ठेवते ज्या मुळे ते एका पिढी कडून दुसऱ्या पिढी पर्यंत पोचते. आज केवळ पुस्तांकान मुळेच आपल्याला आयुर्वेदिक औषधांची माहिती मिळू शकली आहे.पुस्तकांचे खूप फायदे आहेत ह्या मधे कोणती ही क्षंका नाही. पुस्तकामध्ये आपले भविष्य बनवण्याची शक्ती आहे, आणि ते आपल्या जिवनाचा सर्वात महत्त्वपूर्ण भाग आहेत. प्रत्येक यशशवी माणसा मधे एक सवय सामान्य असते आणि ते म्हणजे पुस्तके वाचण्याची. पुस्तके कधी ही खोटे बोलत नाही आणि ते आपले योग्य मार्गदर्शन करतात ते आपले खरे मित्र आहेत. पुस्तकांचे हे फायदे बगता आपण पान पुस्तक वाचण्याची चंगळी सवय निर्माण केली पाहिजे."},{"question":"O que o cartão de visita de Al Capone indicava sua ocupação?","answer":"Um vendedor de móveis usados."},{"question":"नेपालमा कुन जिल्लालाइ सर्बप्रथम बर्डफ्लु संकटग्रस्त क्षेत्र घोषणा गरियो ?","answer":"भक्तपुर"},{"question":"Bebeğim kabız olduğunu nasıl anlarım?","answer":"Kabızlık belirtileri nelerdir? Kabızlığın en önemli belirtisi, kakanın sert, kuru veya ufalanan yapıda olmasıdır. Bebeklerde kabızlığın diğer belirtileri şunlardır: Bebeğiniz ağlıyorsa ve kaka yapmadan önce rahatsız görünüyorsa (Bebekler kaka yaparken biraz zorlama normaldir; bu genellikle kabızlık anlamına gelmez.)"},{"question":"Rahama Sadau","answer":"Rahama Sadau (ti a bi ni ọjọ keje Oṣu kejila ọdun 1993) jẹ oṣere ọmọ Nàìjíríà, ase fiimu ati akorin. Ilu Kaduna ni a bi si ,ibe na de lo dagba si. Rahama kopa ninu awọn idije ijó ati ere nigba ti owa ni ọmọde ati lakoko awọn ile-iwe rẹ. O dide si okiki ni ipari ọdun 2013 lẹhin ti o darapọ mọ Ile- iṣẹ fiimu fiimu Kannywood pẹlu fiimu akọkọ rẹ Gani ga Wane .Rahama farahan ninu ọpọlọpọ awọn fiimu Naijiria ni Hausa ati Gẹẹsi o si jẹ ọkan ninu awọn oṣere Naijiria diẹ ti o sọ Hindi daradara. O jẹ olubori ti oṣere ti o dara julọ (Kannywood) ni City People Entertainment Awards ni ọdun 2014 ati 2015. O tun ṣẹgun Oṣere ti o dara julọ ti Afirika ni 19th Awards Fiimu Afirika ni ọdun 2015 nipasẹ Afirika Voice. Ni ọdun 2017, o di olokiki Hausa akọkọ lati farahan ninu awọn gbajumọ mẹwa Awọn Gbajumọ Awọn Obirin Naijiria to dara julọ. Ni gbogbo iṣẹ rẹ, Sadau ti jẹ oṣere ti o nšišẹ, ti o han ni awọn fiimu mejeeji ati awọn fidio orin.Rahama Ibrahim Sadau ni a bi ni Ipinle Kaduna, Ariwa iwọ-oorun Naijiria ti o jẹ olu ilu akọkọ ti Ipinle Ariwa ti tẹlẹ ti Nigeria si Alhaji Ibrahim Sadau. O dagba pẹlu awọn obi rẹ ni Kaduna lẹgbẹẹ awọn omo iya rẹ mẹta Zainab Sadau, Fatima Sadau, Aisha Sadau ati arakunrin Haruna Sadau.Sadau darapọ mọ ile- iṣẹ fiimu fiimu Kannywood ni ọdun 2013 nipasẹ Ali Nuhu. O ṣe awọn ipa kekere diẹ ṣaaju ki o to loruko lati iṣẹ rẹ ni Gani ga Wane lẹgbẹẹ oṣere Kannywood Ali Nuhu . Ni ọjọ keta Oṣu Kẹwa ọdun 2016, Ẹgbẹ Awọn Onisẹṣe Motion ti Nigeria (MOPPAN), eyiti o jẹ alakoso ni Kannywood, da a duro lati kannywood fun fifihan ninu fidio orin aladun pẹlu akọrin ilu Jos kan, ti oruko re je Classiq. Ni ọdun kan lẹhin ọdun 2017, o kọwe lati toro gafara ni owo MOPPAN. Ni Oṣu Kini ọdun 2018, Gomina ti Ipinle Kano Dokita Abdullahi Ganduje lo gba le, leyin ti o b won saro.Ni ọdun 2016 amo gege bi \\"Oju ti Kannywood\\". Ni Oṣu Kẹwa ọdun, Sadau ṣe ifihan ninu jara fiimu kan lori EbonyLife TV. Ni ọdun 2017, o da ile-iṣẹ iṣelọpọ kan kale ti a npè ni Sadau Pictures ni bi ti o gbe fiimu akọkọ rẹ, Rariya jade Ali Nuhu, Sani Musa Danja, Sadiq Sani Sadiq ati Fati Washa mi awon irawo ere na. O pada si oṣere lati mu olukọ ọmọ ni MTV Shuga. Ni ọdun 2019 MTV Shuga pada wa si wa ni Nigeria fun jara 6, \\"Choices\\", ati Sadau jẹ ọkan ninu awọn oṣere ti n pada fun jara tuntun eyiti o wa pẹlu Timini Egbuson, Yakubu Mohammed, Uzoamaka Aniunoh ati Ruby Akabueze.Sadau kẹkọọ Isakoso Ẹda Eniyan ni ile-iwe ti Iṣowo ati Iṣuna ti Eastern Mediterranean University ni Northern Cyprus."},{"question":"Iye ọjọ́ mélòó ni ó ṣeéṣe kí omíyalé, àgbàrá ya ṣọ́ọ̀bù ṣọṣẹ́ láwọn ìpínlẹ̀ kọ̀ọ̀kan lorílẹ̀-èdè Nàìjíríà, àti pé, kí ni ìjọba sọ nípa rẹ̀?","answer":"Ìjọba Àpapọ̀ ti kéde pé ó ṣeéṣe kí àwọn ìpínlẹ̀ tí odò River Benue gba ọ̀dọ̀ wọn kọjá bẹ̀rẹ̀ sí ní omíyalé àgbàrá ya ṣọ́ọ̀bù ní ọ̀sẹ̀ kan sí àsìkò yìí bí orílẹ̀-èdè Cameroon ṣe ṣí odò Ladgo.Mínísítà fún ìbojú àánú woni àti pípa òṣì rẹ́, Dókítà Betta Edu ní ìgbìmọ̀ kan tí ààrẹ Bọ́lá Tinubu gbé dìde láti wá ojútùú sí ìṣòro náà yóò bẹ̀rẹ̀ sí ní gbé àwọn ètò ka'lẹ̀ láti ríi dájú pé ìpalára tí ìjàmbá náà yóò fà kò ní kọjáa bó ṣe yẹ.Betta Edu rọ àwọn gómínà àwọn ìpínlẹ̀ yìí láti tètè gbé ìgbésẹ̀, kí wọ́n kó àwọn ènìyàn ìpínlẹ̀ wọn tó wà ní àwọn agbègbè tí ẹ̀kúnwọ́ omi yìí le ṣe àkóbá fún lọ sí òkè odò, níbi tí ààbò tó péye ti wà fún wọn.Ó ní Ààrẹ Tinubu níbi ìpàdé ìgbìmọ̀ aláṣẹ Nàìjíríà tó wáyé lọ́jọ́ Ajé ti pa á láṣẹ fún gbogbo àwọn ilé iṣẹ́ tí ọ̀rọ̀ náà kàn láti foríkorí, kí wọ́n wá ọ̀nà àbáyọ sí ìṣòro ọ̀hún.Ó ṣàlàyé pé pẹ̀lú bí Cameroon ṣe ṣí odò Lagdo, kò ní pẹ́ tí àwọn ìpínlẹ̀ tí wọ́n wà ní àwọn bèbè omi yìí yóò bẹ̀rẹ̀ sí ní rí ìpalára rẹ̀ àti pé omíyalé jẹ́ ìṣòro kan gbòógì ní orílẹ̀-èdè Nàìjíríà èyí tó ti fa ìpàdánù ẹ̀mí àti dúkìá.“Ààrẹ ti fún wa níṣẹ́ láti ri dájú pé a gbáradì bó ṣe yẹ fún ìpalára ṣíṣí odò Lagdo.”“Lára àwọn ǹkan tí àwọn ìjọba ìpínlẹ̀ gbọ́dọ̀ kọ́kọ́ mójútó ni pé gbogbo àwọn ojúṣàn àgbàrá àti kòtò ìdominù ló wà ní mímọ́.”Bákan náà ló ní àwọn ìjọba ìpínlẹ̀ yìí gbọ́dọ̀ ṣe ètò ìlanilọ́yẹ̀ tó péye fún àwọn ará ìlú lórí ìpalára omíyalé àgbàrá ya ṣọ́ọ̀bù.”“Gbogbo àwọn ará ìlú tó bá kọ̀, tí wọn kò bá fẹ́ kó kúrò níbi tí omíyalé ti lè ṣe ìjàm̀bá fún wọn ni ìjọba nílo láti mójútó nítorí orílẹ̀-èdè yìí kò tún gbọdọ̀ fojú winá ìpàdánù ẹ̀mí àti dúkìá sọ́wọ́ omíyalé àgbàrá ya ṣọ́ọ̀bù bíi ti ọdún tó kọjá.”Bẹ́ẹ̀ náà ni Mínísítà fétò àyíká, Iziaq Salako, àti Mínísítà fọ́rọ̀ omi àti ìmọ́tótó, Ọ̀jọ̀gbọ́n Joseph Utsez, tí wọ́n wà níbi ìpàdé náà ṣèlérí láti gbé ìgbésẹ̀ akin láti mójútó omíyalé àgbàrá ya ṣọ́ọ̀bù náà."},{"question":"Ƙirƙiri kanun labarai dan wannan labari mai zuwa: Lokacin da Sarauniya Elizabeth II ta hau karaga a 1952, Daular Birtaniya na nan daram Yayin da kasar Indiya, mai lakabin \\"kawar adon kambin sarauta,\\" ta samu 'yanci, daukacin taswirar duniya na damfare da launin ja. Shekaru 20 da suka biyo baya an yi ta sauke tutar Birtaniya a kasashe da dama, wadanda suka kasance karkashin mulkin mallakarta a da, inda suka samu 'yanci. Mafi yawan sababbin shugabannin kasashen rainon Birtaniya tsararrakin Sarauniya ne, don haka ta sansu, tare da dimbim matsalolinsu. Matsayinta ya zama tambarin daidaiton adalcin hadin kai, da ke wakiltar kasashen rainon Ingila ke son cimmawa. Sarauniyar ta fayyace irin matsayin ta hanyar nuni da ra'ayinta na son huldar aiki tare da kungiyar. A cewar Sir Shridath \\"Sonny\\" Ramphal, Sakatare-Janar na kungiyar Commonwealth tun daga 1975 zuwa  1979: ta sarayar da rayuwarta da dabararta tarbiyyart tare da dangantakarta, wajen nuna halin kula ga kungiyar kasashen rainon Ingila ta Commonwealth.\\" Sakamakon haka Mai martaba Sarauniya ta samu kimar darajar mutuntaka. \\"Sarauniya ta kasance wani babban al'amari da ya samu kungiyar Commonwealth,\\" a cewar tsohon shugaban kasar Najeriya Olusegun Obasanjo a shekarar 2002. \\"Ta kasance babbar jigon daidaita al'amura da ban mamaki, ga ta mace mai abin mamaki.\\" Sarauniya ta ziyarci daukacin kasashen da ke kungiyar rainon Birtaniya ta Commonwealth a kalla sau daya, inda ta fara kai ziyarar rangadi a kasashen Austiraliya da New Zealand a shekarar farko da hawanta karagar mulki. Sannan ta fito da tsarin ganawa da shugabanin Commonwealth, inda ake gayyatarsu halartar wata takaitaciyar ganawa a bainar jama'a bayan shekaru bibiyu. \\"Takan gana da kowane shugaban gwamnati a tsakanin mintuna 20 zuwa 30 a kebe,\\" kamar yadda Sonny Ramphal zai iya tunawa. \\"Ko da yaushe ana bata managarcin bayani a takaice. Sai dai 'yan Republican ko shugabanni masu tsattsauran ra'ayi sukan kasance, sun tabbatar da cewa ganawa da Sarauniya muhimin al'amari ne.\\" A matsayin Sarauniya na shugabar je-ka-na-yi-ka ba ta da karfin iko. Amma dai tana da tasiri. Idan shugabanni suka zo mata da matsaloli, a wasu lokuta takan dora su kan hanyar da za a samu warwarar matsalar. Sarki Mswati III na Swaziland zai iya tuna al'amura da dama da suka faru. \\"Takan karfafi gwiwar dimbin mutanen da muke bukatar gani kan wata matsala da muke gabatar mata, ko wani abu mai kama da haka. Daga nan sai mutanen da muke bukatar gani sai su yi wani dan yunkuri.\\" Kimar hadin kan Sarauniya an sha gwada su a lokuta da dama tun gabanin taron shugabannin kungiyar kasashen Commonwealth da aka gudanar a Babban birnin Zambiya Lusaka cikin shekarar 1979. Ta sha matukar wahala ganin yadda Firayiministarta Margaret Thatcher ta shiga rikici da mafi yawan shugabannin kasashen kungiyar Commonwealth kan yadda ta ki amincewa a kakaba wa Afirka ta Kudu takunkumi. Haka kuma a lokacin da makomar kasar da a da ake kira Rhodesia ya haifar da rabuwar kawuna a tsakanin shugabannin kungiyar Commonwealth. Sojojin Ian Smith sun yi luguden bama-bamai kan sansanin 'yan adawa da ke Lusaka kwanaki kadan gabanin taron. Matakin da ya dauka ya bai wa wasu shugabannin damar yin uzuri, musamman Robert Muldoon na New Zealand, wanda ya roki Sarauniya ka da ta halarci taron. Amma, a kamar yadda Sonny Ramphal ya tuna cewa, ta yi matukar jajircewa. \\"Ta bayyana wa shugabannin karara da daukacin Firayiministan kasashen, farare da bakake, tsofaffi da sababbi cewa ba za a raba kungiyar Comonwealth ba, dole ne kungiyar ta Commonwealth ta cimma matsayar daidaita al'amura cikin lumana. \\"Hakika wannan shi ne kimar karfin tasirinta da kimar mutuncinta da ake gani.\\" Sarauniya ta yi aiki tukuru wajen cimma yarjejeniyar zaman lafiya kan al'amarin da mafi yawan mutane ke ganin shi ne lokaci mafi kyawunlamari ga kungiyar Commonwealth. Duk da irin jajircewarta kan kungiyar Commonwealth, kungiyar ba ta kasance ba face 'yar ku ci, ku ba mu kan harkokin duniya, in an kwatantata da kungiyoyi ko hukumomi masu karfi, wadanda suka hada Asusun Lamuni na duniya 'IMF' da Bankin Duniya. Nasarorin da tacimmawa sun kasance kimarsu ba ta da girma a fanonin da suka hada da al'adu da kimiyya da ilimi. Sannan da kafar tattaunawa tsakanin Arewa da Kudu. Makomar shugaban kungiyar Commonwalth ba a san inda ya nufa ba. Domin jagora bai cika zama shugaba ba, kaitsaye, kuma wasu kan iya bijiro da alamar tambaya kan jajircewar sabon Sarki game da kungiyar. Sannan babu wata masaniya kan cewa mutuwar Sarauniya na iya haifar da kasurar tsarin jamhuriya na zaben shugabanni (Repubicanism) a wasu kasashen da har yanzu sarautar Birtaniya ke jan ragamar shugancin kasashen. Masu adawa da sarauta a Austiraliya, alal misali suna da tabbacin cewa mutuwar Sarauniya za ta bayar damar gudanar da zaben raba gardama don sauya kundin tsarin mulki. Kuma an bijiro da irin wadannan bukatun a Jamaica, sannan da ire-irensu a New Zealand. Kasancewa a kungiyar kasashen rainon Birtaniya ta Commonwealth sa-kai ne, kuma wasu kasashen da ke nahiyar Asiya yankin Pacific, ta yiwu su yanke matsaya wajen ficewa dungurungum, inda za su dumfari sababbin al'amuran harkokin rayuwa masu tasiri, kodayake kada kuri'ar Birtaniya na ficewa daga Tarayyar Turai na iya bai wa kasar damar kulla kawance da tsofaffin kawayenta na da. Ba a dai bijiro da irin wadannan tambayoyin ba, game da Elizabeth II kan matsayinta a kungiyar kasashen Comonweath. Fatanta da na iyalanta kamar yadda ta taba furtawa - \\"Karfin warwarar matsala na tattare da hakuri da juna da abokantaka da nuna kauna\\" al'amarin da in aka bijiro da su za su yi tasirin juya akalar harkokin duniya. ©Dukkan hotunan na da hakkin mallaka","answer":"Tabbas, ga kanun labarai don rubutun da aka bayar - Sarauniya Elizabeth II: Waiwaye kan gudunmawar Sarauniyar Ingila da Commonwealth"},{"question":"క్రింద ఇచ్చిన గద్యాన్ని పరిశీలించి 5 ప్రశ్నలని తాయారుచెయ్యండి:మన జానపద కళల్లో ఒకానొక విశిష్టమైన కళారూపం తోలుబొమ్మలాట. ఇది క్రీ.పూ. 3వ శతాబ్దం నాటికే చాలా ప్రచారంలో ఉన్నట్లు తెలుస్తుంది. తెల్లటి వస్త్రాన్ని తెరగా అమర్చి, దానిపై దీపం కాంతిలో బొమ్మల నీడలను పడేటట్లు చేసి బొమ్మలాటను ప్రదర్శిస్తారు. ఈ తోలుబొమ్మలు ఆంధ్రదేశంలోని ప్రాచీన ఓడరేవుల ద్వారా భారతీయులతో బాటు విదేశాలకు వెళ్ళాయి.నేడు పాశ్చాత్య దేశాలలో గొప్పగా చెప్పుకొనే ఛాయా ప్రదర్శనలకు ఈ తోలు బొమ్మలే మూలం. మన దేశంలో ఈ ఆటలో భారత, రామాయణ కథలను ఎక్కువగా ప్రదర్శిస్తుంటారు. ఈ ఆటలోని అల్లాటప్పగాడు, బంగారక్క జట్టుపోలిగాడు, కేతిగాడు వంటి హాస్యపాత్రలు గ్రామీణుల మనసులపై విశేషమైన ముద్రవేశాయి. వినోదాన్ని, విజ్ఞానాన్ని పంచే ఇటువంటి కళారూపాలను కాపాడుకోవడం మన ప్రస్తుత కర్తవ్యం.","answer":"ప్రశ్నలు :1. తోలుబొమ్మలాటలో ఏ కథలు ఎక్కువగా ప్రదర్శిస్తారు ?2. తోలుబొమ్మలాటలు ఎప్పటి నుండి ప్రచారంలో ఉన్నాయి ?3. .విదేశాలలోని ఛాయా ప్రదర్శనకు మూలమేది ?4. మన ప్రస్తుత కర్తవ్యం ఏమిటి ?5. తోలుబొమ్మలాటలోని హాస్యపాత్ర లేవి ?"},{"question":"இயங்குபடத்தின் வரலாறு என்ன? முதல் இயக்கத்திரைப்படம் பற்றி விளக்கவும்.","answer":"இயங்குபடத்தின் வரலாறு:முதன் முதலில் இயங்குபடங்களை உருவாக்க ஓவியங்களே பயன்படுத்தப்பட்டுள்ளன. பல நூற்றாண்டுகளுக்கு முன்னரே இயங்குபட தொழில் நுட்பங்கள் பயன்படுத்தப்பட்டு வந்துள்ளன. அவற்றை குகைகளிலும், பழங்கால தொல்லியல் பொருட்களிலும் கண்டுபிடித்துள்ளனர். பழைய கற்கால குகை ஓவிங்களில் மிருகங்கள் சீரான இயக்கத்தை வெளிப்படுத்துபவையாக வரையபட்டிருந்ததை தொல்பொருள் ஆய்வாளர்கள் கண்டுபிடித்துள்ளனர்.சீனர்கள் ’’’ஜோட்ரோப்’’’ எனும் சாதனத்தை கி.பி 180-இல் கண்டுபிடித்துள்ளனர். 1404-1438-களில் வாய்னிச் கையெழுத்துப் பிரதிகளில் பந்து போன்ற ஒரே மாதிரியான உருவங்கள் வரையப்பட்டுள்ளன. அதனை நடுவிலிருந்து சுழற்றிவிட்டால் பந்து ஓடுவது போன்ற மாயயை உருவாக்குவது போல் அமைத்துள்ளனர். இவை அனைத்தும் முழுமை பெறாத இயங்குபடங்களாகும். இயங்குபடங்களின் வளர்ச்சி திரைப்படவியல் வந்த பின்பே தொடங்கியது. இவை எளிமையானதும் திரைப்படவியலின் முன்னேற்றமே காரணம்.திரைப்படக்கருவி என்பது ஒளிப்படக்காட்டி, அச்சுப்பொறி, புகைப்படக்கருவி ஆகியன அனைத்தும் ஒருங்கே அமையப்பெற்ற கருவியாகும். இதனை உருவாக்கியவர்கள் ஆரம்பகால சினிமா தயாரிப்பாளர்களான லூமியர் சகோதரர்கள் ஆவர். உருவாக்கப்பட்ட ஆண்டு 1894 ஆகும். ஆரம்ப காலங்களில் பெனகிஸ்டோஸ்கோப் (1832), ஜோட்ரோப் (1834), பிராக்ஸினோ ஸ்கோப் (1877) முதலிய சாதனங்கள் வேறுபாடுகள் கொண்ட ஓவிய சட்டங்களை இயக்க உதவியவையாகும். முதல் இயக்கத்திரைப்படம்:பிரான்ஸ் நாட்டைச் சேர்ந்த அறிவியல் ஆசிரியரான சார்லஸ் எமிலி என்பவரே முதன் முதலில் இயங்குபடத்தை தயாரித்து திரையிட்டவர் ஆவார். இவர் பிராக்ஸினோ ஸ்கோபியை 1877-இல் கண்டுபிடித்தார். இதில் புகைப்படச் சுருளில் துளையிடப்பட்டு ஒன்றன் பின் ஒன்று வருமாறு செய்யப்பட்டிருந்தது. பின் திரையிடும் கருவியை 1888-ஆம் ஆண்டு திசம்பர் மாதம் கண்டுபிடித்தார். 1892-ஆம் ஆண்டு அக்டோபர் இருபத்தி எட்டாவது தேதி முதல் இயங்குபடமான ’’’பாவ்ரே பைட்’’’, பாரிஸில் உள்ள முசி கிரேவின் என்னும் திரையரங்கில் திரையிடப்பட்டது. இத்திரைப்படம் ஒளி ஊடுருவக்கூடிய பட்டைகளில் வரையப்பட்ட படங்களினால் உருவாக்கப்பட்டதாகும். தனித்தனியாக வரையப்பட்ட ஐநூறு படங்களினால் பதினைந்து நிமிடங்கள் ஓடும்படி இப்படம் தயாரிக்கப்பட்டிருந்தது. 1900-ஆம் ஆண்டின் தொடக்கத்தில் ஐந்து இலட்சத்திற்கும் அதிகமான மக்கள் இத்திரைப்படத்தினை கண்டுகளித்திருந்தனர்."},{"question":"Apakah maksud \\"bagai bajak wangkang makan diangkat\\"?","answer":"dikatakan kepada orang yang suka kena puji"},{"question":"Inona no anaran’ilay horonan-tsarimihetsika izay misy andiam-biby miezaka hiverina any Etazonia, ka i Madagasikara no niaingany ?","answer":"« Madagascar » no anaran’ilay sarimihetsika novokarin’ny « DreamWorks Animation."},{"question":"Waxaad sheegtaa miraha ama furuutka uroon hooyada uurka Leh?","answer":"Xiliga uurka waxaa lagama maarmaan ah in hooyadu ay cunto cunnooyin nafaqo leh, kuwaasoo aan ku koobnayn hooyada oo kaliya balse uu sidoo kale ka faa’idayo uurjiifka, cunnada fudud ama ay ku badan tahay baruurtu ayaa haboon in aan labadsan xiliga uurka taas badal keedana ay hooyadu joogteyso cunida miraha iyo cunooyinka leh maadada faybarka.Cunidda miraha ama qudaarta ayaa hooyada iyo uurkujirka ba u leh faa’idooyin muhiim ah, sida in hooyadu ay ka hesho macdanta iyo fiitamiinada ay u baahantahay iyo inay ka hortagaan calool istaaga kaasoo ay ka cawdaan qaar badan oo kamid ah hooyooyinka uurka leh. Hooyada uurka leh ayaa sidoo kale ubaahan in marwalba jirkeedu uusan dareemin qalayl la xariirta biyo la’aan.Biyaha ayaa hooyada uurka leh ka caawiya samaynta madheerta taasoo nafaqada u gudbisa uurjiifka kana soo gudbiso wasaqda. Waxay kaloo biyuhu u wanaag san yihiin koritaanka ilmaha uurjiifka ah. Hadaba miraha muhiimka ay ee looga baahan yahay hooyada uurka leh inay joogteyso cunitaan kooda waxaa kamid ah todobadaan noocLiin macaan/bambeello:Waxay hooyada ka caawinaysa in jirkeeda ay ka dhigto mid qoyan aan biyo la’aan ahayn. Liin macaanta ayaa ka kooban macdanta loo yaqaan folate taasoo qayb ka ah walxaha ay ka samaysmaan unugyada dhiiga cas, waxayna ka hortag wanaag san u tahay inay san hooyadu dareemin dhiig yari iyo nafaqo darro soo wajahda xilliga uurka. Liinta ayaa sidoo kale ka kooban fiitamiin C kaasoo ka hortaga dhaawaca soo gaari kara unugyada jirka. Waxay faa’ido balaaran u leedahay uurjiifka waxayna ka hortagtaa cillad ku imaan karta samaysinka maskaxda iyo xangullaha.Canbaha:Cambaha ayaa ka kooban fiitamiinada A iyo C, waxuuna muhiimad u leeyahay hooyada uurka leh iyo ilmaha uur jiifka ahba. Hal koob oo canbe ayaa ka kooban xadiga saxda ee ay hooyadu uga baahan tahay fiitaminada A iyo C. fiitamiinka A ayaa muhiimad u leh uurjiifka, waxuuna ka caawiyaa difaaca jidhka xilliga dhalashada iyo kadibba.Afakaadho:Waxay afakaadhadu ka kooban tahay macdan ay ka mid yihiin magnesium, potassium iyo choline. Hooyooyinka uurka leh ee cunna ama cabba afagaadhada ayaa waxaa ku yar lalabada iyo calool qabadka taasoo loo aaneeyo macdanta magnesium iyo potassium. Afagaadhada ayaa sidoo kale ka kooban fiitamiinada A iyo C, maadada Iron, iyo xaddi faybar ah. Choline ayaa muhiimad u leh koritaanka maskaxda iyo neerfayaasha uurkajiifka."},{"question":"Кандай кызыктуу окуяларды билесиз?","answer":"🇰🇬 Кыргызстандын Мамлекеттик туу күнү 2010-жылдан бери белгиленип келет. Майрам Кыргыз Республикасынын Президентинин 2009-жылдын 10-июнундагы №270 \\"Кыргыз Республикасынын Мамлекеттик туусу жөнүндө\\" Жарлыгы менен белгиленген. Жарлыкка Кыргызстандын жарандарын мекенчилдик жана өлкөнүн мамлекеттик символикасын сыйлоо жандүйнөнү тарбиялоо максатында кол коюлган."},{"question":"Apakah maksud \\"berat kaki\\"? Berilah satu contoh ayat untuknya.","answer":"Ia bermaksud malas. Contoh ayat: Dia berat kaki untuk ke pesta hari jadi temannya."},{"question":"Batun me ake magana a wannan mai zuwa? \\"Afghanistan: masu fashin baki sun nuna shakku kan yiwuwar kulla yarjejeniya\\".  ","answer":"Jumlar : \\"Afghanistan: masu fashin baki sun nuna shakku kan yiwuwar kulla yarjejeniya\\" na batu ne a kan duniya."},{"question":"Inona ary izany: \\" atoko tsy masaka, atono mora foana \\"?","answer":"Ny valiny amin'ny hoe \\" atoko tsy masaka, atono mora foana \\" dia volo ."},{"question":"සිංහල ජන කතාවක් කියන්න ","answer":"මහදැනමුත්තා මඩේ එරීමඔන්න මහදැනමුත්තා දවසක් එයාගේ ගෝලයෝ පස්දෙනා වෙච්ච පොල් බෑ මුණා, ඉඳිකටු පැන්චා, පුවක් බඩිල්ලා, රබ්බඩ අයියා, කෝටුකිතයියා, එක්ක ගමනක් යන්න පිටත් වුණා. ඉතින් මේ ගමන යන්න පාර තිබ්බේ වෙලක් මැදින්.ඔහොම යනකොට ලොකුම ලොකු මඩ වගුරක් හම්බුණා. ගෝලයො ටික මඩ වගුරෙන් එගොඩ වෙන්න බයේ මඩ වගුර වටේට එක් රොක් වී සිටියා. \\"ඔහොම බය වෙලා බෑ ළමයිනේ, !!! මන් එගොඩ වෙලා පෙන්නන්නම්. උඹලා පිටිපස්සෙන් වරෙල්ලා\\" යි කියූ මහදැනමුත්තා වගුර ට බැස්සා. වගුරේ ටික දුරක් ගිය මහදැනමුත්තා වගුරේ එරෙන්න ගත්තා. \\"ළමයිනේ !!! මාව ගොඩට ගනිල්ලා. මාව වගුරේ එරෙනෝ\\" කියා මහදැනමුත්තා අත් ඔසවා දඟලමින් කෑ ගහන්න ගත්තා. එත් ගෝලයෝ පස්දෙනාම නිකම්වත් හෙළවුණේ නැහැ. පස්දෙනාම තුෂ්නීම්භූතව එකිනෙකාගේ මූණ බලා ගත්තා. \\"අනේ ගුරුතුමෝ !!! මඩේ වැටුණාම - ගොඩගන්න කියලා මේ පොතේ ලියලා නැහැනේ. ඉතින් අපි කොහොමද ඉගැන්නුවේ නැති දෙයක් කරන්නේ???\\" එක් ගෝලයෙක් ඇහුවා. \\"අනේ..!! හපෝයි...!!! අනේ..!! හපෝයි...!!! මේක උඹලට උගන්නපු මගේ වැරැද්ද. මෙහෙම ලියා ලියාගනිල්ලා උඹලගේ මහලොකු පොතේ.................කවදහරි කෙනෙක් මඩ වළක වැටුනොත් එතනින් ගොඩගත යුතුයි\\" කියා මහදැනමුත්තා කෝපයෙන් කීවා. ඉන් පස්සේ ගෝලයෝ රොත්ත එකතු වෙලා මහදැනමුත්තා ව මඩ වගුරෙන් ගොඩට ගත්තා."},{"question":"Баткен деген сөздү укканда сиз эмнелерди элестетесиз?","answer":"Баткен деген сөздү укканда өрүк заарлуу бактарды 🌳🌳🌳,  Айгүл гүлдү 🥀,  Төрт көл 🏞️ суусактагычты , кең пейил, мээнеткеч, меймандос элди элестетем.Кыргызстан 🇰🇬."},{"question":"Èrìgì","answer":"Ní kété tí a bá ti kúrò ní eyín òkè tán ni a máa bọ́ sí ibi ẹran, ibi ẹran yìí ni a ń pè ní Èrìgì."},{"question":"' පහතින් ලියන ලද ' තනිපදය කුමක් ද?","answer":"යථෝක්ත යනු ඉහතින් සඳහන් කරන ලදී වන අතර, පහතින් ලියන ලද යන්නට අධෝ සටහන භාවිත කෙරේ."},{"question":"كمل الفقرة:وأكد الأمين العام للمعرض الدولي للبستنة إكسبو الدوحة 2023 محمد علي الخوري، أن اللجنة المنظمة عملت على جذب جميع التقنيات العالمية التي تسهم في","answer":"الحد من التصحر وزيادة الرقعة الخضراء والأراضي الزراعية، والمحافظة على الموارد اليسيرة من المياه الموجودة في الخليج."},{"question":"البوسنة والهرسك إحدى الدول الأوربية المطلة على…؟","answer":"-البحر المتوسط"},{"question":"Гран-при жөнүндө эмне айта аласыз?","answer":"2016-жылга үч жарышка келишим түзүлгөн, бирок календарда көрсөтүлгөн эмес. Американын Гран-приси 15 жылдык келишимге ылайык Нью-Джерсидеги Порт Империал көчөсүндө биринчи жолу өткөрүлмөкчү. Мурда жарыш 2004-жылы башталышы керек болчу, бирок төртүнчү жыл катары менен кийинкиге жылдырылган. Индиянын Гран-приси 2013-жылдагы жарыштан кийин календардан алынып салынган., салык төлөө боюнча талаш-тартыштан кийин. 2014 жана 2015-жылдары жарышты жандандырууга бир нече жолу аракет жасалгандан кийин, анын кайтып келиши 2016-жылга чейин жылдырылган. Бирок, ал дагы бир жолу сезондун акыркы календарынан алынып салынды. 2006-жылы Формула-1 менеджменти 2010-жылдан баштап Кореянын эл аралык трассасында Кореянын Гран-присин өткөрүү боюнча жети жылдык келишимге кол койгон. Бирок, иш-чара 2014-жылы токтотулуп, 2016-жылы үчүнчү сезон катары менен календардан алынып салынган."},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਗਉੜੀ ਪੂਰਬੀ ਮਹਲਾ ੪ ॥ਹਰਿ ਹਰਿ ਅਰਥਿ ਸਰੀਰੁ ਹਮ ਬੇਚਿਆ ਪੂਰੇ ਗੁਰ ਕੈ ਆਗੇ ॥ਸਤਿਗੁਰ ਦਾਤੈ ਨਾਮੁ ਦਿੜਾਇਆ ਮੁਖਿ ਮਸਤਕਿ ਭਾਗ ਸਭਾਗੇ ॥੧॥ਰਾਮ ਗੁਰਮਤਿ ਹਰਿ ਲਿਵ ਲਾਗੇ ॥੧॥ ਰਹਾਉ ॥ਘਟਿ ਘਟਿ ਰਮਈਆ ਰਮਤ ਰਾਮ ਰਾਇ ਗੁਰ ਸਬਦਿ ਗੁਰੂ ਲਿਵ ਲਾਗੇ ॥ਹਉ ਮਨੁ ਤਨੁ ਦੇਵਉ ਕਾਟਿ ਗੁਰੂ ਕਉ ਮੇਰਾ ਭ੍ਰਮੁ ਭਉ ਗੁਰ ਬਚਨੀ ਭਾਗੇ ॥੨॥ਅੰਧਿਆਰੈ ਦੀਪਕ ਆਨਿ ਜਲਾਏ ਗੁਰ ਗਿਆਨਿ ਗੁਰੂ ਲਿਵ ਲਾਗੇ ॥ਅਗਿਆਨੁ ਅੰਧੇਰਾ ਬਿਨਸਿ ਬਿਨਾਸਿਓ ਘਰਿ ਵਸਤੁ ਲਹੀ ਮਨ ਜਾਗੇ ॥੩॥ਸਾਕਤ ਬਧਿਕ ਮਾਇਆਧਾਰੀ ਤਿਨ ਜਮ ਜੋਹਨਿ ਲਾਗੇ ॥ਉਨ ਸਤਿਗੁਰ ਆਗੈ ਸੀਸੁ ਨ ਬੇਚਿਆ ਓਇ ਆਵਹਿ ਜਾਹਿ ਅਭਾਗੇ ॥੪॥ਹਮਰਾ ਬਿਨਉ ਸੁਨਹੁ ਪ੍ਰਭ ਠਾਕੁਰ ਹਮ ਸਰਣਿ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਹਰਿ ਮਾਗੇ ॥ਜਨ ਨਾਨਕ ਕੀ ਲਜ ਪਾਤਿ ਗੁਰੂ ਹੈ ਸਿਰੁ ਬੇਚਿਓ ਸਤਿਗੁਰ ਆਗੇ ॥੫॥੧੦॥੨੪॥੬੨॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 171 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਰਾਮਦਾਸ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਬਾਣੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਸਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"(ਹੇ ਭਾਈ !) ਹਰੀ ਦੇ ਮਿਲਾਪ ਦੀ ਖ਼ਾਤਰ ਮੈਂ ਆਪਣਾ ਸਰੀਰ ਪੂਰੇ ਗੁਰੂ ਅੱਗੇ ਵੇਚ ਦਿੱਤਾ ਹੈ, ਦਾਤੇ ਸਤਿਗੁਰੂ ਨੇ (ਮੇਰੇ ਹਿਰਦੇ ਵਿਚ) ਹਰੀ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਪੱਕਾ ਕਰ ਦਿੱਤਾ ਹੈ, ਮੇਰੇ ਮੂੰਹ ਉਤੇ ਮੇਰੇ ਮੱਥੇ ਉਤੇ ਭਾਗ ਜਾਗ ਪਏ ਹਨ, ਮੈਂ ਭਾਗਾਂ ਵਾਲਾ ਹੋ ਗਿਆ ਹਾਂ ।੧।(ਹੇ ਭਾਈ !) ਗੁਰੂ ਦੀ ਮਤਿ ਉਤੇ ਤੁਰਿਆਂ ਹੀ ਰਾਮ ਹਰੀ (ਦੇ ਚਰਨਾਂ) ਵਿਚ ਲਗਨ ਲੱਗਦੀ ਹੈ ।੧।ਰਹਾਉ।(ਭਾਵੇਂ ਉਹ) ਸੋਹਣਾ ਰਾਮ ਹਰੇਕ ਸਰੀਰ ਵਿਚ ਵਿਆਪਕ ਹੈ (ਫਿਰ ਭੀ) ਗੁਰੂ ਦੇ ਸ਼ਬਦ ਦੀ ਰਾਹੀਂ (ਹੀ ਉਸ ਨਾਲ) ਲਗਨ ਲੱਗਦੀ ਹੈ । ਮੈਂ ਗੁਰੂ ਨੂੰ ਆਪਣਾ ਮਨ ਆਪਣਾ ਤਨ ਦੇਣ ਨੂੰ ਤਿਆਰ ਹਾਂ (ਆਪਣਾ ਸਿਰ) ਕੱਟ ਕੇ ਦੇਣ ਨੂੰ ਤਿਆਰ ਹਾਂ । ਗੁਰੂ ਦੇ ਬਚਨਾਂ ਦੀ ਰਾਹੀਂ ਹੀ ਮੇਰੀ ਭਟਕਣਾ ਮੇਰਾ ਡਰ ਦੂਰ ਹੋ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ ।੨।(ਮਾਇਆ ਦੇ ਮੋਹ ਦੇ) ਹਨੇਰੇ ਵਿਚ (ਫਸੇ ਹੋਏ ਜੀਵ ਦੇ ਅੰਦਰ ਗੁਰੂ ਹੀ ਗਿਆਨ ਦਾ) ਦੀਵਾ ਲਿਆ ਕੇ ਬਾਲਦਾ ਹੈ, ਗੁਰੂ ਦੇ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਗਿਆਨ ਦੀ ਰਾਹੀਂ ਹੀ (ਪ੍ਰਭੂ-ਚਰਨਾਂ ਵਿਚ) ਲਗਨ ਲੱਗਦੀ ਹੈ,ਅਗਿਆਨਤਾ ਦਾ ਹਨੇਰਾ ਪੂਰੇ ਤੌਰ ਤੇ ਨਾਸ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ, ਹਿਰਦੇ-ਘਰ ਵਿਚ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ-ਪਦਾਰਥ ਲੱਭ ਪੈਂਦਾ ਹੈ, ਮਨ (ਮੋਹ ਦੀ ਨੀਂਦ ਵਿਚੋਂ) ਜਾਗ ਪੈਂਦਾ ਹੈ ।੩।ਮਾਇਆ ਨੂੰ ਆਪਣੀ ਜ਼ਿੰਦਗੀ ਦਾ ਆਸਰਾ ਬਣਾਣ ਵਾਲੇ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਰੱਬ ਨਾਲੋਂ ਟੁੱਟ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ, ਨਿਰਦਈ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ, ਆਤਮਕ ਮੌਤ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਆਪਣੀ ਤੱਕ ਵਿਚ ਰੱਖਦੀ ਹੈ ।ਉਹ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਸਤਿਗੁਰੂ ਦੇ ਅੱਗੇ ਆਪਣਾ ਸਿਰ ਨਹੀਂ ਵੇਚਦੇ (ਉਹ ਆਪਣੇ ਅੰਦਰੋਂ ਹਉਮੈ ਨਹੀਂ ਗਵਾਂਦੇ) ਉਹ ਬਦ-ਕਿਸਮਤ ਜਨਮ ਮਰਨ ਦੇ ਗੇੜ ਵਿਚ ਪਏ ਰਹਿੰਦੇ ਹਨ ।੪।ਹੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ! ਹੇ ਠਾਕੁਰ ! ਮੇਰੀ ਬੇਨਤੀ ਸੁਣ, ਮੈਂ ਤੇਰੀ ਸਰਨ ਆਇਆ ਹਾਂ, ਮੈਂ ਤੈਥੋਂ ਤੇਰਾ ਨਾਮ ਮੰਗਦਾ ਹਾਂ । ਦਾਸ ਨਾਨਕ ਦੀ ਲਾਜ ਇੱਜ਼ਤ (ਰੱਖਣ ਵਾਲਾ) ਗੁਰੂ ਹੀ ਹੈ, ਮੈਂ ਸਤਿਗੁਰੂ ਦੇ ਅੱਗੇ ਆਪਣਾ ਸਿਰ ਵੇਚ ਦਿੱਤਾ ਹੈ (ਮੈਂ ਨਾਮ ਦੇ ਵੱਟੇ ਵਿਚ ਆਪਣੀ ਅਪਣੱਤ ਗੁਰੂ ਦੇ ਹਵਾਲੇ ਕਰ ਦਿੱਤੀ ਹੈ) ।੫।੧੦।੨੪।੬੨।\\""},{"question":"\\"ቢል ራስል ከቦስተን ሴልቲክስ ጋር 11 ሻምፒዮናዎችን አሸንፏል\\" የሚለው ጥያቄ ምንድን ነው? ርዕሰ ጉዳዩ ኤን ቢ ኤ ሻምፒዮናዎች ተጫዋቾች ዝርዝር ነው።","answer":"\\"በጣም ብዙ የኤን ቢ ኤ ሻምፒዮናዎችን ያሸነፈ ማን ነው?"},{"question":"ايش معنى كلمة \\"يندف\\"؟","answer":"يندف : يضرب بقوه وعاده ما تكون ضربه بواسطه الكف وتكون مسلطه الى الظهر"},{"question":"次の文章から重要な語彙を探し、その意味を説明しなさい。 アフガニスタンで7日、大きな地震が2回ありました。アフガニスタンを支配しているタリバンは、地震で2000人以上が亡くなって、たくさんの家が壊れたと言っています。被害があった所では、大勢の人がテントで生活しています。夜はとても寒くて、0°Cぐらいになる所もあるため、壊れた家から毛布を探して持ってくる人もいます。食べ物や水だけではなくて、すぐに住むことができる家を作ることも必要になっています。アフガニスタンでは11日にも大きな地震がありました。国連のWFPは、アフガニスタンでは7万人から10万人が地震の被害を受けたと言っています。そして、この人たちを助けるために、日本など世界に協力してほしいと言いました。","answer":"この文章に出てくる重要な語彙とその意味は次の通りである。- 支配: 1）ある土地やそこに住む人々を治めること。2）ものごとを思うように動かすこと。- 被害: 1）損害を受けること。また、受けた害。- テント: 1）キャンプや運動会などで、小屋のような形に張る幕。天幕。- 毛布: 1）羊毛などで織った厚い織物。- 国連: 1）第二次世界大戦が終わった1945年、世界の平和と安全を守るために作られた仕組み。本部はアメリカのニューヨークにある。国連。UN。- 助ける: 1）危ないことや苦しいことから救う。2）力を貸す。手伝う。- 協力: 1）力を合わせて、ものごとを行うこと。"},{"question":"  Sheeg sanadkii uu soo islaamay halyeey-gii Cumar Bin Khadaab RC ?","answer":"Wuxu soo islaamay sanadkii 6-aad ee soo diridii nabi Muxamad NNKH ."},{"question":" Sheeg Qaaraddaha Loo-Yaqaano Qaaradaha Da’da Yar Ama Cusub?","answer":"Waxaa Loo-Yaaqaanaa:-1- Qaaradda America.2- Qaaradda Australia."},{"question":"Madaxa Lalbaad: Xuquuqda, Xorriyaadka Aasaasiga Ah Ee Qofka Iyo Xaddidaadooda.","answer":"Madaxa Lalbaad: Xuquuqda, Xorriyaadka Aasaasiga Ah Ee Qofka Iyo Xaddidaadooda.Qodobka 17aad. Xorriyadda Diinta iyo Caqiiddada. (1) Qof kastaa wuxuu xor u yahay in uu ku dhaqmo dantiisa.(2) Diin aan ahayn Islaamka laguma faain karo Jamhuuriyadda Federaalka Soomaaliya. Qodobka 18aad. Xorriyadda Ra'yiga iyo Afkaarta.(1) Qof kastaa wuxuu xaq u leeyahay in uu yeesho, soo bandhigo ra'yigiüsa iyo in uu doono, inuu helo o0 gudbiyo ra'yigiüisa, xog ama afkaar si kastaba.(2) Xorriyatu qoolka waxaa kar mid, xorriyadda hadalka, saxaafadda iyo wax walba oo soo gelaya warbaahinta clektaroonikada iyo internet-ka.(3) Qof kastaa wuxuu xaq u leeyahay in uu muujyo hal'abuurkiisa faneed, xorriyaddisa aqooneed iyo xorriyadda cilmi-baarista. Qodobka 19aad. Xurmada Hoyga (1) Qofna gurigisa ama meeshii kale ce isaga u gaar ah lama geli karo, lama baari karo, lamana basaasi karo amar garsoore oo sababaysan la'aantiis.(2) Waxaa wajitb ah in amarka garsooraha si toos ah loogu akhriyo degganaha hoyga, baarahana waxaa ka reeban ku xadgudubka sharciga.Qodobka 20aad. Xorriyadda Kulanka, Bannaanbaxa, Cabashada iyo Codsi-wadareedka.(1) Qof kastaa wuxuu xaq u leeyahay in uu abaabulo, kana qaybglo kulammo ama bannaabax oo si xasilooni ah cabasho loogu muujinayo, iyada oo aan oggolaansho loo bahnayn. (2) Qof kastaa wuxuu xaq u leeyahay inuu cabasho qoraal ah u gudbiyo hay'adaha Dawladda.Qodobka 21aad. Xorriyadda Isu-socodka iyo Degitaanka(1) Qof kasta oo si sharci ah ku deggan dhulka Jamhuuriyaddu wuxuu xaq u leeyahay in uu si xor ah u degi karo, ugu dhex-socon karo meel kasta oo dalka ka mid ah, kana bixi karo.(2) Muwaaddin kasta wuxuu xaq u leeyahay soo-gelidda iyo joogitaanka waddanka iyo inuu helo Baasabboo.Qodobka 22aad. Xaqa Ka-qaybgalka Siyaasadda.(1) Muwaaddin kastaa wuxuu xaqu leeyahay in uu ka qayb-qaato arrimaha guud ce dadweynaha. Xaqa kan waxaa ka mid ah: (a) Inuu samaysan karo ama ka mid noqon karo xisbi siyaasadeed, kana qayb-qaadan karo hawlihisa; (b) In xisbi siyaasadecd gudihisa looga dooran karo jago kasta.(2) Muwaaddin kasta po buuxtya shoruudaha sharciga tilmaamayo wuxuu xaq u leeyahay inuu wax doorto, lana doorto.(3) Xuaquuqda ku xusan faqradaha iyo ce qodobkan waa in loogu dhaqmaa si waafaqsan Dastuurkan iyo sharci Baarlamaanka Federalka."},{"question":"Apakah maksud 'buang sauh'? Berikan satu contoh ayat.","answer":"Ia bermaksud berlabuh Contoh ayat: Kapal itu buang sauh di pelabuhan yang berhampiran setelah sebulan belayar tanpa henti."},{"question":"Geef me een lijst met enkele kenmerken van een goede koffiebar?","answer":"Enkele kenmerken van goede koffiebars zijn onder andere: - Zeer goede koffie, ofwel vers lokaal gebrand of verkregen van een kwaliteitsbrander - Hoogwaardige koffiemolens, brouwapparaten en een hoogwaardige espressomachine en goed opgeleide barista's - Verschillende koffiebrandopties (bijv. medium roast, dark roast) en brouwmethoden (bijv. filterkoffie en pour-over) beschikbaar - Een verscheidenheid aan café-gerechten, zoals gebak en croissants, beschikbaar voor aankoop om bij de koffie te serveren - Voldoende zitplaatsen, met stopcontacten beschikbaar bij de meeste stoelen."},{"question":"Hòn đảo lớn nhất thế giới rộng bao nhiêu km2?","answer":"Greenland là hòn đảo lớn nhất và duy nhất trên thế giới có diện tích vượt quá 1 triệu km2. Kích thước của nó là 2,175 triệu km2, gần bằng 1/4 diện tích của Australia.Greenland là nơi sinh sống của 56.000 người, chủ yếu là người Inuit. Đây là một trong những nơi có dân cư thưa thớt nhất trên thế giới."},{"question":"Soạn bài Điều gì giúp bóng đá Việt Nam chiến thắng Ngữ văn lớp 6","answer":"- Văn bản thuật lại một sự kiện theo mối quan hệ nguyên nhân – kết quả thường bao gồm ba thông tin chính: nguyên nhân – diễn biến – kết quả, nhằm trả lời ba câu hỏi lớn: Vì sao lại xảy ra sự việc ấy?, Sự việc ấy diễn ra thế nào?, Kết quả ra sao?.- Khi đọc văn bản thông tin thuật lại một sự kiện theo mối quan hệ nguyên nhân – kết quả:+ Văn bản được đăng ở thethaovanhoa.vn và vào ngày 15/12/2019. Thời điểm đó vào một năm trước (15/12/2018) là trận chung kết lượt về AFF Cup 2018 giữa Việt Nam và Malaysia, kết quả là Việt Nam đã vô địch năm đó.+ Văn bản thuật lại những nguyên nhân khiến bóng đá Việt Nam “thống trị” ở Đông Nam Á thời điểm năm 2019. Sự kiện ấy được nêu ở phần giữa của văn bản.+ Thứ tự triển khai của sự kiện: Giới thiệu những thành công của bóng đá Việt Nam ở thời điểm hiện tại. Nêu nguyên nhân của bóng đá Việt Nam thành công ở thời điểm hiện tại.+ Các yếu tố như nhan đề, sa pô, đề mục, hình ảnh,… trong văn bản có tác dụng thuật lại các sự kiện theo trật tự thời gian, trình bày một cách khoa học, dễ hiểu, sinh động thu hút người đọc và giúp họ ghi nhớ, nắm bắt những sự kiện chính.+ Sự kiện được thuật lại cho người đọc thấy được sự thay đổi, phát triển của nền bóng đá do nhiều nguyên nhân cấu thành nên chứ không phải là may mắn.- Đọc trước văn bản Điều gì giúp bóng đá Việt Nam chiến thắng?; tìm hiểu thêm về đội tuyển bóng đá nam và nữ của Việt Nam ở thời điểm bài viết nêu lên. Ghi lại những thông tin em cho là thú vị:+ Sau 60 năm, đội tuyển U22 bóng đá Việt Nam chính thức giành tấm HCV SEA Games 30 - danh hiệu còn thiếu trong phòng truyền thống mà bóng đá Việt Nam đã rất khao khát trong suốt quãng thời gian dài. + Tuyển Việt Nam và Thái Lan đang là những tên tuổi lớn của bóng đá khu vực khi cả 2 đều lần lượt giữ chức vô địch ở môn bóng đá nữ. Tại SEA Games 2019, các cô gái trẻ của làng bóng đá Việt nam đã kiên cường thi đấu giành thắng lợi đem lại vẻ vang cho nền bóng đá nước nhà+ Đội tuyển bóng đá nam nữ quả thật đã khơi dậy một sự khát khao; gắn kết những mắt xích trong một tập thể mà mỗi người làm tốt phần việc của mình (từ người phiên dịch đến các trợ lý mỗi người mỗi việc); đặt đúng và khai thác đúng những tiềm năng…"},{"question":"जपानमधील सामुराई कोण होते?","answer":"सामुराई हे सरंजामशाही जपानमधील योद्ध्यांचा एक वर्ग होता ज्यांचा उदय हेयान कालखंडात झाला (794-1185) आणि 1868 मध्ये मीजी पुनर्संचयित होईपर्यंत जपानी इतिहासात महत्त्वपूर्ण भूमिका बजावली. \\"सामुराई\\" या शब्दाचा मूळ अर्थ \\"सेवा करणे\\" किंवा \\"त्या\\" असा होतो. जे सेवा करतात,\\" आणि या योद्धांनी सम्राट, शोगुन आणि डेम्यो (जमीन अधिपती) यांच्यासह कुलीन लोकांची सेवा केली.सामुराई संस्कृतीची मुख्य वैशिष्ट्ये आणि पैलूंमध्ये हे समाविष्ट आहे:1. बुशिदो: सामुराईने बुशिदो म्हणून ओळखल्या जाणार्‍या कठोर आचारसंहितेचे पालन केले, ज्याने निष्ठा, सन्मान, स्वयं-शिस्त आणि कर्तव्य यासारख्या सद्गुणांवर भर दिला. बुशिदोने युद्धभूमीवर आणि बाहेर दोन्ही सामुराईच्या वर्तनासाठी मार्गदर्शक म्हणून काम केले.2. सामाजिक पदानुक्रम: सामुराई हे लष्करी अभिजात वर्गाचे होते आणि सामाजिक पदानुक्रमात त्यांना विशेषाधिकार प्राप्त होते. ते सामान्यांपेक्षा वरचे होते परंतु खानदानी लोकांपेक्षा खाली होते. सामुराई वर्ग बहुतेकदा जमिनीच्या मालकीशी संबंधित होता आणि त्यांना त्यांच्या मालकांकडून स्टायपेंड मिळत असे.3. लष्करी प्रशिक्षण: समुराईंना विविध मार्शल आर्ट्स आणि युद्ध तंत्राचे प्रशिक्षण देण्यात आले. तलवारीचा वापर (कटाना) हे एक मूलभूत कौशल्य होते आणि तिरंदाजी, घोडेस्वारी आणि इतर लढाऊ कौशल्ये देखील आवश्यक होती.4. चिलखत आणि शस्त्रे: सामुराई त्यांच्या विशिष्ट चिलखतीसाठी ओळखले जात होते, जे शतकानुशतके विकसित झाले. त्यांच्याकडे कटाना (लँगस्वर्ड), वाकिझाशी (लहान तलवार) आणि युमी (धनुष्य आणि बाण) यासह अनेक शस्त्रे होती.5. डेमियो आणि शोगुन: जपानच्या सरंजामशाहीच्या काळात, देशाची विभागणी डेमियोने शासित प्रदेशांमध्ये केली होती. डेम्यो हे शक्तिशाली जमीनदार होते ज्यांनी सामुराईचे स्वतःचे सैन्य राखले. दुसरीकडे, शोगुन हा सर्वोच्च लष्करी सेनापती होता, जो बहुधा सम्राटाने नियुक्त केला होता आणि डेमियोवर अधिकार ठेवला होता.6. नकार: 19व्या शतकाच्या उत्तरार्धात केंद्रीकृत सरकार आणि आधुनिकीकरणाच्या वाढीसह सामुराई वर्ग कमी होऊ लागला. नवीन सरकारने जपानचे आधुनिकीकरण करण्याचा आणि पारंपारिक सरंजामशाही व्यवस्था रद्द करण्याचा प्रयत्न केल्यामुळे मेजी रिस्टोरेशनने सामुराई युगाचा अंत झाला.आज, सामुराईचा वारसा साहित्य, चित्रपट आणि केंदो आणि आयडो यांसारख्या मार्शल आर्ट्ससह विविध स्वरूपात जतन केला जातो. जपानी संस्कृतीत समुराई हे सन्मान, शिस्त आणि मार्शल पराक्रमाचे प्रतीक आहे."},{"question":"Aiza ny toerana avo indrindra eto Madagasikara ?","answer":"Ny tendron’i Maromokotra no toerana avo indrindra eto Madagasikara, mirefy 2876 metatra ny hahavony."},{"question":"Qui était l'artiste Yayoi Kusama ?","answer":"Yayoi Kusama, artiste contemporaine japonaise, est célèbre pour ses installations immersives et ses motifs à pois. Ses « Infinity Mirror Rooms », telles que « Phalli's Field », créent des environnements immersifs et fascinants qui explorent les thèmes de l'infini, de la répétition et de la relation entre soi et l'espace."},{"question":"Terjemahkanlah penggalan teks Bahasa Inggris yang disadur dari kumpulan cerita anak dunia berikut ke teks dalam Bahasa Indonesia.But a long time ago, the elephant's nose was short and fat. Like a shoe in the middle of its face.Terjemahan:","answer":"Terjemahan dari teks \\"But a long time ago, the elephant's nose was short and fat. Like a shoe in the middle of its face\\" dalam Bahasa Indonesia adalah:Dahulu kala, hidung gajah pendek dan gemuk, ibaratnya seperti sebuah sepatu menempel di tengah-tengah wajahnya."},{"question":"બાર બાર વરસે નવાણ ગળાવ્યાં બાળગીત લખો.","answer":"બાર બાર  વરસે  નવાણ ગળાવ્યાં,  નવાણે નીર નો આવ્યાં જી રેતેડાવો  જાણતલ  તેડાવો  જોશી,  જોશીડા જોશ  જોવરાવો જી રેજાણતલ જોશીડો એમ કરી બોલ્યો, ‘દીકરો ને વહુ પધરાવો જી રે’‘ઘોડા  ખેલવતા  વીર  રે  અભેસંગ!   દાદાજી   બોલાવે   જી રે’‘શું રે કો' છો  મારા  સમરથ  દાદા,  શા કાજે  બોલાવ્યા જી રે?’‘જાણતલ જોશીડો એમ કરી બોલ્યો, દીકરો ને વહુ પધરાવો જી રે’‘એમાં તે શું મારા સમરથ દાદા, પારકી જણીને પૂછી આવો જી રે’‘બેટડો  ધવડાવતાં  વહુ  રે વાધેલી  વહુ,  સાસુજી  બોલાવે જી રે’’શું  રે  કો'  છો  મારા સમરથ  સાસુ,  શા કાજે બોલાવ્યાં જી રે’‘જાણતલ જોશીડો એમ કરી બોલ્યો, દીકરો ને વહુ પધરાવો જી રે’‘એમાં  તે  શું  મારા  સમરથ  સાસુ,   જે  કે'શો  તે કરશું જી રે’’ભાઈ  રે  જોશીડા,  વીર  રે  જોશીડા, સંદેશો  લઈ  જાજે જી રે’‘મારી  માતાને  એટલું  જ  કહેજે,  મોડિયો ને ચૂંદડી લાવે જી રે’‘ઊઠો   રે  મારાં   સમરથ  જેઠાણી,  ઊનાં  પાણી  મેલો  જી રે’‘ઊઠો  રે  મારા  સમરથ  દેરાણી,  માથાં   અમારાં  ગૂંથો  જી રે’‘ઊઠો  રે  મારા  સમરથ   દેરીડા,   વેલડિયું   શણગારો   જી રે’‘ઊઠો  રે  મારા  સમરથ  નણદી,      છેડાછેડી   બાંધો    જી રે’‘ઊઠો  રે  મારા  સમરથ  સસરા,  જાંગીડા ઢોલ  વગડાવો જી રે’‘આવો, આવો  મારા માનસંગ દીકરા,  છેલ્લાં ધાવણ  ધાવો જી રે’પુતર  જઈને  પારણે  પોઢાડ્યો,   નેણલે  આંસુડાંની  ધારું  જી રેઝાંઝ  પખાજ  ને  જંતર  વાગે,  દીકરો  ને  વહુ  પધરાવે  જી રે‘પાછું વાળી જોજો અભેસંગ દીકરા, ઘોડલાં કોણ ખેલવશે જી રે?’‘ઈ  રે  શું  બોલ્યાં   સમરથ  બાપુ,   નાનો  ભાઈ  ખેલવશે  જી રે’‘પાછું વાળીને જોજો વહુ રે વાધેલી વહુ, પુતર કોને ભળાવ્યાં જી રે?’‘કોણ  ધવરાવશે,  કોણ  રમાડશે,  કેમ  કરી  મોટા  થાશે  જી રે?’‘દેરાણી   ધવરાવશે,   નણદી  રમાડશે,  જેઠાણી   ઉછેરશે  જી રે’પહેલે પગથિયે  જઈ  પગ દીધો,  પાતાળે  પાણી  ઝબક્યાં  જી રેબીજે પગથિયે  જઈ  પગ દીધો,  કાંડા તે બુડ પાણી આવ્યાં જી રેત્રીજે  પગથિયે  જઈ  પગ  દીધો,  કેડ   સમાં  નીર  આવ્યાં જી રેચોથે   પગથિયે જઈ  પગ  દીધો,   છાતી સમાં નીર  આવ્યાં જી રેપાંચમે  પગથિયે  જઈ  પગ દીધો,  પરવશ  પડિયા પ્રાણિયા જી રે‘એક હોંકારો દ્યો ને  અભેસંગ,  ગોઝારાં પાણી કોણ પીશે જી રે?’‘પીશે તે  ચારણ, પીશે તે  ભાટો,  પીશે  અભેસંગનો  દાદો જી રે’‘એક હોંકારો દ્યો ને વાધેલી વહુ, ગોઝારાં પાણી કોણ પીશે જી રે?’‘પીશે તે  વાણિયા,  પીશે તે  બ્રાહ્મણ, પીશે વાળુભાના લોકો જી રે’તરી છે ચૂંદડી ને તર્યો છે મોડિયો, તર્યા અભેસંગનાં ખોળિયાં જી રેગાતાં  ને  વાતાં  ઘરમાં  આવ્યાં,  ઓરડા  અણોસરા  લાગે  જી રેવા'લાં હતાં  તેને ખોળે  બેસાડીયા,  દવલાંને  પાતાળ  પૂર્યાં  જી રે"},{"question":"ਮੱਲੜ੍ਹ ਦੀ ਖੇਤੀ ਵਿਚ ਮਹੱਤਤਾ ਤੇ ਚਾਨਣਾ ਪਾਓ ।","answer":"ਮੱਲੜ ਦੀ ਖੇਤੀ ਵਿਚ ਮਹੱਤਤਾ-1. ਛੇਤੀ ਗਲਣ ਵਾਲਾ ਮੱਲ ਪਾਉਣ ਨਾਲ ਮਿੱਟੀ ਦੇ ਕਿਣਕੇ ਆਪਸ ਵਿਚ ਇਸ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਜੁੜ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ ਕਿ ਉਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਦੀਆਂ ਛੋਟੀਆਂ ਅਤੇ ਪੋਲੀਆਂ (ਨਰਮ, ਭੁਰਭੁਰੀਆਂ) ਡਲੀਆਂ ਬਣ ਜਾਂਦੀਆਂ ਹਨ । ਇਸ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਦਾ ਮੁੱਲੜ ਰੇਤਲੀ ਅਤੇ ਚੀਕਣੀ ਦੋਹਾਂ ਕਿਸਮਾਂ ਦੀ ਚੋਂ ਲਈ ਵਧੀਆ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ । ਮੱਲੜ ਰੇਤਲੀ ਮਿੱਟੀ ਤੋਂ ਖੁਰਦਰੇ ਕਣਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਆਪਸ ਵਿਚ ਜੋੜਨ ਵਿਚ ਮਦਦ ਕਰਦਾ ਹੈ ਅਤੇ ਚੀਕਣੀ ਮਿੱਟੀ ਨੂੰ ਪੋਲੀ ਕਰ ਦਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ ਜਿਸ ਨਾਲ ਇਸ ਦਾ ਆਇਤਨ ਵੱਧ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ । ਹਵਾ ਦੀ ਆਵਾਜਾਈ ਸੌਖੀ ਅਤੇ ਤੇਜ਼ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ । ਇਸ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਮੱਲੜ ਰੇਤਲੀ ਤੇ ਚੀਕਣੀ ਦੋਹਾਂ ਪ੍ਰਕਾਰ ਦੀਆਂ ਭੋਆਂ ਨੂੰ ਵਧੇਰੇ ਭੁਰਭੁਰੀ ਅਤੇ ਉਪਜਾਊ ਬਣਾ ਦਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ ।2. ਮੱਲੜ ਤੋਂ ਨੂੰ ਪੋਲੀ ਕਰ ਦਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ ਜਿਸ ਨਾਲ ਭਾਂ ਦੀ ਪਾਣੀ ਸੋਖਣ ਦੀ ਸ਼ਕਤੀ ਵਿਚ ਕਾਫ਼ੀ ਵਾਧਾ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ ਅਤੇ ਤੋਂ ਪਾਣੀ ਨੂੰ ਵਧੇਰੇ ਲੰਬੇ ਸਮੇਂ ਤਕ ਆਪਣੇ ਅੰਦਰ ਸਾਂਭ ਕੇ ਰੱਖ ਸਕਦੀ ਹੈ ।3. ਤੋਂ ਵਿਚ ਮੌਜੂਦ ਲਾਭਕਾਰੀ ਤੇ ਉਪਯੋਗੀ ਜੀਵਾਣੂ ਮੱਲੜ੍ਹ ਤੋਂ ਆਪਣਾ ਭੋਜਨ ਵੀ ਪ੍ਰਾਪਤ ਕਰਦੇ ਹਨ । ਮੱਲ ਦੇ ਵਿਘਟਨ ਨਾਲ ਜੋ ਕਾਰਬਨ ਪੈਦਾ ਹੁੰਦੀ ਹੈ, ਉਹ ਇਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਜੀਵਾਣੁਆਂ ਲਈ ਭੋਜਨ ਦਾ ਕੰਮ ਦਿੰਦੀ ਹੈ । ਉਸ ਨਾਲ ਉਹ ਵਧੇਰੇ ਸ਼ਕਤੀਸ਼ਾਲੀ ਰੂਪ ਵਿਚ ਕਿਰਿਆ ਕਰਨ ਦੇ ਯੋਗ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ ।4. ਬੂਟਿਆਂ ਦੀਆਂ ਜੜ੍ਹਾਂ ਜ਼ਮੀਨ ਵਿਚ ਛੇਦ ਕਰਕੇ ਧਰਤੀ ਨੂੰ ਪੋਲੀ ਕਰ ਦਿੰਦੀਆਂ ਹਨ । ਜੜਾਂ ਦੇ ਗਲਣ-ਸੜਨ ਤੋਂ ਬਾਅਦ ਛੇਦਾਂ ਰਾਹੀਂ ਪਾਣੀ ਧਰਤੀ ਦੇ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਚਲਿਆ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ ਅਤੇ ਆਕਸੀਜਨ ਗੈਸ ਦੇ ਅੰਦਰ ਜਾਣ ਅਤੇ ਕਾਰਬਨ ਡਾਈਆਕਸਾਈਡ ਗੈਸ ਦੇ ਬਾਹਰ ਨਿਕਲਣ ਲਈ ਵੀ ਇਹ ਛੇਕ ਮਦਦ ਜਾਂ ਸਹਾਇਤਾ ਕਰਦੇ ਹਨ ।5. ਮੱਲੜ੍ਹ ਤੋਂ ਕਈ ਪੌਸ਼ਟਿਕ ਤੱਤ ਜਿਵੇਂ ਨਾਈਟਰੋਜਨ, ਗੰਧਕ, ਫ਼ਾਸਫ਼ੋਰਸ ਆਦਿ ਪ੍ਰਾਪਤ ਹੁੰਦੇ ਹਨ । ਇਹ ਤੱਤ ਦੇ ਕਣਾਂ ਨਾਲ ਚਿਪਕੇ ਰਹਿੰਦੇ ਹਨ । ਜ਼ਰੂਰਤ ਪੈਣ ‘ਤੇ ਪੌਦਾ ਇਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਤੱਤਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਵਰਤ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ ।6. ਕਈ ਭੋਆਂ ਦੀ ਤਾਸੀਰ ਅਜਿਹੀ ਹੁੰਦੀ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਪੌਦੇ ਤੋਂ ਵਿਚ ਮੌਜੂਦ ਲੋੜੀਂਦੇ ਤੱਤ ਪ੍ਰਾਪਤ ਨਹੀਂ ਕਰ ਸਕਦੇ । ਪਰ ਮੱਲੜ੍ਹ ਦੀ ਮੌਜੂਦਗੀ ਵਿਚ ਇਹ ਤੱਤ ਪੌਦੇ ਦੇ ਵਰਤਣ ਯੋਗ ਬਣ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ । ਉਦਾਹਰਨ ਵਜੋਂ ਤੇਜ਼ਾਬੀ ਜ਼ਮੀਨਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਫ਼ਾਸਫ਼ੋਰਸ ।7. ਮੱਲੜ੍ਹ ਦੇ ਗਲਣ-ਸੜਨ ਨਾਲ ਕਈ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਦੇ ਤੇਜ਼ਾਬ ਪੈਦਾ ਹੁੰਦੇ ਹਨ ਜੋ ਕਿ ਖਾਰੀਆਂ ਆਂ ਦਾ ਖਾਰਾਪਣ ਘੱਟ ਕਰਦੇ ਹਨ । ਇਹ ਤੇਜ਼ਾਬ ਅਤੇ ਕਾਰਬਨੀ ਗੈਸਾਂ (ਜਿਹੜੀਆਂ ਆਪ, ਵੀ ਤੇਜ਼ਾਬੀ ਗੁਣ ਰੱਖਦੀਆਂ ਹਨ) ਪੋਟਾਸ਼ੀਅਮ ਆਦਿ ਨਾਲ ਮਿਲ ਕੇ ਥੋਂ ਦੇ ਖਾਰੇਪਨ ਨੂੰ ਘਟਾ ਕੇ ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਪੌਦਿਆਂ ਦੇ ਉੱਗਣ ਅਤੇ ਵਧਣ-ਫੁੱਲਣ ਦੇ ਅਨੁਕੂਲ ਅਤੇ ਢੁੱਕਵਾਂ ਬਣਾਉਂਦੇ ਹਨ ।8. ਮੱਲੜ੍ਹ ਭੋ-ਤਾਪ ਨੂੰ ਸਥਿਰ ਰੱਖਣ ਵਿਚ ਵੀ ਮਦਦ ਕਰਦਾ ਹੈ । ਬਾਹਰਲੇ ਤਾਪਮਾਨ ਵਿਚ ਵਾਧਾ ਘਾਟਾ ਮੱਲੜ੍ਹ ਵਾਲੀ ਤੋਂ ਦੇ ਤਾਪਮਾਨ ਉੱਤੇ ਬਹੁਤ ਅਸਰ ਨਹੀਂ ਪਾਉਂਦਾ ।9. ਕਈ ਤੱਤ ਪੌਦੇ ਨੂੰ ਬਹੁਤ ਥੋੜ੍ਹੀ ਮਾਤਰਾ ਵਿਚ ਹੀ ਚਾਹੀਦੇ ਹੁੰਦੇ ਹਨ । ਇਹ ਤੱਤ ਰਸਾਇਣਿਕ ਖਾਦਾਂ ਤੋਂ ਪ੍ਰਾਪਤ ਨਹੀਂ ਹੁੰਦੇ । ਇਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਦੀ ਘਾਟ ਨਾਲ ਫ਼ਸਲਾਂ ਦੀ ਪੈਦਾਵਾਰ ਬਹੁਤ ਘੱਟ ਸਕਦੀ ਹੈ ਅਤੇ ਵਾਹੀਕਾਰ ਨੂੰ ਕਾਫ਼ੀ ਨੁਕਸਾਨ ਹੋ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ । ਇਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਵਿਚੋਂ ਕਾਫ਼ੀ ਸਾਰੇ ਤੱਤ ਮੱਲੜ੍ਹ ਵਿਚੋਂ ਮਿਲ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ ।"},{"question":"Đọc đoạn văn sau và đưa ra một tiêu đề phụ hợp với nội dung: TP HCM cần có cơ chế trả lương cho người tài theo thị trường, mức trần 120-150 triệu một tháng mới có thể mời các nhà khoa học xây dựng chiến lược, đó là kiến nghị của nhiều chuyên gia tại hội thảo cơ chế, chính sách đặc thù phát triển TP HCM theo Nghị quyết 54, ngày 30/7, nhằm giúp thành phố thu hút các nhà khoa học. Tuy nhiên, mức trần này liệu đã đủ hấp dẫn để thu hút người tài? Hồi tốt nghiệp Đại học, tôi xin việc với mức lương 2,5 triệu đồng một tháng. Cả năm sau, lương của tôi mới lên được 6 triệu đồng. Sau đó, tôi làm hồ sơ xin đi nước ngoài làm việc chân tay, mỗi tháng kiếm được 90 triệu đồng, trừ chi phí ăn ở, thuế bảo hiểm (sau này lấy lại được) thì mỗi tháng tôi còn được khoảng 70 triệu đồng. Làm việc bảy năm, đủ điều kiện nhập tịch, tôi bỏ việc đó để làm việc đúng chuyên ngành. Lúc bỏ, lương mỗi năm của tôi làng nhàng cũng cỡ 2,3 tỷ đồng (100 nghìn USD). Mức lương này vẫn đang bị chủ ép vì lúc đó tôi vẫn là một tay nhập cư, chưa có quốc tịch. Rồi tôi nhảy qua việc mới, đúng chuyên ngành, cộng thêm bảy năm kia vẫn đèn sách, được đi học nâng cao kiểu \\"học nghề\\" bên Việt Nam. Khi vào công ty, lương mỗi năm của tôi được nâng lên 3,8 tỷ đồng (162 nghìn USD), trừ thuế má mọi thứ, mỗi năm tôi vẫn để được trên 3,2 tỷ đồng. Chưa kể y tế lẫn giáo dục ở đây đều được miễn phí. >> Du học về nước khó tìm việc vì ảo tưởng lương cao Ở được hơn chục năm, thấy Việt Nam giờ có nhiều cơ hội, dịch dã mắc kẹt có cơ hội ở lại lâu, nên tôi cũng có ý định về Việt Nam sinh sống, khởi nghiệp cho thân quen, chung tay đổi mới đất nước. Tôi làm hồ sơ đi xin việc bên Khu công nghệ cao phía đông Sài Gòn cho một công ty công nghệ lớn. Duyệt CV một tuần, họ báo lại tôi mức lương khả quan tầm 50 triệu đồng một tháng (lương thưởng khoảng 750 triệu đồng một năm), nghe thì rất ổn so với mức lương ở Việt Nam, nhưng so với các nước thì quả thực còn kém xa. Thậm chí, mức lương IT này ở Việt Nam của tôi còn không bằng mức lương hơn 10 năm trước tôi làm một tay \\"cu li\\" ở nước ngoài. Đã thế những người có CV tốt, có năng lực đạt mức lương 50 triệu đồng một tháng trở lên hầu như đều có khả năng để đi nước ngoài, thậm chí được nước ngoài còn săn đón, nhất là người chuyên về mảng công nghệ - mảng mà Việt Nam giờ đang cần nhất. Thế thì đừng hỏi nhân tài đi đâu? Người ở lại cũng chỉ vì nặng nhất chữ tình, chữ thương cho đất nước mà thôi. Như tại Australia, chỉ cần làm \\"thợ hồ\\" mà tay nghề cứng cỡ 5 năm kinh nghiệm là bạn có thể dễ dàng kiếm 400 đôla Australia mỗi ngày (tương đương 280 USD) và 102.000 USD một năm, chưa kể thưởng. Nói vậy để thấy chính sách thu hút nhân tài với đề xuất mức trần 120-150 triệu đồng một tháng ở ta còn thua cả người làm việc chân tay ở nước ngoài. Anger Sour >> Quan điểm của bạn thế nào? Gửi bài tại đây. Bài viết không nhất thiết trùng với quan điểm VnExpress.net.","answer":"'Lương chuyên gia IT không bằng làm chân tay ở nước ngoài'"},{"question":"السؤال: من هو حبيب الله؟","answer":"الإجابة: سيدنا محمد عليه أفضل الصلاة وأتم السلام."},{"question":"Apakah jawapan untuk teka-teki berikut: Benda yang berjalan setiap saat, tiada orang yang boleh berhentikan ia.","answer":"Jawapannya ialah masa. "},{"question":"Hãy đặt một tiêu đề phù hợp với đoạn văn sau: UBND tỉnh Lạng Sơn đã chỉ đạo UBND TP Lạng Sơn làm rõ trách nhiệm, tổ chức kiểm điểm và có hình thức xử lý kỷ luật đối với tập thể, cá nhân liên quan đến các vi phạm, sai sót tại dự án khu đô thị mới Mai Pha, xã Mai Pha, TP Lạng Sơn. Cận cảnh dự án khu đô thị mới Mai Pha dính nhiều lình xình  Dự án khu đô thị mới Mai Pha với diện tích 91,73 ha, tổng vốn đầu tư là 3.135 tỉ đồng, trong đó sơ bộ chi phí thực hiện dự án không bao gồm chi phí bồi thường, giải phóng mặt bằng là 2.651 tỉ đồng, chi phí bồi thường, giải phóng mặt bằng đã bao gồm chi phí hỗ trợ, tái định cư: 484 tỉ đồng.  Dự án có quy mô dân số là 9.621 người, tổng số hộ là 2.721, trong đó nhà ở liền kề 2.457 hộ, nhà ở biệt thự 264 hộ, nhà tái định cư 119 hộ, nhà ở xã hội 152 hộ thấp tầng theo kiểu chia lô và khoảng 2.100 căn hộ nhà ở xã hội cao tầng. Nhà đầu tư trúng thầu là liên danh Công ty CP Đầu tư Hải Phát và Công ty TNHH Hà Sơn.  Để thực hiện dự án này có tới 603 hộ dân và 3 tổ chức bị ảnh hưởng do thu hồi đất.  Dự án vấp phải sự phản đối quyết liệt đến từ người dân khi giá đền bù quá rẻ khiến nhiều người dân không chấp nhận. Nhiều người dân bức xúc trước cách xử lý của chính quyền sở tại.  \\"Nếu lấy đất để xây trường học, bệnh viện, đất quốc phòng an ninh hay nhà ở xã hội thì chúng tôi đồng thuận. Tuy nhiên, đây là dự án khu đô thị. Chúng tôi mất hết đất sản xuất mà chỉ được đền bù có vài chục, vài trăm ngàn đồng mỗi mét vuông thì sao có thể chấp nhận\\" - ông N.T.Q. (một người dân bị thu hồi đất ở xã Mai Pha) bày tỏ.  Bức xúc không được giải đáp thỏa đáng khi thực hiện dự án, nhiều người dân xã Mai Pha đã khiếu kiện vượt cấp. Chủ tịch UBND tỉnh Lạng Sơn Hồ Tiến Thiệu sau đó liên tục đối thoại với người dân kèm những lời hứa sẽ điều tra lại việc thống kê diện tích đất lúa, xem xét quy trình cưỡng chế.  Ông Nguyễn Văn Hạnh, Chủ tịch UBND TP Lạng Sơn, cho hay UBND TP Lạng Sơn đã phát hiện có sai sót trong quá trình tham mưu, thực hiện dự án này.  Kết quả rà soát sổ địa chính và hồ sơ biến động cho thấy tổng diện tích đất lúa bị thu hồi, chuyển đổi trong dự án là 18,39 ha, không phải 8,38 ha như số liệu thống kê trước đó.  Nhiều diện tích đất lúa đã bị thống kê sai, khiến tổng diện tích đất lúa trong dự án được TP Lạng Sơn trình lên tỉnh chỉ còn hơn 8 ha. Do diện tích đất lúa dưới 10 ha nên thẩm quyền quyết định phê duyệt dự án do tỉnh Lạng Sơn quyết, không phải trình lên Thủ tướng chính phủ. HĐND tỉnh Lạng Sơn cũng đã thông qua nghị quyết thu hồi đất liên quan đến dự án này.  Hiện tại, theo ghi nhận của Báo Người Lao Động, nhiều diện tích đất tại đây vẫn được người dân thực hiện canh tác, trồng hoa màu. ","answer":"\\"Phản ánh sai sót và tranh luận về dự án khu đô thị mới Mai Pha, TP Lạng Sơn\\""},{"question":"પ્રખ્યાત ચિત્રકાર રવિશંકર રાવળના જીવન વિશે જણાવો.","answer":"તેમનો જન્મ ગુજરાતના ભાવનગરમાં ઔદીચ્ય બ્રાહ્મણ પરિવારમાં થયો હતો. આપમેળે આગળ વધેલા પિતા રાવ સાહેબ મહાશંકર રાવળ સૌરાષ્ટ્રની એક માત્ર બેંક “ભાવનગર દરબાર બેંક”ના પ્રણેતા હતા, તેમને કલાના સ્રોત રવિભાઈને તેમના બા (માતાજી) માણેકબા પાસેથી મળ્યાં. ઇ.સ. ૧૯૦૯માં તેઓ મેટ્રિક પાસ થયા અને તેજ વર્ષે તેમના લગ્ન શિવશંકર ત્રવાડીના પુત્રી રમાબેન સાથે થયા.૧૯૧૧માં ભાવનગરની શામળદાસ કોલેજમાં વિનયન શાખામાં પ્રવેશ મેળવ્યો. પરંતુ વિનયનનો અભ્યાસ પડતો મૂકી, મુંબઈની સર જે. જે. સ્કૂલ ઓફ આર્ટ્સમાં પ્રવેશ મેળવ્યો. ૧૯૧૬માં સર્વશ્રેષ્ઠ વિદ્યાર્થી તરીકે અભ્યાસમાં ઉત્તીર્ણ થતાં ચોવીસ વર્ષની વયે તેમને જે. જે. સ્કૂલ ઑફ આર્ટ્સનો મેયો ચંદ્રક પ્રદાન થયો હતો. ૧૯૧૫માં સાહિત્ય પરિષદ દ્વારા સુરતમાં યોજાયેલ કલાપ્રદર્શનમાં તેમના ત્રણ ચિત્રો પ્રદર્શિત થયા અને રૌપ્ય ચંદ્રક મેળવ્યો. ૧૯૧૭માં તેમના ચિત્ર 'બિલ્વમંગળ'ને બોમ્બે આર્ટ્સ સોસાયટીનો સુવર્ણચંદ્રક પ્રાપ્ય થયો. ૧૯૧૭થી જ્ 'કલાની કદર' નામના પહેલા લેખથી કલા વિષયક પત્રકારત્વ શરૂ કર્યું. આ લેખ વડોદરાથી પ્રકટ થતાં 'સાહિત્ય' માસિકના સપ્ટેમ્બર માસના અંકમાં પ્રકાશિત થયો હતો. ૧૯૨૪માં અમદાવાદમાં કુમાર સામયિકના સ્થાપક અને પ્રથમ તંત્રી બન્યા. સરદાર પટેલ વિશ્વવિદ્યાલય, વડોદરામાં માનાર્હ કલા-અધ્યાપક. ૧૯૩૦માં સાહિત્યકારોએ તેમને રણજિતરામ સુવર્ણચંદ્રક અર્પ્યો, ઇ. સ. ૧૯૩૩માં બ.ક.ઠાકોરે ચિત્રકલાને કવિતાની માજણી બેનડી કહી, ૧૯૩૫માં 'ગુજરાત ચિત્રકલા સંઘ'ની સ્થાપના કરી. ઇ. સ. ૧૯૩૬માં ગાંધીજીએ કહ્યું, \\"મારી છાતી તેમના ચિત્રો જોઈ ઊછળી\\", આગળ જતાં કાકા કાલેલકરે તેમને 'ગુજરાતના કલાગુરુ'ના સ્થાને બિરદાવ્યા. ૧૯૩૬માં જાપાનનો ત્રણ માસનો પ્રવાસ ખેડ્યો. ૧૯૩૮માં કરાછી ખાતે આયોજીત 'ગુજરાત સાહિત્ય પરિષદ'ના અધિવેશનના અધ્યક્ષ બન્યાં. ૧૯૪૧માં આર્ટ્સ સોસાયટી ઓફ ઈન્ડિયાના પ્રમુખ બન્યા. ૧૯૫૦માં મ.સ.યુનિવર્સિટી ખાતે લલિત કોલેજ શરૂ કરવા માટે રચાયેલ બોર્ડમાં તેઓ શામિલ થયા. ૧૯૫૨-૫૩માં વિયેના વિશ્વશાંતિ પરિષદમાં હાજરી આપી. ભારત સરકારે ઇ.સ. ૧૯૬૫માં તેમનું પદ્મશ્રીથી બહુમાન કર્યું. આ જ વર્ષે તેમને સોવિયેત લૅન્ડ નહેરુ ઍવોર્ડ પણ મળ્યો.તેઓએ અમદાવાદમાં 'ગુજરાત કલાસંઘ'ની સ્થાપના કરી હતી. તેઓએ 'ગુજરાત રાજ્ય લલિતકલા અકાદમી'ના વાઇસ ચેરમેનના પદને શોભાવ્યું હતું. ૧૯૭૦માં તેઓ લલિતકલા અકાદમીએ ફેલોશીપ ઍવોર્ડ તથા તામ્રપત્ર દ્વારા તેમનું બહુમાન કર્યું. વીસમી સદીના મધ્યાંતે જ્યારે ગુજરાતમાં ચિત્રકારની જાણ માત્ર દુકાનોના પાટિયા લખતા ચિતારા તરીકે હતી ત્યારે કલાનુ પુન:પ્રતિષ્ઠાન કરવાનું માન રવિશંકર રાવળને ફાળે જાય છે."},{"question":"文1: しかし、今日私たちが見ている教会は,、1640年にアゴスティノ・アヴァンゾによって設計され、1655年に改修された。 文2: しかし、今日私たちが見ている教会は 1640年に改修され、アゴスティノ・アヴァンツォによって設計され、1655年に奉献されました．質問:第1文と第2文は同じ意味を表しているか、異なる意味を表しているか。","answer":"異なる意味を表している。"},{"question":"పరిశ్రమల వర్గీకరణను వివరించండి.","answer":"పరిశ్రమలను సాధారణముగా దిగువ విధాలుగా వర్గీకరించవచ్చు.1) ప్రాథమిక పరిశ్రమలు : ఈ పరిశ్రమ ప్రకృతిపై ఆధారపడి, ప్రకృతి సహాయముతో వస్తువులను ఉత్పత్తి చేస్తుంది. ఉదా : వ్యవసాయము, చేపలు పట్టుట, అటవీకరణ మొదలైనవి.2) ప్రజనన పరిశ్రమలు : ఈ పరిశ్రమలు వంశ క్రమానికి చెందిన కొన్ని జాతి మొక్కలను, పశువులను, పక్షులను పునరుత్పత్తి చేసి, వాటిని అమ్మడం ద్వారా లాభాన్ని ఆర్జిస్తాయి. ఉదా : నర్సరీలు, కోళ్ళ పరిశ్రమ, పట్టు పురుగుల పరిశ్రమ.3) ఉద్గ్రహణ పరిశ్రమలు: ప్రకృతి వనరుల నుంచి వస్తువులను వెలికితీసే కార్యకలాపాలతో ముడిపడివున్న పరిశ్రమలను ఉద్గ్రహణ పరిశ్రమలు అంటారు. ఉదా : ఖనిజాల త్రవ్వకము, బొగ్గు, ఇనుప ఖనిజము మొదలైనవి. గనుల నుంచి వెలికితీయడము మొదలైనవి.4) వస్తు తయారీ పరిశ్రమలు : ముడిపదార్థాలు లేదా సగం తయారైన వస్తువుల నుంచి పూర్తిగా తయారైన వస్తువులుగా ఉత్పత్తిచేసే వాటిని వస్తు తయారీ పరిశ్రమలు అంటారు. ఉదా : ఇనుము – ఉక్కు, యంత్ర పరికరాలు, సిమెంటు మొదలైనవి.5) వస్తు నిర్మాణ పరిశ్రమలు : రోడ్లు, వంతెనలు, భవనాలు, ప్రాజెక్టులు మొదలైనవాటి నిర్మాణాన్ని చేపట్టే పరిశ్రమలను వస్తు నిర్మాణ పరిశ్రమలుగా చెప్పవచ్చును.6) సేవారంగ పరిశ్రమలు : ప్రత్యక్షముగా గాని, పరోక్షముగా గాని ప్రజలకు ఆవశ్యకమైన సేవలను అందజేసే ప్రజోపయోగ సంస్థలను సేవా పరిశ్రమలు అంటారు. ఉదా : హోటల్ పరిశ్రమ, టూరిజమ్ పరిశ్రమ మొదలైనవి."},{"question":"Indicar la respuesta correcta a la siguiente pregunta: ¿Cuál es la mayor cantidad de Grammys ganado por un artista?","answer":"La respuesta correcta es 32. Beyoncé con un total de 32 premios, es a su vez la persona con más premios ganados. Los ha conseguido como solista, colaboración y producción."},{"question":"Dünyanın 7 katmanı nedir?","answer":"Dünya'nın iç şematik görünümü. 1. kıta kabuğu - 2. okyanus kabuğu - 3. üst manto - 4. alt manto - 5. dış çekirdek - 6. iç çekirdek - A: Mohorovičić süreksizliği - B: Gutenberg Süreksizliği - C: Lehmann – Bullen süreksizliği."},{"question":"مزارع: منجل(أ) نجار: مسمار(ب) حداد: مبرد(ج) جراح: سماعة(د) مقص: قماش","answer":"الإجابة (ب) صاحب المهنة والأداة التي يستخدمها"},{"question":"Saan nanggaling ang ulam na adobo sa Pilipinas?","answer":"Ang salitang adobo ay nagmula sa salitang Espanyol na adobar, na nangangahulugang \\"marinade\\" o \\"pickling sauce.\\" Ang pagkakaroon ng tangy dish ay unang naitala noong 1613 ng Kastila na si Pedro de San Buenaventura."},{"question":"Qual é a capital do Líbano?","answer":"A capital do Líbano é Beirute. É maior cidade do Líbano, localiza-se numa península no Mediterrâneo, e é o maior e principal porto marítimo do país."},{"question":"Berikan jawapan untuk teka-teki berikut: Apakah jenama tingkap yang paling ramai orang guna?","answer":"Jawapannya ialah Microsoft kerana \\"Microsoft Windows\\" (tingkap bermaksud \\"window\\" dalam Bahasa Inggeris) ialah salah satu sistem operasi yang banyak digunakan oleh ramai orang di seluruh dunia."},{"question":"Cé hé Joe Heaney. ","answer":"Bhain Seosamh Ó hÉanaí nó Joe Éinniú nó Joe Heaney clú náisiúnta agus idirnáisiúnta amach dó féin de bharr a chuid amhránaíochta ar an sean-nós. Tá cáil na scéalaíochta air freisin."},{"question":"Mikä on salaman lämpötila kun se iskee?","answer":"Korkein kuumuus esiintyy pääsalaman aikana sen edetessä äkillisesti salamakanavassa, jonka esisalama on \\"avannut\\". Pääsalaman huipussa lämpötila on ehkä 30 000 celsius-astetta, ja laskee 30 mikrosekunnin aikana 10 000 asteeseen. Salaman lämpötilan keskiarvona voidaan siis pitää 20 000 astetta.Esisalaman syntyessä saattaa sen etenevässä kärjessä vallita vastaava lämpötila. Moni-iskuisen salaman pääsalamoiden välillä lämpötila laskee 100 millisekunnin aikana 4000 asteeseen tai sen alle. 4000 asteessa kanava johtaa vielä hyvin sähköä, 2000 asteessa se on muuttunut käytännössä eristeeksi."},{"question":"小説「太陽の季節」の著者で参議院、衆議院の議員を経て大臣も経験。１９９９年に東京都の知事にも当選した人は誰？","answer":"石原慎太郎です。"},{"question":"Ilé-ẹjọ́ rọ Alájáàwà tilu Àjáàwà loye, wọn lọna eru lo gba depo ọba","answer":"Ile-ẹjọ giga tipinlẹ Ọyọ ti pàṣẹ pé ki Alájáàwà tilu Àjáààwà, ni ipinlẹ Ọyọ, Ọba Thompson Oyetunji, kuro lori àpèrè ọba.Lọjọ kọkànlá, oṣù kẹta, ọdun 2020, nijọba ipinlẹ Ọyọ fi Ọmọọba Oyetunji jọba ilu Ajaawa. Ṣugbọn lọjọ Ajé, Mọnde, ọjọ kẹẹẹdogun, oṣù kejì, ọdun 2021 yii, l’Onídàájọ Sherifat Adéyẹmí paṣẹ pé kí ìjọba gba ọpa àṣẹ àti ìwé ẹri ti wọn fún ùn gẹgẹ bíi ọba kuro lọwọ ẹ̀ kíá.Awọn to du oye ọba Àjáàwà, ỌmọọbaAzeez Oyebunmi ati Ọmọọba Kamorudeen Salami, lati idile Olumọle, ni wọn pẹjọ ta ko iyansipo Ọmọọba Oyetunji sipo ọbaLara awọn ti wọn tun pe lẹjọ, ti wọn sì jẹ olujẹjọ nínú ẹjọ ọ̀hún ni Gomina ipinlẹ Ọyọ, Ẹnjinnia Ṣeyi Makinde, kọmiṣanna feto oye jijẹ ati ọrọ ìjọba ibilẹ atawọn mi-in.Wọn ní kijọba rọ ẹni tí wọn fi jọba naa loye nitori ọna eru ni wọn gbà fi í síbẹ̀.Pẹlu bo ṣe jẹ pe igbẹjọ ṣẹṣẹ bẹrẹ lori ọrọ ipo oba Ajaawa ni, ile-ẹjọ ti rọ baba naa lati yee maa pera ẹ̀ lÁlájáàwà tilu Àjáàwà tititi oun yóò fi gbe idajọ kalẹ lori ẹjọ náà.O waa sun igbẹjọ mi-in sí ọjọ kẹrindinlogun, oṣu yìí.Lẹyin tile-ẹjọ ti ṣe ohun tí wọn n fẹ, Amofin Orodiran ti i ṣe agbẹjọro olupẹjọ, kan saara sí adajọ kootu naa, o ni àṣẹ ododo ti adajọ pa yii ni yóò jẹ kí awọn eeyan tubọ n’igbagbọ ninu ẹka eto idajọ orileede yii."},{"question":" Sheeg maxaa la oran jiray ninkii dilay Cali Bin Abii Daalib?","answer":"Cali Binu Abidalib ninki dilay waxaa la oran jiray C/raxmaan Binu Muljin."},{"question":"ఆర్మూరు పురపాలక సంఘము 2006 లో స్థాపించబడింది. దీనిని మూడవ గ్రేడ్గా విభజించారు. ఈ పట్టణంలో మొత్తం 23 వార్డులు ఉన్నాయి. దీని అధికార పరిధి 26.07km2 (10.07sqmi).[3]","answer":"ఆర్మూర్ పట్టణ వైశాల్యం ఎంత?"},{"question":"Hoàn thành tiếp câu sau: Hà Nội vào thu, chắc hẳn ai cũng thấy lòng khoan khoái khi chạy xe ở những con đường rợp bóng cây xanh như phố Hoàng Diệu hay đường Thanh Niên. Nhưng nếu muốn xoá tan mọi buồn phiền thì chắc chắn bạn phải đến trải nghiệm cung đường \\"huyền thoại\\" mang tên Phan Đình Phùng.","answer":"Ngay từ những ngày chớm thu, tôi nghe phong thanh trên mạng xã hội người ta đổ xô đi tận hưởng check-in nhiều lắm. Nó thôi thúc tôi phải chạy đi kiểm nghiệm ngay. Quả thật cung đường này chính là điểm nhấn tạo dấu ấn khó phai khi nhắc đến trời thu năm nay, bởi đâu chỉ có mỗi thơ mộng mà nó còn khiến bất cứ ai ghé đến cũng phải bật cười."},{"question":"O ṣoju mi koro (Apa Kin-in-ni)","answer":"Eelo ni wọn n ta bẹntiroolu, epo mọto bayii o. Boya ọgọjọ naira ni lita kan, bọya naira mọkanlelọgọjọ ni o, ko sẹni to le sọ pato. Bi ẹnikẹni ba sọ pe ohun to n ṣẹlẹ ni Naijiria bayii ye oun, tọhun yoo jẹ oloṣelu, tabi ẹnikan to fẹran lati maa tan ara rẹ jẹ. Lojoojumọ lohun gbogbo n dorikodo: bi o yiju sibi yii, ọran; bi o yiju sọhun-un, ijangbọn ni. Gbogbo ohun tijọba yii ṣeleri pata lo fọ yanga loju wa bayii, gbogbo ohun ti wọn ni awọn yoo ṣe ni wọn ko ṣe, eyi ti wọn si ni awọn yoo tun ṣe, wọn tubọ n ba a jẹ si i ni. Bo ba jẹ ileri ti awọn araabi yii ṣe ni, ko yẹ ka wa nibi kan ki epo bẹntiroolu maa jẹ wa niya, tabi ki owo ti wọn yoo maa ta a ni Naijiria wọn ju iye ti wọn n ta a nibomi-in lọ. Nigba to jẹ awa la ṣe e, ọdọ wa ni wọn ti n wa a, bawo ni epo yoo ṣe wọn lọdọ wa. Ṣugbọn ohun to n ya gbogbo aye lẹnu ni pe awa ọmọ Naijiria ti a wa ninu awọn orilẹ-ede ti a ni epo bẹntiroolu ju lọ lagbaaye, awa naa ni iya kinni naa n jẹ ju lọ. Nigba tiijọba yii n bọ, lara ileri ti wọn ṣe ni pe iya kinni naa ko ni i jẹ wa mọ, bẹẹ ni ki i ṣe pe a oo maa ri epo naa ra kaakiri kọ, owo ti yoo jẹ ko ni i jẹ inira fun wa. Nigba ti wọn n sọrọ yii, iye ti wọn n ta epo yii jẹ naira mẹtadinlaaadọrun-un (N87), ṣugbọn bi a ti n sọrọ yii, owo epo naa ti fẹẹ bọ si ilọpo meji, nitori bii naira mejilelọgbọn (N162) ni wọn n ta a lawọn ibi kan. Ki lo le fa iru eleyii! Ko si ohun to n fa a ju iwa awọn aṣaaju wa lọ, iwa ti Aarẹ Muhammadu Buhari leri pe oun yoo parẹ, ṣugbọn to jẹ bo ṣe de tan, niṣe ni iwa naa n buru si i. Ko si bi epo ko ṣee ni i wọn ni Naijiria. Nigba to ṣe pe bo tilẹ jẹ awa la n wa a lati inu ilẹ, nigba ti a ba wa a tan, ilu oyinbo ni a oo gbe e lọ lati fọ ọ, awọn oyinbo ti wọn ba fọ epo naa ni wọn yoo ṣẹṣẹ gbe e pada wa fun wa, ti wọn yoo si ta a ni ibamu si iye ti wọn ba n ra dọla lagbaaye. Ki lo de ti Naijiria ko le fọ epo ti awọn ọmọ Naijiria yoo lo, ti wọn yoo si tun ri i ta sẹyin odi! Ko si ohun to fa a ju iwa ibajẹ, ikowojẹ ti iru rẹ ko si nibi kan laye yii mọ, ati iwa imọtara-ẹni-nikan to ṣoro gan-an lati gbagbọ pe awọn ẹda kan yoo ni iru rẹ. Ki i ṣe pe a ko ni ileeṣẹ to n fọ epo bẹntiroolu, ṣugbọn eyi ti awọn ijọba ologun aye Yakubu Gowon ati tawọn ṣọja mi-in ti ṣe naa lo wa nibẹ, lọdọọdun ni wọn si n tun un ṣe, ti atunṣe naa ko gbeṣẹ. Nidii eyi ni wọn ṣe fawọn kan ni lansẹnsi pe ki wọn maa ra epo bẹntiroolu wa lati oke-okun, ọwọ awọn yii si ni agbara wa, awọn ni wọn n ṣe wa bo ṣe wu wọn, nitori awọn ijọba wa fun wọn ni agbara ti ko tọ si wọn. Ko si orilẹ-ede mi-in ti wọn ti n ṣe eyi, ti Naijiria nikan ni. Ki Buhari too de si ilu yii bii olori wa tuntun, ọpọ alaye lo ṣe nipa ọrọ owo-epo yii, eyi to fi han pe oun naa mọ bi nnkan ti n lọ, ṣugbọn iyanu buruku lo jẹ pe latigba to ti de, kaka ki ewe agbọn dẹ lọrọ naa, koko lo n le. Awọn ti wọn n ko owo jẹ, awọn ti wọn n gba owo ijọba lai taja fun wọn, awọn ti wọn n gba owo-epo bẹntiroolu ti wọn ko gbe wọle ati awọn eeyan raurau bẹẹ lo n ba nnkan jẹ, eyi to si buru ju ni pe bi wọn ti wa ninu awọn ijọba to kọja lọ, bẹẹ ni wọn pọ ninu ijọba Buhari yii bii nnkan. Koda ti ijọba Buhari yii fẹrẹ le ju tawọn ti wọn ti wa tẹlẹ lọ. Ibeere ni pe kin ni Buhari n ṣe fawọn ti wọn n ko owo epo jẹ! Lọjọ wo ni Buhari fẹẹ pese ile-ifọpo ti wọn yoo ti maa fọ epo ti yoo to gbogbo ọmọ Naijiria i lo gẹgẹ bo ti ṣeleri nigba to fẹẹ gbajọba. Lọjọ wo ni Buhari yoo mu nnkan dẹrun fawọn ọmọ Naijiria, awọn ohun to n ṣẹlẹ yii ko daa o!Awọn oponu kan wa nilẹ yii, awọn ọlọpọlọ kukuru, alaimọkan. Loju tiwọn, awọn lawọn n gbeja Buhari, tabi pe awọn lawọn n ṣe ẹgbẹ oṣelu APC, bi wọn ko ba si mura, awọn funra wọn ni wọn yoo pa Buhari. Nigba ti ijọba ba wa, ko si ohun to dara bii ki awọn ti wọn ba sun mọ awọn olori wọn ba wọn sọ ootọ ọrọ. Gbogbo ẹnikẹni to ba sun mọ olori ijọba ti ko le ba a sọrọ, iru awọn bẹẹ yoo pada pa olori orilẹ-ede bẹẹ ni, bi wọn ko ba pa a sọrun, wọn yoo pa a saye. Ohun to ṣe ni laaanu ni pe awọn ti wọn n tẹle Buhari, paapaa, ọpọ awọn eeyan ti wọn wa ninu APC, ki i ba baba naa sọ ootọ ọrọ, koda, ko maa wọ inu igbo lọ, ko si maa gbe gbogbo ọmọ Naijiria wọbẹ lọ. Wọn yoo sọ pe ohun to n ṣe lo dara ju lọ, ati pe awọn ko ri iru eeyan daadaa, to si kun oju oṣuwọn bẹẹ ri laye awọn. Bẹẹ ohun to n ṣẹlẹ yii ko daa, awọn naa si mọ. Boya oṣelu ni wọn wa n ṣe ni o, boya ọrọ ẹsin lo si bo wọn loju, boya aigbọn si ni, ko sẹni to mọ rara. Ti ọrọ owo-epo yii tilẹ  baayan ninu jẹ, nitori awọn kan ti jade pe bi awọn ijọba agbaye ti n ṣe ni Buhari ṣe, lati jẹ ki awọn kan maa diye le owo-epo naa bo ba ṣe wu wọn. Awọn yii ko ranti sọ fun awọn eeyan pe awọn ijọba orilẹ-ede aye ti wọn n mẹnuba yii yoo ti ri i pe owo-oṣu awọn eeyan awọn ba iye ti wọn yoo maa ra epo mọto mu. Wọn ko jẹ fi owo kun owo-epo lẹẹmẹta lẹẹmẹrin laarin ọdun diẹ, to si jẹ owo-oṣu wọn ko le kọbọ kan si i. Awọn ko jẹ fi biliọnu mẹwaa tun ileeṣe-ifọpo ṣe laarin ọdun kan ki ileeṣẹ ifọpo naa ma si fọ epo koroba kan ṣoṣo bayii gẹgẹ bi ileeṣẹ NNPC ti n ṣe. Awọn ko ni i fi titi wọn silẹ lai ṣe, wọn ko si ni i fi ọsibitu wọn silẹ lai le tọju alaisan, wọn yoo ti ṣe ohun gbogbo letoleto ki wọn too fi owo kun owo-epo wọn. Gbogbo ohun to yẹ ki ijọba Buhari ṣe ni wọn fi silẹ ti wọn ko ṣe, eyi lo si jẹ ko jẹ nigbakigba ti wọn ba ni awọn fi kun owo-epo bayii, inira to n ba gbogbo ilu ki i ṣe kekere. Ki waa ni awọn kan jokoo ti wọn n kan saara si ijọba to n ni mẹkunnu lara si, kin ni wọn n ri jẹ ninu ijọba yii to bẹẹ ti laakaye wọn fi parẹ mọ wọn ninu! Tabi ọpọlọ wọn ko pe tẹlẹtẹlẹ ni. O ma ṣe o. Ẹ ba Buhari sọ ootọ ọrọ, ijọba rẹ n ni ilu lara; ẹ ba a sọ ootọ ọrọ, ko ma jẹ funra yin lẹ oo pa baba naa saye!Awọn oṣiṣẹ ijọba gbogbo n leri bayii, wọn ni awọn yoo daṣẹ silẹ nitori ohun ti ijọba n ṣe lori ọrọ owo-epo bẹnitiroolu, wọn ni gbogbo eyi ti wọn n ṣe yii, awọn ni iya rẹ yoo jẹ ju lọ. Nigba ti owo-epo ba ti lọ soke, o daju pe owo mọto yoo lọ soke si i, bẹẹ ni owo ọja gbogbo yoo lọ soke, nigba ti owo-oṣu awọn oṣiṣẹ ko si le, inira yoo pọ fun wọn, nitori owo wọn ko ni i too na mọ. Awọn ẹgbẹ awọn olukọ fasiti naa ni awọn paapaa ko fara mọ ọn, awọn naa si le bẹrẹ iyanṣelodi tawọn naa. Gbogbo awọn wọnyi lo ṣee fi ewe mọ, bi awọn oṣiṣẹ ba daṣẹ silẹ, ti awọn olukọ fasiti naa daṣẹ silẹ, lori ijokoo naa lawọn eeyan yoo ti yanju ẹ, ti kaluku yoo si pada sẹnu iṣẹ wọn. Eyi ti ko dara ko ṣẹlẹ ni ti awọn dokita o. Ohun yoowu to ba fa ibinu, ti gbogbo dokita ilẹ yii fi leri pe awọn yoo da iṣẹ silẹ, ki ijọba tete yanju ẹ ni, ki wọn fi igberaga, ko-kan-wa, tabi ohun yoowu ti wọn ba n ṣe silẹ, ki wọn gbaju mọ ti awọn dokita yii, ki wọn si ri i pe awọn fori ẹ ti sibi kan. Ohun to ṣe gbọdọ ri bẹẹ ni pe ọwọ awọn eeyan yii ni eto alaafia gbogbo araalu wa, bi ko ba si si alaafia, ko sẹni to le ṣe ohunkohun. Ẹni to ba ni alaafia ni i ṣejọba, ẹni to ba ni alaafia ni i lọ sibi iṣẹ, ẹni to ba si ni alaafia naa ni i da iṣẹ silẹ. Bi ohun gbogbo ba fẹẹ lọ deede, ti ijọba yoo si fi ifẹ gidi han si gbogbo araalu, afi ki wọn ri i pe awọn dokita yii ko da iṣẹ silẹ, nitori idaṣẹ silẹ wọn lewu ju tẹlomi-in lọ. Ẹ ma jẹ ki wọn daṣẹ silẹ o, ẹ yaa tete pe wọn pada.Ko si ohun ti eeyan le ṣe, iwa to ba ti mọ-ọn-yan lara, koda, ki tọhun lọ si igberi okun, ko tun de igberi ọsa, iwa naa ni yoo maa hu nibẹ, ko si sohun teeyan le ri ṣe si i. Ijọba Naijiria lawọn n binu si ijọba ilẹ Ghana, ni wọn ba binu rangbọnda, ni Lai Muhammed ti i ṣe minisita fun eto iroyin ba gbe iwe aramanda kan lati fi kilọ fun ijọba ilẹ Ghana, o ni wọn n gun Naijiria garagara, bi wọn ko ba si jawọ, wọn yoo ri pipọn oju ijọba awọn. Ohun meji ni ijọba Naijiria n tori ẹ binu si wọn ni Ghana, akọkọ ni pe wọn wo ile to n ṣoju ijọba Naijiria ni Ghana. Naijiria lo kọ ile naa, nibẹ ni wọn si n lo bii ileeṣẹ to n ṣoju wọn. Lojiji lawọn kan wo ile naa ni bii oṣu meji sẹyin, ọrọ naa ka Naijiria lara. Lọna keji, ijọba Ghana ni ki awọn oniṣowo ọmọ Naijiria to ba wa ni Ghana san miliọnu kan owo dọla ti Ghana ki wọn too le maa ba iṣẹ wọn lọ nibẹ, bi bẹẹ kọ, awọn yoo ti ṣọọbu wọn pa. Iru ẹgbin wo lo ta le wa yii! Ohun tijọba Naijiria n wi ree, ni wọn ṣe kọwe ibinu si Ghana. Ṣugbọn ijọba ilẹ Ghana ko binu, suuru ni wọn fi ṣe alaye fun wọn. Wọn ni ile ti wọn sọ pe wọn wo yii, awọn kọ lawọn wo o, nitori ijọba Naijiria ko beere ilẹ lọwọ awọn, awọn ko si fun wọn nilẹ, ọwọ awọn ọmọ onilẹ ni wọn ti lọọ rẹnti ilẹ wọn, wọn ko si fọrọ naa to ijọba leti. Adehun ti wọn jọ ṣe pẹlu awọn ọmọ onilẹ ni pe wọn yoo lo ilẹ naa fun ọdun mẹwaa pere, wọn yoo si maa sanwo fun wọn. Bii ogoji ọdun sẹyin ni adehun naa ti pari, ijọba Naijiria ko san owo fun awọn onilẹ ti wọn gba ilẹ lọwọ ẹ, wọn ko si kuro lori ilẹ, ohun to si fa ija laarin awọn ati awọn ọmọ onilẹ niyi, ko si ohun to kan ijọba Ghana. Ṣe iru ẹ ṣee gbọ! Pe Naijiria lọ si ilu oniluu, wọn ralẹ nibẹ, wọn ko san rẹnti mọ fun ogoji ọdun, onilẹ wole wọn, wọn bẹrẹ si i pariwo. Ni gbogbo aye, ijọba orilẹ-ede kan ni yoo fun ijọba orilẹ-ede mi-in ni aaye ti wọn yoo kọle wọn si nibẹ, orilẹ-ede kan ko ni i ra ilẹ lọwọ aladaani, afi ti Naijiria yii nikan. Ni ti awọn ti wọn fẹẹ gbowo lọwọ wọn, wọn ni awọn ṣe bẹẹ nitori ọpọlọpọ awọn ti wọn wa ni Ghana ti wọn jẹ ọmọ Naijiria yii, iṣẹ buruku ni wọn n ṣe, iwa ọdaran ni wọn n hu, awọn si ti sọ ọ laimọye igba fun ijọba Naijiria, ṣugbọn to jẹ ti awọn ba ti wa laimọye igba, ẹni to yẹ ko da awọn lohun ko ni i da awọn lohun, nigbẹyin, wọn yoo dẹ ọmọ kekere lẹnu iṣẹ ọba kan si awọn, gbogbo ẹjọ ti awọn ba si fi sun, ibẹ ni yoo pari si, ijọba Naijiria ko ni i ṣe nnkan kan. Ghana ni o ya awọn lẹnu pe ijọba wa le maa binu bayii lori ọrọ ti awọn ti sọ titi ti wọn ko da awọn lohun lẹẹkan. Ninu gbogbo ohun to wa nilẹ yii, iṣe ile lo ru Naijiria deta yii, ohun ti wọn n ṣe nile naa ni wọn lọọ ṣe nita. Nigba to jẹ ọwọ awọn agbero ọmọ onilẹ ni gbogbo eeyan ti n ralẹ, to si jẹ bo o lọọ fẹjọ sunjọba, o ko ni i ri eeyan gidi ba sọrọ, afi ẹni ti owo ba wa lọwọ ẹ, ohun to gbe wọn de Ghana ree, iyẹn naa lo si sọ Naijiria di ẹni abuku loju aye. Gẹgẹ bii iṣe wọn, wọn ko tun le wadii ọrọ ki wọn too maa kọwe ibinu, iyẹn ni Ghana ṣe fi wọn wọlẹ ni gbangba ode. Nigba wo lawọn ijọba tiwa ni Naijiria yoo ṣe ohun ti gbogbo aye n ṣe! Abi bi nnkan wa yoo ṣe maa lọ naa niyi ni! Ta ni yoo ba wa tun ilẹ yii ṣe! Eleyii ma waa ga o!"},{"question":"नेवार सभ्यताले काठमाडौं उपत्यकामा पानी व्यवस्थापन प्रणालीको विकासमा कसरी योगदान पुर्‍यायो?","answer":"नेवार सभ्यताले काठमाडौं उपत्यकामा उन्नत पानी व्यवस्थापन प्रणालीहरू प्रदर्शन गर्‍यो, जसमा जटिल ढुङ्गाका टुक्राहरू (हिटिस) र ढुङ्गाका धाराहरू थिए जसले दैनिक प्रयोग र धार्मिक अनुष्ठानहरूको लागि पानी वितरण गर्न सहज बनायो।"},{"question":"fenoy ny banga:\\"Ny marina toy ny trondro vaventy ka _\\"","answer":"\\"Ny marina toy ny trondro vaventy ka tsy hita raha tsy amin’ny rano lalina\\""},{"question":"问：吉姆·帕森斯在饰演谢尔顿时有何表现？","answer":"答：吉姆·帕森斯在饰演谢尔顿时表现出色，他准确地捕捉了这个角色的特点，并赢得了多个奖项，包括四次艾美奖最佳喜剧男主角奖。"},{"question":"\\"Skrini refoni rakatsemuka, ndinoda kudzoserwa mari yangu\\" ndeapi manzwiro echirevo chapfuura?","answer":"Mutsara uyu unoratidza manzwiro asina kunaka sezvo munhu ari kuodzwa mwoyo nefoni yaakatengeserwa yakatsemuka skrini."},{"question":"السؤال: من من أمهات المؤمنين كانت أخت معاوية ؟","answer":"الإجابة: أم حبيبة"},{"question":"శివాజీ కొలువులోని వారంతా నిశ్చేష్టులవడానికి కారణం ఏమిటి?","answer":"సో దేవుడు విజయోత్సాహంతో ఉన్నాడు. ఓడిపోయిన వీరుని, అతని రాణివాసాన్ని బంధించి తీసుకొని వచ్చాడు. పుణ్యవాసమైన రాణివాసాన్ని బంధించి తెచ్చినందుకు శివాజీకి చాలా కోపం వచ్చింది. ఏ హిందువుడూ ఆ విధంగా ప్రవర్తించడన్నాడు. తన ఆజ్ఞ పట్టించుకోలేదని ఆగ్రహించాడు. సో దేవుడు తన ప్రాణాలు తానే పోగొట్టుకొంటున్నాడని హెచ్చరించాడు. గర్వాన్ని సహించనన్నాడు.శివాజీ కళ్లు ఎఱ్ఱబారాయి. పెదవులు కోపంతో వణికాయి. కనుబొమ్మలు కదిలాయి. ఆయన హుంకరించాడు. కోపంతో గర్జించాడు. ఈ పరిస్థితికి శివాజీ కొలువులోని వారంతా భయపడ్డారు. నిశ్చేష్టులయ్యారు."},{"question":"次の文章を読んで、その内容に適したタイトルを付けてください： 「バーグルエン哲学・文化賞」は、7年前にアメリカの研究所が「哲学のノーベル賞」にしたいと考えて作った賞です。人間が自分のことを深く知ることや人間が前に進んでいくことができるように、すばらしい研究をした人に毎年贈っています。賞金は100万ドルです。今年は、哲学を研究している柄谷行人さんが、アジアで初めてこの賞をもらいました。柄谷さんは兵庫県尼崎市出身で、81歳です。夏目漱石などの作家についての本や、政治経済学、哲学の歴史についての本も書いています。賞を贈った研究所は、柄谷さんの研究で、民主主義や資本主義が深くわかるようになったと話しています。柄谷さんは「自分がこのような大きな賞をもらうとは思っていなかったので、びっくりしました。専門以外にもいろいろな研究をしてきたことに意味があると言ってもらいました」と喜んでいました。","answer":"「哲学のノーベル賞」を初めてアジアで日本人がもらった"},{"question":"බැවහර බසෙහි සොබාව එසේම නො?මෙම වැකිය නිවැරදිද? මෙහි තේරුම කිම?","answer":"දකුණු පළාතේ එක්තරා ප්‍රදේශයකදී පමණක්, මට මෙම වචනය සාමාන්‍ය කතාබහේදී භාවිත කරන්නන් හමු වී ඇත.' ඔහේ ගෙදර යනවනො?' මෙහි අර්ථය, 'ඔබ ගෙදර යනවා නේද?' යන්නමයි.අප ජීවත් වූ ප්‍රදේශයේ ඇත්තන්මෙය කීවේ, ' ඔහේ ගෙදර යනවනෙ?' ලෙසයි.ඒ අනුව බැලුවම, මේ වැකිය නිවැරදියි. අරුතද දැන් පැහැදිලි ඇතැයි සිතමි."},{"question":"క్రింద ఇచ్చిన సినిమా పాటలోని ఒక భాగం యొక్క సాహిత్యంపై విశ్లేషణ చెయ్యండిఈశుని మ్రోల.. హిమగిరి బాల..ఈశుని మ్రోల.. హిమగిరి బాల..కన్నెతనము ధన్యమయిన గాథకణకణలాడే తామసాన కాముని రూపము బాపీ..ఆ కోపీ..కాకలు తీరీ కను తెరచి తను తెలసీతన లలనను పరిణయమాడిన ప్రబంధముఅవధరించరయ్యా విద్యల నాదరించరయ్యా..","answer":"ఇప్పుడింక తాము చెప్పబోయే కధా పరిచయం చేస్తున్నారు. కన్యగా ఉన్న హిమవంతుని  కుమార్తె ఈశ్వరుని సేవించి ఏ విధంగా తన కన్నెతనాన్ని ధాన్యం చేసుకునేలా ప్రవర్తించిందో ఆ చరిత్ర చెబుతున్నామయ్య విని తరించండి అంటున్నారు. బాగా కాలిన నిప్పుల ఎర్రదనాన్ని తెలియపరిచే పదం ‘కణ కణ’.  బాగా ఎర్రగా కాలిన నిప్పులంతా రౌద్రంగా ఉన్న పరమ శివుడు – నేను ఎవరినైనా మోహావేశుల్ని  చేయగలనన్న మదించిన తామస గుణంతో ఉన్న మన్మధుని శరీరాన్ని బూడిద చేసి, ఆగ్రహం ఉపశమించి, కనులు తెరిచి తనను తాను తెలుసుకొని – తనకు సేవలు చేస్తున్న కన్యను తన లలన గా గుర్తించి – అంటే ఆ కన్య తన అర్ధాన్ని పార్వతియే అని తెలుసుకొని ఆమెను వివరినా కథను వినండయ్యా అంటున్నారు.  ఇక్కడితో కధా వస్తువు పరిచయం పూర్తవుతుంది. ఇప్పుడిక పాత్రల పరిచయం."},{"question":"🇰🇬 Манас эпосу 📚Сагымбай Орозбаков төрөлгөн жыла) 1864 б) 1865в) 1866 г) 1867","answer":"Туура жообу:г) 1867"},{"question":"次の段落を完成させなさい： 国は今年、発達障害かもしれない子どもがどのくらいいるか小学校と中学校に聞きました。発達障害は、文章を読むことや書くこと、計算などがうまくできなかったり、周りの人に気持ちをうまく伝えることができなかったりすることです。","answer":"その結果、国は、小学校と中学校の子どもの8.8％が発達障害かもしれないと言いました。10年前の6.5％より多くなりました。 この中で、特別に勉強などを助ける必要があると学校が考えている子どもは28％でした。このため、国の会議に出席した専門家は「28%以外の子どもも助けるように考えなければなりません」と話しています。そして「クラスの先生だけではなくて、学校全体で助けていくことが大事です」と話しています。"},{"question":"Suponha que você esteja no Brasil e, de acordo com as regras do Código de Defesa do Consumidor (CDC), qual o prazo mínimo de garantia?","answer":"O prazo mínimo de garantia é 30 dias para serviços e produtos não duráveis e 90 dias para serviços e produtos duráveis."},{"question":"Quais foram as principais contribuições de Albert Einstein para a filosofia?","answer":"Albert Einstein, embora mais conhecido por suas contribuições científicas, teve impacto na filosofia da ciência. Sua teoria da relatividade desafiou concepções tradicionais do espaço e tempo, influenciando debates filosóficos sobre a natureza da realidade. Einstein também expressou ideias filosóficas sobre a busca por uma compreensão unificada da natureza."},{"question":"కింద పదాలను కలిపి సంధుల పేర్లను రాయండి. సంధి సూత్రాలు తెల్పండి.అ) మొదట + మొదటఆ) దేవ + ఐశ్వర్యంఇ) దేశ + ఔన్నత్యంఈ) కడ + కడఉ) అతి + ఉగ్ర","answer":"అ) మొదట + మొదట = మొట్టమొదట = ఆమ్రేడిత ద్విరుక్తటకారాదేశ సంధిసూత్రము :ఆమ్రేడితం పరంగా ఉంటే, ‘కడ’ మొదలైన శబ్దాల మొదటి అచ్చు మీద అన్ని అక్షరాలకూ ‘ట్ట’ వస్తుంది.ఆ) దేవ + ఐశ్వర్యం = దేవైశ్వర్యం = వృద్ధిసంధిసూత్రము :అకారమునకు ఏ, ఐలు పరమైనపుడు ఐ కారమూ, ఓ, ఔ లు పరమయితే ఔ కారమూ ఏకాదేశంగా వస్తాయి.ఇ) దేశ + ఔన్నత్యం = దేశాన్నత్యం = వృద్ధి సంధిసూత్రము :అకారమునకు ఏ, ఐలు పరమైనపుడు ఐ కారమూ, ఓ, ఔ లు పరమయితే ఔఔ కారమూ ఏకాదేశంగా వస్తాయి.ఈ) కడ + కడ . = కట్టకడ – ఆమ్రేడిత ద్విరుక్తటకారాదేశ సంధిసూత్రము :ఆమ్రేడితం పరంబగునపుడు కడాదుల తొలియచ్చు మీది వర్ణంబులకు ద్విరుక్తటకారంబగు.ఉ) అతి + ఉగ్ర = అత్యుగ్ర = యణాదేశ సంధిసూత్రము :ఇ, ఉ, ఋ లకు అవసవర్ణమైన అచ్చులు పరమైతే, య, వ రలు ఆదేశంబగు."},{"question":"Raha jerena ireto fehezanteny manaraka ireto:Fehezanteny 1: Nitsidika ny raibe sy renibeny izy ny faran’ny herinandro.Fehezanteny 2: Nandeha nitsidika ny raibe sy renibeny izy ny faran’ny herinandro.Mitovy ve ny fehezan-teny teo aloha?","answer":"Eny, ireo fehezanteny roa ireo dia manondro ny fitsidihany ny raibe sy renibeny tamin'ny faran'ny herinandro."},{"question":"Apakah maksud 'beroleh lumpur di tempat yang kering'?","answer":"Ia bermaksud beroleh kesusahan dengan tidak disangka-sangka"},{"question":"Hãy chọn đáp án đúng nhất cho câu hỏi sau:Khi phát hiện cháy, cần thực hiện các động tác theo trình tự nào dưới đây:a. Hô to: Cháy! Cháy! Cháy!, cúp cầu dao điện, tham gia chữa cháy, đồng thời gọi điện thoại báo lực lượng chữa cháy chuyên nghiệp.b. Gọi điện thoại báo lực lượng chữa cháy chuyên nghiệp, cúp cầu dao điện, hô to: Cháy! Cháy! Cháy!, tham gia chữa cháy.c. Hô to: Cháy! Cháy! Cháy!, cúp cầu dao điện, đồng thời gọi điện thoại báo lực lượng chữa cháy chuyên nghiệp.","answer":"Đáp án: a"},{"question":"கேள்வி : இந்தியாவின் முதல் பெண் ரயில் ஓட்டுநர்","answer":"பதில் : ரசியா"},{"question":"Cuba jawab teka-teki berikut: Ia adalah segala anda tetapi tak guna untuk orang lain, apanya?","answer":"Jawapannya ialah otak. "},{"question":"请回答以下问题：问题：云计算是什么？","answer":"答案：云计算是一种通过互联网提供计算资源和服务的模式，可以实现按需获取和共享计算资源。"},{"question":"Sheeg Wax marka ay siyaadaan sii naaqusa?","answer":"Waa Dayaxa."},{"question":"Diniho ity teny manaraka ity: “Ny vehivavy rehetra dia ratsy fitondran-tena, izany no zava-misy.” Misy resaka fankahalana ve ilay fanambarana?","answer":"Eny, misy fanaratsiana momban'ny vehivavy ny fanambarana."},{"question":"ukupita kuti?","answer":"ndikupita ku nsika kukagula zovala. komaso kukagula zakudya."},{"question":"Tohizo ity ohabolana ity :  “Andevolahy maty hariva ka .....................”","answer":" “Andevolahy maty hariva ka vovon’amboa no solon-tafondrony.”"},{"question":"માધવ રામાનુજ ની \\"એકવાર યમુનામાં આવ્યું’તુ પૂર \\" કવિતા લખો.","answer":"એકવાર યમુનામાં આવ્યું’તુ પૂર,મથુરાથી એકવાર માથે મૂકીને કોઈ લાવ્યું’તું વાંસળીના સૂર.પાણી તો ધસમસતા વહેતા રહે ને આમ ગોકુળમાં વહેતી થઈ વાતો,એમ કોઈ પૂછે તો કહી ના શકાય અને આમ કોઈ ભવભવનો નાતો,ફળિયામાં શેરીમાં પનઘટ કે હૈયામાં બાજી રહ્યા છે નૂપુર.ઝૂકેલી ડાળી પર ઝૂક્યું છે આભ કંઈ જોવામાં થાય નહીં ભૂલ,એવું કદંબવૃક્ષ મહેંકે છે ડાળી પર, વસ્ત્રો હશે કે હશે ફૂલ,પાણી પર અજવાળું તરતું રહે ને એમ આંખોમાં ઝલમલતું નૂર.કાંઠો તો યમુનાનો પૂનમ ગોકુળીયાની વેણ એક વાંસળીના વેણ,મારગ તો મથુરાનો પીંછુ તો મોરપિંછ નેણ એક રાધાના નેણ,એવા તે કેવા ક્હેણ તમે આવીયા કે લઈ ચાલ્યા દૂર દૂર દૂર."},{"question":"Jawab soalan teka-teki ini: Apabila terlepas destinasi semasa memandu kereta ataupun motosikal, anda perlu?","answer":"Jawapannya ialah gostan"},{"question":"Bilakah Sarawak mula mempunyai pentadbiran sendiri? Pilih jawapan yang betul dari pilihan berikut.  A.16 Sept 1963 B. 31 Ogos 1957 C. 22 Julai 1963 D. 16 Sept 1957","answer":"Jawapan yang betul adalah C. 22 Julai 1963."},{"question":"\\"ඕලාරික\\" යන පදයෙහි නිවැරදි අර්ථය පහදා දෙනු මැනවි.","answer":"ඕලාරික යනු ඝන,තද,දැඩි යන තේරුම දේ.ධර්මයහි දේවාදී ශරීර සියුම් බවත්..මනුෂ්‍ය ශරීරය ඕලාරික බවත් කියවේ"},{"question":"වර්ෂාවේ දී දියමන්ති ඇද හැලෙන්නේ කුමන ග්‍රහලෝකයේ ද ?","answer":"යුරේනස්  සහ නෙප්චුන් "},{"question":"క్రింది సంఖ్యల జాబితాలో అంకశ్రేణి కానిది ఏది ?A) 1, 2, 3, 4, ……..B) 3, 3, 3, 3, ……..C) 6, 3, 0, – 3, ……D) 6, 4, 1, – 3, ……..","answer":"D) 6, 4, 1, – 3, …….."},{"question":"Một hộp có 12 chiếc thẻ cùng loại, mỗi thẻ được ghi một trong các số 1, 2, 3, ..., 12; hai thẻ khác nhau thì ghi hai số khác nhau. Rút ngẫu nhiên một chiếc thẻ trong hộp.a) Viết tập hợp B gồm các kết quả có thể xảy ra đối với số xuất hiện trên thẻ được rút ra.b) Xét biến cố “Số xuất hiện trên thẻ được rút ra là số chia hết cho 3”. Nêu những kết quả thuận lợi (có thể xảy ra) cho biến cố trên.c) Tìm tỉ số của số các kết quả thuận lợi cho biến cố trên và số phần tử của tập hợp B.","answer":"a) Tập hợp các kết quả có thể xảy ra đối với số xuất hiện trên thẻ được rút ra là: B = {1; 2; 3; ...; 12}.Số phần tử của tập hợp B là 12.b) Từ 1 đến 12 có các số chia hết cho 3 là: 3; 6; 9; 12.Do đó có 4 kết quả thuận lợi cho biến cố “Số xuất hiện trên thẻ được rút ra là số chia hết cho 3”.c) Tỉ số của số các kết quả thuận lợi cho biến cố “Số xuất hiện trên thẻ được rút ra là số chia hết cho 3” và số phần tử của tập hợp B bằng 4/12 = 1/3"},{"question":"من هي أول امرأة حازت على لقب طبيب؟","answer":"الطبيبة الإنجليزية اليزابيث باكويل."},{"question":"次のタイトルに基づいて、このトピックに関する記事を書きなさい： 3年前に中止になった高校野球　11月に甲子園で交流する","answer":"3年前の夏、新型コロナウイルスが広がって、日本でいちばんの高校を決める野球の大会が中止になりました。18日、大会に出ることができなかった３年前の高校生たちが、甲子園球場で試合などを行う計画の発表がありました。計画の名前は「あの夏を取り戻せ」です。3年前に県の大会で優勝した高校などの約1000人が11月29日に集まって、試合などを行って交流します。この計画を考えた大学生の大武優斗さんは3年前、高校3年生でした。大武さんは「今も悔しい気持ちが続いています。仲間と一緒に、この気持ちを終わりにする1日にしたいです」と話しました。福井県の敦賀気比高校で野球をしていた宮階宣全さんは「甲子園が私のすべてでした。今の力を全部出したいです」と涙を見せながら話しました。大会を開くために必要な約7000万円は、来月からインターネットで集めます。"},{"question":"Manomeza famintinana ho an'ity lahatsoratra manaraka ity:\\"Ny fiheveran-tena dia vato fehizoron'ny toe-tsaina salama sy matoky tena. Ny fikolokoloana ny hasarobidin'ny tena dia ny fanekena ny tanjany, ny fametrahana tanjona azo tratrarina, ary ny fampiharana ny fangoraham-po. Amin'ny alàlan'ny fandraisana ny fiheveran-tena ho an'ny tenany, ny olona dia afaka manokatra ny tanjany feno, mikatsaka ny faniriany, ary mamakivaky ireo fanamby eo amin'ny fiainana miaraka amin'ny faharetana sy ny fahatokian-tena.\\"","answer":"Mazava ho azy, ity ny famintinana ny lahatsoratra:Ny fikolokoloana ny fiheveran-tena ho an'ny tenany no fahafantarana ny tanjaka, fametrahana tanjona ary ny fanazaran-tena amin'ny fangorahana, ahafahan'ny olona mampiasa ny fahaiza-manaony ary miatrika ireo fanamby eo amin'ny fiainana amim-pahatokiana sy faharetana."},{"question":"Ziraat Bankası yabancı uyruklu hesap açma nasıl yapılır?","answer":"Başvuru dilekçeniz Pasaport aslı + oturum müsaade kartı aslı (Aufenthaltstitel) veya Alman kimliğinizin aslı ile şahsen şubelerimize başvurmanız halinde T.C. Ziraat Bank A.Ş.'nin ilgili şubesine 30 Euro bedel karşılığında iletilecektir."},{"question":"文章からキーワードを選び、その解釈を述べなさい。 大阪府と大阪市は、カジノや国際会議を開く会場、ホテルなどが1つになったリゾート「IR」を作ることを計画しています。大阪湾にある人工の島「夢洲」にIRを作って、2029年にオープンする計画です。政府は14日、IRについて話し合う会議を開きました。会議では、観光庁が集めた専門家が計画について調べた結果の報告がありました。ホテルの会社などの経営が安定しているかどうかや、ギャンブルをやめることができない人を増やさない工夫などについて調べて、問題がないという報告でした。このため、政府が計画を認めました。IRの計画について政府が認めたのは初めてです。岸田総理大臣は「IRができると、関西や日本の経済がよくなると考えています」と話しました。","answer":"この文章に含まれるキーワードとその解釈は以下です。- 人工: 1）自然にできたものでなく、人の力で作ること。- オープン: 1）開くこと。開場。2）かくしだてをしないようす。3）おおわれていない。4）公式でない。- 政府: 1）国の政治を行うところ。2）内閣。- 話し合う: 1）たがいに話す。おたがいに相手の話を聞き、自分も話す。2）意見を出し合う。- 結果: 1）あることがもとになって起こったことがらやようす。- 報告: 1）ものごとのなりゆきや、結果などを知らせること。また、その内容。- 経営: 1）事業をやっていくこと。- 安定: 1）つり合いが取れて、すわりがよいこと。2）激しい変化がないこと。- 増やさ: 1）多くする。- 工夫: 1）よい方法をいろいろ考えること。また、考えついた方法。- 認め: 1）実際に見る。2）確かにそのとおりだと判断する。3）承知する。許す。4）値打ちがあると考える。評価する。5）確かに自分のしたことであると同意する。- 総理大臣: 1）内閣総理大臣のこと。内閣の最高責任者で、国会議員の中から議員が選び、天皇によって任命される。首相。総理。- 関西: 1）京都・大阪・兵庫・奈良などの地方を指す言葉。"},{"question":"Waxaad sheegtaa waxyaalaha Sababa madowga Indhaha hoostooda Ku dhaca iyo qaabka loo baabi’Iyo ?","answer":"Barnamijkayga manta waxan idinku hayaa oo aan soo qatay madowga ku dhaca indhaha hoostooda  iyo bararka, runtiina dhantaala quruxda wajiga dumarka. Waxaan marka hore idin yar dareensiinaya waxyaabah keena oo dhan dhibtan soo gaadha indhaha hoostooda.Madowgan indhaha hoostooda ku dhaca (dark circles under eyes), ayaa dad badani isoo waydiiyeen, waxyaabah lagu gooyn karo. Sababtaas awgeed, waxan jecelahay inaan ka hadlo waxa keena, iyo sida la isaga gooyn karo. Waxaa jirta marka hore, Somali ahaan waxaynu cunaa cuntooyinka kuwa ugu cafimad darada badan ee ay ka midka yihiin , bariis, baasto, suugo, besbaas, iyo wixii milix iyo saliidiba ku badan tahay. Cuntooyinkan ayaa ah kuwa ugu badan ee dila jidhka dumarka, gaar ahaan indhaha hoostooda.Hadaba, madoowgan ayaa ah mid ku yimaada xaalado caafimad daro awgood, oo kale duwan, waxaana sababa jidhka ay ku yaalaan indhuhu oo ah, jidhka ugu khafiifsan jidhka wajiga, runtiina aad u jelicsan oo hadii aan la ilaalin ama aan la daryeelin halis u ah wax yaabo badan oo ku dhaca. Dhiiga bina aadamka ayaa markuu wareega sameeynayo soo dhex mara xidido yar yar, kuwaasoo loo yaqaano (capillaries) oo sababa dhibtada ugu wayn ee indhaha ku timaada, xididadan ayaa hadii ay soo gaadho awood daro ay ku mari kari wayaan dhiigagu, noqda kuwa daciifa runtiina dhiigaasi uu ku soo duxo, jidhka gaar ahaan indhaha hoostooda, indhaha hoostooda oo ah halka ugu khafiifsan jidhka, ayaan haba yaraatee u saamixin inuu dhiiga wareegeesu u maro si fiican.Sababahan, ayaa ah kuwo ku yimaada uun xaaladaha caafimad daro iyo jidhkoo nafaqadoodu is dhinto. Dhiigagan ayaa markay ku soo duxaan jidhka indhaha hoostooda fadhiista, ka bacdin ilaa ay soo gaadhayaan jidhka sare oo ay ka dhigayaan jidh madoow. Dhiiga kacsan ama loo yaqaano dhiig karka ayaa isna keen idhaha hoostoodu bararto, iyo cuntada milixda badan.Masaliska wajiga (facial muscles) ayaa iyaguna noqda kuwo isku soo uruura, ama bilaa awood noqda , marka qofka xaladiisa cafiimaaad is badasho.Waxa kaloo iyaguna keena dhibatadan madoowga indhaha hoostooda, maadooyinka jidhka siiya nafaqada oo door wayn ka qaata quruxda jidhka markay yaryihiin dumarku loona yaqaano (collagen) oo ka samaysan (amino acid), hadii ay daciifaan oo ay shaqayn kari waayaan dhibatadana ku timada dumarka, waxa fiican inay gabadhu ilaaliso jidhkeeda inta ay yartahay, wallow ay danba u daciifaan maadooyinkani quruxduna guurto marka la gaboobo!??Dhibatada kale ee laga qado madoowgan ayaa ah makeup- lagu seexdo, kaasoo indhaha soo gaadhsiiya dhibato kale, runtii jidhka indhahu ay ku yaalan ayaa ah jidh u bahan in si taxdir leh loo ilaaliyo, ama lala socdo jidhku wuxu u bahanyahay ama uu tabayo.Hadaba, markaa qofka biniaadamka ah ay isbadasho xaaladiisa caafimad, kuwaasoo kale ah:Hurdo LaaanWalwal iyo walbahaaarIndhaha oo cun cuna qofka (allergies)Sigaarka badan ee la cabo, wallow dumarku shaqo ku lahayn!?Biyo yaraanta (dehydration)Daalka badan ee ku dhaca cidhbaha qofka, ama kululaadaBunka badan ee la cabogabowgaOohinta badanSanboorkaMarmarka badan ee indhaha lagu sameeyo."},{"question":"Inona ny nosy malagasy any amin'ny avaratr'i Madagasikara.1. Nosy Sainte Marie2. Nosy Be","answer":"Safidy 2. Nosy Be no nosy any amin'ny avaratr'andrefan'i Madagasikara."},{"question":"Адам организми жөнүндө факт.","answer":"Адамдын баш мээсинде бир секундада 100 000 химиялык реакция өтөт."},{"question":"ලක්දිව බෞද්ධ ඉතිහාසයේ සඳහන් පරිදි , මාර්ගඵලලාභී ප්‍රථම සිංහල කාන්තාව කවුද ?","answer":"ලක්දිව බෞද්ධ ඉතිහාසයේ සඳහන් පරිදි , මාර්ගඵලලාභී ප්‍රථම සිංහල කාන්තාව අනුලා බිසව,"},{"question":"கர்மவீரர் காமராசர் என்னும் தலைப்பில் கட்டுரை ஒன்று எழுதுக.","answer":"முன்னுரை:தென்னாட்டு காந்தியாய் தமிழ் மண்ணில் அவதரித்து தமிழகத்தை மலர்ச்சியுறச் செய்த காமராசர், 1903-ஆம் ஆண்டு ஜூலை 15ல் விருதுநகரில் பிறந்தார். இவர் பெற்றோர் குமாரசுவாமி-சிவகாமியம்மாள் என்பவர்கள் ஆவர். தமிழ் மண்ணின் தவப்புதல்வராய் இருந்து ‘என் கடன் பணிசெய்து கிடப்பதே’ எனும் நோக்கில் இம்மண்ணிற்காக வாழ்ந்த திருமகன் இவர் என்றால் மிகையாகாது.வளர்ச்சி:நிமிர்ந்த நடையும், நேர்கொண்ட பார்வையும் அஞ்சாமல் கருத்தினை எடுத்து வைப்பவர் திருநாட்டிற்காக திருமணத்தைத் துறந்தவர்.முயற்சி:1954-ஆம் ஆண்டு காமராசர் முதல்வராகத் தேர்ந்தெடுக்கப்பட்டார். இவரின் ஆட்சிக் காலத்தினைத் தமிழகத்தின் பொற்காலம் எனக் கூறலாம். மக்களோடு மக்களாய்க் கலந்து மக்கள் படும் துன்பத்தினைத் தீர்த்து வைக்கும் இவர் ‘ஏழைகளின் நண்பன்’ எனப் போற்றப்பட்டார்.நெகிழ்ச்சி:கிராமங்கள்தோறும் பள்ளிகள் திறந்திடச் செய்தார். ஏழை மாணவர்களின் அல்லல் கண்டு இலவச மதிய உணவுத் திட்டத்தை’ வகுத்து செயல்படுத்தினார்.சின்னஞ்சிறுவர்களிடையே வேறுபாடுகளைக் களைந்திட சீருடைத் திட்டத்தினைக் கொண்டு வந்தார். தொழில் துறையில் தம் பார்வையைத் திருப்பி பல்வேறு தொழிலகங்களுக்கு வழிகளை ஏற்படுத்தினார்.மகிழ்ச்சி :1963 வரை ஒன்பது ஆண்டு காலம் அரும்பணிகள் ஆற்றிய இவர், காங்கிரஸ் கட்சியை வலுப்படுத்த ஏற்படுத்தப்பட்ட திட்டத்தின் மூலம் மூத்த தலைவர்களை பதவி விலகச் சொல்லி தாமும் தம்முடைய முதல்வர் பதவியிலிருந்து விலகினார்.முகமலர்ச்சி:மக்கள் அவரை பல்வேறு பெயர்களாலும், படிக்காத மேதை, ஏழைகள் நண்பன், கரும வீரர், காலாகாந்தி என அழைத்தலால் அனைத்துப் பெயர்களும் காமராசருக்கே உரித்தாயிற்று.அழற்சி:காமராசரின் நிலச் சீர்திருத்த உச்சவரம்பு சட்டமும், மும்மொழியாக்கத் திட்டமும் (இந்தியுடன்) பின்னடைவை ஏற்படுத்தின. திராவிடக் கட்சியானது தனது பேச்சு, எழுத்து மூலம் தடுமாற்றம் ஏற்பட வழிவகை செய்தது.முடிவுரை:‘காலா காந்தி’ என்ற பெயரினுக்கு ஏற்ப காந்தி பிறந்த தினத்தன்று, 1975 அக்டோபர் 2ல் காமராசர் மறைந்தார். காந்தி பிறந்த தினமானது காமராசரின் நினைவு தினமாக ஆயிற்று. காமராசரின் பிறந்த தினம், இனி ‘தியாகிகள் தின’ மாகக் கொண்டாடப்படுகிறது."},{"question":"Siapakah pengarah filem Crouching Tiger, Hidden Dragon?","answer":"Ang Lee"},{"question":"දෙසැම්බර් 7 ගැන කථා කරමු.","answer":"දෙසැම්බර් 7, ග්‍රෙගරි දින දසුනට අනුව අවුරුද්දේ 341 වන දිනය වේ (අධික අවුරුද්දක නම් 342 වන දිනය). අවුරුද්ද අවසන් වීමට තවත් දින 24 ඉතිරිව තිබේ."},{"question":"DC 有什么好吃的？","answer":"DC 是一个多元化的城市，拥有来自世界各地的餐厅。"},{"question":"Apakah maksud \\"bagai diiris dengan sembilu\\"? Berikan satu contoh ayat. ","answer":"Maksudnya ialah perasaan yang sangat pedih. Contohnya, hatinya bagai diirus dengan sembilu apabila mendapat khabar tentang kemalangan yang menimpa suaminya. "},{"question":"Soalan: Bilakah episod seterus untuk The Handmaid's Tale disiarkan? Jawapan:","answer":"6 Jun 2018"},{"question":"ഒരു വ്യക്തിക്ക് ജലാംശം നിലനിർത്താനുള്ള എല്ലാ വഴികളുടെയും ഒരു ലിസ്റ്റ് തരൂ. ","answer":"- ഒരു ഗ്ലാസിൽ നിന്ന് വെള്ളം കുടിക്കുക - ഒരു പൈ ഉപയോഗിച്ച് വെള്ളം കുടിക്കുക - ഒരു പൈപ്പിൽ നിന്ന് വെള്ളം കുടിക്കുക - ഒരു ഐസ് ക്യൂബ് കഴിക്കുക- ഒരു IV എടുക്കുക - ഒരു ഇലക്ട്രോലൈറ്റ് പാനീയം കുടിക്കുക"},{"question":"Ата-энеге насаат...","answer":"Өз балаңды өзүңдөй же сен каалагандай болот деп күтпө, ага өз алдынча болуусуна жардам бер. "},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਗਉੜੀ ਮਹਲਾ ੫ ॥ਮੋਹਨ ਤੇਰੇ ਊਚੇ ਮੰਦਰ ਮਹਲ ਅਪਾਰਾ ॥ਮੋਹਨ ਤੇਰੇ ਸੋਹਨਿ ਦੁਆਰ ਜੀਉ ਸੰਤ ਧਰਮ ਸਾਲਾ ॥ਧਰਮ ਸਾਲ ਅਪਾਰ ਦੈਆਰ ਠਾਕੁਰ ਸਦਾ ਕੀਰਤਨੁ ਗਾਵਹੇ ॥ਜਹ ਸਾਧ ਸੰਤ ਇਕਤ੍ਰ ਹੋਵਹਿ ਤਹਾ ਤੁਝਹਿ ਧਿਆਵਹੇ ॥ਕਰਿ ਦਇਆ ਮਇਆ ਦਇਆਲ ਸੁਆਮੀ ਹੋਹੁ ਦੀਨ ਕ੍ਰਿਪਾਰਾ ॥ਬਿਨਵੰਤਿ ਨਾਨਕ ਦਰਸ ਪਿਆਸੇ ਮਿਲਿ ਦਰਸਨ ਸੁਖੁ ਸਾਰਾ ॥੧॥ਮੋਹਨ ਤੇਰੇ ਬਚਨ ਅਨੂਪ ਚਾਲ ਨਿਰਾਲੀ ॥ਮੋਹਨ ਤੂੰ ਮਾਨਹਿ ਏਕੁ ਜੀ ਅਵਰ ਸਭ ਰਾਲੀ ॥ਮਾਨਹਿ ਤ ਏਕੁ ਅਲੇਖੁ ਠਾਕੁਰੁ ਜਿਨਹਿ ਸਭ ਕਲ ਧਾਰੀਆ ॥ਤੁਧੁ ਬਚਨਿ ਗੁਰ ਕੈ ਵਸਿ ਕੀਆ ਆਦਿ ਪੁਰਖੁ ਬਨਵਾਰੀਆ ॥ਤੂੰ ਆਪਿ ਚਲਿਆ ਆਪਿ ਰਹਿਆ ਆਪਿ ਸਭ ਕਲ ਧਾਰੀਆ ॥ਬਿਨਵੰਤਿ ਨਾਨਕ ਪੈਜ ਰਾਖਹੁ ਸਭ ਸੇਵਕ ਸਰਨਿ ਤੁਮਾਰੀਆ ॥੨॥ਮੋਹਨ ਤੁਧੁ ਸਤਸੰਗਤਿ ਧਿਆਵੈ ਦਰਸ ਧਿਆਨਾ ॥ਮੋਹਨ ਜਮੁ ਨੇੜਿ ਨ ਆਵੈ ਤੁਧੁ ਜਪਹਿ ਨਿਦਾਨਾ ॥ਜਮਕਾਲੁ ਤਿਨ ਕਉ ਲਗੈ ਨਾਹੀ ਜੋ ਇਕ ਮਨਿ ਧਿਆਵਹੇ ॥ਮਨਿ ਬਚਨਿ ਕਰਮਿ ਜਿ ਤੁਧੁ ਅਰਾਧਹਿ ਸੇ ਸਭੇ ਫਲ ਪਾਵਹੇ ॥ਮਲ ਮੂਤ ਮੂੜ ਜਿ ਮੁਗਧ ਹੋਤੇ ਸਿ ਦੇਖਿ ਦਰਸੁ ਸੁਗਿਆਨਾ ॥ਬਿਨਵੰਤਿ ਨਾਨਕ ਰਾਜੁ ਨਿਹਚਲੁ ਪੂਰਨ ਪੁਰਖ ਭਗਵਾਨਾ ॥੩॥ਮੋਹਨ ਤੂੰ ਸੁਫਲੁ ਫਲਿਆ ਸਣੁ ਪਰਵਾਰੇ ॥ਮੋਹਨ ਪੁਤ੍ਰ ਮੀਤ ਭਾਈ ਕੁਟੰਬ ਸਭਿ ਤਾਰੇ ॥ਤਾਰਿਆ ਜਹਾਨੁ ਲਹਿਆ ਅਭਿਮਾਨੁ ਜਿਨੀ ਦਰਸਨੁ ਪਾਇਆ ॥ਜਿਨੀ ਤੁਧਨੋ ਧੰਨੁ ਕਹਿਆ ਤਿਨ ਜਮੁ ਨੇੜਿ ਨ ਆਇਆ ॥ਬੇਅੰਤ ਗੁਣ ਤੇਰੇ ਕਥੇ ਨ ਜਾਹੀ ਸਤਿਗੁਰ ਪੁਰਖ ਮੁਰਾਰੇ ॥ਬਿਨਵੰਤਿ ਨਾਨਕ ਟੇਕ ਰਾਖੀ ਜਿਤੁ ਲਗਿ ਤਰਿਆ ਸੰਸਾਰੇ ॥੪॥੨॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 248 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਅਰਜਨ ਦੇਵ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਬਾਣੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਹਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"ਹੇ ਮਨ ਨੂੰ ਮੋਹ ਲੈਣ ਵਾਲੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ! ਤੇਰੇ ਉੱਚੇ ਮੰਦਰ ਹਨ, ਤੇਰੇ ਮਹਲ ਐਸੈ ਹਨ ਕਿ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦਾ ਪਾਰਲਾ ਬੰਨਾ ਨਹੀਂ ਦਿੱਸਦਾ ਹੇ ਮੋਹਨ! ਤੇਰੇ ਦਰ ਤੇ ਤੇਰੇ ਧਰਮ-ਅਸਥਾਨਾਂ ਵਿਚ, ਤੇਰੇ ਸੰਤ ਜਨ (ਬੈਠੇ) ਸੋਹਣੇ ਲੱਗ ਰਹੇ ਹਨ ।ਹੇ ਬੇਅੰਤ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ! ਹੇ ਦਇਆਲ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ! ਹੇ ਠਾਕੁਰ! ਤੇਰੇ ਧਰਮ-ਅਸਥਾਨਾਂ ਵਿਚ, ਤੇਰੇ ਸੰਤ ਜਨ ਸਦਾ ਤੇਰਾ ਕੀਰਤਨ ਗਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ । (ਹੇ ਮੋਹਨ!) ਜਿਥੇ ਭੀ ਸਾਧ ਸੰਤ ਇਕੱਠੇ ਹੁੰਦੇ ਹਨ ਉਥੇ ਤੈਨੂੰ ਹੀ ਧਿਆਉਂਦੇ ਹਨ । ਹੇ ਦਇਆ ਦੇ ਘਰ ਮੋਹਨ! ਹੇ ਸਭ ਦੇ ਮਾਲਕ ਮੋਹਨ! ਤੂੰ ਦਇਆ ਕਰ ਕੇ ਤਰਸ ਕਰ ਕੇ ਗਰੀਬਾਂ ਅਨਾਥਾਂ ਉਤੇ ਕਿਰਪਾਲ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈਂ । (ਹੇ ਮੋਹਨ!) ਨਾਨਕ ਬੇਨਤੀ ਕਰਦਾ ਹੈ—ਤੇਰੇ ਦਰਸ਼ਨ ਦੇ ਪਿਆਸੇ (ਤੇਰੇ ਸੰਤ ਜਨ) ਤੈਨੂੰ ਮਿਲ ਕੇ ਤੇਰੇ ਦਰਸਨ ਦਾ ਸੁਖ ਮਾਣਦੇ ਹਨ ।੧। ਹੇ ਮੋਹਨ! ਤੇਰੀ ਸਿਫ਼ਤਿ-ਸਾਲਾਹ ਦੇ ਬਚਨ ਸੋਹਣੇ ਲੱਗਦੇ ਹਨ, ਤੇਰੀ ਚਾਲ (ਜਗਤ ਦੇ ਜੀਵਾਂ ਦੀ ਚਾਲ ਨਾਲੋਂ) ਵੱਖਰੀ ਹੈ । ਹੇ ਮੋਹਨ ਜੀ! (ਸਾਰੇ ਜੀਵ) ਸਿਰਫ਼ ਤੈਨੂੰ ਹੀ (ਸਦਾ ਕਾਇਮ ਰਹਿਣ ਵਾਲਾ) ਮੰਨਦੇ ਹਨ, ਹੋਰ ਸਾਰੀ ਸ੍ਰਿਸ਼ਟੀ ਨਾਸ-ਵੰਤ ਹੈ ।ਹੇ ਮੋਹਨ! ਸਿਰਫ਼ ਤੈਨੂੰ ਇਕ ਨੂੰ (ਅਸਥਿਰ) ਮੰਨਦੇ ਹਨ—ਸਿਰਫ਼ ਤੈਨੂੰ—ਜਿਸ ਦਾ ਸਰੂਪ ਬਿਆਨ ਨਹੀਂ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ, ਜੋ ਤੂੰ ਸਭ ਦਾ ਪਾਲਣਹਾਰ ਹੈਂ, ਤੇ ਜਿਸ ਤੈਂ ਨੇ ਸਾਰੀ ਸ੍ਰਿਸ਼ਟੀ ਵਿਚ ਆਪਣੀ ਸੱਤਾ ਵਰਤਾਈ ਹੋਈ ਹੈ ।ਹੇ ਮੋਹਨ! ਤੈਨੂੰ (ਤੇਰੇ ਭਗਤਾਂ ਨੇ) ਗੁਰੂ ਦੇ ਬਚਨ ਦੀ ਰਾਹੀਂ (ਪਿਆਰ-) ਵੱਸ ਕੀਤਾ ਹੋਇਆ ਹੈ, ਤੂੰ ਸਭ ਦਾ ਮੁੱਢ ਹੈਂ, ਤੂੰ ਸਰਬ-ਵਿਆਪਕ ਹੈਂ, ਤੂੰ ਸਾਰੇ ਜਗਤ ਦਾ ਮਾਲਕ ਹੈਂ । ਹੇ ਮੋਹਨ! (ਸਾਰੇ ਜੀਵਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਮੌਜੂਦ ਹੋਣ ਕਰਕੇ) ਤੂੰ ਆਪ ਹੀ (ਉਮਰ ਭੋਗ ਕੇ ਜਗਤ ਤੋਂ) ਚਲਾ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈਂ, ਫਿਰ ਭੀ ਤੂੰ ਹੀ ਆਪ ਸਦਾ ਕਾਇਮ ਰਹਿਣ ਵਾਲਾ ਹੈਂ, ਤੂੰ ਹੀ ਜਗਤ ਵਿਚ ਆਪਣੀ ਸੱਤਾ ਵਰਤਾਈ ਹੋਈ ਹੈ । ਨਾਨਕ ਬੇਨਤੀ ਕਰਦਾ ਹੈ—(ਆਪਣੇ ਸੇਵਕਾਂ ਦੀ ਤੂੰ ਆਪ ਹੀ) ਲਾਜ ਰੱਖਦਾ ਹੈਂ, ਸਾਰੇ ਸੇਵਕ-ਭਗਤ ਤੇਰੀ ਸਰਨ ਪੈਂਦੇ ਹਨ ।੨। ਹੇ ਮੋਹਨ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ! ਤੈਨੂੰ ਸਾਧ ਸੰਗਤਿ ਧਿਆਉਂਦੀ ਹੈ, ਤੇਰੇ ਦਰਸਨ ਦਾ ਧਿਆਨ ਧਰਦੀ ਹੈ । ਹੇ ਮੋਹਨ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ! ਜੇਹੜੇ ਜੀਵ ਤੈਨੂੰ ਜਪਦੇ ਹਨ, ਅੰਤ ਵੇਲੇ ਮੌਤ ਦਾ ਸਹਮ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਨੇੜੇ ਨਹੀਂ ਢੁਕਦਾ । ਜੇਹੜੇ ਤੈਨੂੰ ਇਕਾਗਰ ਮਨ ਨਾਲ ਧਿਆਉਂਦੇ ਹਨ, ਮੌਤ ਦਾ ਸਹਮ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਪੋਹ ਨਹੀਂ ਸਕਦਾ (ਆਤਮਕ ਮੌਤ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਉਤੇ ਪ੍ਰਭਾਵ ਨਹੀਂ ਪਾ ਸਕਦੀ) । ਜੇਹੜੇ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਆਪਣੇ ਮਨ ਦੀ ਰਾਹੀਂ, ਉਹ ਆਪਣੇ ਬੋਲ ਦੀ ਰਾਹੀਂ, ਆਪਣੇ ਕਰਮ ਦੀ ਰਾਹੀਂ, ਤੈਨੂੰ ਯਾਦ ਕਰਦੇ ਰਹਿੰਦੇ ਹਨ, ਉਹ ਸਾਰੇ (ਮਨ-ਇੱਛਤ) ਫਲ ਪ੍ਰਾਪਤ ਕਰ ਲੈਂਦੇ ਹਨ । ਹੇ ਸਰਬ-ਵਿਆਪਕ! ਹੇ ਭਗਵਾਨ! ਉਹ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਭੀ ਤੇਰਾ ਦਰਸਨ ਕਰ ਕੇ ਉੱਚੀ ਸੂਝ ਵਾਲੇ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ ਜੋ (ਪਹਿਲਾਂ) ਗੰਦੇ-ਕੁਕਰਮੀ ਤੇ ਮਹਾ ਮੂਰਖ ਹੰੁਦੇ ਹਨ ।ਨਾਨਕ ਬੇਨਤੀ ਕਰਦਾ ਹੈ—ਹੇ ਮੋਹਨ! ਤੇਰਾ ਰਾਜ ਸਦਾ ਕਾਇਮ ਰਹਿਣ ਵਾਲਾ ਹੈ ।੩। ਹੇ ਮੋਹਨ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ! ਤੂੰ ਬੜਾ ਸੋਹਣਾ ਫਲਿਆ ਹੋਇਆ ਹੈਂ, ਤੂੰ ਬੜੇ ਵੱਡੇ ਪਰਵਾਰ ਵਾਲਾ ਹੈਂ । ਹੇ ਮੋਹਨ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ! ਪੁੱਤਰਾਂ ਭਰਾਵਾਂ ਮਿੱਤਰਾਂ ਵਾਲੇ ਵੱਡੇ ਵੱਡੇ ਟੱਬਰ ਤੂੰ ਸਾਰੇ ਦੇ ਸਾਰੇ (ਸੰਸਾਰ-ਸਮੁੰਦਰ ਤੋਂ) ਪਾਰ ਲੰਘਾ ਦੇਂਦਾ ਹੈਂ ।ਹੇ ਮੋਹਨ! ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਨੇ ਤੇਰਾ ਦਰਸਨ ਕੀਤਾ, ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਅੰਦਰੋਂ ਤੂੰ ਅਹੰਕਾਰ ਦੂਰ ਕਰ ਦਿੱਤਾ । ਤੂੰ ਸਾਰੇ ਜਹਾਨ ਨੂੰ ਹੀ ਤਾਰਨ ਦੀ ਸਮਰੱਥਾ ਵਾਲਾ ਹੈਂ । ਹੇ ਮੋਹਨ! ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ (ਵਡ-ਭਾਗੀਆਂ) ਨੇ ਤੇਰੀ ਸਿਫ਼ਤਿ-ਸਾਲਾਹ ਕੀਤੀ, ਆਤਮਕ ਮੌਤ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਨੇੜੇ ਨਹੀਂ ਢੁਕਦੀ ।ਹੇ ਸਭ ਤੋਂ ਵੱਡੇ! ਸਰਬ-ਵਿਆਪਕ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ! ਤੇਰੇ ਗੁਣ ਬੇਅੰਤ ਹਨ, ਬਿਆਨ ਨਹੀਂ ਕੀਤੇ ਜਾ ਸਕਦੇ । ਨਾਨਕ ਬੇਨਤੀ ਕਰਦਾ ਹੈ—ਮੈਂ ਤੇਰਾ ਹੀ ਆਸਰਾ ਲਿਆ ਹੈ, ਜਿਸ ਆਸਰੇ ਦੀ ਬਰਕਤਿ ਨਾਲ ਮੈਂ ਇਸ ਸੰਸਾਰ-ਸਮੁੰਦਰ ਤੋਂ ਪਾਰ ਲੰਘ ਰਿਹਾ ਹਾਂ ।੪।੨।\\""},{"question":"মি. রহমান বাংলাদেশের নাগরিক। তিনি ২৩শে জুন দ আফ্রিকার একটি শহরে বেড়াতে যান। সেখান থেকে কিছুদিন পর জাহাজ দিয়ে চ্যাথাম দ্বীপপুঞ্জ অতিক্রম করে তিনি ব্রাজিলে বেড়াতে যান। মি. রহমানের ভ্রমণকৃত দেশগুলোর পরিবেশের সাথে অভিযোজনে সক্ষম হতে হলে তাকে কী করতে হবে? মতামত দাও।","answer":"মি. রহমানের ভ্রমণকৃত দেশগুলোর পরিবেশের সাথে অভিযোজনে সক্ষম হতে হলে তাকে পোশাকে পরিবর্তন আনতে হবে।পৃথিবীর বার্ষিক গতি অনুযায়ী ২১শে জুন সূর্যের উত্তরায়ণের শেষ দিন । এই দিন সূর্যরশ্মি কর্কটক্রান্তির উপর লম্বভাবে পতিত হয়। ২১ শে জুনের পর দেড়মাস পূর্ব থেকে দেড় মাস পর পর্যন্ত মোট তিনমাস পৃথিবীর উত্তর গোলার্ধে উত্তাপ বেশি থাকে। এ সময় উত্তর গোলার্ধে গ্রীষ্মকাল আর এ সময়ে সূর্য দক্ষিণ গোলার্ধে তির্যকভাবে কিরণ দেয়। এজন্য সেখানে তখন শীতকাল।উদ্দীপকে মি. রহমান বাংলাদেশের নাগরিক। তিনি ২৩শে জুন দক্ষিণ আফ্রিকার একটি শহরে বেড়াতে যান। কিছুদিন পর তিনি ব্রাজিলে বেড়াতে যান। বাংলাদেশ পৃথিবীর উত্তর গোলার্ধে অবস্থিত। তাই ২১ শে জুনের আগে ও পরের দেড় মাস করে মোট তিনমাস বাংলাদেশে গ্রীষ্মকাল। কিন্তু মি. রহমানের বেড়াতে যাওয়া দেশ দক্ষিণ আফ্রিকা ও ব্রাজিল পৃথিবীর দক্ষিণ গোলার্ধে অবস্থিত। তাই ২১শে জুনের আগে ও পরের দেড় মাস করে মোট তিনমাস এসব দেশে শীতকাল। মি. রহমান যেহেতু ২১শে জুনের পর এসব দেশে বেড়াতে গেছেন সেহেতু সেখানে গিয়ে তিনি শীতকাল পাবেন এবং সেখানে তাকে পরিবেশের সাথে খাপ খাইয়ে নিতে শীতের পোশাক পরিধান করতে হবে।উপরের আলোচনা থেকে বলা যায়, মি. রহমানের ভ্রমণকৃত দেশগুলোতে তার বেড়াতে যাওয়া সময়ে শীতকাল বিরাজ করায় সেখানে তাকে অভিযোজনের জন্য শীতের পোশাক নিয়ে যেতে হবে।"},{"question":"சிறுநீரகக் கல் நோயாளிகளுக்கான உணவுகள் என்னென்ன?","answer":"சிறுநீரக கற்கள் உள்ளவர்களுக்கான பொதுவான உணவு முறைகள்:இளநீர்: இதில் பொட்டாசியம், மெக்னீஷியமும் அதிகம் உள்ளன. இவை சிறுசீரகக் கற்களின் முன்னோடிகளான படிகங்களைக் கரைத்து படிய விடாமல் தடுக்க வல்லவை.காரட், பாகற்காய்: இவற்றில் சிறுநீரகக் கற்களின் படிகங்களை தடுக்கும் பலவித தாது உப்புக்கள் உள்ள தாக கண்டறியப் பட்டுள்ளது.பழங்கள், பழச்சாறுகள்:வாழைப்பழம், எலுமிச்சை: இவற்றில் விட்டமின் பி-6 சத்தும், சிட்ரேட் சத்தும் அதிகம் உள்ளன. இவை சிறுநீரகக் கற்களின் ஒரு முக்கிய அங்கமான ஆக்சலேட் என்ற இரசாயனத்துடன் சேர்த்து அதைச் சிதைத்து படிய விடாமல் தடுத்து சிறுநீரகக் கற்கள் உருவாகாமல் தடுக்க வல்லவை.பைபானப்பிள் சாறு: இதில் சிறுநீரக கற்களின் கருவாக இருக்கும் ஃபைப்ரின் எனப்படும் சத்தை சிதைக்கும் நொதிகள் உள்ளன.கொள்ளு:இதில் உள்ள சில நீர்ப் பொருட்கள் சிறுநீரகக் கற்கள் உருவாவதை தடுக்கும் திறன் கொண்டவை. நார்ச்சத்து உள்ள உணவுகள்.பாதாம் பருப்பு, பார்லி ஓட்ஸ்: போன்றவற்றில் சிறுநீரக கற்கள் வராமல் தடுக்கும் பலவித சத்துகள் உள்ளன. பொதுவாக சில காய்கறிகள், பழங்களைத் தவிர தினமும் உணவில் நார்சத்து உள்ள காய்கறிகள், பழங்கள், முழு தானியங்களை அதிகமாக சேர்த்துக் கொள்வது உடல் ஆரோக்கியத்திற்கு நல்லது.கற்கள் வருவதையும் தடுக்கும்.உப்பு: உணவில் உப்பையும் பெருமளவு குறைத்துக் கொள்வது சிறுநீரில் கால்சியம் சத்து வெளியா வதை தடுத்து சிறுநீரகக் கற்கள் வரும் வாய்ப்பை குறைப்பதாக இப்போது கண்டறியப்பட்டுள்ளது.தவிர்க்க வேண்டிய உணவுப் பொருட்கள்:காய்கறிகள்: தக்காளி விதைகள் (விதை நீக்கப்பட்ட தக்காளி சேர்த்துக்கொள்ளலாம்) பாலக் கீரை, பசலைக் கீரை இவற்றில் ஆக்சலேட் சத்து அதிகம் உள்ளது.கத்திரிக்காய், காளான், காலிஃப்ளவர் இவற்றில் சிறுநீரக கற்களின் மற்றொரு அங்கமான யூரிக் அமிலம் அதிகம் உள்ளது. பரங்கிக்காய் இதில் யூரிக் அமிலமும் அதன் மூலப் பொருளான ப்யூரின்களும் அதிகம் உள்ளன. இந்தக் காய்கறிகளைத் தவிர்க்கவும்.பழங்கள்: சப்போட்டா, திராட்சை இவற்றில் ஆக்சலேட் அதிகம்.எள்: இதில் அதிக ஆக்சலேட் உள்ளது. அதிகம் எடுத்துக் கொள்வதை தவிர்க்கவும்.அசைவ உணவுகள்: ஆட்டிறைச்சி, மாட்டிறைச்சி, கோழிக் கறி, முட்டை, மீன் இவை அனைத்திலும் ப்யூரின்களும், யூரிக் அமில மும் அதிகம். யூரிக் அமில வகைக் கற்கள் உள்ளவர்கள் தவிர்க்க வேண்டும்.முந்திரிப்பருப்பு: இதில் அதிக ஆக்சலேட் உள்ளது. சிறுநீரகக் கற்கள் பெரும்பாலும் கால்சியம் மற்றும் ஆக்சலேட் கலந்தவை ஆகும். இதனைத் தவிர்க்கவும்.சாக்லேட், சாக்லேட் கலந்த தின்பண்டங்கள், காபி, டீ ஆகியவற்றிலும் ஆக்சலேட் உள்ளது. எச்சரிக்கை தேவை. தினமும் பன்னிரண்டு டம்ளர் நீர் அருந்தவும், கடினத்தன்மை உள்ள நீராய் இருந்தால் காய்ச்சி வடிகட்டி குடிக்கவும்.கற்களின் வகைகளுக்கேற்ற சிறப்பு உணவு முறைகள்:கால்சியம் மற்றும் ஆக்சலேட் கலந்த வகை கற்கள்:  தினமும் பன்னிரண்டு டம்ளர் நீர் அருந்தவும். அதிக கால்சியம் உள்ள பால், பால் பொருட்கள் மற்றும் வேர்க்கடலை, ஆக்சலேட் அதிகம் உள்ள சாக்லேட், கோலா கலந்த பானங்கள் மேற்கூறிய மற்ற உணவுகளை குறைத்துக் கொள்ளவும். வயிறு அல்சருக்கு சில சமயம் எடுத்துக் கொள்ளும் ஜெலுசில் போன்ற கால்சியம் கலந்த ஆன்டா சிட் மருந்துகளைத் தவிர்க்கவும். உணவில் உப்பையும் குறைத்துக் கொள்ளவும்.யூரிக் அமில வகை கற்கள்: தினமும் பன்னிரண்டு டம்ளர் நீர் அருந்தவும். ப்யூரின்கள் அதிக உள்ள மட்டன், சிக்கன், முட்டை, மீன், பால் போன்ற உணவு வகைகளைத் தவிர்க்கவும்.ஸ்ட்ரூவைட் வகை கற்கள்: இந்த வகை கற்கள் சிறுநீரகங்களில் கிருமி தாக்கத்தால் வருகின்றன. மருத்துவர் பரிந்துரைக்கும் கிருமிக் கொல்லி மருந்துகள் மருந்துகளை தவறாமல் எடுத்துக் கொள்ளவும் தினம் குறைந்தது பன்னிரண்டு டம்ளர் நீர் அருந்தவும்.சிஸ்டின் வகைக் கற்கள்: இவை மிக அபூர்வமானவை. மீன் உணவை தவிர்க்கவும். தினமும் பன்னிரண்டு டம்ளர் நீர் அருந்தவும்."},{"question":"Podaj pięć pierwszych cyfr ciągu Fibbonacciego.","answer":"Jasne, oto one: 0,\\t1,\\t1,\\t2,\\t3."},{"question":"Hiện tại tôi đang có ý định phẫu thuật điều trị tật khúc xạ và tôi đã tìm hiểu trên mạng hiện nay có rất nhiều phương pháp. Xin cho tôi biết phương pháp nào là an toàn và tối ưu nhất hiện nay.","answer":"Chào bạn, hiện có 4 phương pháp điều trị tật khúc xạ phổ biến hiện nay.– Lasik phổ thông, Lasik Extra (Lasik phối hợp Crosslinking): Giá thành hợp lý, song có tỷ lệ biến chứng nhất định trong và sau phẫu thuật (80% biến chứng kiên quan đến vạt giác mạc).– Femto-Lasik: Giá thành cao hơn so với Lasik vì kết hợp 2 loại laser, cải thiện độ chính xác và an toàn, phục hồi nhanh sau mổ, vẫn còn tỷ lệ biến chứng vạt giác mạc nhất định.– Smart Surface: Phẫu thuật không chạm, không tạo vạt giác mạc, thuận lợi, dễ làm, chi phí tốt, nhưng có thể gây đau sau mổ 1-2 ngày.– Relex Smile: Chi phí cao nhưng nhiều ưu điểm như không tạo vạt giác mạc, đường mổ 2mm nhỏ, giảm tối đa biến chứng vạt, khô mắt và nhiễm trùng; rút ngắn thời gian mổ còn 23 giây mỗi mắt, độ chính xác cao; bệnh nhân không đau và phục hồi nhanh ngay ngày đầu sau mổ, nên đặc biệt phù hợp với đối tượng hoạt động mạnh (chơi thể thao, ngành nghề phi công, cảnh sát…)."},{"question":"Lidokain ne tür ilaç?","answer":"Lidokain hidroklorür, lokal anestezik ve antiaritmik bir ilaçtır. Lidokain hidroklorür klinik olarak infiltrasyon anestezisi, epidural anestezi, yüzey anestezisi (mukozal anestezi için torakoskopi veya abdominal cerrahi dahil) ve sinir iletim bloğu için kullanılır."},{"question":"Izinto zonke zithatha isikhathi;Ilanga liphuma ngesal' isikhathi,Ihlobo liyafika ngesalo lodwa,Nobusika bufika buhamba bodwa;Nawe uzofika phambili ngesakho,Nguyen’ owaziyo uMdali ngalokho,Ubude abuphangwa.Mawungaphang' izinto eziphakeme,Ngoba uzofika nawe kuzo ume,Thatha nje kancane ukuya phambiliBambelelela ngezandla zakho zombili,Uyojabula nawe usufikile,Ngokuqinisela kwakh' usuvunile;Ubud' ungabuphangi.Nawe mfana osaqala isikole,Mana isibindi uyoze utholeLokho okuhle okubona phambili,Fumbath' isikole ngezandla zombili,Ikhona uyofika phambili nawe,Uze uthole lokho okungangawe;Ubude abuphangwa.1. Phawula ngempumelelo yembongi yokusebenzisa impindwa kule nkondlo. ","answer":"Imbongi iphumelele kahle ukusebenzisa impindwa ethi, ‘ubudeabuphangwa/ungabuphangi’ ukugcizelela ukuthi ungabojaha izinto ukubazenzeke ngokushesha"},{"question":"Ity misy toe-java-niseho: “Nifanena tamin’ny mpitari-dàlana iray teo an-toerana antsoina hoe Carlos i Jennifer, rehefa nandehandeha.” Raha mamorona fanontaniana avy amin'io toe-javatra io isika, ary ny valin'io fanontaniana io dia \\"Carlos\\", inona no fanontaniana?","answer":"Iza ilay mpitari-dàlana teo an-toerana nifanena tamin'i Jennifer nandritra ny dia?"},{"question":"Àjẹsára àrùn dìgbòlugi","answer":"Àjẹsára àrùn dìgbòlugi jẹ́ àjẹsára tí à ń lò láti fi dènà àrùn dìgbòlugi. Àwọn oríṣiríṣi wọn wà tí a lè lò láìséwu, tí wọ́n sì ń ṣiṣẹ́ bó ti yẹ. A lè lò wọ́n láti fi dènà àrùn dìgbòlugi ṣáájú tàbí fún àkókò díẹ̀ lẹ́yìn tí ènìyàn bá ti wà ní sàkání ibití kòkòrò àrùn rẹ̀ gbé wà, bíi kí ajá tàbí àdán gé ni jẹ. Agbára àti kojú àìsàn tí ènìyàn yóò ní jẹ́ èyítí yóò pẹ́ títí lẹ́yìn tí ènìyàn bá ti gba ìwọ̀n egbògi náà mẹ́ta. A má a ń sábà fún ni ní àwọn àjẹsára náà nípasẹ̀ abẹ́rẹ́ tí a ń gún sínú awọ tàbí ẹran ara ẹni. Lẹ̀yìn tí ènìyàn bá ti wà ní sàkání ibití kòkòrò àrùn rẹ̀ gbé wà, a má a ń sábà gba àjẹsára náà pẹ̀lú àwọn àkóónú inú ẹ̀jẹ̀ tí ngbógun ti àwọn kòkòrò àrùn nínú ara ti àrùn dìgbòlugi. A gba ni níyànjú láti fún àwọn tó wà lábẹ́ ewu wíwà ní sàkání ibití àrùn náà gbé wà ní àjẹsára kí wọ́n tó lọ sí irú sàkání bẹ́ẹ̀. Àwọn àjẹsára náà a má a ṣiṣẹ́ lára ènìyàn àti lára àwọn ẹranko mìíràn. Gbígba àjẹsára fún ajá jẹ́ ìgbésẹ̀ tó lágbára láti dènà àrùn náà lára ènìyàn.A lè lò wọ́n láìséwu fún ẹnikẹ́ni pẹ̀lú ọjọ́-orí yòówù. Iye àwọn ènìyàn tó tó 35 sí 45 nínú ọgọ́ọ̀rún a má a ní ìrírí pípupa yòò àti dídunni ojú ibi abẹ́rẹ́ náà fún ìwọ̀n ìgbà díẹ́. Iye àwọn ènìyàn tó tó 5 sí 15 nínú ọgọ́ọ̀rún lè ní ibà, ẹ̀fọ́rí, tàbí kí èébì má a gbé wọn. Lẹ́yìn tí ènìyàn bá ti wà ní sàkání ibití ènìyàn ti lè kó àrùn dìgbòlugi, kò sí ohun tó ní kí ènìyàn má gba àjẹsára náà. Púpọ̀ lára àwọn àjẹsára náà kò ní ohun ti a n pè ní thimerosal nínú. Àwọn àjẹsára tí a ṣe pẹ̀lú iṣan-ara ni à ń lò ní àwọn orílẹ̀-èdè méèló kan, pàápàá ní Éṣíà àti Latin Amẹ́ríkà, ṣùgbọ́n agbára wọn kò pọ̀ púpọ̀, bẹ́ẹ̀ sì ni àtúnbọ̀tán wọn pọ̀ púpọ̀. Nítorí náà ni Àjọ Ìlera Àgbáyé kò ṣe gba ni nímọ̀ràn láti má a lò wọ́n.Àìmọye ènìyàn káàkiri àgbáyé ni a ti fún ní àjẹsára náà, a sì mọ̀ pé èyí a má a dáàbò bo iye àwọn ènìyàn tó ju 250,000 lọ lọ́dún. Ó wà lórí Àkójọ Àwọn Egbògi Kòṣeémáàní ti Àjọ Ìlera Àgbáyé (World Health Organization), àwọn òògùn tó ṣe pàtàkì jùlọ tí a nílò fún ètò ìlera ìbẹ̀rẹ̀pẹ̀pẹ̀ yòówù. Iye owó rẹ̀ lójú pálí jẹ́ 44 sí 78 USD fún ètò ìtọ́jú lẹ́ẹ̀kanṣoṣo ní ọdún 2014. Ní ilẹ̀ Amẹ́ríkà ètò ìtọ́jú lẹ́ẹ̀kanṣoṣo ti àjẹsára dìgbòlugi jú 750 USD lọ."},{"question":"Завершите следующий отрывок: На Олимпийских играх 2012 года в Лондоне Мисси стала одной из главных героинь, выиграв 5 медалей, включая 4 золота. Франклин стала первой на обеих дистанциях на спине — 100 и 200 метров, а также выступала в победном составе сборной США в","answer":"комбинированной эстафете 4 по 100 метров и в эстафете 4 по 200 метров вольным стилем. В эстафете 4 по 100 метров вольным стилем американки при участии Мисси выиграли бронзу. На дистанции 100 метров на спине в финале Франклин установила рекорд Америки (58,33), а на дистанции 200 метров на спине победила с новым мировым рекордом (2.04,06). Выступала Франклин в Лондоне и на дистанциях 100 и 200 метров вольным стильным: на первой из них она стала пятой (0,20 сек до третьего места), а на 200-метровке — четвёртой (лишь 0,01 сек отставания от третьего места)."},{"question":"පහත නාම පදයට අදාළ පුරුෂ ලිංග නාම පාදක කුමක්ද? භාර්යාව ","answer":"ස්වාමියා"},{"question":"ਡਾਕਟਰ ਨੇ ਮਰੀਜ਼ ਦੀ ਬੀਮਾਰੀ ਦਾ ਨਿਰੀਖਣ ਕੀਤਾ। | ਇਸ ਦਾ ਕਾਰਨ ਕੀ ਸੀ? ਚੋਣ 1 : ਉਸਨੇ ਮਰੀਜ਼ ਦੇ ਲੱਛਣਾਂ ਦੀ ਪਛਾਣ ਕੀਤੀ। ਚੋਣ 2 : ਉਸਨੇ ਮਰੀਜ਼ ਨੂੰ ਗੋਲੀਆਂ ਲਿਖ ਕੇ ਦਿੱਤੀਆਂ। ","answer":"ਚੋਣ 1 : ਉਸਨੇ ਮਰੀਜ਼ ਦੇ ਲੱਛਣਾਂ ਦੀ ਪਛਾਣ ਕੀਤੀ।"},{"question":"about తేలుకుట్ల.Snippet: తేలుకుట్ల, గుంటూరు జిల్లా, గురజాల మండలానికి చెందిన గ్రామము. ఇది మండల కేంద్రమైన గురజాల నుండి 8 కి. మీ. దూరం లోను, సమీప పట్టణమైన మాచర్ల నుండి 41 కి. మీ. దూరంలోనూ ఉంది. 2011 భారత జనగణన గణాంకాల ప్రకారం ఈ గ్రామం 771 ఇళ్లతో, 3048 జనాభాతో 981 హెక్టార్లలో విస్తరించి ఉంది. గ్రామంలో మగవారి సంఖ్య 1516, ఆడవారి సంఖ్య 1532. షెడ్యూల్డ్ కులాల సంఖ్య 159 కాగా షెడ్యూల్డ్ తెగల సంఖ్య 336. గ్రామం యొక్క జనగణన లొకేషన్ కోడ్ 589841[1].పిన్ కోడ్: 522415What's the answer?","answer":"981 హెక్టార్ల"},{"question":"السؤال: ما هي أطول سورة في القرآن الكريم ؟","answer":"الإجابة: سورة البقرة"},{"question":"Qual técnico português comandava o time do Flamengo na final do Mundial Interclubes em 2019, contra a equipe inglesa do Liverpool?","answer":"O técnico foi o Jorge Jesus."},{"question":"බුදු දහමේ එන  විකාර රූප තුන ගැන විස්තර කරන්න.","answer":"ලහුතා රූපය, මුදුතා රූපය, කම්මඤ්ඤතා රූපය යන මේ තුන විකාර රූපයෝ ය. ඔවුහු සෑම කල්හි ම ඔවුනොවුන් වෙන් නොවී එක ම රූප කලාපයකට එකට බැඳී උපදින්නෝ ය. ඔවුනොවුන් ගෙන් වෙන් කළ නො හෙන සේ එකට ම බැඳී උපදනා ඒ රූපයන්ගේ ලක්ෂණ වෙන් වෙන් වශයෙන් තේරුම් ගත හැකි වන්නේ වරින් වර ශරීරයේ ඇතිවන ලහුතාදීන් ගේ විරුද්ධ වූ ස්වභාවයන් අනුව සිතීමෙනි. එබැවින් ඒවායේ ලක්ෂණ විරුද්ධ ස්වභාවයන්ගේ අනුසාරයෙන් දක්වනු ලැබේ."},{"question":"متى أنشئ أول مسجد في فرنسا ؟","answer":"1926"},{"question":"请回答以下问题：问题：什么是神经网络？","answer":"答案：神经网络是一种由人工神经元构成的计算系统，模拟人脑的神经网络结构，用于进行模式识别和机器学习任务。"},{"question":"以下这句的问题:\\"根据Urbain Le Verrier的预测,1846年9月23日至24日的晚上,在柏林天文台,天文学家约翰·戈特弗里德·加勒 (辅助海因里希·路易·德·阿雷斯特) 通过望远镜观察证实了一个主要行星的存在,并根据Le Verrier的计算进行了工作\\"? 主题是海王星的发现.","answer":"\\"谁发现了星球海王星?\\""},{"question":"Which 1995 movie—The Net or 28 Days, or Wrestling Ernest Hemingway—starred Sandra Bullock as Angela Bennett?","answer":"Sandra Bullock plays the role of Angela Bennett in the 1995 film \\"The Net\\". In the movie, a systems analyst who doesn't have many personal friends finds out that her house has been cleared out and all of her personal data have been erased. She needs to figure out how to take back who she is."},{"question":"బాల్య వివాహాలు మీద వ్యాసం రాయండి.","answer":"బాల్యవివాహాలు అంటే చిన్నతనంలోనే పెళ్ళిళ్లు చేయడం. ఒకప్పుడు ఆటలాడుకొనే వయస్సులోనే పెళ్ళిళ్ళు చేసేవారు. బ్రిటిష్ ప్రభుత్వం శారదా చట్టం పెట్టి చిన్నతనంలో పెళ్ళి చేయరాదని నిషేధించింది.బాల్యవివాహాలు మంచివి కావు. చిన్నతనంలో భార్యాభర్తలు ఒకరినొకరు అర్థం చేసుకోలేరు. తల్లిదండ్రుల, అత్తమామల పెత్తనం సాగుతుంది. దానితో చిక్కులు వస్తాయి. 13, 14 ఏళ్ళ వయస్సులోనే వారికి సంతానం కలుగుతుంది. అందువల్ల ఆడువారికి ఆరోగ్యం పాడవుతుంది.కాబట్టి ప్రభుత్వము ఇప్పుడు 18 ఏళ్ళు నిండిన యువతీయువకులకే పెళ్ళిళ్ళు చేయాలని నియమం పెట్టింది. భార్యాభర్తలు ఇద్దరూ పెద్దవారైతే వారు ఒకరినొకరు ప్రేమగా మంచిగా చూసుకుంటారు. వారు వారికి పుట్టిన పిల్లలను చక్కగా పెంచుతారు. వారి పిల్లలు బలంగా, ఆరోగ్యంగా పెరుగుతారు. వారి ఆరోగ్యం కూడా బాగుంటుంది.కాబట్టి బాల్య వివాహాలను అరికట్టాలి. వయస్సు వచ్చిన పిల్లలకే పెళ్ళిళ్లు చేయాలి. అప్పుడు వారి జీవితాలు ఆనందంగా హాయిగా సాగుతాయి."},{"question":"Vua nào ở ngôi lâu nhất dưới triều Nguyễn?a. Gia Longb. Tự Đứcc. Minh Mạngd. Thiệu Trị","answer":"b. Tự ĐứcVua Tự Đức tên thật là Nguyễn Phúc Hồng Nhậm, trị vì 36 năm, từ 1847 đến 1883. Ông được đánh giá là một vị vua tốt, chăm chỉ xem xét việc triều chính nhưng không quyết đoán.Dưới thời Tự Đức, quân Pháp lần đầu nổ súng xâm lược Việt Nam vào năm 1858. Để chủ quyền đất nước dần rơi vào tay người Pháp, hoàng đế Tự Đức ngậm ngùi là học chưa thành, chí chưa thỏa, danh hão chưa đủ để trừ tội thực, sức yếu chưa đủ để làm việc nặng.Không có con nối dõi nên khi ông băng hà, nhà Nguyễn trải qua thời kỳ đen tối 4 tháng thay 3 vua.Sau Tự Đức, Minh Mạng là vị vua ở ngôi lâu thứ hai (1820-1841). Ông có nhiều cải cách quan trọng, như bỏ dinh, trấn, lập các tỉnh trong cả nước (31 tỉnh), định lại quan chế, lương bổng của quan lại thời này, khuyến khích dân khai hoang lập ấp...Lãnh thổ Việt Nam dưới thời vua Minh Mạng được mở rộng nhất trong lịch sử và trở thành nước hùng mạnh. Năm 1838, ông đổi tên nước thành Đại Nam.Lo ngại tranh chấp trong hoàng tộc, vua Minh Mạng nghĩ ra phép đặt tên đôi cho dòng đế (vua) và dòng thân (anh em). Ông làm 11 bài thơ, một bài đặt là Đế hệ thi còn 10 bài kia đặt là Phiên hệ thi tặng cho 10 thân vương khác (4 hoàng tử đã qua đời trước khi vua lên ngôi). Ý nghĩa sâu sắc của cả 11 bài thơ này là phân chia các hoàng tử con của vua Gia Long làm hai hệ: đế hệ và phiên hệ. Đế hệ là dòng vua, là người có quyền thừa kế ngai vàng của tổ nghiệp. Còn phiên hệ là dòng thân, là bờ rào bao bọc xung quanh, bảo vệ cho ngai vàng ấy vững bền.Vua Minh Mạng có tổng cộng 142 người con, gồm 74 hoàng tử và 68 công chúa."},{"question":"azavao ny hoe rako-pelana","answer":"ny hoe rako-pelana dia midika hoe rakotra felana na feno felana"},{"question":"කෝපි වල ඉතිහාසය කුමක්ද?","answer":"කෝපි වල ඉතිහාසය නූතන ඉතියෝපියාවේ සියවස් ගණනාවක් පැරණි මුඛ සම්ප්‍රදාය දක්වා දිව යයි. කෙසේ වෙතත්, කෝපි ප්‍රථම වරට වගා කළ ස්ථානය හෝ 15 වන සියවසට පෙර එහි පරිභෝජනය පිළිබඳ සෘජු සාක්ෂි සොයාගෙන නොමැත. යේමනයේ සූෆි ආරාම යාච්ඤාවලදී අවධානය යොමු කිරීමට උපකාරයක් ලෙස කෝපි භාවිතා කරන ලදී. කෝපි පසුව 16 වැනි සියවසේ මුල් භාගයේදී ලෙවන්ට් සහ පර්සියාවට ව්‍යාප්ත විය. එය ඔටෝමාන් සහ මාම්ලුක් සමාජයේ හලාල් ද යන්න පිළිබඳව යම් මතභේදයක් ඇති විය. වාණිජ මධ්‍යධරණී වෙළඳ මාර්ග හරහා කෝපි 16 වන සියවසේ දෙවන භාගයේදී ඉතාලියට පැමිණි අතර මධ්‍යම සහ නැගෙනහිර යුරෝපීයයන් ඔටෝමන්වරුන්ගෙන් කෝපි ගැන ඉගෙන ගත්හ. 17 වන ශතවර්ෂයේ මැද භාගය වන විට එය ඉන්දියාව සහ නැගෙනහිර ඉන්දීය කොදෙව් වෙත ළඟා විය. කෝපි හවුස් බටහිර යුරෝපයේ 17 වන සියවසේ අගභාගයේදී, විශේෂයෙන් එංගලන්තයේ සහ ජර්මනියේ ස්ථාපිත වනු ඇත. නව ලෝකයේ මුල්ම කෝපි වගාව වූයේ 1720 දී ගේබ්‍රියෙල් ඩි ක්ලියු විසින් මාර්ටිනික් වෙත කෝපි පැළ ගෙන ආ අවස්ථාවේදීය. මෙම බෝංචි පසුකාලීනව කෝපි ගස් 18,680 ක් පැළ වූ අතර එමඟින් එය අනෙකුත් කැරිබියානු දූපත් වන Saint-Domingue වෙත සහ මෙක්සිකෝව දක්වා ව්‍යාප්ත විය. 1788 වන විට, Saint-Domingue ලෝකයේ කෝපිවලින් අඩක් සැපයීය. 1852 වන විට, ගෝලීය වශයෙන්, බ්‍රසීලය විශාලතම කෝපි නිෂ්පාදකයා බවට පත් වූ අතර එතැන් සිට එම තත්ත්වය දරයි. 1950 සිට කාලපරිච්ඡේදය තුළ තවත් ප්‍රධාන නිෂ්පාදකයින් කිහිප දෙනෙකු, විශේෂයෙන් කොලොම්බියාව, අයිවරි කෝස්ට්, ඉතියෝපියාව සහ වියට්නාමය බිහිවීම හේතුවෙන් ක්‍රීඩා පිටිය පුළුල් විය. දෙවැන්න කොලොම්බියාව අභිබවා ගොස් 1999 දී දෙවන විශාලතම නිෂ්පාදකයා බවට පත් විය. නවීන නිෂ්පාදන ශිල්පීය ක්‍රම සහ කෝපි විශාල වශයෙන් නිෂ්පාදනය කිරීම අද එය ගෘහ භාණ්ඩයක් බවට පත් කර ඇත."},{"question":"تفاوت سنتور قدیم و فعلی چیست ؟","answer":"ساز سنتور پیشتر با ۱۲ وتر سیم بم و ۱۲ وتر سیم زیر ساخته می‌شد و سنتور ۱۲ خرکی نامیده می‌شد. امروزه سنتور ۱۰ خرک و سنتور ۱۱ خرک نیز ساخته می‌شود. سنتور ۹ خرک رایج‌ترین گونه سنتور است که پر استفاده‌ترین نوع آن سنتور «سُل کوک» است و نت‌های ردیف بر اساس آن نوشته شده‌اند. در سنتور ۹ خرک، چنانچه بر اساس راست کوک تنظیم شود، به ترتیب سیم‌ها از پایین بر مبنای می-فا-سل کوک می‌شوند و برای اجرای گروهی و ارکستر باره است."},{"question":"請回答這個問題：地球上最古老的建築材料是什麼？","answer":"答案：石頭"},{"question":"මම මැජික් උපක්‍රමවලට දක්ෂ වන්නේ කෙසේද?","answer":"පැය ගණන් පුහුණුවීම් තුළින් ඔබට මැජික්වල දක්ෂතා ලබා ගත හැකිය. කාඩ්පත් තට්ටුවක් ලබා ගැනීම සහ ඒවා අල්ලාගෙන සමෘද්ධිමත් වන ආකාරය ඉගෙන ගැනීම ආරම්භ කිරීමට හොඳ ක්‍රමයකි, මන්ද මැජික් අත්වල මාංශ පේශි මතකය හරහා ගොඩනගා ඇති අතිශය දක්ෂතාවයක් ගනී. මෙය හොඳ වීමට පැය ගණනක් පුනරාවර්තනය වේ. ඔබ ඉන්ද්‍රජාලයට කොතරම් දක්ෂද යන්න බලපාන වෙනත් සාධක වන්නේ ඒ සඳහා ඔබේ උනන්දුවයි. ඔබ එයට උනන්දුවක් නොදක්වන්නේ නම්, ඔබට මැජික් කිරීමට දක්ෂ නොවනු ඇත. ඔබට සමාජ ශාලාවකට සම්බන්ධ වී ඒ ගැන උනන්දුවක් දක්වන වෙනත් පුද්ගලයින් සමඟ මැජික් උපක්‍රම පුහුණු කළ හැකිය. ඇමරිකන් ඉන්ද්‍රජාලිකයන්ගේ සංගමය (SAM) සම්බන්ධ වීමට හොඳම සංවිධානයකි."},{"question":"ప్రశ్న  : వైద్య మరియు లోహ విజ్ఞానశాస్త్ర రంగాలలో గుప్తుల కాలంలో సాధించిన విజయాలేవి?","answer":"వైద్యశాస్త్రం :చరకుడు మరియు సుశ్రుతుడు గుప్తుల కాలంలో గొప్ప వైద్య పరిజ్ఞానం గల నిపుణులు. గాయపడిన ముక్కులకు ప్లాస్టిక్ సర్జరీ చేసిన మొట్టమొదటి భారతీయ శస్త్రచికిత్స నిపుణుడు సుశ్రుతుడు. గుప్తుల కాలంలోని వైద్యులు విరిగిపోయిన ఎముకలను సరిచేసి ఆపరేషన్లు కూడా చేసేవారు. ఔషధంతో కూడిన మొక్కలను వ్యాధులను నయం చేయడంలో ఉపయోగించేవారు. వ్యాధి కంటే వ్యాధికి గల మూల కారణాన్ని నిర్మూలించాలని వైద్యులు భావించేవారు.లోహ విజ్ఞాన శాస్త్రం :గుప్తుల కాలంలో శాస్త్రవేత్తలు లోహశాస్త్ర పరిజ్ఞానంలో నిపుణులు. ఇనుము మరియు ఉక్కుతో ఆయుధాలు తయారు చేసేవారు. ఆధునిక బంగారు నాణేలను పోలి ఉండే వాటిని కూడా వీరి కాలంలో ముద్రించుట జరిగినది."},{"question":"Kazeem ti dero ile-ẹjọ o, ọrẹ rẹ lo pa to fẹẹ fi ṣoogun owo ni Kwara","answer":"Ile-ẹjọ Magistreeti kan niluu Ilọrin, ti fi igbẹjọ Kazeem ati awọn mẹta miiran ti wọn jọ gbimọ-pọ pa ọrẹ rẹ, Bukọla Ojo, ni ilu Patigi, nijọba ibilẹ Patigi, nipinlẹ Kwara, si ọjọ kẹjọ, oṣu keje, ọdun yii, to si ni ki wọn wa ni ahamọ titi di ọjọ igbẹjọ.Iroyin to tẹ ALAROYE lọwọ ni pe, Kazeem to jẹ ọrẹ timọtimọ si Bukọla Ojo, lo pinnu lati fi ọrẹ rẹ ṣe oogun owo, to si gbimọ-pọ pẹlu awọn mẹta miiran ki iṣẹ naa le rọrun fun un lati ṣe. Igbeyawo Ojo ti n sun ile diẹdiẹ, eyi lo mu ki wọn tan an lọ sinu igbo pe ko waa wo maaluu ti awọn ba ra fun ayẹyẹ igbeyawo rẹ to n bọ lọna, ti wọn si ṣeku pa a. Ọkan ninu awọn ọrẹ yii, Madu Jeremiah, lo ṣeto bi wọn ṣe ri ibọn ti wọn fi pa ọkunrin ọhun.Lẹyin ti wọn pa a tan ni wọn ge ori rẹ, ati apa mejeeji, ti Kazeem si ko o lọ sọdọ Muhammad Chatta ti yoo ba a fi ṣe oogun owo. Mohammed tun gbe foonu oloogbe fun Jimoh Abdullateef, wọn fi pe mọlẹbi rẹ, wọn si n beere fun milionu mejila owo itusilẹ ẹni ti wọn ti seku pa, ki ọwọ palaba wọn too ṣegi.Agbefọba, Moshood Adebayọ, waa rọ Magistreeti Adeniyi lati fi awọn afurasi naa si ahamọ titi di ọjọ igbẹjọ. Adeniyi ti ni ki awọn mẹrẹẹrin maa lọọ gbatẹgun lọgba ẹwọn titi di ọjọ igbẹjọ mi-in."},{"question":"O ma ṣe o, ayẹyẹ ọjọọbi Sunny Ade ku ọla, iyawo rẹ ku lojiji","answer":"Bi ayẹyẹ ọjọọbi ọdun karundinlọgọrin ti ilu-mọ-ọn-ka agba ọjẹ onkọrin juju nni, Ọmọọba Sunday Iṣọla Adeniyi Adegẹye tawọn eeyan mọ si King Sunny Ade, iba ṣe dun to, o ku ọjọ kan ki ariya naa waye ni iyawo rẹ, Ọnarebu Risikat Adejọkẹ Adegẹye, ku lojiji.Afẹmọju ọjọ Iṣẹgun, Tusidee, ọjọ kọkanlegun, oṣu kẹsan-an yii, niṣẹlẹ naa waye ni ile obinrin naa to wa lagbegbe Amuwo-Ọdọfin, nipinlẹ Eko.Ninu atẹjade kan to tẹ ALAROYE lọwọ, Akọwe kansu ijọba ibilẹ Amuwo Ọdọfin, Ẹnjinnia Ṣeyi Ipinlaye, sọ pe aisan ranpẹ kan ti n ba obinrin naa finra ṣaaju iku rẹ yii.Oloogbe Adegẹye ti figba kan jẹ amofin to ṣoju agbegbe Amuwo-Ọdọfin nileegbimọ aṣofin Eko, oun si ni ondije-dupo si ileegbimọ aṣoju-sofin apapọ l’Abuja.Ẹnjinnia Ipinlaye sọ pe “ibanujẹ nla ni iku Mama Gẹye, gẹgẹ bawọn ololufẹ rẹ ṣe maa n pe e, jẹ fun awọn eeyan Amuwo-Ọdọfin ati ipinlẹ Eko. A ba Ọba orin Juju, King Sunny Ade, atawọn mọlẹbi Adegẹye kẹdun gidigidi. A ṣadura ki Ọlọrun tẹ oloogbe safẹfẹ rere.Ọjọruu, Wẹsidee, ọjọ kejilelogun, oṣu kẹsan-an, ni ayẹyẹ ọjọọbi Sunny Ade maa n waye lọdọọdun."},{"question":"請回答這個問題：地球上最古老的文字是哪一種？","answer":"答案：古埃及的象形文字"},{"question":"Su’aal: Sheeg Imisa Kiilo Meter (KM) Ayey Isu Jiraan Washinton Iyo New York?","answer":"Jawaab: Waxay Isku Jiraan 6000-Km."},{"question":"ما هو السؤال: \\"المسلسل مبني على الأنثروبولوجيا الجنائية وعلم الآثار الجنائية ، مع تركيز كل حلقة على ملف قضية مكتب التحقيقات الفيدرالي المتعلق بالغموض وراء البقايا البشرية التي جلبها عميل مكتب التحقيقات الفيدرالي الخاص سيللي بوث (ديفيد بورياناز) إلى عالم الأنثروبولوجيا الجنائية الدكتورة تمبرانس \\"بونز\\" برينان (إيميلي ديشانيل) \\"؟ الموضوع هو بونز(المسلسل التلفزيوني).","answer":"السؤال هو: \\"أحداث مسلسل بونز بتدور عن أيه؟\\""},{"question":"Напиши продовження тексту:  Група B стала найбільш сенсаційною групою на турнірі. Майбутні олімпійські чемпіони — збірна Чехословаччини, у складі якоої були присутні шість бронзових призерів Євро-1980, спромоглися перемогти лише в одному матчі, два інших звівши у нічию. ","answer":"Щоправда навіть цей рахунок дозволив збірній вийти у плей-оф з першого місця. А збірна Нігерії, яка також напередодні Олімпіади стала переможцем Кубку африканських націй 1980, взагалі зайняла останнє місце групи, здобувши лише одне очко."},{"question":"من هو أول من حيَّا النبي ﷺ بتحية الإسلام؟","answer":"ج : الصحابي الجليل أبو ذر الغفاري رض الله عنه"},{"question":"Tôi thích ăn bún, phở vào buổi sáng vì dễ tiêu hóa, chồng tôi lại thích ăn đồ khô như xôi, bánh mì cho chắc dạ, no lâu. Vậy ăn đồ nước hay đồ khô tốt hơn?","answer":"Mỗi người có lựa chọn cho bữa sáng khác nhau, tùy sở thích, cân nặng, tuổi tác, khả năng chi trả. Không có công thức ăn uống nào cho tất cả mọi người, vì thế không thể so sánh món nước hay khô tốt hơn. Bản chất bữa sáng là cung cấp năng lượng cho cơ thể, món ăn nào cung cấp calo hợp lý, cân đối đều rất tốt.Theo đó, món ăn cung cấp khoảng 300-500 kcal là hợp lý. Mọi người nên thay đổi thực đơn, tránh ăn một món liên tục, gây nhàm chán.Với trẻ nhỏ, người cao tuổi, nên ăn sáng bằng các thực phẩm mềm, dễ tiêu hóa. Còn với người mắc bệnh nền như tiểu đường, béo phì, ung thư, cần có chế độ cụ thể, phù hợp.Lưu ý, nhiều người có thói quen ăn sáng bằng bún, phở, xôi, bánh mì mà thiếu rau xanh, vì vậy cần cân nhắc đưa rau vào các món ăn của mình để đa dạng dinh dưỡng, đủ 4 nhóm chất, gồm: bột đường, protein, chất béo, vitamin và khoáng chất.Một gợi ý bạn có thể tham khảo cho bữa sáng là món bánh mì kẹp trứng, hoặc bánh mì lát kết hợp trứng ốp. Nhóm tinh bột từ bánh mì kết hợp cùng protein, chất béo trong trứng và dầu rán, vitamin và khoáng chất từ các loại rau gia vị như đu đủ, cà chua, dưa chuột, rau mùi, giúp bữa sáng đầy đủ, đa dạng và cân bằng."},{"question":"Oviana no nankalazaina ny  andro maneran-tany ho an’ny tazomoka na « paludisme » ho an’ny taona 2023 ity?","answer":"Nankalaizaina ny 15 Mey ny andro maneran-tany ho an’ny tazomoka na « paludisme » ho an’ny taona 2023 ity."},{"question":"Fizaran-taona inona no manaraka avy hatrany ny fahavaratra?","answer":"Ny fararano dia manaraka avy hatrany ny fahavaratra araka ny filaharan'ny fizaran-taona."},{"question":"Save translationځمکه یو ګردي څیز ګڼل کیږي. د ځمکې په اړه کوم اختیار غلط ګڼل کیږي.1. ځمکه اکثره اوبه دي.2. ځمکه اکثره ګرده ده.3. ځمکه چپه ده.","answer":"غلط انتخاب دا دی - 3. ځمکه چپه ده"},{"question":"次の段落を完成させなさい： 鹿児島県姶良市では、2匹のくもが戦う「くも合戦」を行っています。400年以上続いていて、国が大切にしている文化です。","answer":"新型コロナウイルスの問題で「くも合戦」はしばらくありませんでした。18日に久しぶりに行うと、100人ぐらいがくもを持って集まりました。 長さ60cmの細い棒の上で、コガネグモというくもの雌2匹が戦います。棒から落としたり、相手に糸を巻いたりしたくもが勝ちます。参加した人たちは、声を出して応援したり、ビデオを撮ったりしていました。 9歳の男の子は「えさをあげて大事にくもを育てました。負けて残念でしたが、来年も出たいです」と話していました。20年以上参加しているお年寄りは「またくも合戦がにぎやかにできて、うれしいです。次は孫と一緒に参加したいです」と話していました。"},{"question":"Ci ban kembaar la réwum Géorgie nékk","answer":"Réwum Géorgie mu ngi nékk ci kembaar bi ñuy wakh Asie"},{"question":"Which operations are necessary to transform \\" tHe Cat’S mEOw :)\\" into \\"The Cat’s Meow\\" using Excel?MIDPROPERTRIMRIGHTUPPER","answer":"To transform the string \\" tHe Cat’S mEOw :)\\" into \\"The Cat’s Meow,\\" you can use the following operations:TRIM: This operation will remove leading and trailing spaces from the original string.Result after TRIM: \\"tHe Cat’S mEOw :)\\"PROPER: This operation will capitalize the first letter of each word and make the rest of the letters lowercase.Result after PROPER: \\"The Cat’S Meow :)\\"MID: This operation will extract a portion of the string, excluding the smiley face \\":)\\".Result after MID: \\"The Cat’S Meow\\"So, by applying these operations in the specified order (TRIM, PROPER, MID), you can transform the original string into \\"The Cat’s Meow.\\""},{"question":"Tại sao Mặt trời thường có màu vàng, hoàng hôn hay chiều tà có màu cam, đỏ?","answer":"Mặt Trời phát ra ánh sáng trắng (là tập hợp vô số ánh sáng đơn sắc có màu biến thiên từ đỏ -> tím), như vậy Mặt trời có màu trắng. Nhưng nếu quan sát trên Trái đất, chúng ta thường nhìn thấy Mặt trời có màu vàng vì:Trên Trái đất, một vài bước sóng ngắn của ánh sáng Mặt trời (lam, chàm, tím) đã bị các phân tử khí tán xạ mạnh nên bị loại bỏ ra khỏi chùm ánh sáng chiếu trực tiếp từ Mặt trời tới mắt người quan sát.Do đó, các màu còn lại: Đỏ, cam, vàng, lục cùng nhau xuất hiện. Hơn nữa, hai trong ba màu nhạy cảm đối với mắt là đỏ và lục khi trộn với nhau sẽ ra màu vàng. Giữa trưa hè, Mặt trời thường có màu vàng trắng và chuyển dần thành vàng cam khi Mặt trời xuống thấp hơn.Khi Mặt trời bắt đầu lặn hoặc lúc mới mọc, ánh sáng cần phải đi một đoạn đường dài hơn qua không khí để đến được vị trí mà bạn nhìn thấy. Do ánh sáng có bước sóng càng ngắn thì càng bị không khí tán xạ mạnh nên lúc đó sẽ có càng nhiều ánh sáng bị tán xạ hơn, chỉ những ánh sáng có bước sóng dài nhất như đỏ, cam... mới có thể xuyên qua lớp không khí dày để tới vị trí của bạn. Lúc này, Mặt trời cũng tối hơn và màu sắc của Mặt trời cũng chuyển từ màu vàng lúc ban ngày sang màu cam và sau đó đến màu đỏ."},{"question":"Indro misy toe-javatra: \\"Paris, renivohitra mahafinaritra an'i Frantsa, dia fonenan'ny iray amin'ireo rafitra malaza indrindra eran-tany, ny Tour Eiffel. Ity tilikambo vy vita amin'ny vy ity dia miakatra mijoalajoala any amin'ny lanitra Parisiana, manolotra fomba fijery manaitra ny Tanànan'ny Fahazavana avy amin'ny sehatra fijerena azy.\\" Raha ohatra ka \\"Paris\\" no valiny dia inona no mety fanontaniana napetraka?","answer":"Aiza no misy ny Tour Eiffel?"},{"question":"\\"Жеңишбек\\" поэмасы туурасындагы факты...","answer":"\\"Жеңишбекти\\" окуп отурсаң эрте жазда көл жээгиндеги атыр жытка мас болгондон да аша кетесиң… \\"Жеңишбектей\\" таттуу-рахаттуу аба жок, болсо да аз.Ошентип, \\"Жеңишбекти\\" экранга чырагым\\" келди. Бул багытта тажрыйбам жок болсо да бел байладым, ким билет эмне болорун… Эгер, чебердин колуна түшсө укмуш эле болор эле!\\", — деп жазган экен тээ 1955-жылдары."},{"question":"TAMBAYA: Yaya za a rubuta ɗari biyu da hamsin da tara a matsayin lamba?","answer":"Amsa: 259"},{"question":"في أي عهد من عهود الخلفاء الراشدين كانتمعركة القادسية ؟","answer":"- في عهد سيدنا عمر بن الخطاب"},{"question":"Inona ny volana aorinan'ny aogositra?","answer":"Septambra ny volana aorinan'ny aogositra"},{"question":"Cual es el tema principal de esta pregunta: ¿Cuál estado es el 2do más pequeño por área y 6to más pequeño por población?. ","answer":"El tema principal de esta pregunta es comparar la población de un área y de otra. "},{"question":"Quel élément porte le nom du mot grec signifiant vert ?","answer":"L'élément « chlore » doit son nom au mot grec « khloros », qui signifie vert. Le nom est dérivé de la couleur verdâtre du chlore gazeux, observée lors de sa première isolation et étude. Le chlore est un élément non métallique hautement réactif qui est essentiel à divers processus biologiques et industriels, notamment son utilisation comme désinfectant et dans la production de plastiques et d'autres produits chimiques."},{"question":"Joxeel péeteg waat yi ci kàddu gii: Te da nga léen xàm ci séen màndarga; da nga léen man a xàm ìtam ci séen galéen u waxìin.","answer":"Waat yi nekk ci kàddu gii di \\"Te da nga léen xàm ci séen màndarga; da nga léen man a xàm ìtam ci séen galéen u waxìin.\\" ak séen i péete ñoo di:Te: CCONJda: AUXnga: PRONléen: PRONxàm: VERBci: ADPséen: PRONmàndarga: NOUN;: PUNCTda: AUXnga: PRONléen: PRONman: VERBa: PARTxàm: VERBìtam: ADVci: ADPséen: PRONgaléen: NOUNu: ADPwaxìin: NOUN.: PUNCT"},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਸਲੋਕ ਮਃ ੧ ॥ਕੁਬੁਧਿ ਡੂਮਣੀ ਕੁਦਇਆ ਕਸਾਇਣਿ ਪਰ ਨਿੰਦਾ ਘਟ ਚੂਹੜੀ ਮੁਠੀ ਕ੍ਰੋਧਿ ਚੰਡਾਲਿ ॥ਕਾਰੀ ਕਢੀ ਕਿਆ ਥੀਐ ਜਾਂ ਚਾਰੇ ਬੈਠੀਆ ਨਾਲਿ ॥ਸਚੁ ਸੰਜਮੁ ਕਰਣੀ ਕਾਰਾਂ ਨਾਵਣੁ ਨਾਉ ਜਪੇਹੀ ॥ਨਾਨਕ ਅਗੈ ਊਤਮ ਸੇਈ ਜਿ ਪਾਪਾਂ ਪੰਦਿ ਨ ਦੇਹੀ ॥੧॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 91 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਨਾਨਕ ਦੇਵ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਬਾਣੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਹਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"ਭੈੜੀ ਮਤ (ਮਨੁੱਖ ਦੇ ਅੰਦਰ ਦੀ) ਮਿਰਾਸਣ ਹੈ, ਬੇ-ਤਰਸੀ ਕਸਾਇਣ ਹੈ, ਪਰਾਈ ਨਿੰਦਿਆ ਅੰਦਰ ਦੀ ਚੂਹੜੀ ਹੈ, ਤੇ ਕ੍ਰੋਧ ਚੰਡਾਲਣੀ (ਹੈ ਜਿਸ) ਨੇ (ਜੀਵ ਦੇ ਸ਼ਾਂਤ ਸੁਭਾਉ ਨੂੰ) ਠੱਗ ਰੱਖਿਆ ਹੈ  ਜੇ ਇਹ ਚਾਰੇ ਅੰਦਰ ਹੀ ਬੈਠੀਆਂ ਹੋਣ, ਤਾਂ (ਬਾਹਰ ਚੌਂਕਾ ਸੁੱਚਾ ਰੱਖਣ ਲਈ) ਲਕੀਰਾਂ ਕੱਢਣ ਦਾ ਕੀਹ ਲਾਭ ? ਜੋ ਮਨੁੱਖ ‘ਸੱਚ’ ਨੂੰ (ਚੌਂਕਾ ਸੁੱਚਾ ਕਰਨ ਦੀ) ਜੁਗਤਿ ਬਣਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ, ਉੱਚੇ ਆਚਰਨ ਨੂੰ (ਚੌਂਕੇ ਦੀਆਂ) ਲਕੀਰਾਂ ਬਣਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ, ਜੋ ਨਾਮ ਜਪਦੇ ਹਨ ਤੇ ਇਸ ਨੂੰ (ਤੀਰਥ) ਇਸ਼ਨਾਨ ਸਮਝਦੇ ਹਨਹੇ ਨਾਨਕ ! ਜੋ ਹੋਰਨਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਭੀ ਪਾਪਾਂ ਵਾਲੀ ਸਿੱਖਿਆ ਨਹੀਂ ਦੇਂਦੇ, ਉਹ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੀ ਹਜ਼ੂਰੀ ਵਿਚ ਚੰਗੇ ਗਿਣੇ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ ।੧।\\""},{"question":"සිසිල් යන වචනයට අදහසක් ගෙන දෙන වචනය ලියා  දක්වන්න.","answer":"සිසිල් යන්නට විරුද්ධ අර්ථයක් ඇති පදය උණුසුම් වේ. "},{"question":"ጥያቄ፦ በላሊበላ የጌታ ልደት ቀን በቤተ ማርያም የሚቀርበው ልዩ ዝማሬ ምን ይባላል?\\t","answer":"መልስ፦ ቤዛ ኩሉ"},{"question":"س231- اشمن سنه دارت أول بطولة لكرة القدم في العالم؟","answer":"ج231- عام 1930"},{"question":"Jawab pananya ieu: Batu naon nu dihasilkeun ku déposisi jeung sémentasi? a. marmer jeung batu metamorf. b. batu keusik jeung batu sédimén.c. granit jeung batu ignéus intrusif.d. batu apung jeung batu ignéus extrusif.","answer":"Batu nu dihasilkeun ku déposisi jeung sémentasi nyaéta batu keusik jeung batu sédimén (b)."},{"question":"Fariparito ny atao hoe fanahy tahotra","answer":"Azo lazaina fa voaloham-pahendrena ny fananana tahotra.”Mamy ny miaina”; “Raha maty aho , matesa rahavana ary raha maty rahavana, matesa ny omby.”Heverina ho zava-dehibe ny aina ka arovana amin’ny alalan’ny  fitadiavana sakafo, fiarovan-tena, fanarahan-dalàna. Atao ireo satria atahorana ho faty ny aina."},{"question":"Awọn ọdọ ṣewọde ni Kutọ, wọn ni ki Buhari maa lọ","answer":"Iwọde ti wọn ti n kede rẹ pe yoo waye kaakiri awọn ipinlẹ lorilẹ-ede yii kuku waye, o kan jẹ pe ọna ọtọ ni kaluku wọn gbe e gba ni. Ni Kutọ, l’Abẹokuta, laaarọ ọjọ kejila, oṣu kẹfa, ọdun yii, bawọn eeyan kan ṣe lọọ tẹti sọrọ Gomina Dapọ Abiọdun ni papa iṣere MKO Abiọla, bẹẹ lawọn kan naa n fẹhonu han ni Kutọ kan naa, ti wọn ni afi ki Aarẹ Buhari maa ba tiẹ lọ.Akọle oriṣiiriṣii lawọn ọdọ to n ṣewọde naa gbe dani, eyi to hande ni ju nibẹ ni ti ‘Buhari must go’ iyẹn ni pe dandan ni ki Buhari lọ.Orin oriṣiiriṣii lawọn oluwọde naa n kọ ti wọn fi n sọ pe Naijiria ti bajẹ, wọn ni mẹkunnu ko le da gaari ra, wọn ko rowo ra ounjẹ sinu ara wọn.Bakan naa ni wọn sọ pe ijọba amunisin to  kan n ti awọn eeyan kan mọle fọdun pipẹ ni Buhari n ṣe, wọn ni ki Aarẹ tu gbogbo awọn to ja fun ẹtọ ọmọniyan ti wọn ko satimọle silẹ, ki wọn jẹ ki wọn maa lọ sile wọn.Awọn oluwọde yii ko fajagbọn, bẹẹ ni wọn ko ṣe jagidijagan, orin ti wọn n kọ pẹlu awọn akọle ti wọn gbe dani ni wọn lo bii nnkan ijijagbara."},{"question":"الجملة غير المشكلة: \\"صلون إليه الأخبار وأحوال السوقة فصل ومن الشروط اللوازم للمحتسب أن يكون عفيفا عن أموال الناس متورعا عن قبول الهدية من المتعيشين وأرباب الصناعات فإن ذلك رشوة وقد قال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم أ لعن الله الراشي والمرتشي ولأن التعفف عن ذلك أصون لعرضه وأقوم لهيبته ويلزم المحتسب غلمانه\\"الجملة المشكلة: ","answer":"\\"َصِلُونَ إلَيْهِ الْأَخْبَارَ وَأَحْوَالَ السُوقَةِ فَصْلٌ وَمِنْ الشُرُوطِ اللَوَازِمِ لَلْمُحْتَسِبِ أَنْ يَكُونَ عَفِيفًا عَنْ أَمْوَالِ النَاسِ مُتَوَرِعًا عَنْ قَبُولِ الْهَدِيَةِ مِنْ الْمُتَعَيِشِينَ وَأَرْبَابِ الصِنَاعَاتِ فَإِنَ ذَلِكَ رِشْوَةٌ وَقَدْ قَالَ النَبِيُ صَلَى اللَهُ عَلَيْهِ وَسَلَمَ أ لَعَنَ اللَهُ الرَاشِيَ وَالْمُرْتَشِيَ وَلِأَنَ التَعَفُفَ عَنْ ذَلِكَ أَصَوْنُ لِعَرْضِهِ وَأَقْوَمُ لِهَيْبَتِهِ وَيُلْزِمُ الْمُحْتَسِبُ غِلْمَانَهُ\\""},{"question":"Bridgetown moy péeyu ban réw?","answer":"Bridgetown moy péeyu réwum Barbade"},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਸੁਣਿਐ ਮੁਖਿ ਸਾਲਾਹਣ ਮੰਦੁ ॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 2 ਤੋਂ ਲਈ ਗਈ ਇੱਕ ਤੁਕ ਦਾ ਵਾਕ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਨਾਨਕ ਦੇਵ ਜੀ ਇਸ ਬਾਣੀ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਹਨ।ਇਸਦਾ ਮਤਲਬ ਇਹ ਹੈ,\\"ਮੰਦਾ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਭੀ ਮੂੰਹੋਂ ਰੱਬ ਦੀਆਂ ਸਿਫ਼ਤਾਂ ਕਰਨ ਲੱਗ ਪੈਂਦਾ ਹੈ, \\""},{"question":"Мага кызыктуу факты жазып берчи ?","answer":"Албетте , мына сизге кызыктуу факты :Америка Кошмо Штаттарында туура эмес токтотулгандыгы үчүн мыйзам бузгандарды унаалардын дөңгөлөктөрү эмес, алдыңкы айнеги тосулуп турат.Кылмышкер унаа токтоочу жайга салык төлөгөндөн кийин, анын телефонуна СМС код келип түшөт, аны блокаторго киргизет.  Ошондой эле айдоочу алынып салынган блокаторду атайын чогултуу пунктуна жеткирүүгө милдеттүү, антпесе ага жаңы ири айып пул салынат"},{"question":"Pitakon ing ngisor iki kanggop nakokake panggonan sing bener yaiku...A. Sapa jenengmu?B. Ing ngendi omahmu?C. Apa sing mbok butuhake?Jawaban:","answer":"Jawaban: B. Ing ngendi omahmu?"},{"question":"Inona ary izany: izay teraka lahy avokoa?","answer":"lahin-jiro"},{"question":"What are Split Pins ?","answer":"These are sometimes called cotter pins and they are made of annealed iron or brass wire. They are generally of semi-circular cross-section and are used to prevent nuts from loosening. "},{"question":"السؤال: من هو النيي الملقب بالذبيح؟","answer":"الإجابة: اسماعيل عليه السلام"},{"question":"Manampy amin’ny fitazomana ny lanja sy ny habe ny fihinanana sakafo be otrik'aina. Marina sa Diso?","answer":"Marina, manampy amin’ny fitazomana ny lanja sy ny habe ny  fihinanana sakafo be otrik'aina. "},{"question":"ලංකාවේ ආණ්ඩුකාර සහ අග්‍රාණ්ඩුකාර යන , තනතුරු දෙකෙහිම කටයුතුකල පුද්ගලයන් දෙදෙනා කවුද ?","answer":"සර් හෙන්‍රි මන්ක් මේසන් මුවර්.සෝල්බරි සාමි"},{"question":"Акодондор булар ...","answer":"Акодондор (лат. Akodon) - аламандардын бир уруусу, буларга Бразилия акодону (А. arviculoides) кирет."},{"question":"வினா: தகடூரை ஆண்ட அதியமானை வென்ற சேரன்?","answer":"விடை: பெருஞ்சேரல் இரும்பொறை"},{"question":"ਸੰਗਰੂਰ, 30 ਅਕਤੂਬਰਭਾਈ ਗੁਰਦਾਸ ਗਰੁੱਪ ਆਫ਼ ਇੰਸਟੀਚਿਊਸ਼ਨਜ਼ ਵੱਲੋਂ ਪੰਜਵੀਂ ਸਾਲਾਨਾ ਅਥਲੈਟਿਕ ਮੀਟ ਕਰਵਾਈ ਗਈ। ਇਸ ਮੌਕੇ ਜ਼ਿਲ੍ਹਾ ਪੁਲੀਸ ਮੁਖੀ ਡਾ. ਸੰਦੀਪ ਗਰਗ ਮੁੱਖ ਮਹਿਮਾਨ ਅਤੇ ਜਤਿੰਦਰ ਸਿੰਘ ਬੈਨੀਪਾਲ ਕਮਾਂਡੈਂਟ ਆਈਆਰਬੀ ਲੱਡਾ ਕੋਠੀ ਵਿਸ਼ੇਸ਼ ਮਹਿਮਾਨ ਵਜੋਂ ਸ਼ਾਮਲ ਹੋਏ। ਪ੍ਰਧਾਨਗੀ ਇੰਸਟੀਚਿਊਸ਼ਨਜ ਦੇ ਚੇਅਰਮੈਨ ਡਾ. ਗੁਨਿੰਦਰਜੀਤ ਸਿੰਘ ਜਵੰਧਾ ਨੇ ਕੀਤੀ।ਮੁਕਾਬਲਿਆਂ ਦੌਰਾਨ 100 ਮੀਟਰ ਦੌੜ, 200 ਮੀਟਰ, 400 ਮੀਟਰ, 800 ਮੀਟਰ ਅਤੇ 4 ਗੁਣਾ 100 ਦੌੜਾਂ ਤੋਂ ਇਲਾਵਾ ਲੰਮੀ ਛਾਲ, ਉੱਚੀ ਛਾਲ, ਡਿਸਕਸ ਥਰੋ, ਰਿਲੇਅ ਦੌੜ, ਜੈਵਲਿਨ ਥਰੋ ਆਦਿ ਦੇ ਮੁਕਾਬਲੇ ਕਰਵਾਏ ਗਏ। ਇਸ ਤੋਂ ਇਲਾਵਾ ਕੁਝ ਮੰਨੋਰੰਜਕ ਖੇਡਾਂ ਜਿਵੇਂ ਰੱਸਾਕਸ਼ੀ, ਚਮਚਾ ਦੌੜ, ਤਿੰਨ ਟੰਗੀ ਦੌੜ ਆਦਿ ਕਰਵਾਈਆਂ ਗਈਆਂ। ਮੁਕਾਬਲਿਆਂ ਦੌਰਾਨ ਇੰਸਟੀਚਿਊਸ਼ਨਜ਼ ਦੇ ਇੰਜਨੀਅਰਿੰਗ, ਬੀ.ਐਡ, ਮੈਨੇਜਮੈਂਟ, ਪੌਲੀਟੈਕਨਿਕ, ਲਾਅ ਕਾਲਜ, ਨਰਸਿੰਗ ਅਤੇ ਡਿਗਰੀ ਕਾਲਜਾਂ ਦੇ ਵਿਦਿਆਰਥੀਆਂ ਨੇ ਭਾਗ ਲਿਆ। ਲੜਕਿਆਂ ਵਿੱਚੋਂ ਨਿਮੁਕ ਟੀਟੂ ਭਾਈ ਗੁਰਦਾਸ ਇੰਜਨੀਅਰਿੰਗ ਕਾਲਜ ਅਤੇ ਲੜਕੀਆਂ ਵਿੱਚੋਂ ਸਵਿਤਾ ਰਾਣੀ ਭਾਈ ਗੁਰਦਾਸ ਪੌਲੀਟੈਕਨਿਕ ਕਾਲਜ ਨੂੰ ਬੈਸਟ ਅਥਲੀਟ ਦੇ ਖਿਤਾਬ ਨਾਲ ਨਿਵਾਜਿਆ ਗਿਆ।ਭਾਈ ਗੁਰਦਾਸ ਇੰਜਨੀਅਰਿੰਗ ਕਾਲਜ ਦੀ ਟੀਮ ਨੇ ਓਵਰਆਲ ਟਰਾਫ਼ੀ ਜਿੱਤੀ ਤੇ ਭਾਈ ਗੁਰਦਾਸ ਮੈਨੇਜਮੈਂਟ ਕਾਲਜ ਦੀ ਟੀਮ ਦੂਜੇ ਸਥਾਨ ’ਤੇ ਰਹੀ। ਭਾਈ ਗੁਰਦਾਸ ਬੀ.ਐਡ ਕਾਲਜ ਦੀ ਟੀਮ ਨੂੰ ਬੈਸਟ ਮਾਰਚ ਪਾਸਟ ਲਈ ਚੁਣਿਆ ਗਿਆ। ਇਨਾਮ ਵੰਡ ਸਮਾਗਮ ਮੌਕੇ ਚੇਅਰਮੈਨ ਡਾ. ਗੁਨਿੰਦਰਜੀਤ ਸਿੰਘ ਜਵੰਧਾ ਨੇ ਕਿਹਾ ਕਿ ਖੇਡਾਂ ਵਿਦਿਆਰਥੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਸਰਵਪੱਖੀ ਵਿਕਾਸ ਦੇ ਨਾਲ ਨਾਲ ਉਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਅੰਦਰ ਸਮਾਜਿਕ ਅਗਵਾਈ ਦੀ ਭਾਵਨਾ ਦਾ ਵਿਕਾਸ ਕਰਦੀਆਂ ਹਨ। ਉਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਜੇਤੂ ਵਿਦਿਆਰਥੀਆਂ ਨੂੰ ਮੈਡਲਾਂ ਤੇ ਟਰਾਫ਼ੀਆਂ ਨਾਲ ਸਨਮਾਨਿਤ ਕੀਤਾ।ਇਸ ਮੌਕੇ ਬਲਜਿੰਦਰ ਕੌਰ ਜਵੰਧਾ ਸਕੱਤਰ ਭਾਈ ਗੁਰਦਾਸ ਗਰੁੱਪ ਅਤੇ ਡਾ. ਸੁਵਰੀਤ ਕੌਰ ਜਵੰਧਾ ਡੀਨ ਭਾਈ ਗੁਰਦਾਸ ਗਰੁੱਪ ਮੌਜੂਦ ਸਨ।ਚੇਅਰਮੈਨ ਡਾ. ਗੁਨਿੰਦਰਜੀਤ ਸਿੰਘ ਜਵੰਧਾ ਦਾ ਸੰਦੇਸ਼ ਕੀ ਸੀ?","answer":"ਇਨਾਮ ਵੰਡ ਸਮਾਰੋਹ ਮੌਕੇ ਚੇਅਰਮੈਨ ਡਾ: ਗੁਨਿੰਦਰਜੀਤ ਸਿੰਘ ਜਵੰਧਾ ਨੇ ਕਿਹਾ ਕਿ ਖੇਡਾਂ ਵਿਦਿਆਰਥੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਸਰਵਪੱਖੀ ਵਿਕਾਸ ਦੇ ਨਾਲ-ਨਾਲ ਸਮਾਜਿਕ ਅਗਵਾਈ ਦੀ ਭਾਵਨਾ ਦਾ ਵਿਕਾਸ ਕਰਦੀਆਂ ਹਨ |"},{"question":"Terjemahkanlah penggalan teks Bahasa Jawa yang disadur dari kumpulan cerita anak dunia berikut ke teks dalam Bahasa Indonesia.Besuke ana lumba-lumba liwat. Lumba-lumba iku liwat ing ndhuwur banyu, ngunjal ambegan jero banjur nyilem. Razia nyoba nglangi kaya lumba-lumba. Dheweke ngangkat sirahe ana ing ndhuwur banyu.Terjemahan:","answer":"Hari berikutnya seekor lumba-lumba lewat. Ia muncul ke permukaan air, mengambil napas, dan kembali menyelam. Rasya mencoba berenang seperti lumba-lumba. Ia mengangkat kepalanya ke atas permukaan air."},{"question":"Disangkakan langit itu rendah, dipandang dekat, dicapai tak boleh'. Apakah ia?","answer":"Ia bermaksud sebelum mencuba sesuatu pekerjaan itu janganlah dikatakan mudah atau senang"},{"question":"Türkiye 220 mi 230 mu?","answer":"Türkiye için şebeke gerilimi 230V ve 50 Hz'dir."},{"question":"شنوهي السوره اللي تذكر فيها صلاة العيد والأضحية؟","answer":"سورة الكوثر"},{"question":"විසිවැනි සියවසේ පෙරදිග ලෝකයේ පහලවූ , අනාත්මවාදී දාර්ශනිකයා  කවුද ?","answer":"විසිවැනි සියවසේ පෙරදිග ලෝකයේ පහලවූ , අනාත්මවාදී දාර්ශනිකයා වන්නෙ ක්‍රිෂ්ණමූර්ති තුමා ය. ."},{"question":"Ndàx man ngaa jubbanti mbind mii?Ñu ne: \\"Ñaanal nu sa Boroom mu leeral nu luy meloom\\". - Mu ne: \\"Naka Moom nee na: nag wa du wu màggat, du aw sëll, dafa digg-dóomu. Def leen li ñu leen sant\\".","answer":"Waaw! Mi ngii:Ñu ne: \\"Ñaanal nu sa Boroom mu leeral nu lu'y meloom\\". - Mu ne: \\"Naka Moom nee na: nag wa du wu màggat, du aw sëll, da fa digg-dóomu. Defléen li ñu léen sant\\"."},{"question":"Ano ang taong 1982 sa Roman numerals?","answer":"Ang katumbas ng taong 1982 sa Roman numerals ay MCMLXXXII. Ito ang kahulugan ng bawat titik ng Roman numeral na ito:M = 1000CM = 900 (Kapag iniligay sa harapan ng isang titik ang isa pang titik na may mas maliit na halaga, ibinabawas ang mas maliit na halagas sa mas malaki. Dahil C=100, nagiging 1000 - 100 = 900 ang CM.)LXXX = 80 (Kapag inulit ang isang titik, idinadagdag ang halaga nito. Dahil L=50 at X=10, nagiging 50 + 10 + 10 + 10 = 80 ang LXXX.)II = 2 (I=1 kaya nagiging 1 + 1 = 2 ang II.)"},{"question":"Inona no mampiavaka ny ankizy latsaka ny 18 taona sy ny mihoatra ny 18 taona?","answer":"Ny ankizy latsaka ny 18 taona dia mbola eo ambany fifehezan’ny ray aman-dreny. Ny mihoatra ny 18 taona kosa dia tokony ho efa mahaleo tena. Arakaraka ny eo am-pelatanan’ny ray aman-dreny sy ny zanaka ny fanaovana izany."},{"question":"เหตุการณ์สำคัญจากข้อความต่อไปนี้คืออะไร: อานันท์ ปันยารชุน ได้เข้ามารับหน้าที่ประธานคณะกรรมการปฏิรูปประเทศ หลังการชุมนุมของแนวร่วมประชาธิปไตยต่อต้านเผด็จการแห่งชาติ พ.ศ. 2553 ยุติลง ในช่วงเดือนกรกฎาคม พ.ศ. 2553 โดยทำหน้าที่ยกร่างแผนปฏิบัติการที่สามารถนำไปปฏิบัติ และแก้ไขปัญหาความอยุติธรรม และความเหลื่อมล้ำที่เกิดขึ้น ซึ่งคณะกรรมการดังกล่าวประกอบด้วยคณะกรรมการ จำนวน 19 คน ทำงานคู่ขนานไปกับคณะกรรมการสมัชชาปฏิรูปประเทศ ซึ่งไม่สามารถแก้ไขอะไรได้ กินเงินภาษีอย่างเดียว","answer":"การชุมนุมของแนวร่วมประชาธิปไตยต่อต้านเผด็จการแห่งชาติ พ.ศ. 2553"},{"question":"(ephakamisa ikhanda) Sekunguwe njalo baba?(sakuncokola) Ubuza ibhasi libhaliwe?(naye athi ukumamatheka) Hawu! Kanti wena sewaba yibhasi? (bahlekebobabili)(ahlale kwesinye isihlalo) Uboshiwe ngempela uDlamini. Kusasa uzoyakobingelela imantshi.Ashile! Kuhle-ke uma eboshiwe. (athule kancane)Nginovadlwana kodwa mina baba.Kodwa! Kodwa! Uvadlwana! Yini manje?(ngokuzithoba) Baba! Igazi likaMbandlwa lichithekile, induna yaboshwa.Konke lokhu akusho lutho kuwe?(ngolaka) Uthini manje? Mina ngibona kuzobathambisa ukuboshwakwenduna.(aphakamise izwi nomoya wakhe wenyuke) Hhayi bo! Ubathathakancane wena abantu bakule ndawo. Uyakhumbula ngesikhathi sodlame?Iningi labantu balapha bayayithanda inkosi futhi bayayihlonipha. (ehliseumoya) Baba, ngicela ukubone lokhu engikushoyo. Mina bengingacabangiukuthi lesi simo sizoze sifike kuleli banga esesikulo. Uyabona, nenja umaikhonkotha uke unganaki. Wethuke uphele uma isizifikela ngamazinyokuwe. Baba, izwe lizobheduka. Mina ngibona kungcono wena uzehliseenkosini noma uyeke kwabona ubukhansela lobu.(ethukuthela) Hheyi! Hheyi! Kanti usudleni wena? Lezi zinto ozishoyozombili angizamukeli! Lungamane luchitheke uphoko! Lutho mfazi! Ngeke!(enyuke ngolaka naye) Ubani umfazi weBafana? Ubiza mina ngomfazi?Wena awufuni ukuboniswa! Ngiyakutshela, uyongikhumbula seluchithekilelolu phoko lwakho.(abhoke kakhulu) Uzwa kanjani wena! Angisilo ivaka mina! Futhi, vala lomlonyana wakho singaze sethusane.1. Tomula umusho osesiqeshini ofakazela ukuthi uMaShezi wakuthokozelaukuboshwa kukaDlamin","answer":"Ashile! / Kuhle-ke uma eboshiwe."},{"question":"Beqil ma mbind mii:Wax nañu ne: \\"Kenn du dugg Àjjana ku dul ku nekk (Yahuud walla Nasaraan)\\". Loolu dey seen mébét la ñoom. - Neel: \\"Indileen seenu lay, ndegam ñu dëggu ngeen\\".","answer":"Mbind mi jub a ngi nii:Wàx na ñu ne: \\"Kenn du dugg Àjjana ku dul ku nekk (Yahuud walla Nasaraan)\\". Loolu de séen mébat la ñoom. - Neel: \\"Indiléen séen u lày, ndegam ñu dëggu ngéen\\"."},{"question":"Completa la siguiente frase: Daria Martyniuk (15 de marzo de 1994) es una deportista rusa que compite en esgrima y es especialista en la modalidad de espada. Ganó una medalla de plata en el ","answer":"Campeonato Europeo de Esgrima del año 2017, en la modalidad por equipos."},{"question":"¿Cómo se denominan las variaciones de un mismo idioma? Teniendo en cuenta la pregunta anterior, escriba un contexto que contenga la respuesta. Puede ser de 1 a 20 frases. El contexto:","answer":"Primero, es fundamental definir algunos términos para mejorar el entendimiento de la variación lingüística. Para distinguir entre dos o más variantes de un idioma, los lingüístas hablan de dialectos, o variedades de una lengua. Por ejemplo, el español de las Islas Canarias tiene distintas características que no están presentes en el español de Castilla-La Mancha. También, cuando hay un conjunto de dialectos, o variedades, se llama un macrodialecto. Por ejemplo, el conjunto de los dialectos cubano, dominicano, y puertorriqueño forma el macrodialecto ‘caribeño’. Finalmente, los distintivos que forman la particularidad lingüística de un individuo se llama idiolecto, y es único ya que incluye el uso de vocabulario, gramática y pronunciación de ese individuo en particular. De todo esto, es importante entender que cada lengua empezó como dialecto de otra y está formada por un conjunto de variedades que puede transformar con tiempo. Por ejemplo, el español, el francés, el italiano, el portugués, el romano, el catalán, el gallego, y muchas otras lenguas vienen de latín, y en algún momento eran solamente un dialecto de latín. A lo largo de varios siglos se les reconoció como lenguas independientes."},{"question":"Inona no antontan-taratasy manomboka amin'ny andian-teny hoe \\"Isika vahoaka\\"?1. Ny Fanambarana ny Fahaleovantena2. Ny volavolan-dalàna3. Lalàm-panorenan'i Etazonia","answer":"Safidy 3 - Ny Lalàm-panorenan'i Etazonia dia manomboka amin'ny andian-teny hoe \\"Isika vahoaka.\\""},{"question":"පහත තේරවිල්ල විසඳන්න.කැලේට පාන","answer":"ගඳ පාන"},{"question":"Waaku salaame?","answer":"Waa kaa qaade, maxaan kaa caawiyaa walaalo?"},{"question":"යූටියුබය මුදාහල අතිශය ප්‍රථම වීඩියෝව","answer":"යූ ටියුබ් වෙත උඩුගත කරන ලද පළමු වීඩියෝව නම් කර ඇත්තේ \\"Me at the zoo\\" යනුවෙනි. එය 2005 අප්‍රේල් 23 දින වේදිකාවේ සම-නිර්මාතෘවරයෙකු වන Jawed Karim විසින් උඩුගත කරන ලදී. වීඩියෝව තත්පර 18ක් දිග වන අතර කරීම් සැන් ඩියාගෝ සත්වෝද්‍යානයේ අලි ගාල ඉදිරිපිට සිට අලි ගැන කෙටියෙන් සාකච්ඡා කරන අයුරු දැක්වේ."},{"question":"Inona no atao hoe famadihana?","answer":"Ara-bakiteny :-Asa atao ho fampisehoana ny lafy tsy mbola hita amin’ny zavatra iray, toy ny akanjo, boky, tain’omby, …- Fiovan’ny olona nitokisana nanjary fahavalo (Rakibolana Malagasy)Famadihana : anarana ilazana ny toe-javatra miseho amin’ny endrika vaovao, tsy mbola hita."},{"question":"What does isiXhosa word \\"krazula\\" mean in English?","answer":"It means to strip, tear, and pull off. "},{"question":"కింద ఇచ్చిన భావం వచ్చేలాగా పద్యం రాయండి:క. అని చెప్పిన న మ్మానినిసునయోక్తుల కలరి భూమిసురుఁ దా కృష్ణుంగున నేయుట యిహపద సా“ధన మగు నని మదిఁ దలంచి తన పతితోడన్చు. నీవు సెప్పిన యట్ల రాజీవనేత్రుపాదపద్మంబు లాశ్రయింపంగం జనుట.పరమశోభన మా చక్రపాణి కిపుడుగానమైన గొంపోవఁ గలదె మనకు ?","answer":"భార్య మాటలకు కుచేలుడు సంతోషించాడు. శ్రీకృష్ణుని చూచుట ఇహలోక, పరలోక సుఖములకు సాధనమగునని భావించి, తన భార్యతో ఇట్లు పలికినాడని “నీవన్నట్లు శ్రీకృష్ణుని పాదపద్మములను ఆశ్రయించుట మిక్కిలి శుభదాయకమే. కాని ఆయనకు తీసుకొని వెళ్లుటకై మన దగ్గర ఏదైన కానుక ఉన్నదా ?” అని కుచేలుడు భార్యనడిగెను."},{"question":"Burburkii dimoqraadiyada somaaliya10- MAXAA LAGA DHAXLEY NIDAAMKII 21 OCT.g) -HIRGELINTA QORAALKA AF SOOMAALIGA.","answer":"Burburkii dimoqraadiyada somaaliya10- MAXAA LAGA DHAXLEY NIDAAMKII 21 OCT.g) -HIRGELINTA QORAALKA AF SOOMAALIGA.Waxa keliya oo laga dhaxley oo dadka u faaiideyey waa ololihii af somaliga oo ay hirgeliyeen taasoo la oran karo waa talaabo fiican oo ayan dowladihii ka horeyey ayan ku guuleysan in kastoo arintaas la hadal hayey 1973dii ayaa af soomaaliga la qorey 1974dii ayaa ololaha la aadey waxaana ka qeyb qaatey ardeyda dugsiga dhexe iyo kuwa sare oo dadoodu gaareysey 16 san. Runtii qeybaha kala duwan ee wasaaradaha wey ka qeyb qaateen masuuliyadaa xoogeedase ha lahaato wasaarada waxbarashada rutii ardada guul weyn ayey soo hoyeen oo la taaban karo waxeyna ku soo dhameesteen si sharaf leh waxaana ka faaiideystey dad badan oo joogey miyiga iyo magaaladaba oo manta waxna qora waxnaakhriya, waana waxa keliya oo laga soo qaadi karo nidaamkii 21 oct ee ka koobnaa 25 sarkaal."},{"question":"Ederede ntinye: \\"Mee ka uto gị dị ụtọ na Izu Culinary Masterclass , ememe gastronomic nke emere site na Julaị 20 ruo 25th na Epicurean Haven Resort. Ndị na-esi nri ama ama sitere na gburugburu ụwa ga-ezukọ iji kuzie nka nri ha site na ngosipụta nri na ọmụmụ ihe. Site na usoro achịcha achịcha dị mgbagwoju anya ruo nchikota ose dị egwu, mmemme a na-ekwe nkwa ịkwalite nka nri gị.\\" Chọpụta ihe omume:","answer":"Aha mmemme: izu Culinary MasterclassỌnọdụ: Epicurean Haven ResortỤbọchị: Julaị 20 ruo 25th"},{"question":"අප්‍රාණවාචී සියලුම නාමපද නපුංසකලිංග (නිර්ලිංග) වේද?එසේ නොවේ නම් යෙදෙන්නේ කෙසේද?","answer":"සංස්කෘත බසින් පැමිණි ඇතැම් අප්‍රාණවාචී නාමපද, එම බසේ යෙදෙනා පරිදි , ස්ත්‍රීලිංග ලෙසද සලකනු දැකිය හැකියි.උදා: ගංගාගංගා යන්න, ගංගා තොමෝ යයි ස්ත්‍රී ලිංග පදයක් ලෙස ලිවිය හැකියි. නමුත් එය ගංගා තෙමේ යයි, පුරුෂ ලිංග පදයක් සේ ලිවිය නොහැකිය.පුරුෂ ලිංග පදද මෙසේම දැකිය හැකියි.සූර්‍යයා - සූර්‍ය යන්න අප්‍රාණවාචී පදයකි. නමුත් එය සූර්යයා ලෙස ලියූවිට, ප්‍රාණවාචී පුරුෂ ලිංග පදයක් වේ. නමුත් එයට ස්ත්‍රී ලිංග පදයක් නොමැත."},{"question":"Sebagai negara yang berbentuk republik dan menganut asas demokrasi, pemerintahan di Indonesia dijalankan oleh pengampu kekuasaan yang merujuk pada konsep klasik 'Trias Politica'. Apa itu Trias Politica dan bagaimana implementasinya di Indonesia? ","answer":"Trias Politica adalah konsep pembagian kekuasaan oleh John Locke yang kemudian dikembangkan oleh Montesquieu. Trias Politica meyakini bahwa pemisahan kekuasaan dapat membuat proses pemerintahan berjalan stabil dan demokratis. Cabang kekuasaan dalam Trias Politica terdiri atas tiga yaitu eksekutif, legislatif, dan yudikatif. Ketiga cabang kekuasaan ini bekerja dalam mekanisme 'saling kontrol dan saling mengimbangi' atau biasa disebut dengan terminologi 'checks and balances'. Di Indonesia, Trias Politica diimplementasikan melalui pembagian kekuasaan yang dipegang oleh lembaga negara berikut. 1. Kekuasaan LegislatifKekuasaan legislatif diamanatkan untuk membuat undang-undang. Di Indonesia terdapat tiga badan legislatif, yaitu Majelis Permusyawaratan Rakyat (MPR), Dewan Perwakilan Rakyat (DPR), dan Dewan Perwakilan Daerah (DPD). 2. Kekuasaan EksekutifKekuasaan eksekutif diamanatkan untuk menjalankan roda pemerintahan menurut ketetapan undang-undang. Di Indonesia, kekuasaan eksekutif dipegang oleh presiden yang kemudian mendelegasikan wewenangnya melalui kabinet (menteri). 3. Kekuasaan Yudikatif Kekuasaan Yudikatif diamanatkan untuk menjalankan kekuasaan kehakiman, yaitu kekuasaan untuk mengadakan peradilan yang ditujukan bagi penegakan hukum dan keadilan. Di Indonesia, kekuasaan ini dijalankan oleh Mahkamah Agung (MA) dan Mahkamah Konstitusi (MK). "},{"question":"असंलग्न राष्ट्रहरुको १७औ शिखर सम्मेलन कहाँ हुदैछ ?","answer":"वेनेजुएला"},{"question":"ရုက္ခဗေဒနဲ့ ဓာတုဗေဒတိိုးတက်မှုတွေနဲ့အတူ အလယ်ခေတ်အစ္စလာမ်မှာ Muhammad ibn Zakarīya Rāzi နဲ့ Abu al-Qasim al-Zahrawi တို့အပါအဝင် ပညာရှင်များအကြောင်း ဖော်ပြပေးပါအထက်ပါမေးခွန်းကို စာကြောင်း ၂၀ လောက်ထိ အဖြေရေးပေပါ။ နောက်ခံအကြောင်းအရာ -","answer":"အရှေ့အလယ်ပိုင်းက ရုက္ခဗေဒနဲ့ ဓာတုဗေဒ တိုးတက်မှုတွေဟာ အလယ်ခေတ် အစ္စလာမ်မှာ ဆေးပညာကို ဆေးပညာကို အဓိကအားဖြင့် ဖွံ့ဖြိုးစေခဲ့တယ်။ ဥပမာအားဖြင့် မိုဟာမက် ဘင် ဇာကာရီယာ ရာဇီ (Rhazes) (၈၆၅<unk>၉၁၅) က ဓာတုဒြပ်ပေါင်းတွေရဲ့ ဆေးဘက်ဆိုင်ရာ အသုံးတွေကို မြှင့်တင်ဖို့ လုပ်ဆောင်ခဲ့တယ်။ အဘူ အယ်လ်-ကာစီမ် အယ်လ်-ဇာဟာရဝီ (အဘူလ်ကာစီစ်) (၉၃၆<unk>၁၀၁၃) သည် ဆေးဝါးများကို အထက်မြက်စေခြင်းနှင့် စွန့်ထုတ်ခြင်းဖြင့် ပြင်ဆင်မှုကို စတင်ခဲ့သည်။ သူ့ရဲ့ Liber servitoris ဟာ အထူးစိတ်ဝင်စားစရာဖြစ်တာက ၎င်းက စာဖတ်သူကို ဟင်းချက်နည်းတွေပေးပြီး အဲဒီအချိန်က ယေဘုယျသုံးတဲ့ ရှုပ်ထွေးတဲ့ ဆေးဝါးတွေကို ပေါင်းစပ်တဲ့ ရိုးစင်းတဲ့ ဆေးတွေ ပြင်ဆင်ပုံကို ရှင်းပြလို့ပါ။ Sabur Ibn Sahl (၁၈၆၉ သေဆုံး) သည် ဆေးဝါးစာပေကို စတင်ခဲ့သော ပထမဆုံးဆရာဝန်ဖြစ်ပြီး ရောဂါများအတွက် ဆေးဝါးနှင့် ဆေးဝါးအမျိုးမျိုးကို ဖော်ပြခဲ့သည်။ အယ်လ်-ဘီရူနီ (၉၇၃-၁၀၅၀) သည် ဆေးပညာဆိုင်ရာ တန်ဖိုးအရှိဆုံး အစ္စလာမ်ရေးရာလက်ရာတစ်ခုဖြစ်သော Kitab al-Saydalah (ဆေးဝါးများ၏စာအုပ်) ကိုရေးသားခဲ့ပြီး ယင်းတွင် ဆေးဝါးများ၏ ဂုဏ်သတ္တိများကို အသေးစိတ်ဖော်ပြခဲ့ပြီး ဆေးဝါးဆိုင်၏ အခန်းကဏ္ဍနှင့် ဆေးပညာရှင်၏တာဝန်များနှင့် တာဝန်များကိုဖော်ပြခဲ့သည်။ တကယ်တော့ သူဟာ ဆေးပညာဆိုင်ရာ စာအုပ်တစ်အုပ်ကို ရိုးရိုးဆေးဝါးများအတွက် ရည်စူးခဲ့တယ်။ ဘဂ္ဂဒက်နှင့်ကက်သရိုမှ အယ်လ်-မာရီဒင်နီနှင့် အီဘန် အယ်လ်-ဝဖစ် (၁၀၀၈-၁၀၇၄) တို့၏လက်ရာများသည်လည်း ကြီးမားသော သက်ရောက်မှုရှိခဲ့ပြီး ၎င်းတို့နှစ်ဦးစလုံးသည် လက်တင်ဘာသာဖြင့် အကြိမ်ငါးဆယ်ကျော် ပုံနှိပ်ခဲ့ကာ De Medicinis universalibus et particularibus အဖြစ် 'Mesue' the younger နှင့် 'Abenguefit' ၏ Medicamentis simplicibus အဖြစ်ပေါ်ပေါက်ခဲ့သည်။ Peter of Abano (1250<unk>1316) က De Veneris ဆိုတဲ့ ခေါင်းစဉ်နဲ့ al-Maridini ရဲ့လက်ရာကို ဘာသာပြန်ပြီး ဖြည့်စွက်ချက်တစ်ခု ထည့်သွင်းခဲ့တယ်။ Al-Muwaffaq ၏ ဤကဏ္ဍမှ ဆောင်ရွက်ချက်များသည်လည်း ရှေ့ဆောင်လမ်းပြများ ဖြစ်သည်။ ၁၀ ရာစုမှာ နေထိုင်ခဲ့တဲ့ သူက ဆေးဝါးတွေရဲ့ စစ်မှန်တဲ့ ဂုဏ်သတ္တိတွေရဲ့ အခြေခံတွေကို ရေးသားခဲ့ပြီး အခြားအရာတွေအနက် ကြေးနီအောက်ဆိုဒ်ကို သရုပ်ဖော်ကာ ဆီလီကွန်အက်ဆစ်နဲ့ ရင်းနှီးခဲ့တယ်။ သူဟာ sodium carbonate နဲ့ potassium carbonate တို့ကို ရှင်းလင်းစွာ ခွဲခြားခဲ့ပြီး ကြေးနီဒြပ်ပေါင်းများ အထူးသဖြင့် ကြေးနီ vitriol နဲ့ ခဲဒြပ်ပေါင်းများရဲ့ အဆိပ်အတောက်ဖြစ်မှုကို ထောက်ပြခဲ့ပါတယ်။ သူဟာ ပင်လယ်ရေကို စုပ်ယူမှုကိုပါ ဖေါ်ပြခဲ့ပါသေးတယ်။"},{"question":"iza ny renivohitr’I frantsa?","answer":"ny renivohitr’I frantsa dia Parisy"},{"question":"Gaano karaming vitamin C ang kailangan ko sa aking katawan?","answer":"Ang mga nasa hustong gulang na 19 hanggang 64 ay nangangailangan ng 40mg ng vitmaic C sa isang araw. Dapat mong makuha ang lahat ng vitamic C na kailangan mo mula sa iyong pang-araw-araw na diyeta."},{"question":"Bedelsiz sermaye artırımı kazandırır mı?","answer":"Hisse fiyatları çok artarsa alım satım işlemleri yavaşlayacaktır. Bunun önüne geçebilmek adına bedelsiz sermaye artırımı yapılarak hem daha çok sayıda hissenin piyasalarda işlem görmesi sağlanır hem de senetlerin likiditesi artmış olur."},{"question":"1/5 र 2/3 भिन्नहरू थप्नुहोस् र परिणामलाई सरलीकृत अंशको रूपमा व्यक्त गर्नुहोस्।","answer":"भिन्नहरू थप्नको लागि, एउटा साझा भाजक फेला पार्नुहोस्, जुन यस अवस्थामा 15 हो। त्यसैले, (1/5) + (2/3) = (3/15) + (10/15) = 13/15।"},{"question":"Đọc đoạn văn sau và đưa ra một tiêu đề phụ hợp với nội dung:   Thanh Hóa phong độ phập phù Đến thời điểm này, Thanh Hoá được đánh giá là có phong độ phập phù thuộc dạng bậc nhất của V.League. Họ có thể cầm hoà được Hải Phòng ở thời điểm đội bóng đất Cảng đang có phong độ tốt nhất, thắng đậm SHB Đà Nẵng và Sài Gòn, nhưng lại thua CLB TP.HCM hoặc để Nam Định chia điểm ngay trên sân nhà. Viettel và nhiệm vụ phải thắng Về phía Viettel, sau khi thay tướng với sự xuất hiện của HLV Bae Ji Won trên ghế nóng, đội bóng này cũng đang dần tìm thấy sự ổn định. Mặc dù CLB Viettel lúc này vẫn chưa có hàng thủ như ý khi trung vệ đội trưởng Bùi Tiến Dũng và Đức Chiến dính chấn thương. Song với sự ổn định của hàng tiền vệ cùng phong độ khá tốt của các chân sút hàng công, họ chắc hẳn đang rất tự tin trong việc giành thắng lợi ở xứ Thanh.  Nguồn: https://tcdulichtphcm.vn/the-thao/truc-tiep-bong-da-thanh-hoa-viettel-no-luc-bat-thanh-v-league-...Nguồn: https://tcdulichtphcm.vn/the-thao/truc-tiep-bong-da-thanh-hoa-viettel-no-luc-bat-thanh-v-league-het-gio-c28a36003.html ","answer":"Trực tiếp bóng đá Thanh Hóa - Viettel: Nỗ lực bất thành (V-League) (Hết giờ)"},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਮਃ ੩ ॥ਹੋਰੁ ਕੂੜੁ ਪੜਣਾ ਕੂੜੁ ਬੋਲਣਾ ਮਾਇਆ ਨਾਲਿ ਪਿਆਰੁ ॥ਨਾਨਕ ਵਿਣੁ ਨਾਵੈ ਕੋ ਥਿਰੁ ਨਹੀ ਪੜਿ ਪੜਿ ਹੋਇ ਖੁਆਰੁ ॥੨॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 84 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਅਮਰਦਾਸ ਜੀ ਇਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਵਾਰਾਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਸਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"ਹੋਰ (ਮਾਇਆ ਸੰਬੰਧੀ) ਪੜ੍ਹਨਾ ਵਿਅਰਥ ਉੱਦਮ ਹੈ, ਹੋਰ ਬੋਲਣਾ (ਭੀ) ਵਿਅਰਥ (ਕਿਉਂਕਿ ਇਹ ਉੱਦਮ) ਮਾਇਆ ਨਾਲਿ ਪਿਆਰ (ਵਧਾੳਂੁਦੇ ਹਨ) ਹੇ ਨਾਨਕ ! ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੇ ਨਾਮ ਤੋਂ ਬਿਨਾ ਕੋਈ ਭੀ ਸਦਾ ਨਹੀਂ ਰਹਿਣਾ (ਭਾਵ, ਸਦਾ ਨਾਲ ਨਹੀਂ ਨਿਭਣਾ), (ਇਸ ਵਾਸਤੇ) ਜੇ ਕੋਈ ਹੋਰ ਪੜ੍ਹਨੀਆਂ ਹੀ ਪੜ੍ਹਦਾ ਹੈ ਖ਼ੁਆਰ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ ।੨।\\""},{"question":"Một trường trung học cơ sở tổ chức cho lớp 6D gồm 40 học sinh đi tham quan học tập ngoại khóa. Toàn bộ chi phí chuyến đi sẽ chia đều cho mỗi học sinh. Đến ngày đi, 4 học sinh của lớp 6D không tham gia được. Hỏi, mỗi bạn tham gia còn lại phải đóng thêm 25 000 đồng so với dự kiến chi phí ban đầu. Tổng chi phí cho chuyến đi là bao nhiêu?","answer":"Số học sinh đi du lịch là:40 – 4 = 36 (học sinh)Tổng số tiền các bạn phải đóng thêm là: 25 000 . 36 = 900 000 (đồng)Số tiền các bạn phải đóng thêm chính là tổng số tiền phải đóng của 4 học sinh không đi, do đó, theo dự kiến, mỗi bạn phải đóng số tiền là: 900 000 : 4 = 225 000 (đồng)Tổng chi phí cho chuyến đi là:225 000 . 40 =  9 000 000 (đồng)Vậy tổng chi phí cho chuyến đi là 9 000 000 đồng. "},{"question":"Hay ve ny manadino ny olon-tiana voalohany?","answer":"Azo inoana fa tsy hanadino tanteraka ny olon-tiana voalohany, satria mety hamela soritra ara-pihetseham-po maharitra izany. Mety hihena anefa izany fihetseham-po izany rehefa mandeha ny fotoana."},{"question":"السؤال: ما هي مكونات المونة الإسمنتية؟","answer":"الإجابة: الصلصال أو الإسمنت ، أو خليط منهما وقد يضاف إليهما الرمل، ثم يضاف إليها الماء."},{"question":"*أين تقع مدينة العين ؟","answer":"الإمارات"},{"question":"請問英國歌曲的編曲和製作有哪些突出的特點？","answer":"答：英國歌曲的編曲和製作具有豐富的層次感和技巧，注重音樂結構和聲音效果的細膩處理。"},{"question":"Ala ti ko le ṣẹ ni ki n dara pọ mọ ẹgbẹ APC – Makinde","answer":"Pẹlu bi iroyin ṣe gba ilu kan pe gomina ipinlẹ Ọyọ Ẹnjinnia Ṣeyi Makinde, n gbero lati fi ẹgbẹ oṣelu PDP to fi ṣàtẹ̀gùn dépò gomina silẹ lati dara pọ mọ APC to jẹ ẹgbẹ oṣelu alatako ni ipinlẹ naa, gomina yii sọ pe inu oun dun pe APC n fẹ oun ninu ẹgbẹ wọn, ṣugbọn ala ti ko le ṣẹ ni ki oun dara pọ mọ wọn.Lati ọsẹ to kọja niroyin ti n gbe e kiri pe awọn alatilẹyin Makinde ti dara pọ mọ ẹgbẹ oṣelu Onígbàálẹ̀, ati pe gomina yii funra rẹ ti dara pọ mọ ẹgbẹ naa labẹnu.Wọn ní nitori pe awọn araalu ko gba ti gomina yii mọ nitori ọwọ yẹpẹrẹ to fi mu ọrọ eto aabo lo ṣe pinnu lati lọ sinu ẹgbẹ APC.Ṣugbọn nigba to n sọrọ lori ahesọ iroyin naa ninu atẹjade ti Akọwe iroyin ẹ, Ọgbẹni Taiwo Adisa, fi ṣọwọ sawọn oniroyin n’Ibadan, lọsẹ yii, o ni kò sí ootọ kankan ninu gbogbo iroyin naa, ṣugbọn ahesọ iroyin naa kò yà oun lẹnu, awọn àṣeyọrí ti oun n ṣe lọ́lọ́kan-ò-jọ̀kan lo mu ki oun maa da ẹgbẹ APC lọrun.O ṣalaye pe, “Pẹlu ofin ati ilana iṣejọba awa-ara-wa ni Gomina Makinde fi n mojuto ọrọ eto aabo ni ipinlẹ yii. O gba pe gbogbo ẹni to ba ti n huwa ọdaran pata lọta ijọba, ti oluwa rẹ yoo sì jiya to bá tọ sí i labẹ ofin lai fi ti ẹya ti iru ẹni bẹẹ ba ti wa ṣe.”“idí tó ṣe wù awọn ẹgbẹ oṣelu alatako naa pe ki oun dara pọ mọ wọn ko ṣẹyin ọpọlọpọ aseyori ti oun ti ṣe lẹnu ọdun kan o ti oun ti dépò gomina“Awọn APC waa ro pe nnkan to daa ju fun awọn lati ṣe bayii ni ki Gomina Makinde wa sinu ẹgbẹ awọn lati waa dupo gomina lorukọ ẹgbẹ naa. Wọn mọ pe iṣejọba rẹ yóò ṣàtúnṣe sí gbogbo nnkan ti iṣejọba ẹgbẹ oṣelu awọn ti bajẹ sẹyin, ẹgbẹ APC ni yóò sì gba ògo àṣeyọrí naa”."},{"question":"Smart board යන්නට දිය හැකි සිංහල වචනය කුමක්ද?","answer":"සුහුරු පුවරුව"},{"question":"दक्षिण भारतातील पल्लव राजघराण्याचा काळ हा शिल्पकलेचा कोणता युग मानला जातो ?","answer":"सुवर्णयुग"},{"question":"కింది ప్రశ్నకు సమాధానం ఇవ్వండివాతావరణం, జీవావరణం పదాలను వర్ణించండి. ","answer":"1. వాతావరణం: భూమిచుట్టూ రక్షణాత్మకంగా ఉండే వాయు పొరను వాతావరణం అంటారు.2. జీవావరణం: జీవరాశులు అన్నింటిని అనగా మొక్కలు, జంతువులు, మానవులను ఉమ్మడిగా జీవావరణం అంటారు."},{"question":"GARASHADA GUUSHA!","answer":"Waa Maxay Guul? Waxaa jirta su’aal ahayd waa maxay guul oo la weyddiiyay akhristayaasha wargeyska ‘The Dreamer’s Guide Motivation Newsletter.’ Bal aan kuu soo gudbiyo jawaabaha ay ka soo kala bixiyeen.  Isaac Alex Phiri:  Ma sheegi karo macneha dhabta ah ee guusha, laakiinse waxaan ku soo koobi lahaa hab fudud oo ah: In aad gaarto barta ay riyadaada kuu tilmaamayso; markaad hesho wixii aad u baahnayd; markaad ka salgaarto duruufaha iyo caqabadaha nolosha. Geoffrey Nkhoma:  “Guushu waxaan u arkaa farxadda; farxaddaas oo ka imaanaysa markii aynu aragno dadka aynu jecelnahay.” Janett Kalale:  “Guushu macneheedu waa in aad gaarto natiijada ugu sarrayso, uguna suurtagalsan hiigsigeeda.” Mary Masumbuko:  Guushu waa in aad isku dhiibto Alle, waa bixiyaha nolosha dhabta ah ee aadanuhu raadiyo. Guushu waa xakamaynta nolosha, in aad qaabayso qorsheha nolosha iyo in aad xaqiijiso [Sidii aad ku gaari lahayd yoolkaaga]…taas ayaan guul u arkaa. Humphery:  “Waxaan guul u garanayaa sida soo socota: Farxadda qoyska; xiriirka aad la leedahay Alle iyo ku kalsoonaanta nafta.” "},{"question":"'मै मेरी झांशी नही दूंगी’ हे उद्गार कोणाचे आहे ?","answer":" राणी लक्ष्मीबाई"},{"question":"Apakah soalan untuk: \\"Wizard of Oz, yang dikenali semasa pemerintahannya sebagai Great and Powerful Oz, adalah julukan Oscar Zoroaster Phadrig Isaac Norman Henkel Emmannuel Ambroise Diggs, watak fiksyen di Land of Oz, yang dicipta oleh penulis Amerika L. Frank Baum.\\"? Topiknya ialah Wizard of Oz (karakter).","answer":"\\"apakah nama ahli sihir dari Oz?\\""},{"question":"శీర్షిక: రైతుల ఆందోళనలు: దిల్లీ సరిహద్దుల్లో అవరోధాలను పెంచుతున్న ప్రభుత్వం. రైతులు ఏమంటున్నారు?ఒక ఊహాత్మక కథనం యొక్క ఎగువ శీర్షికను బట్టి, కథనాన్ని ఊహించుకోండి.","answer":"దీంతో ఈ మూడు మార్గాల్లో భారీగా ట్రాఫిక్ జామ్ అయింది. ఈ మూడు ప్రాంతాల్లో పోలీసులు భారీ ఎత్తున బారికేడ్లు కూడా ఏర్పాటు చేస్తున్నారు.కేంద్ర పభుత్వం తీసుకువచ్చిన కొత్త వ్యవసాయ చట్టాలకు వ్యతిరేకంగా ఈ మూడు ప్రాంతాల్లో రైతులు ఆందోళన ప్రదర్శనలు చేస్తున్నారు.ఇప్పుడు ఆ ప్రాంతాల్లో పరిస్థితులు ఎలా ఉన్నాయంటే.గాజీపుర్ సరిహద్దులో రైతులు ఆందోళన చేస్తున్న స్థలంలో ఆదివారం సాయంత్రం భద్రతా చర్యలు పెంచారు.ఉత్తర్‌ప్రదేశ్ నుంచి దిల్లీ వచ్చే రహదారులపై వివిధ స్థాయిల్లో అవరోధాలు పెట్టి మూసేశారు. కాలి బాటలను సైతం మూసేశారు.‘‘ఈ రోజు ఉదయం నాకు దారి వెతుక్కునేందుకే రెండు గంటలు సరిపోయింది. ఈ ప్రాంత డీసీపీని సాయం కోరా. ఆయన సాయం చేసేందుకు ప్రయత్నించినా, చాలా సేపు ట్రాఫిక్ జామ్‌లో చిక్కుకుని ఉండిపోయా’’ అని సీనియర్ పాత్రికేయుడు ప్రభాకర్ మిశ్ర అన్నారు. ఆయన రెండు నెలలుగా దిల్లీలో రైతుల ఆందోళనల గురించి వార్తలు, కథనాలు రాస్తున్నారు.ఆనంద్ విహార్ గుండా గాజియాబాద్ వచ్చే మార్గం మాత్రమే తెరిచి ఉంది. ఈ మార్గంలోనూ రోడ్డుకు ఒకే వైపు తెరిచిపెట్టారు. దీంతో ట్రాఫిక్ కొన్ని కిలోమీటర్ల మేర నిలిచిపోయింది.ఇలా దారులన్నీ ఎందుకు మూసేయాల్సి వచ్చిందన్నదానిపై దిల్లీ పోలీసులు ఎలాంటి వివరణా ఇవ్వడం లేదు. క్షేత్ర స్థాయిలో ఉన్న పోలీసు సిబ్బంది మాత్రం పైనుంచి వచ్చిన ఆదేశాలను పాటిస్తున్నామని చెబుతున్నారు.ఎవరూ ముందుకు వెళ్లకుండా పర్యవేక్షణ చేసేందుకు తమను నియమించారని గాజీపుర్‌లో ఉన్న కొంతమంది యువకులు చెప్పారు.గాజీపుర్‌లో రైతులు తిరిగి పోగైన తర్వాత వారి గుంపు మరింత పెరుగుతోంది. తమ టెంట్లు మరింత ముందుకు కదలకుండా, పోలీసులు ఈ చర్యలు తీసుకుంటూ ఉండొచ్చని రైతులు అంటున్నారు.ఇక్కడి  వసుంధర, వైశాలీ, ఇందిరాపురం, కౌశాంబీ లాంటి ప్రాంతాల్లో ఉన్న చాలా మంది దిల్లీలో ఉద్యోగాలు చేస్తుంటారు. రహదారులు మూసేయడంతో వాళ్లంతా ఇబ్బందులు ఎదుర్కోవాల్సి వస్తోంది.‘‘నేను ఇక్కడే ఉండేవాణ్ని కాబట్టి కాలి నడకన వెళ్లే దారులు తెలుసు. కానీ, అవి తెలియని చాలా మంది చాలా ఇక్కట్లు పడుతున్నారు’’ అని నొయిడా 62 సెక్టార్‌లో రైల్వే పరీక్ష రాసి తిరిగివస్తున్న మనీష్ యాదవ్ బీబీసీతో చెప్పారు.అంతర్జాతీయ సరిహద్దులను తలపిస్తున్న దిల్లీ సరిహద్దులు."},{"question":"uye we-bulukudu, what does it mean?","answer":"to stumble, fall on knees."},{"question":"ජනගහණ ඝනත්වය2021 ජූලි මාසයේ දී ඇලස්කා අර්ධද්වීපයට ආසන්නයෙන් ඒකක 8.2ක දැවැන්ත භූ කම්පනයක් සිදුවිය. නමුත් ඔබට ඒ ගැන කිසිදු මතකයක් නොමැතිවීමට ඉඩ තිබේ.","answer":"ජනගහණ ඝනත්වය2021 ජූලි මාසයේ දී ඇලස්කා අර්ධද්වීපයට ආසන්නයෙන් ඒකක 8.2ක දැවැන්ත භූ කම්පනයක් සිදුවිය. නමුත් ඔබට ඒ ගැන කිසිදු මතකයක් නොමැතිවීමට ඉඩ තිබේ.මේ චිග්නික් භූ කම්පනය එක්සත් ජනපදයේ ඉතිහාසයේ හත්වැනියට විශාලතම භූ කම්පනය ලෙස සැලකෙන නමුදු, එය කිසිවෙකුට තුවාල සිදුකළේ හෝ මරණයට පත්කළේ නැත. ඊට හේතුවූයේ, එය ප්‍රධාන ජනාවාසයන්ගෙන් බැහැරව, පොළව මතුපිට සිට සාපේක්ෂව ගැඹුරෙන් සිදුවූ භූ කම්පනයක් වූ හෙයිනි.ඊට අසමානව, 2010 ජනවාරියේ හෙයිටියේ සිදුවූ ඒකක 7.0ක භූ කම්පනයෙන් මහා විනාශයක් සිදුවිය - පුද්ගලයින් 250,000කට වැඩි පිරිසක් මරණයට පත්වීයැ යි ඇස්තමේන්තු කෙරුණි. තවත් 300,000ක් පමණ දෙනා තුවාල ලැබූ අතර මිලියන 1.5ක පමණ පිරිසක් අවතැන් විය.අගනුවර වූ පෝට්-ඕ-ප්‍රින්ස් වෙත භූ කම්පනයේ පූර්ණ බලපෑම දැනුණු අතර, විශාල මරණ සංඛ්‍යාවක් සිදුවීමට එහි අධික ජනගහණය (වර්ග කිලෝමීටරයට මිනිසුන් 27,000ක්) ද හේතුවිය."},{"question":"இந்தப் பத்தியின் தொடர்ச்சியை எழுதுங்கள் பெரிய சம்பவங்கள் பலவற்றுள் 1946 ஆம் ஆண்டில் கிரேட் கல்கத்தா கொலைகள், பீகார் மற்றும் கர்முக்தேஷ்வர், நவகாளி படுகொலைகள், 1947 ஆம் ஆண்டில் ஜம்முவில் படுகொலை செய்யபட்ட முஸ்லிம்கள், பின் முஸ்லிம்கள் பெரிய அளவில் கொலை செய்யப்பட்ட ஹைதராபாத் போலோ நடவடிக்கை, பின்னர் கொல்கத்தாவில் முஸ்லிம் எதிரான கலவரம், 1950 ஆம் ஆண்டின் பாரிசல் கலவரங்கள், 1964 ஆம் ஆண்டின் கிழக்கு-பாக்கிஸ்தான் கலவரம், 1969 ஆம் ஆண்டின் குஜராத் கலவரம், 1984 பேவண்டி கலவரம, 1985 குஜராத் கலவரம், 1989 பாகல்பூர் கலவரம், பம்பாய் கலவரம், 1983 ஆம் ஆண்டில் நெல்லி கலவரம் மற்றும் 2002 ஆம் ஆண்டில் குஜராத் கலவரம் மற்றும் 2013 ஆம் ஆண்டில் முசாபர்நகர் கலவரம் .","answer":"பீகார்"},{"question":"Dựa trên tiêu đề sau, hãy viết một bài báo nói về chủ đề này: AFF minh oan cho U19 Việt Nam, Indonesia phản ứng gay gắt. Trong đoạn văn, ý chính là về kết quả điều tra trận đấu giữa U19 Việt Nam và U19 Thái Lan, trong đó AFF đã khẳng định rằng trận đấu này không có dấu hiệu dàn xếp tỷ số, phản bác cáo buộc từ Indonesia. Nhân vật chính là Liên đoàn bóng đá Indonesia (PSSI), đặc biệt là Tổng thư ký PSSI, Yunus Nusi và Chủ tịch PSSI, Mochamad Iriawan, có các phản ứng và tuyên bố về việc này, cùng với trưởng đoàn đội U19 Indonesia, Endri Erawan, cũng chia sẻ quan điểm của đội bóng.","answer":"Hôm qua, AFF đã công bố kết quả điều tra trận đấu giữa U19 Việt Nam và U19 Thái Lan. Theo đó, họ khẳng định trận đấu này không có dấu hiệu dàn xếp tỷ số. Điều này trái ngược với cáo buộc của Indonesia trước đó. Sau khi thông tin này được công bố, Liên đoàn bóng đá Indonesia (PSSI) đã có phản ứng gay gắt. Chia sẻ trước báo giới, Tổng thư ký PSSI, Yunus Nusi nhấn mạnh: \\"Sau chuyện này, chúng tôi sẽ nghiên cứu kỹ phương án rời khỏi AFF. Sau đó, chúng tôi sẽ đưa ra quyết định cuối cùng. Hãy cho chúng tôi thêm một chút thời gian để thảo luận. Sau đó, PSSI sẽ công bố thông tin cuối cùng trước công chúng\\". Trong khi đó, trưởng đoàn đội U19 Indonesia, Endri Erawan cho biết: \\"Chúng tôi cảm ơn AFF vì đã phản hồi đơn khiếu nại của PSSI. Về cơ bản, chúng tôi chấp nhận quyết định này. Đội bóng chỉ muốn làm rõ xem trận đấu giữa U19 Việt Nam và U19 Thái Lan có dấu hiệu dàn xếp tỷ số hay không. Giờ thì chúng tôi đã có câu trả lời\\". Vào ngày 12/7, PSSI đã gửi đơn khiếu nại lên AFF tố cáo. Sau đó, họ tức giận khi cơ quan quyền lực cao nhất của bóng đá Đông Nam Á không đưa ra phản hồi trong vòng hai tuần qua. Điều đó khiến cho Chủ tịch PSSI, Mochamad Iriawan vô cùng tức giận. Tờ Bola Sport bình luận về động thái của Indonesia: \\"Mặc dù PSSI tôn trọng phán quyết cuối cùng của AFF nhưng họ không hài lòng. Không loại trừ khả năng, họ sẽ có động thái mới trong tương lai. Liệu chăng, PSSI vẫn quyết định rời khỏi AFF hay không? Câu trả lời sẽ có ngay vào tháng 8 tới khi lễ bốc thăm AFF Cup 2022 được tổ chức ở Bangkok, Thái Lan\\". Trước mắt Indonesia vẫn đăng cai giải U16 Đông Nam Á. Giải đấu này sẽ khai màn vào hôm nay. Ở giải đấu, U16 Việt Nam sẽ nằm chung bảng với U16 Indonesia."},{"question":"Slutför den här frasen: ‎Fomina har tillhört truppen i ‎‎det ryska landslaget till och från genom åren.‎‎ Hon spelade för Ryssland redan i ‎‎handbolls-","answer":"EM 2010 ‎och även i VM ‎‎2011.‎‎ ‎‎ Hon deltog sedan också i olympiska ‎‎spelen i‎‎ ‎‎London, men var sedan borta ur landslaget under mästerskapen i flera års tid. ‎‎ Vid ‎‎VM 2019 återkom hon och vann‎‎ hon en bronsmedalj med det ryska laget. 2020 blev hon femma i ‎‎EM.‎‎ Främsta internationella meriten med ryska landslaget vann hon i ‎‎damernas turnering i handboll vid olympiska sommarspelen 2020 i Tokyo.‎‎ ‎ Innan OS 2020 hade hon spelat 140 landskamper och gjort 294 mål i ryska landslaget."},{"question":"أجب على السؤال ده: السكر بيتكون من الكربون والهيدروجين والأكسجين. السكر هو مثال على ايه من التالي؟ اختر إجابتك من: [أ] ذرة. [ب] مركب. [ج] إلكترون. [د] خليط. الجواب:","answer":"[ب]."},{"question":"Qual é a resposta correta para esta pergunta: \\"George Washington foi eleito em 1792?\\"","answer":"A resposta correta para a pergunta é Sim."},{"question":"\\"Ай толгонун билбейт ... \\" деген макал-лакапты улантып берчи ?","answer":"Сиз суранган макал-лакаптын жообу мындай болушу мүмкүн : \\"Ай толгонун билбейт, жигит болгонун билбейт\\""},{"question":"মোকলেছ সাহেব পেশায় মৎস্যবিদ। দেশে মাছের ঘাটতি পূরণের জন্য প্রযুক্তি ব্যবহার করে নতুন নতুন প্রজাতির মাছ উৎপাদন করেন। তার অফিসে প্রবেশের জন্য দরজার সামনে রাখা একটি মেশিনে আঙ্গুলের ছাপ দিলে দরজা খুলে যায়। অতঃপর তার কক্ষে প্রবেশের জন্য দরজার সামনে রাখা একটি মেশিনের দিকে তাকালে দরজা খুলে যায়।উদ্দীপকের আলোকে অফিসে প্রবেশ ও কক্ষে প্রবেশের জন্য কৌশল দুটির মধ্যে কোনটি বেশি সুবিধাজনক? বিশ্লেষণ কর।","answer":"উদ্দীপকে অফিসে প্রবেশ ও কক্ষে প্রবেশ উভয় ক্ষেত্রেই বায়োমেট্রিক্স প্রযুক্তি ব্যবহৃত হলেও এদের মধ্যে পদ্ধতিগত ও আচরণিক বৈশিষ্ট্য শনাক্তকরণে পার্থক্য রয়েছে।উদ্দীপকে দেখা যায়, মোকলেছ সাহেব তার অফিসে প্রবেশের জন্য দরজার সামনে রাখা একটি মেশিনে আঙ্গুলের ছাপ দিলে দরজা খুলে যায় এবং তার কক্ষে প্রবেশের জন্য দরজার সামনে রাখা একটি মেশিনের দিকে তাকালে দরজা খুলে যায়। এক্ষেত্রে আঙুলের ছাপ ও তাকিয়ে থাকা তথা চোখের আইরিশ বায়োমেট্রিক্সের অন্যতম দুটি উপাদান। ফিঙ্গারপ্রিন্ট এবং আইরিশ স্ক্যানিং বায়োমেট্রিক্স সিস্টেমে কোনো ব্যক্তির সংরক্ষিত নির্দিষ্ট ডেটার সাথে তাৎক্ষণিক ইনপুটকৃত একই বায়োমেট্রিক্স ডেটা (ঐ ব্যক্তির আঙুলের ছাপ এবং চোখের মণির চারপাশে বেষ্টিত রঙিন বলয় বা আইরিশ) ম্যাচিং বা মেলানোর মাধ্যমে ব্যক্তিকে শনাক্ত করা যায়। সুতরাং মোকলেছ সাহেবের অফিসের দরজার বায়োমেট্রিক্স প্রযুক্তিতে ফিঙ্গার প্রিন্টের মাধ্যমে এবং তার কক্ষের দরজায় আইরিশ স্ক্যানিং-এর মাধ্যমে প্রবেশ প্রক্রিয়া সম্পন্ন হয়ে থাকে।তবে উভয়ক্ষেত্রে বায়োমেট্রিক্স ডেটা গ্রহণকারী ডিভাইসদ্বয়ের মধ্যে প্রথমটির দাম সস্তা, সহজলভ্য ও ব্যবহার সহজ। এছাড়াও ফিঙ্গারপ্রিন্ট বায়োমেট্রিক্স পদ্ধতিটি দুই-একটি ব্যতিক্রম ছাড়া প্রায় সকল ক্ষেত্রেই ব্যক্তি শনাক্তকরণে সহজ ও দ্রুততার সাথে শতভাগ সফলতা প্রদান করতে সক্ষম। আবার এ পদ্ধতিতে শারীরিক কোনো ঝুঁকি নেই। অন্যদিকে আইরিশ স্ক্যানিং বায়োমেট্রিক্স পদ্ধতিটি অত্যন্ত ব্যয়বহুল এবং এতে প্রচুর মেমোরি ব্যবহৃত হয় ৷ তাছাড়া এটি চোখের জন্য খানিকটা ক্ষতিকরও বটে।উপরিউক্ত বিশ্লেষণে বলা যায় এ দুই বায়োমেট্রিক্স পদ্ধতির মধ্যে আঙুলের ছাপ বা ফিঙ্গারপ্রিন্ট পদ্ধতিটিই নিরাপত্তার ক্ষেত্রে অধিকতর কার্যকর ও বহুল ব্যবহৃত পদ্ধতি।"},{"question":"සෛලය යනු කුමක්ද?","answer":"සෛල යනු සියළුම ජීවීන්ගේ මූලික ව්‍යුහමය, කෘත්‍යමය සහ ජෙෙවීය ඒකක වේ. ජීවයේ කුඩාම ඒකකය වන සෙෙලයට ස්වාධීනව ප්‍රතිවලිත වීමේ හැකියාව පවතීින අතර, සෙෙලය \\"ජීවයේ තැනුම් ඒකකය\\" ලෙසද හැඳින්වෙි. සෙෙල පිළිබඳව හැදෑරීම සෙෙල ජීව විද්‍යාව නම් වේ.පටලයකින් ආවරණය වූ සෛලප්ලාස්මයකින් සෙෙල සමක්විත වේ. ඒ තුල ප්‍රෝටීන හා න්‍යෂ්ටික අම්ල වැනි විවිධ ජීව අණු රැසක් අන්තර්ගතය. ජීවීන් ප්‍රධාන වශයෙන් ඒකසෛලීය (එක් සෙෙලයකින් පමණක් සමන්විත ජීවීන්; බැක්ටීරියාවන්) හා බහුසෛලීය (ශාක සහ සතුන්) වශයෙන් කොටස් දෙකකට වර්ගීකරණය කල හැකි වේ. ශාක සහ සතුන්ගේ දේහ තුල අන්තර්ගත වන සෙෙල සංඛ්‍යාව ජීව විශේෂයෙන් විශේෂයට වෙනස් වේ. පරිණත මිනිස් දේහයක් තුල සෙෙල ට්‍රිලියන 100 ක් පමණ ඇතැයි සැළකෙයි. බොහොමයක් ශාක සහ සත්ව සෙෙල දැකගත හැකි වන්නේ අන්වීක්ෂ භාවිතයෙන් පමණක් වන අතර, සෙෙල වල විශාලත්වය මයික්‍රොමීටර 1 - 100 ත් අතර පමණ වේ.සෙෙලය ප්‍රථම වරට සොයාගන්නා ලද්දේ 1665 වසරේදී රොබට් හුක් විසිනි. 1839 වසරේදී මුල්ම වරට සෙෙල වාදය, මතායස් ජේකොබ් ශ්ලයිඩන් සහ තියඩෝර් ශ්වාන් විසින් දියුණු කොට, සියළුම ජීවීන් සමන්විත වන්නේ තනි සෙෙලයකින් හෝ සෙෙල විශාල ගණනකින් බවත්, එම සෙෙල ඇතිවන්නේ පෙර පැවති සෙෙල වලින් බවත්, ජීවියෙකුගේ ජෙෙවීය ක්‍රියාවලීන් සෙෙල තුල සිදුවන බවත්, සියළුම සෙෙල තුල එහිලා වූ කෘත්‍යයන් පාලනය කිරීම සඳහා සහ තොරතුරු ඊලඟ පරම්පරාවේ සෙෙල වෙත සම්ප්‍රේෂණය කිරීමට අදාල ප්‍රවේණික තොරතුරු අන්තර්ගත වන බවත් ප්‍රකාශ කරන ලදී. මීට වසර බිලියන 3.5 කට පමණ පොරාතුව, පෘතුවිය මත මුල්ම සෙෙලය ඇතිවන්නට ඇතැයි විශ්වාස කෙරේ."},{"question":"Iwadii bẹrẹ lori awọn mẹta ti wọn yin Stephen lọrun pa, ti wọn tun ji mọto ẹ lọ l’Ekoo","answer":"Titi dasiko yii lawọn eeyan ṣi n daro iku gigbona tawọn afurasi adigunjale mẹta kan, Ọladimeji, ẹni ogun ọdun, Sodiq Taiwo, ẹni ọdun mẹtalelogun ati Rilwan Nasiru, ẹni ọdun mẹtadinlọgbọn, fi pa awakọ ileeṣẹ UBER, Stephen Oluwaniyi. Niṣe ni wọn yin ọkunrin naa lọrun pa, wọn si tun gbe mọto ẹ lọ, kọwọ too ba wọn.Ba a ṣe gbọ, ọjọ kẹfa, oṣu kẹsan-an, ta a wa yii niṣẹlẹ ibanujẹ naa waye, lagbegbe Mẹiran, lọna marosẹ Sango si Eko.Ninu alaye ti afẹsọna oloogbe naa ṣe nigba to lọọ fẹjọ sun ni teṣan ọlọpaa, o ni akẹkọọ-gboye ni ololufẹ oun, ẹkọ nipa iṣẹ dokita lo ka ni fasiti, ṣugbọn airiṣẹ lo mu ko ṣi maa fi ọkọ ayọkẹlẹ rẹ ṣiṣẹ pẹlu ileeṣẹ UBER, ti wọn n ṣeto irinajo fawọn eeyan l’Ekoo. Nọmba ọkọ naa ni LAGOS KSF 830 GX.O ni ẹnikan lo pe e lori aago pe oun fẹẹ haaya ọkọ, ko waa gbe oun, lọkunrin naa ba lọ gẹgẹ bo ṣe maa n lọ tẹlẹ, laimọ pe ajo alọọde lo n lọ. Nigba to ki Stephen pada sile, ti wọn ko ri i ni wọn bẹrẹ si i wa a kaakiri, ki wọn too kan oku ẹ nisalẹ biriiji marosẹ to wa l’Abule Ẹgba.Alukoro ileeṣẹ ọlọpaa Eko ni iwadii awọn fihan pe niṣe ni wọn kọkọ yin ọkunrin naa lọrun, ti wọn si ju oku ẹ latoke sisalẹ biriiji naa.Bawọn ọlọpaa ṣe gbọrọ yii lawọn ọtẹlẹmuyẹ ti fọn sigboro, ọjọ kẹta, iyẹn ọjọ Wẹsidee, lọwọ ba awọn amookunsika ẹda mẹtẹẹta nibi ti wọn sa pamọ si, ni wọn ba fi pampẹ ofin gbe wọn. Lẹyin naa ni wọn jẹwọ ibi ti wọn gbe mọto ẹni ẹlẹni si, wọn si jẹwọ pe loootọ awọn lawọn pa oloogbe naa, wọn ni mọto ẹ lawọn fẹẹ ji, ṣugbọn o ba awọn ṣagidi ni.Kọmiṣanna ọlọpaa ipinlẹ Eko, Hakeem Odumosu, ti ni ki iwadii bẹrẹ lori awọn afurasi ọdaran naa, iwadii naa si ti bẹrẹ ni Panti, Yaba, lẹka ileeṣẹ ọtẹlẹmuyẹ, ti wọn taari wọn si."},{"question":"கேள்வி :  \\"சிலை மேல் எழுத்து போல\\"  -இப்பழமொழி விளக்கும்  பொருள்  யாது ?","answer":"பதில்:  பழமொழியின்  பொருள்:   சிறுவயதில் கற்கும் அறக்கருத்துகள் சிலைமேல் எழுத்து போல் மனதிலே நிலைத்து நின்று நம் வாழ்வை வழி நடத்தும்."},{"question":"ਗਰਮ ਪਾਣੀ ਪ੍ਰਾਪਤ ਕਰਨ ਲਈ ਸੂਰਜੀ ਪਾਣੀ ਹੀਟਰ ਦਾ ਉਪਯੋਗ ਕਿਸ ਦਿਨ ਨਹੀਂ ਕਰ ਸਕਦੇ ?(a) ਧੁੱਪ ਵਾਲੇ ਦਿਨ(b) ਬੱਦਲਾਂ ਵਾਲੇ ਦਿਨ(c) ਗਰਮ ਦਿਨ(d) ਪੌਣ ਵਾਲੇ ਦਿਨ ।","answer":"(b) ਬੱਦਲਾਂ ਵਾਲੇ ਦਿਨ ।"},{"question":"Waa imisa qaybood tawxiidku maxayse kala yihiin?","answer":"Tawxiidka waxaa loo qaybiyaa:-3-saddex qaybood oo kala ah (qeexidda magacyada tawxiidka ee kala duwan waxaad ka fahmi suáalaha ku xiga);-1. Tawxiidu rubuubiya= Rabbinimada2. Tawxiidu Uluuhiya= Ilaahnimada3. Tawxiidu al-asmaa wa-sifaat."},{"question":"Що таке стабілізуючий добір?","answer":"За відносно стабільних умов середовища стабілізуючий добір елімінує (усуває) всі крайні відхилення як непристосовані і зберегає середнє значення ознаки - норму, яка встановилася раніше і пристосованість якої вже доведена результатом попереднього добору. Це консервативна форма добору, яка зменшує мінливість ознаки, звужує норму реакції, підтримує стабільність фенотипу і не сприяє еволюційним змінам.  Учення про стабілізуючий добір розробив І.І. Шмальгаузен (1884-1963). Дію стабілізуючого добору можна пояснити на багатьох прикладах. Так, після снігопаду і сильних вітрів у Південній Америці було знайдено 136 оглушених і напівживих домових горобців (Passeter domesticus). У лабораторії 72 з них вижили, а 64 загинули. Ті, що загинули, мали або дуже довгі, або дуже короткі крила, а ті, що вижили, - середні, \\"нормальні\\" крила. Стабілізуюча форма добору у природних популяціях діє повсюдно. Одним із непрямих доказів цього є той факт, що переважна більшість особин у популяції має середнє значення ознаки. Стабілізуючий добір діє у тісному взаємозв'язку з рушійною формою добору. Так, до промислової революції стабілізуючий добір усував з популяції темних метеликів, а в індустріальних умовах той самий добір усуває світлу форму з популяції метеликів-меланістів."},{"question":"Slutför den här frasen: Världsmästerskapen i skidflygning hålls vartannat år. I motsats till världsmästerskapen i nordisk skidsport hålls de vid jämna årtal. Första världsmästerskapen i skidflygning avgjordes i Planica 1972 och sedan 2004","answer":"finns dessutom en lagtävling."},{"question":"Apakah maksud 'manis mulutnya bercakap seperti santan manisan, di dalam bagai empedu'?","answer":"Ia bermaksud perkataan yang lemak manis biasanya berisi tipu semu di dalamnya"},{"question":"Awọn tọọgi kọlu awọn ọdọ to n ṣewọde SARS l’Oṣogbo, wọn ṣa wọn ladaa yannayanna","answer":"Ọrọ ifẹhonuhan tako SARS niluu Oṣogbo, di wahala laaarọ ọjọ Abamẹta, Satide, opin ọsẹ yii, nigba ti awọn tọọgi kan ya bo wọn, ti wọn si bẹrẹ si i ṣa wọn ladaa.Orita Ọlaiya ni wahala ti bẹrẹ, ti gbogbo awọn olugbe agbegbe naa si n sa kijokijo kaakiri fun ẹmi wọn.Mẹta lara awọn ọmọ to n fi ẹhonu han yii ni ada ba, ọkan lara wọn, Ọlatokun Oloyede, si ṣeṣe lori.Bi awọn tọọgi ọhun ṣe pitu ọwọ wọn tan, ti wọn si lọ, lawọn olufẹhonuhan ọhun pada bọ sita lọpọ yanturu si i, ti wọn si pinnu pe wahala ṣẹṣẹ bẹrẹ ni."},{"question":"Neefta wax nooga faahfaahi.","answer":"Neefta(Asthma).Neefta waa xaalad caafimaad oo muddo-dheer saameysa marinnada hawada. Waxay sababtaa barar iyo ciriiri taas oo xaddideysa isku socodka hawada ee sambabada.Si aad u fahamto cudurka neefta, waxaa lagama maarmaan ah in wax yar aad ka fahamto waxa dhaca markaad neefsaneyso.Caadi ahaan, neef kasta oo aad qaadatid waxay martaa sankaaga ama afkaaga waxayna hoos ugu dhaadhacdaa hungurigaaga iyo marinnadaada neefta, ugu dambayntiina waxay gaaraysaa sambabadaada.Waxaa jira marinno haweedyo badan oo yar yar oo sanbabadaada ku dhaxyaalla kuwaas oo kaa caawiya in oksijiinta hawada ka soo baxda ay gaarsiiso dhiiggaaga.Astaamaha neefta waxay imaaddaan markii dahaarka marinnada hawadu maraan ay bararaan ka dibna muruqyada yar yar ee ku hareeraysan ay adkaadaan. Waxaa markaas ka dib marinnada hawada buuxinaya  xab, waxaana sii yaraanaya xaddiga hawo ee mari kara meesha.Marka ay sidaasi dhacdo waxaa dareemeysaa neef “qabasho” iyo qufac, waxa kaloo culeys ka dareemaysaa laabta taas oo astaan u ah cudurka neefta.Calaamadaha neeftaAstaanta ugu caansan ee neefta waa xiiqitaan, oo ah dhawaaq uu qofka sameeyo marka ay neefta ku dhagto.Calaamadaha kale ee neefta waxaa ka mid noqon kara:Qufac, gaar ahaan habeenkii, markaad qosleyso, ama marka aad ordaysoCuleys dhanka laabta ahNeef qabashoHadalka oo kugu adkaadoCabsi la xiriirta in neefta ay kugu dhagtayDaalNuuca cudurka neefta ee aad qabtid ayay ku xirantahy astaamaha aad isku arkayso.Qof kasta oo cudurkan neefta qaba qasab maaha inuu lahaado calaamadaha aan kor kusoo xusnay. Haddii aad u maleyneyso in calaamadaha aad isku aragtay ay calaamad u noqon karaan xaalad sida neefta oo kale, la kulan dhakhtar si aad u xaqiiqsato.Maxaa keena neefta?Xirfadlayaasha caafimaadku wali si sax ah uma oga waxa keena neefta, laakiin arrimaha la xiriira hiddaha iyo deegaanka ayaa labaduba waxay umuuqdaan inay door muhiim ah ka qaataan cudurka neefta.Waxyaabaha  keena neefta waxaa ka mid ah:1. UurkaSida lagu sheegay hal daraasad oo lagu kalsoonaan karo, Sigaar cabista xilliga hooyada ay uurka leedahay waxay u muuqataa inay kordhinayso halista cunugga uurka ku jiro inay ku dhacdo neef waqti dambe oo noloshiisa ka mid ah. Haweenka qaarkood waxay sidoo kale isku arkaan astaamo neef yari ah inta ay uurka leeyihiin.2. CayilkaMaqaal ayaa sheegay in cudurka neefta uu u muuqdo inuu ku badan yahay dadka cayilan marka loo eego dadka aan cayilneyn. Qorayaashu waxay xuseen in daraasad ay sameeyeen ay ku arkeen in carruur horay u cayilneed marka uu miisaankooda hoos u dhacay ay ka yaraadeen astaamaha neefta.3. SigaarkaSigaar cabiddu waxay kicin kartaa astaamaha cudurka neefta, maqaal laga qoray arrintaan ayaa sheegay in neefta, waxyeello u geysato sambabada qofka xataa haddii uusan cabin sigaar, kawarran marka haddii qofka uu sigaar sii cabo, waxaa qofka kusii kordhaaya halista ah inay ku dhacaan cudurro kala duwan oo saameeya sambabada, kuwaas oo saameen ku yeesha neefsashadiisa.4. Bay’adaWaxyaabaha xasaasiyadda keena sida wasakheynta hawada, guriga gudihiisa iyo dibaddiisaba, waxay kicin karaan cudurka neefta.Waxyaabaha bay’ada ka imaada ee kiciya xasaasiyadda neefta waxa ka mida:BoorkaDufta xaywaanaadkaBusta ka imaata nadiifinta guryaha iyo rinjigaInniinaha kasoo baxa cowskaQiiqa baabuurta5. Stress kaStress ka ama walbahaarka wuxuu keeni karaa calaamadaha neefta, Saynisyahannadu sidoo kale waxay heleen caddayn lagu kalsoon yahay oo sheegaysa in neefta ay u badan tahay dadka qaba xaaladaha caafimaadka maskaxda sida niyad-jabka.Daraasado kale ayaa waxay soo jeediyeen in stress ka muddada-dheer uu horseedi karo isbedello keena neefta joogtada ah.6. HiddahaWaxaa jira ilo lagu kalsoon yahay oo sheegaya in neefta ay ku dhacdo qoysaska. Taasoo macneheedu tahay in waalidka haddii uu qabo cudurka neefta ay u gudbi karaan ilmaha.Dhawaan, saynisyahannadu waxay muujiyeen qaar ka mid ah isbedellada hidde-sidaha ee door ka ciyaari kara cudurka neefta.Nuucyada neeftaCudurka neefta waxa uu u dhici karaa siyaabo badan oo kala duwan, laakiin waxyaabaha kiciya inta badan waa isku mid. Waxaa ka mid ah wasakhda hawada ka soo baxda, fayrasyada, dufta xaywaanada, iyo qiiqa sigaarkaNuucyada cudurka neefta waxa ka mid ah:1. Mid bilaabata xilliga caruurnimadaWaa muhiim in cunugga uu helo daryeel caafimaad haddii lagu arko astaamaha neefta, maadaama ay noqon karto mid naftiisa halis ku ah. Dhakhtar ayaa kaala talin kara qaar ka mid ah hababka ugu wanaagsan ee loo maareeyo xaaladda cunuggaaga.Mararka qaarkood, neefta ayaa laga yaabaa inay soo fiicnaato marka uu ilmuhu qaan gaaro. Balse badanaa, waa ay sii jirtaa ilaa uu qofka ka weynaado waa uuna la noolaadaa.2. Mid bilaabata xilliyada dambeNeefta waxay qofka ku dhici kartaa da ‘kasta oo uu jiro. Sida lagu sheegay daraasad la sameeyay 2013, dadka waaweyn waxay uga badan yihiin carruurta inay yeeshaan calaamado joogto ah.Waxyaabaha qaarkood ee saameeya halista cudurka neefta ee xilliga dambe bilaabata waxaa ka mid ah:XasaasiyaddaArrimo la xiriira hormoonnoCayilkaWalbahaarkaSigaar cabidda3. Mid ku xiran xilli gooni ahNeefta nuucaan ah waxa kiciyo waxyaabo qofka u keena xasaasiyad waxyaabahaas oo imaada xilliyo ka mid ah sanadka. Tusaale ahaan, hawada qabow ee xilliga qaboobaha ama iniinaha ka imaada cowska xilliga xagaaga ayaa kicin kara calaamadaha neefta.Dadka qaba neef xilliyadeedka, kaliya ma qabaan neefta xilligaas balse badanaa ma dareemaan astaamo xilliyada kale ee sanadka.Sidee loo daaweeyaa neefta?Daawooyinka cudurka neefta waxay u kala baxaan labo qaybood oo aasaasi ah:1. Daawo deg deg ahDaawooyinkan waa in loo isticmaalaa oo keliya haddii ay jiraan calaamadaha neefta ama “neef qabasho” deg deg ah, Waxay qofka siiyaan gargaar deg deg ah si ay kaga caawiyaan inuu neefsado.Daaweyntaas waxaa ka mid ah:Dhanka dawooyinka waxa la adeegsadaa kuwa la yidhaah sanbabo kala bixiyayaasha(Bronchodilators) sida:1)kuwa wakhtiga kooban hawl gala (short acting beta-2  agonist inhalers) sida Albuterol sidoo kalena loo yaqaan  Salbutamol iyo Terbutaline.walaw ay tahay in laga taxadaro dadka leh xanuunada wadnaha,fiixda gaar ahaan hypothyroidism,macaanka iyo dhiigkarka .2) kuwa loo yaqaan (Anticholinergic drugs ) sida Ipratropium bromide iyo Tiotropium waana kuwo faa'ido u leh in la siiyo bukaanada qaba xanuunada wadnaha kuwaas oo ay halis u tahay in la siiyo dawayiinka aynnu qaybta 1aad ku sheegnay iyo Theophylline oo ah iyana dawo loo adeegsado xanuunada sanbabada ku dhaca sida asthma oo kale  .Markay aadka u darantahay heerka xiiqduna waxa la siiyaa bukaanka dawooyinka (Corticosteriods ) la yidhaah oo maalin leh ah kuwaas oo badanaa la siiyo dadka waawayn hoosna u dhiga ololka(inflammation) hawo mareenka kuwaas oo hoos u dhiga kicitaanka neef qabatinka dawooyinkaasna waxa ka mid ah Fluticasone .)Sidoo kale markay aadka u darantahay waxa la siiyaa bukaanka kuwa wakhtiga dheer hawl gala ee la yidhaahdo (Long acting beta-2 agonist inhalers) sida Salmetarol iyo Formeterol.Dawooyinka kale ee la siiyo xaaladaha ay aadka u darantahay xiiqduna waxa ka mid ah nooca loo yaqaan (Leukotriene modifiers.) sida  Montelukast,Zafirlukast iyo  Zileuton .Dawooyinkaan waxay ku fal galaan daqiiqado gudahood si ay u dabciyaan marinnada hawada ee adkaaday. Waxaa loo qaadan karaa qaab neefsasho ah.Gargaarka deg degga ahHaddii aad u maleyneyso in qof kula joogo oo qabay cudurka neefta ay kusoo kacday neefta, u sheeg inay si kore u fariistaan kuna caawi inay isticmaalaan dawooyinkooda neefsashada. Labo ilaa lix mar ku buufi daawada, Haddii astaamuhu ay sii socdaan in ka badan 20 daqiiqo, mar labaad sii daawada, haddii wareegga labaad ee daawada uusan wax ka tarin, waa inaad ka gaarsiisaa isbitaal si daryeel deg deg ah uu u helo qofka.Haddii aad tahay qof mar walba u baahan inuu isticmaalo daawooyinka deg degga ah, waxa lagama maarmaan ah in dhakhtarka aad weydiisatid nooc kale oo daaweyn ah oo muddo dheer xakamayn karta neefta.2. Dawooyin muddo dheer ahDaawooyinkan, oo maalin walba la qaato, waxay kaa caawinayaan yareynta calaamadahaaga neefta, laakiin ma maareeyaan calaamadaha deg degga ah ee neefta."},{"question":"வினா : காமராசர் எந்த ஆண்டு தமிழக முதல்வரானார்?","answer":"விடை : 1954"},{"question":"Địa danh Mường Lát trong bài thơ \\"Tây Tiến\\" của Quang Dũng, thuộc tỉnh nào?Sài Khao sương lấp đoàn quân mỏi,Mường Lát hoa về trong đêm hơi.","answer":"Mường Lát ở Thanh HoáNhà thơ Quang Dũng, tên thật là Bùi Đình Diệm, sinh năm 1921, quê ở huyện Đan Phượng, Hà Tây, nay là Hà Nội. Sinh ra trong gia đình vừa làm ruộng, vừa buôn bán, Quang Dũng học hết trung học ở Hà Nội, sau năm 1945 thì đi bộ đội.Tây Tiến là bài thơ tiêu biểu, thể hiện sâu sắc phong cách nghệ thuật của nhà thơ, được in trong tập Mây đầu ô. Theo sách giáo khoa Ngữ văn lớp 12 (Nhà xuất bản Giáo dục Việt Nam, 2011), Tây Tiến là đơn vị bộ đội thành lập năm 1947 có nhiệm vụ phối hợp với quân đội Lào bảo vệ biên giới Việt - Lào, Thượng Lào, Tây Bắc Bộ Việt Nam. Địa bàn đóng quân và hoạt động suốt miền núi Tây Bắc từ Châu Mai, Châu Mộc sang Sầm Nứa cho tới miền Tây Thanh Hóa.Chiến sĩ Tây Tiến phần đông là thanh niên Hà Nội, trong đó có nhiều học sinh, sinh viên như Quang Dũng. Họ chiến đấu trong những hoàn cảnh rất gian khổ, thiếu thốn về vật chất, bệnh sốt rét hoành hành dữ dội.Bài thơ nhắc hàng loạt địa danh. Dưới đây là khổ đầu tác phẩm:Sông Mã xa rồi Tây Tiến ơi!Nhớ về rừng núi, nhớ chơi vơi.Sài Khao sương lấp đoàn quân mỏi,Mường Lát hoa về trong đêm hơi.Theo chú giải của sách giáo khoa, Sài Khao (còn gọi là Mường Sài) thuộc tỉnh Sơn La; Mường Lát thuộc tỉnh Thanh Hoá. Hiện, Mường Lát là huyện vùng cao biên giới nằm ở tận cùng phía Tây Thanh Hoá"},{"question":"What is Colombo's historical significance?","answer":"Colombo, the capital of Sri Lanka, boasts a rich history dating back to ancient times when it served as a trading hub for various civilizations, including Arab, Indian, and Chinese merchants. Its historical significance is highlighted by landmarks like the Old Dutch Hospital and the colonial-era architecture in the Fort area."},{"question":"كمل الفقرة:ومنذ غزو قبرص 27هـ/649م وما تلاه من أحداث تشجع المسلمون على ركوب البحر واحتاجوا لإنشاء الأساطيل، ويُعلل ابن خلدون (ت 808هـ/1406م) هذا الأمر -في ‘المقدمة‘- بقوله: \\"والسّبب في ذلك أنّ العرب لبداوتهم لم يكونوا مهرة في ثقافته وركوبه، والرّوم والإفرنجة لممارستهم أحواله.. مرنوا عليه وأحكموا الدّارية بثقافته، فلمّا","answer":"استقرّ الملك للعرب وشمخ سلطانهم وصارت أُمم العجم.. تحت أيديهم، وتقرّبَ كُلّ ذي صنعة إليهم بمبلغ صناعته، واستخدموا من النَّوَاتية (= الملّاحين) في حاجاتهم البحريّة أمماً، وتكرّرت ممارستهم للبحر وثقافته؛ استحدثوا بُصَراء بها فشَرِهوا إلى الجهاد فيه، وأنشؤوا السُّفن فيه.. وشحنوا الأساطيل بالرّجال والسّلاح\\"."},{"question":"இந்திய அரசியமைப்பு நடைமுறைக்கு வந்த ஆண்டு? \\t1. 19422. 19503. 19454. 1947","answer":"2. 1950"},{"question":"නව්‍යකරණයේ ඉහළම සමාගම ලෙස වර්තමාන ලෝකයේ සැලකෙන්නේ කවර සමාගමද?","answer":"නව්‍යකරණයේ ඉහළම සමාගම ලෙස වර්තමාන ලෝකයේ සැලකෙන්නේ ඇපල් සමාගමය."},{"question":"لماذا خلق الله النجوم؟","answer":"خلقها لثلاث: زينة للسماء، ورجوماً للشياطين وعلامات يهتدى بها في البر والبحر."},{"question":"Nitori pe wọn ṣepolongo fun Tinubu, ẹgbẹ APC le ọmọ ẹgbẹ wọn meji danu l’Ekiti","answer":"Nitori pe wọn dara pọ mọ SWAGA, iyẹn ẹgbẹ to n ṣepolongo fun Aṣiwaju Bọla Ahmed Tinubu, ẹgbẹ APC ipinlẹ Ekiti ti fi ọwọ osi juwe ile fun meji ninu awọn ọmọ ẹgbẹ oṣelu wọn, Ọgbẹni Kayọde Adetifa ati Jide Ọṣọ, lati Wọọdu kẹsan-an laduugbo Owaye, niluu Ayede-Ekiti, nijọba ibilẹ Ọyẹ.SWAGA lorukọ ẹgbẹ kan ti wọn da silẹ lati ṣe ipolongo fun Aṣiwaju Bọla Ahmed Tinubu lọdun 2023, ti wọn si ṣabẹwo sipinlẹ Ekiti laipẹ yii, ni pataki ju lọ, awọn ọmọ ẹgbẹ APC.Ẹ oo ranti pe ahesọ kan ti n ja ranyin pe Gomina Kayọde Fayẹmi naa n gbero lero lati dije dupo aarẹ lọdun 2023 yii kan naa.Ṣaaju ni ẹgbẹ naa ti kọkọ yọ alaga Wọọdu kẹjọ nijọba ibilẹ Ado-Ekiti, Ọgbẹni Clement Afọlabi, nipo lori ẹsun kan naa.Iwe idaduro yii lo wa ninu lẹta meji ọtọọtọ ti Abejide Ṣọla, Alaga APC Wọọdu kẹjọ atawọn oloye ẹgbẹ mi-in buwọ lu.Lẹta naa, ti wọn kọ lọjọ kọkanlelọgbọn, oṣu karun-un, ọdun yii, ka lapa kan pe: “A ri i ninu iṣe ati ihuwasi rẹ pe o n ṣiṣẹ ta ko ibaṣepọ ẹgbẹ wa, ni pataki ju lọ, nipinlẹ Ekiti, eyi to buru ju ni pe o da ẹgbẹ kan silẹ to o pe ni “SWAGA” laarin Wọọdu kẹsan ni ilu Ayede-Ekiti.“Latari eyi, gbogbo igbimọ olori ati alaṣẹ wọọdu yii ti fọwọ si i lati juwe ọna ita fun ẹ ninu ẹgbẹ APC, tori pe o ṣiṣẹ ta ko ilọsiwaju ẹgbẹ wa.Nigba to n sọrọ lori iṣẹlẹ yii, Alukoro fun eto iroyin ẹgbẹ APC nipinlẹ Ekiti, Ọnarebu Ade Ajayi, sọ pe awọn meji naa ti ẹgbẹ le danu ṣẹ sofin ni, igbesẹ wọn si le fa iyapa ati ẹlẹyamẹya laarin ẹgbẹ naa. Ṣugbọn o ni ki i ṣe nitori SWAGA lawọn fi le wọn."},{"question":"السؤال: ما اسم النبيّ الذي آمن به جميع قومه؟      ","answer":"  الجواب: نبيّ الله يونس عليه السلام."},{"question":"Iphone X genel bilgiler","answer":"iPhone X (iPhone Ten), Apple tarafından üretilen ve 2017 yılında piyasaya sürülen bir akıllı telefondur. iPhone X, iPhone serisinin 10. yıl dönümü için özel olarak tasarlanmıştır. İşte iPhone X hakkında genel bilgiler:Ekran:iPhone X, 5.8 inç büyüklüğünde Super Retina OLED ekranı ile gelir. Ekran, yüksek kontrast oranı, canlı renkler ve HDR (High Dynamic Range) özellikleri sunar.Tasarım:iPhone X, ön yüzü neredeyse tamamen ekranla kaplı bir tasarıma sahiptir. Kenarlarda ve üst çerçevede minimal bir çerçeve bulunur, alt kısımda ise fiziksel bir ana ekran düğmesi yer almaz.Face ID:iPhone X, geleneksel parmak izi okuyucu Touch ID'nin yerine Face ID adı verilen yüz tanıma teknolojisini kullanır. Bu, kullanıcının yüzünü tanıyarak telefonu kilidini açmasına ve ödemeleri onaylamasına olanak tanır.İşlemci:iPhone X, Apple'ın kendi tasarladığı A11 Bionic çipsetini kullanır. Bu, daha hızlı performans, enerji verimliliği ve yapay zeka uygulamaları için özel bir işlem birimi sağlar.Kamera:Arka tarafta çift kamera sistemi bulunur: 12 MP geniş açılı ve telefoto lens. Gelişmiş görüntü işleme ve optik görüntü stabilizasyonu özellikleri vardır. Ayrıca, ön kamera 7 MP çözünürlüğünde ve TrueDepth teknolojisi ile geliştirilmiştir.Kablosuz Şarj:iPhone X, kablosuz şarj özelliği ile gelir. Qi kablosuz şarj standartlarını destekler.iOS Sürümü:İlk çıktığında iOS 11 işletim sistemiyle gelmiştir. Ancak, zamanla yeni iOS sürümleri ile güncellenmiştir.Depolama Seçenekleri:iPhone X, 64GB ve 256GB olmak üzere iki farklı depolama seçeneği sunar.Renk Seçenekleri:iPhone X, gümüş ve uzay grisi olmak üzere iki farklı renk seçeneği sunar.iPhone X, Apple'ın inovatif tasarım ve teknolojiyi bir araya getirdiği bir üründür. Ekranın büyüklüğü, yüz tanıma teknolojisi, gelişmiş kamera özellikleri ve kablosuz şarj gibi özelliklerle dikkat çekmiştir. Ancak, bu model daha sonra iPhone XS ve iPhone XR modelleriyle yerini almıştır."},{"question":"Terjemahkanlah penggalan teks Bahasa Jawa yang disadur dari kumpulan cerita anak dunia berikut ke teks dalam Bahasa Indonesia.\\"Ayo dolan karo aku, Nga,\\" ajake Kethek. \\"Akeh-akehan mangan gedhang.\\" LAP! LAP! Kethek ngemplok gedhang. \\"\\"Emoh,\\"\\" wangsulane Singa. \\"Mengko aku kalah.\\"Terjemahan:\\"","answer":"Terjemahan dari penggalan teks Bahasa Jawa tersebut dalam Bahasa Indonesia adalah:\\"Hai, Singa, ayo sini main denganku!\\" ajak Monyet. \\"Bagaimana kalau kita adu siapa yang bisa makan pisang lebih banyak?\\" Swish, swish, swish! Suara monyet begitu gesitnya melahap pisangnya. \\"Aku tidak ingin bermain,\\" jawab Singa. \\"Nanti aku kalah.\\""},{"question":"Tôi thường chăm sóc da ngay sau khi tắm vào khoảng 18-19h, nhưng thời gian này có phù hợp không vì làn da không cải thiện nhiều?","answer":"Khoảng thời gian 21-23h là khung giờ vàng để da hấp thụ tốt dưỡng chất. Quá trình ngủ là lúc cơ thể và làn da bắt đầu chuyển sang chế độ tự sửa chữa, tái tạo, khôi phục những tổn thương. Đây cũng là thời điểm các dưỡng chất từ sản phẩm chăm sóc da hoạt động hiệu quả nhất.Khi ngủ, cơ thể sản sinh ra một lượng lớn hormone melatonin và cả HGH (the human growth hormone). Hormone melatonin hoạt động giúp cơ thể chống lại những tổn thương trên da bằng cách thay thế tế bào chết hoặc hư hại bằng tế bào mới. Còn hormone HGH chịu trách nhiệm phối hợp và thúc đẩy quá trình phục hồi tái tạo tế bào da.Ngoài ra, trong quá trình ngủ, làn da không phải tiếp xúc với những tác nhân xấu như lớp trang điểm, môi trường ô nhiễm, tia UV... Do đó, buổi tối là khoảng thời gian hoàn hảo để áp dụng các bước chăm sóc da đầy đủ như tẩy trang, rửa mặt, tẩy da chết, toner, mặt nạ cấp ẩm, serum, chống lão hóa, dưỡng trắng, điều trị mụn.Từ 23h đến 4h sáng, các tế bào mới có thể được sản sinh gấp đôi. Nếu ngủ sâu trong khoảng thời gian này, cơ thể sẽ thu được một lượng lớn các tế bào thay thế tế bào già.Những ngày đi ngủ sớm, bạn sẽ thấy da trông khỏe hơn, tươi tắn hơn, các lỗ chân lông thu nhỏ, da tiết ít dầu hơn. Quan trọng hơn, những vết ửng đỏ thường thấy ở làn da nhạy cảm sẽ giảm hẳn."},{"question":"පරිගණක සිසිලනය යනු කුමක්ද?","answer":"පරිගණක සිසිලනය යනු පරිගණක උපාංගවලින් තාපය ඉවත් කිරීමේ ක්‍රියාවලියයි. පරිගණක සිසිල්කරණ විධි රාශියකි. පරිඝනකයේ ධාරිතාව, අවට පරිසර තත්ව මත අදාල පරිගණකය සඳහා සිසිල්කරණ පද්ධති තෝරාගනි.පරිගණක පද්ධතිය තුළ උපාංග මගින් මෙහෙයුමක් අතරතුරදී විශාල ප්‍රමාණයකින් තාපය උත්පාදනය වේ. මෙයට මධ්‍යම සැකසුම් ඒකක, චිප් සමූහය හා දෘඩ ධාවක සමග රූපක පත්‍ර (Graphics card) ඇතුළත් වන නමුත් ඊට පමණක් සීමා නොවේ. මෙම උපාංග ඒවායෙහි ස්ව ආරක්ෂක උෂ්ණත්වවල රඳවා තබා ගැනීමට මෙම තාපය විසුරුවා හැරිය යුතුය. එමෙන්ම විවිධ නිෂ්පාදන ක්‍රම හා අතිරේක කොටස් භාවිතාකර ගනිමින් උපාංගවල තාපය ආරක්ෂාකාරී මට්ටමක රඳවා ගනී. ප්‍රධාන වශයෙන් මෙය සිදුකරනුයේ තාපය මුක්ත කරන පෘෂ්ඨික වර්ගඵලය වැඩි කරගැනීමට තාප ගිල්ලුම් ද , පරිගණක කොටස් මගින් රත් වූ වාතය අවට සිසිල් වාතය හා හුවමාරුවීම සීඝ්‍ර කිරීමටද පංකා භාවිතයෙන් ද සමහරක් අවස්ථාහිදී මෘදු සිසිලනය මගින් ද පරිගණක කො‍ටස් අවකරණයෙන් තාප ජනනය කිරීම අඩු කිරීම වැනි ක්‍රම වලිනි. අධිකව රත් වුණු කොටස් කෙටි උපරිම ආයු කාලයක් පෙන්නුම් කරන අතර නිතර නිතර දෝෂ ඇතිවී පද්ධතිය තුළ ක්‍රියා විරහිත වීම හෝ බිඳවැටීම් හට ගනී."},{"question":"Fanontaniana: Avy aiza no miposaka ny masoandro? Valiny:","answer":"Avy any atsinanana no miposaka ny masoandro. "},{"question":"Hãy đặt một tiêu đề phù hợp với đoạn văn sau: Các phương thức xét tuyển này gồm: xét theo kết quả học tập bậc THPT (mã phương thức xét tuyển 200), xét theo kết quả đánh giá năng lực do ĐHQG Hà Nội tổ chức năm 2022 (mã 402), xét kết hợp chứng chỉ quốc tế với kết quả thi tốt nghiệp THPT (mã 409), xét kết hợp chứng chỉ quốc tế với kết quả học tập bậc THPT (mã 410) và xét kết hợp giải học sinh giỏi với kết quả thi tốt nghiệp THPT (mã 500). Đại học Thương mại lưu ý, từ ngày 2/8/2022, thí sinh cần đăng nhập theo tài khoản đã được trường cấp khi đăng ký xét tuyển trực tuyến để tải Giấy báo đủ điều kiện trúng tuyển. ","answer":"Điểm chuẩn xét học bạ Đại học Thương mại cao nhất cả nước với 33,5 điểm"},{"question":"１８８８年に電磁波の存在を確認したドイツの物理学者で、周波数の単位にその名を残すのは誰でしょう？","answer":"ヘルツです。"},{"question":"ලෝකයේ වැඩිම ජනගහනයක් සිටින රට කුමක්ද?","answer":"ලෝකයේ වැඩිම ජනගහනයක් සිටින්නේ ඉන්දියාවේය. ඉන්පසුව වැඩි ජනගහනයක් ඇත්තේ චීනය, ඇමරිකා එක්සත් ජනපදය, ඉන්දුනීසියාව සහ පකිස්තානය යන රටවල්වලය. රටවල් දහහතරක (14) මිලියන 100ට වැඩි ජනගහනයක් ඇත. රටවල් අනූ එකක (91) මිලියන 10ට වැඩි ජනගහනයක් ඇත."},{"question":"Шодокондун бүркүтүндөй","answer":"Жулкунуп, жутунуп турган, нысапсыз. Шодокондун бүркүтүндөй эле жутундум (Кыдырмышев)."},{"question":"Manana an'ity teny nakorontana ity ianaosatapVinavinao ilay teny rehefa alamina","answer":"Ilay teny rehefa alamina dia \\"patsa\\""},{"question":"Apakah jawapan untuk teka-teki ini? Apa yang hitam jadi merah dalam air panas?","answer":"Jawapannya ialah udang kerana ia menjadi merah apabila ia dimasak."},{"question":"खालील म्हणीचा मराठीत सुलभ अर्थ सांगा .--गळ्यात पडले झुंड हसून केले गोड","answer":"गळ्यात पडल्यावर वाईट गोष्टी सुद्धा गोड मानून घ्यावे लागते."},{"question":"fenoy ny banga :\\"Voalavo anaty siny, _\\"","answer":"\\"boribory ny lanitra\\""},{"question":"வினா:    தமிழரின் பாரம்பரியமும் தற்காலத்தில் அதன் சீர்கேடுகளும் என்னும் தலைப்பில் கட்டுரை ஒன்று எழுதுக.","answer":"விடை:ஆப்பிள் இன்று இந்திய சந்தையினை வியாபித்து நின்றாலும், சில ஆலயங்களின் பிரசாதம் என்ற அளவுக்கு வந்துவிட்டாலும் அப்பழம் உடலுக்கு நல்லதா என்றால் இல்லை.இறைவன் சில விஷயங்களை மிக அழகாகச் செய்திருக்கின்றான்.குளிர் பிரதேசத்தில் சக்தி கொடுக்கும் காய்கனிகள்,பாலை நிலத்தில் வெப்ப நிலத்தில் சக்தி கொடுப்பவை என அந்தந்தச் சூழலுக்கு ஏற்பப் படைத்திருக்கின்றான்.தமிழ்நாட்டுப் பனை கொடுக்கும் பதனீர் அப்படியானது, அது உடலுக்கு குளிர்ச்சி. இங்கு விளையும் அரிசி முதல் பயிர்வரை இங்கு வாழும் மக்களுக்கும் அவர்களுடைய உடலுக்கும் ஏற்றது. அப்படித்தாம்ம் இருப்பிடச் சூழலிற்கேற்பப் படைப்பப் பட்டுள்ளது.அரேபிய பேரீச்சம்பழம் அந்தச் சூழலுக்கு ஏற்றது, ஒட்டகங்கள் அங்கு தாக்குபிடிக்க படைக்கபட்டிருப்பது போல அங்குவாழும் மனிதருக்கானது அந்த கனி. மிகக்குறைவான அளவில் இருப்பினும் அங்குள்ள மக்களுக்குத் தேவையான சக்தியைத் தரும்படி அமைந்துள்ளது அது. உண்ணூம் போது அதை விழுங்கத் தண்ணீர் குடிக்க வேண்டிய தேவை எழாது. அது வளர்வதற்கும் தண்ணீர் தேவை இல்லை; பாலையிலும் வளரும். ஏனென்றால் அங்கு தண்ணீரே ஒரு அரும் பொருளாகும்!!ஆப்பிள் உடலுக்கு சூடு கொடுக்கும் பழம். குளிர் பிரதேசத்தில் அது விளையும் குளிர்பிரதேச மக்களுக்கான பழம் அது.மா பலா வாழை என விளைவித்து, இங்கு வாழும் ம்க்களுக்குப் பொருத்தமான சரியான பழத்தை இப்பூமி இங்கு விளைவிக்கிறது.இங்கு வெள்ளையன் வரும்வரை எல்லாம் சரியாக இருந்தது, சூடான பூமியில் உடலை மேலும் சூடேற்றி உஷ்ணக் கோளாறுகளான வயிற்றுப் புண், அசீரணம், வயிற்றுப் போக்கு, மலச்சிக்கல், சர்க்கரை நோய், இரத்த அழுத்த நோய், கண்பார்வைக் குறைகள், உடல் வலுக் குறைவு, அதிக உடல் வெப்பத்தால் ஏற்படும் மலட்டுத் தனம் ஆகிய ஐரோப்பிய நோய்களை உருவாக்கும் பழமோ உணவோ இங்கு இல்லை.வெள்ளையன் மிளகை தேடித்தான் வந்தான். வந்தவன் மிளகை வாங்கிவிட்டு சத்தற்றதும் நற்காரம் இல்லாததுமான மிளகாய் வற்றலை விட்டுவிட்டு சென்றான். அது தென் அமெரிக்காவில் இருந்து வந்தது.தக்காளியும் உருளையும் அப்படி வந்ததே. புகையிலையும் அப்படி வந்ததே.இங்கு காரத்துக்கு நல்லமிளகு பயன்படுத்தும் முறையே இருந்தது. உண்டபின் வெற்றிலையோடு மிளகும் பாக்கும் சுண்ணாம்பும் ஏலமும் வைத்தே தாம்பூலம் தரிக்கும் பழக்கம் இருந்தது.வெள்ளையன் சமையலுக்கு வற்றலை கொடுத்தான், வெற்றிலைக்குப் புகையிலைப் பாக்கைக் கொடுத்தான். மிளகை அவன் கொண்டு சென்றான்.கருப்பட்டியும் வெல்லமும் இங்கு இனிப்புக்கான பொருட்களாய் இருந்தன. அவற்றிகுப்பதிலாகச் சீனியினைத் திணித்தான். நாட்டுக் சர்க்கரையும் பனங்கருப்பட்டியும் நிறைந்து வழிந்த சர்க்கரைச் சந்தை மெல்லச் சுருங்கியது; பின்னர் ஏறத்தாழக் காணாம்லே போய் விட்டது!உடலிற்குச் சத்துக்களும் நோய் எதிர்ப்பும் வலைமையும் தரும் பனங்கள், தென்னங்கள் ஆகிய பானங்கள் இருந்த இடத்தை தன்நாட்டு ஒயினாலும், சாராயத்தாலும் இன்னும் எதெல்லாமோ இரசாயன உப்புக் கரைசல்களைக் கொண்டு நிரப்பினான்.தேங்காய் இருந்த இடத்தை எதுவெல்லாமோ பிடித்தது. தேங்காய் எண்ணெய் கொலஸ்ட்ரால் உடையது என்று பயமுறுத்தித் அதற்குப் பதிலாகத் தன்நாட்டுப் பாமாயில் மற்றும் செயற்கை எண்ணெய்களை உணவுல் புகுத்தினான்.மிளகு, அரிசி, கருப்பட்டி, தானியப் பயிர்கள், சிறுதானியங்கள் என்றிருந்த தமிழர் உணவில் புகையிலை, சீனி, மிளகாய் என எதையெல்லாமோ திணித்தான்.நோய்கள் பெருகின.ஆப்பிளை அப்படித்தான் இங்கு பயிரிட்டான். ஆப்பிளை மட்டுமா கொணர்ந்தான்? கேரட், பீட்ரூட் இன்னும் குளிரில் விளையும் பல பயிர்களைக் கொணர்ந்தான். அது அவனுடைய நாட்டு மக்களுக்குச் சரியானவை; நம் நாட்டு மக்களுக்கானவை அல்ல.ஏற்கனவே உஷ்ணத்தில் வாழும் மக்களுக்கு இவை ஏன்? அவை கூடுதல் உஷ்ணத்தை ஏற்றின‌அத்தோடு விட்டானா?அவன் ஏற்படுத்திய உலகபோர்கள் அரிசி தட்டுப்பாட்டை உருவாக்கின. விளைவு தமிழருக்கு சப்பாத்தியும் பரோட்டாவும் அறிமுகமாயின‌.சப்பாத்தி என்பது நெய் சேர்க்காமல் உண்ணகூடா உணவு. ஆம் அதில் உஷ்ணம் அதிகம், அரேபியர் அதை தயிரோடு உண்பர்; வட இந்தியர் நெய்யோடு உண்பர்; தமிழன் அதை உண்ணத் தெரியாமல், மிக அதிகக் காரத்துடன் உண்டான், உடல் வெப்பம் மிக அதிகமாக்கும் இப்பழக்கம்.நோய் பெருகிற்று. அதாவது சூடான பூமியில் சூடு கொடுக்கும் உணவினை உண்டு நம் உடலை நாமே கெடுத்துக் கொண்டோம்.வெள்ளையனின் குளிர்நாட்டில் அரிசி கஞ்சியும், பனங்கள்ளும் குடிக்க சொல்லுங்கள், அவன் குடிப்பானா? குடித்தால் என்னாகும் என அவனுக்குத் தெரியும், அவன் தன் சமூகத்தைக் காத்துகொண்டு நம் சமூகத்தைக் கெடுத்துக் கொண்டிருக்கின்றான்உஷ்ணத்தால் ஏற்படும் நோய்க்கு விஞ்ஞானம் காரணம் சொல்லாது. இங்கு உஷ்ணத்தை கட்டுபடுத்த நல்லெண்ணெய் குளியலும் நெய்யும் இன்னும் பலவும் இருந்தது.எல்லாம் பழமைத் தனம் என ஒழிக்கபட்டன.இன்று கிடைக்கும் எல்லா எண்ணெய்களும் கலப்படம். இப்போதுள்ள தலைமுறை டால்டாவினை நெய் என்றும் கலப்பட எண்ணெயினை சுத்தமான எண்ணெய் எனவும் நம்பிக் கொண்டுள்ளது!!காரணம் அதற்கு உண்மையான பொருளும் மணமும் எப்படி இருக்கும் என்றே தெரியவில்லை; என்ன செய்யும்?எண்ணெயில் கலப்படம், உணவு பொருளில் கலப்படம் , இவை எல்லாம் இன்று ருசி இல்லா உணவை மட்டுமல்ல; ஆரோக்கியமில்லா உணவினை கொடுத்துவிட்டன‌.நெய்யும் பாலும் வெண்ணெயும் போலி என அரசினரின் ஆராய்ச்சிக் கழகங்களே சொல்லும் நிலையென்றால் தனியார் நிலையங்கள் எப்படி இருக்கும்?எதையோ தின்று எதையோ குடித்து, எதையோ புகைத்து, எதையோ மென்று இல்லா நோய்கள் எல்லாவற்றையும் இழுத்துக் கொண்டு விட்டாது தற்காலத் தமிழர் சமுதாயம்!!எதை உண்டாலும் கசப்பாய் முடிப்பது உலகளாவிய உணவு முறையாய் இருந்தது. சீனாவில் தே எனும் கசப்பு பானத்தை அருந்துவார்கள். ஆப்ரிக்காவிலும் அரேபியாவிலும் காப்பி இருந்தது.தமிழனுக்கு வேப்பம்பூத் துவையலும் பாகற்காயும் அன்றாடம் சமையலில் இருந்தது. பாகம் என்றால் சமையல். அதில் இருக்க வேண்டிய காய் பாகற்காய் ஆனதுஇவை முறையாக இருந்தவரை சர்க்கரை நோய் இல்லைபாலில் காப்பி, டீ , சீனி என வெள்ளையன் ஏற்படுத்திய வியாபார தந்திரம் இன்று நம் வாழ்வியல் அங்கமாக மாறிவிட்டது, காபியும் டீயும் பருகியே தீரவேண்டியவை அல்ல‌.அவை இன்றியும் வாழமுடியும். அது போக பேக்கரிகள் வந்து நிரம்பியிருக்கின்றன. வெறும் சக்கை மாவான மைதாவால் தயாரிக்கப் படும் பரோட்டாவும் பேக்கரியும் இன்னும் பலவும் இங்கு ஏற்ற விஷயம் அல்ல.இவை பெருக பெருக மருத்துவ மனைகளும் பெருகுகின்றன. அவை பெருகித் தன்னாட்டு மருந்துக் கம்பெனிகள் வருமானம் பெற வேண்டும் என்பதுதான் அவன் நோக்கம்!இச்சமூகம் எவ்வளவு நல்ல விஷயங்களை நாகரீகம் என இழந்து இன்று சீழ்பிடித்த சமூகமாக மாறிவிட்டது என நினைக்கும் பொழுது இதன் எதிர்காலத்தை நினைத்துத் தலையே சுற்றுகின்றது.ஏகப்பட்ட விஷயங்களை இழந்துவிட்டோம். ஆனால் எதை எல்லாம் இழந்து கொண்டிருக்கிறோம் என்பதை இந்துமத ஆலயங்களிலும் இந்த நாட்டின் பாரம்பரியமான பண்டிகை மற்றும் சடங்குகளிலும் காணலாம்.இந்து தெய்வங்களுக்கு பாரம்பரியமாக படைக்கபடும் பழம், பானம் எல்லாம் உடலுக்கு நல்லவையேதுளசி போல் அருமருந்தில்லை. அங்கு பயன்படும் எலுமிச்சை முதல் எள் வரை எல்லாமே நன்மை கொடுப்பவை. தாம்பூலத் தட்டில் காணப்படும் வெற்றிலை முதல் எல்லாம் ஆரோக்கியமே. தேர்களில் தெய்வங்களுக்கு வீசபடும் மிளமும் உப்பும் உடலுக்கு எக்காலமும் நன்மையே.உங்களுக்கு ஆரோக்கியமான உணவு எது என்று தெரிய வேண்டுமென்றால் இந்துக்களின் உணவினைப் பாருங்கள்.நைவேத்தியம் எனப்படும் உணவு முறையாக தயாரிக்கபடுமானால் அதை விட ஆரோக்கிய உணவு வேறு இல்லை.அசைவத்தில் கூடக் கிராம ஆலயங்களில் உள்ள நடைமுறை விதிகளைக் கவனிக்கலாம். ஆடும் சேவலும் எப்படி இருந்தால் அங்கு பலியிட வேண்டும்; அவற்றாய் எப்படிச் சமைக்க வேண்டும் என்ற விதிகள் உண்டு. அதன்படி உண்டால் அவையும் ஆரோக்கியமே. பிராய்லர் கோழியினை அங்கு வெட்டுவதில்லைசனிகிழமை தோறும் நல்லெண்ணெய் தேய்த்தால் உடல் உஷ்ணம் வராது.அதிகாலை சேவலோடு எழுவதும் அந்தியில் பறவைகள் ஓயும்பொழுது தூக்கத்தை தழுவதும் நோய்க்கு இடம் கொடா.மலைமேல் ஏறித் தெய்வத்தை வணங்குவது, உயர்ந்த மலைக் காற்று மக்களுக்குக் கிடைப்பதற்காகவே. குளிர் ஆறுகளில் குளிப்பதும் ஆரோக்கியமே. மாதம் இருமுறையாவது இருக்கும் விரதம் உடலை வலுபடுத்தும். சீரண மண்டலத்திற்கு ஓய்வு கொடுத்துச் சுத்தப் படுத்தும் ஒரு வழக்கம்.தமிழரின் பாரம்பரிய உணவு, பழக்க வழக்கங்களில் இன்னும் ஏராளமான விஷயங்கள் உண்டு. அவைகள எல்லாம் இழந்ததன் விளைவு நீரிரிழிவு முதல் ஏகபட்ட நோய் ஒருபுறம் பெருகுகின்றன.மறுபுறத்தில் உடல் வலிமைக் குறைவால் கருத்தரிப்பு சிக்கல் சிசேரியன் எனப் படைப்புச் சக்தி மிக்க மெண்ணினம் தனது தன்மையை இழந்து வருகிறது.பழமையினை மீட்டெடுத்து நல்வாழ்வு வாழ இந்துமதம் உதவும். நம் முன்னோரின் நலமான பலமான வாழ்வின் ரகசியம் அங்குதான் புதைந்திருக்கின்றது.அதை மீட்டெடுப்பீர்களாயின் நல்வாழ்வு கிட்டும். மாறாக அதெல்லாம் பழமை என ஒதுக்குவீராயின் டாக்டரும் மருந்துகடைகாரனுமே உங்களுக்கு தெய்வமாவான்.தெய்வ வழிபாட்டுச் சம்பிரதாயம்ங்களையும் அவற்றின் உடல் நலத்தையும் மன நலத்தையும் அந்த உணவு மற்றும் விரத முறைகளை மறந்தவனுக்கு அதுதான் கதி.அப்படி ஒரு பலஹீனமான சமூகமாக இந்தியா உருவாக வேண்டும் என வெள்ளையன் ஆசைபட்டதன் விளைவுதான் இங்கு உருவான இந்து எதிர்ப்பு கோஷ்டிகள்.இந்துமதம் ஒழிய ஒழிய இங்கு நோய் கூடும் என்பதும் இந்தியா தன் மருந்து மற்றும் மருத்துவத்தின் வேட்டைகாடாகும் என்பது அக்காலத்தில் இருந்தே அவன் கணக்கு.அது மிளகை திருடி வற்றலை கொட்டுவதில் தொடங்கி இன்றைய கே.எப்.சி வரை தொடர்கின்றதுநாம் பாரம்பரியத்தை மீட்டெடுத்தால் தவிர நம் ஆரோக்கியத்தை திருப்பமுடியாது. அந்தப் பாரம்பரியம் இந்து ஆலயங்களின் வழிபாட்டிலும் உணவுப்பழக்கங்களிலும் சமுதாய வாழ்வு நெரிகளிலும் உடை, வீடு, பொருட்கள் ஆகியவற்றின் பயன்பாட்டிலும் இன்னும் பலவற்றிலுமே இருக்கின்றது. என்று அதை இச்சமூகம் உணருமோ அன்றே இங்கு நல் ஆரோக்கியம் திரும்பும்.மாறாக கண்டதையும் உண்டுவிட்டு தெருத் தெருவாக கடற்கரை கடற்கரையாக நடைப் பயிற்சி உடற்பயிற்சி செய்தாலும் ஆகபோவது ஒன்றுமில்லைநடக்க வேண்டியது கோவில்களை நோக்கி, அங்கேதான் இருக்கின்றது உடல் நலத்துக்கான மருந்து"},{"question":"این متن در مورد چه رویداد مهمی صحبت می کند: \\"جمیسون در سال ۱۹۸۷ دوباره جهت پیوستن به ناسا اقدام نمود و از بین ۲٬۰۰۰ متقاضی، برای اولین گروه پانزده نفره فضانوردان پس از انفجار چلنجر، انتخاب گردید.\\"","answer":"این متن در مورد پیوستن جمیسون به ناسا صحبت می‌کند."},{"question":"Tên gọi Đà Nẵng có ý nghĩa gì?","answer":"Theo ngôn ngữ Chăm, \\"Đà Nẵng\\" có thể được giải thích là \\"sông lớn\\", \\"cửa sông lớn\\". Cổng thông tin điện tử thành phố cho biết địa danh này đã được ghi chú trên các bản đồ được vẽ từ thế kỉ XVI trở đi. Điều đó có nghĩa là, từ rất sớm, trong cách hình thành tên gọi, tính chất cửa sông lớn, tính chất cảng thị đã được lưu ý như một điểm quan trọng của thành phố Đà Nẵng.Các hồ và sông lớn xung quanh và trong Đà Nẵng gồm hệ thống sông Vu Gia - Thu Bồn (Quảng Nam), sông Cu Đê và sông Hàn chảy qua thành phố, khu vực đầm phá Tam Giang (Thừa Thiên Huế). Những sông, hồ này tạo thành nguồn nước chính cho khu vực."},{"question":"Hãy đặt một tiêu đề phù hợp với đoạn văn sau: ","answer":"Kẻ cướp tiệm vàng hạ vũ khí, lính bắn tỉa rút khỏi hiện trường"},{"question":"Qual é a população do estado em que o Rio Trinity está localizado?","answer":"29,200,000"},{"question":"Hoàn thiện đoạn văn sau: Sau khi Nhật Bản đầu hàng vô điều kiện ","answer":"vào năm 1945, Thân vương Takamatsu trở thành chủ tịch danh dự của các tổ chức từ thiện, văn hóa và thể thao khác nhau bao gồm Hiệp hội Mỹ thuật Nhật Bản, Hiệp hội Đan Mạch-Nhật Bản, Hiệp hội Pháp-Nhật, Hiệp hội Bệnh phong, Hiệp hội trồng trọt, Hiệp hội bóng rổ Nhật Bản và Hiệp hội phúc lợi Saise. Ông cũng từng là người bảo trợ của Hội Chữ thập đỏ Nhật Bản (ngày nay, Chủ tịch danh dự là Hoàng hậu Michiko) và là người đóng góp chính của NBTHK (Nihon Bijutsu Token Hozon Kyokai). Ông cũng là Chủ tịch danh dự của Ủy ban trù bị thành lập Đại học Cơ đốc giáo quốc tế (ICU) ở Mitaka, Tokyo."},{"question":"ماهي طريقة عمل معمول التمر السعودي؟","answer":"المقاديرلتحضير العجينة:1 ملعقة صغيرة محلب6 ملعقة كبيرة سكر½ كوب زيت نباتي3 كوب دقيقرشة ملح1 كوب أو اكثر حليب سائل او ماء حسب الحاجة اثناء العجن2 كوب زبدة مذوبة او سمن3 كوب سميد ناعملتحضير الحشوة:2 كوب تمر½ ملعقة صغيرة قرفة مطحونة2 ملعقة صغيرة سمسم½ ملعقة صغيرة زيتطريقة التحضير1.    لتحضير العجينة، ضعي في وعاء الدقيق والسميد والسكر والملح والمحلب، واخلطي المكونات الجافة مع بعضها2.    في وعاء صغير، ذوبي الزبدة والزيت معاً ثم اضيفي مزيج المواد الدهنية فوق المكونات الجافة واخلطي بيديك مع الفرك جيداً حتى يتشبع الدقيق والسميد3.    اسكبي الحليب (أو الماء) تدريجياً مع العجن باستمرار للحصول على عجينة طرية وسهلة التشكيل4.    غطي العجينة واتركيها جانباً ترتاح لمدة ساعتين5.    لتحضير الحشوة، اعجني في وعاء التمر جيداً مع السمسم والزيت والقرفة، ثم شكلي عجينة التمر على شكل كرات صغيرة بحجم حبة البندق6.    حمي الفرن على درجة حرارة 180 مئوية7.    ادعكي العجينة مرة واحدة ثمّ شكليها إلى كرات متوسطة الحجم8.    اصنعي فجوة في وسط كل كرة عجينة وضعي بداخلها كرة تمر صغيرة، ثم اغلقي كرة العجين بتأن وروية9.    ضعي العجينة في القالب المخصص بالأقراص واكبسيها بخفة براحة يدك، ثم اضربي القالب بروية على سطح صلب ليخرج منه القرص10.    صفي الأقراص في صينية مع ترك مسافة بينها وادخليها الفرن لمدة 10 دقائق او حتى تنضج ويصبح لونها ذهبياً11.    أخرجي أقراص التمر من الفرن واتركيها لتبرد تماماً، ثم قدميها."},{"question":"சுற்றுச்சூழல் பற்றிய இருநூறு வார்த்தைகள் கட்டுரை வரைக.","answer":"பூமியின் சூழல் பூமியை சூரிய குடும்பத்தில் உயிர் மற்றும் நிலைத்தன்மை சாத்தியமான ஒரே கோளாக ஆக்குகிறது. காலத்தின் தொடக்கத்திலிருந்தே, பூமி கிரகத்தின் அனைத்து மக்களுக்கும் அவர்கள் உயிர்வாழ்வதற்கு தேவையான அனைத்தையும் வழங்கியுள்ளது. மறுபுறம், மனிதர்கள் தங்கள் சுயநலத்திற்காக அனைத்து இயற்கை வளங்களையும் சுரண்டி, பூமியை தரிசு நிலமாக ஆக்கியுள்ளனர்.மனிதர்கள் சுற்றுச்சூழலின் ஒருங்கிணைந்த பகுதியாகும் மற்றும் அவர்களின் சொந்த நலனுக்காகவும், தாவரங்கள் மற்றும் விலங்குகள் உட்பட கிரகத்தின் அனைத்து மக்களுக்காகவும் வாழ்க்கை நிலைமைகளை பராமரிக்க ஒரு பெரிய பொறுப்பைக் கொண்டுள்ளனர். இயற்கை வளங்கள் மற்றும் ஒட்டுமொத்த சுற்றுச்சூழலின் சமநிலை மேலாண்மை அனைத்து உயிரினங்களின் நல்வாழ்விற்கும் முழு உலகத்தின் பொருளாதார வளர்ச்சிக்கும் முக்கியமானது. வளங்களின் பயன்பாட்டை (புதுப்பிக்கத்தக்க மற்றும் புதுப்பிக்க முடியாதவை) திறம்பட நிர்வகிப்பது, வளங்களில் குறைந்தபட்சம் ஒரு பகுதியையாவது உரிமை கோருவதற்கான அதிகாரத்திற்காக நாடுகள், மாநிலங்கள் மற்றும் மக்களுக்கு இடையே உள்ள பல சர்ச்சைகளைத் தீர்க்க உதவும். சுற்றுச்சூழலின் ஆரோக்கியம் இன்றியமையாதது என்பதை மக்கள் புரிந்து கொள்ள வேண்டிய நேரம் இது, சுற்றுச்சூழல் ஆரோக்கியமாக இருந்தால் மட்டுமே அனைத்து உயிரினங்களும் வாழ வாய்ப்புள்ளது."},{"question":"請回答這個問題：美國文化中的「伍德斯托克音樂節」是什麼？","answer":"答案：伍德斯托克音樂節是1969年在紐約州伍德斯托克舉辦的一場著名音樂盛事"},{"question":"Ao amin'ny vondrona mpianatra, misy Anna, Bob ary Carol. I Anna no mahay matematika, i Bob no mahay siansa, ary i Carol no mahay teny frantsay.Inona no azontsika tsoahina avy amin’ireo fanambarana etsy ambony ireo?A. Bob no tsara indrindra amin'ny teny frantsay.B. Carol no tsara indrindra amin'ny siansa.D. Anna no tsara indrindra amin'ny matematika.E. Carol no mahay matematika.","answer":"Ny valiny marina dia D. Anna no tsara indrindra amin'ny matematika."},{"question":"Rumor has it that 3.72 గ్రాములు /సెం.మీ3 is the answer to అల్యూమినియం ఆర్సనైడ్ సాంద్రత ఎంత?","answer":"అల్యూమినియం ఆర్సెనైడ్ ఆరెంజిరంగు స్పటికరూపంలో ఏర్పడి ఉండును.అల్యూమినియం ఆర్సెనైడ్ అణుభారం 101.9031 గ్రాములు/మోల్. 25°C ఉష్ణోగ్రత వద్ద అల్యూమినియం ఆర్సెనైడ్ సాంద్రత 3.72 గ్రాములు /సెం.మీ3. నీటిలో కరుగదు"},{"question":"آیا از سازنده ساختمان می‌توان آپارتمان بخریم یا حتماً باید مالک ضمن موافقت قرارداد را امضاء کند؟","answer":"این سؤال بسیار مهم و جنبه حیاتی دارد. اگر قصد خرید یا پیش‌خرید آپارتمانی را از یک ساختمان دارید و فروشنده آن سازنده همان ساختمان است حتماً به دو موردتوجه کنید، اول این‌که واحدها بین ملک و سازنده تقسیم‌شده باشد و در قرارداد مشارکت یا جداگانه تقسیم‌نامه تنظیم کرده باشند دوم اینکه سازنده حق فروش داشته باشد و اینکه آیا برای فروش شرطی گذاشته‌شده یا خیر. برای مثال ممکن است در قرارداد مشارکت شرط شده، سازنده بعد از ۸۰ درصد پیشرفت یا بعد از مرحله سفت‌کاری حق فروش یا پیش‌فروش واحدهای خود را دارد. اگر این موارد رعایت نشود، مالک می‌تواند از طریق دادگاه ابطال مبایعه‌نامه فی‌مابین سازنده و پیش خریدار را بخواهد."},{"question":"四国４県の県名に使われている漢字８文字の内、２文字を組み合わせてできる、本州にある県は何県？","answer":"愛知県（愛媛の愛と高知の知）です。"},{"question":"සූෆිගේ උපමා  කතා  ඔබ දන්නවද ?ඔබ දන්නා  සූෆිගේ උපමා  කතා වක් කියන්න.","answer":"මම සූෆිගේ උපමා  කතා  කිහිපයක්ම දන්නවා .මේ ඉන් එක කතාවක්.කතාවේ නම  \\"බලවන්තයා \\".හමුදාවක එක් ජනරාල්වරයෙක් තම කණ්ඩායමෙන් වෙන් ව වල්මත් වී රට හරහා යන්නේ එක් කුඩා ගමකට ආවේය. ඔහු යායුතු මග සොයා ගත නොහැකිව සිටියද තම තත්වය අමතක කර සිටියේ නැත.ගැමියෝ ඔහු වටා රොක් වූහ. ඔහු අණ දුන්නේය. තම අශ්වයාට ආහාර දෙන්නැයි ඔහු ගැමියන්ට අණ දුන්නේය. ඔවුන් ඒ අණ පිළිපැද්දේ නැත. අශ්වයා සඳහා ස්තාලයක් පිළියෙල කරන්නැයිද තමාට ජලය හා පොරෝණා සපයන්නැයිද ඔහු නියෝග කළේය. ඒත් කිසිවෙක් ඔහු කී දේ කරන්නට ඉදිරිපත් නොවූහ.‘නුඹලා මේ මොහොතේ ම මගේ අණ පිළිපැද්දේ නැති නම් මම නුඹලාට දැඩි දඬුවම් පමණුවනවා’ ජනරාල්වරයා රැුස්ව සිටි පිරිසට තර්ජනය කරමින් මොර දුන්නේය.ගැමිනායකයා මෙහිදී ඉදිරියට ආවේය. ‘‘මට පෙනෙන්නෙ නෑ ඔහේ එච්චර බලවන්තයෙක් කියල. ඉතින් ඔහේ කොහොමද ඒ වගේ දෙයක් අපට කරන්නෙ’’ ඔහු ජනරාල්වරයාගෙන් ඇසීය.ජනරාල්වරයා එයින් වඩාත් කෝපාවිෂ්ට විය. ‘‘මං තමුසෙලට මොකුත් කරනව නෙමෙයි, මං අණ දෙනවා’’ ඔහු දැඩි ස්වරයෙන් කීවේය.‘‘අණ දෙනව කිව්වේ මොකක්ද?’’ ගැමිනායකයා  ඇසීය.‘‘මං කියනව කර්නල්ට, කර්නල් කියනව මේජර්ට, මේජර් කියනවා කපිතන්ට, කපිතන්කියනවා ලූතිනන්ට, ලූතිනන් කියනව සාජන්ට්ට,   සාජන්ට් අරන් එනව භට පිරිසක්. ඇවිත් නුඹලාව බිත්තියක් ඉස්සරහින් පෙළ ගස්සලා වෙඩි තියල මරලා දානව එක පාරින්ම. තේරුණාද?’’ ජනරාල්වරයා ගුගුලේය.දැන් තමයි ඔහේ කියන දේ අපට තේරුණේ. ඔය සාර්ජන්ට් කියන කෙනා නම් ඇත්තෙන්ට ම බලවත් අයෙක් වෙන්න  ඕනෑ. තාමත් අපි දැක්කෙ ඔහෙව විතරයි. අප සාර්ජන්ට්ව මුල ඉඳල ම මුණ ගැහුනා නම් මේ තරම් කරදර වෙන්නෙ නෑ නෙ.’’ ගැමිනායකයා කීවේය."},{"question":"Zer da eguzki sistema?","answer":"Eguzki sistema eguzkiaren inguruan biratzen duten planeta, asteroide, satelite eta beste objektu kosmiko batzuen multzoa da."},{"question":"Hãy viết một đoạn văn ít nhất 200 chữ dựa trên nội dung được nói tới trong câu sau: Vợ luôn nghĩ cảm xúc bản thân trước khi để ý tới tôi","answer":"Tôi 33 tuổi, xuất thân trong gia đình khó khăn, tự lực trong con đường học vấn và sự nghiệp, có nhà riêng ở thành phố trước khi quen và cưới vợ. Ngoài công việc chính, tôi yêu thích kinh doanh thêm bên ngoài, cũng gặt hái được những thành tựu nhỏ. Từ sự tính toán làm ăn của tôi, vợ chồng có nhà, có xe và đất đai khác. Tôi luôn tự xác định vai trò trụ cột của mình. Tôi không hút thuốc, không nhậu nhẹt, thích giao lưu với bạn bè thân tình. Bố mẹ và chị gái tôi đong đầy tình cảm, yêu quý, tôn trọng bản ngã và dành nhiều sự quan tâm cho con dâu. Tôi sống tình cảm và cân bằng rất tối mối quan hệ giữa bố mẹ, chị gái với vợ; giữa họ chỉ có niềm vui, không có xung đột. Không những thế, tiếng nói của tôi trong gia đình luôn được mọi người lắng nghe và tôn trọng. Với gia đình ngoại, tôi được ba mẹ và các em vợ yêu mến, được đại gia đình bên vợ tin tưởng và tôn trọng. >> Tôi yêu vợ nhiều nhưng không hiểu được tính cách cô ấy Vợ tôi, 30 tuổi, sinh ra ở thành phố, lao động chân tay vừa đủ để trang trải cho chi phí cá nhân. Sức khỏe yếu nên vợ không làm được những việc nặng, dễ dị ứng thời tiết, không chịu được cuộc sống áp lực dù là về vật chất hay tinh thần. Vợ dễ cáu giận và khó chịu, là người chung thủy nhưng không khéo léo và sâu sắc trong ứng xử với chồng hoặc gia đình chồng. Vợ không bị ràng buộc bất cứ trách nhiệm nào với gia đình chồng trừ khi tự nguyện. Trong thâm tâm, tôi vẫn luôn cảm ơn vợ vì biết em yêu tôi theo cách của em. Tôi chấp nhận việc mình không nhận được sự chia sẻ, gánh vác một phần kinh tế trong cuộc sống dù có những lúc cảm giác một mình gồng gánh mọi thứ rất mỏi mệt. Tôi chưa bao giờ trách cứ vợ điều này vì mỗi người có một năng lực khác nhau. Tôi chấp nhận em sinh ra ở thành phố nên khả năng chịu áp lực trong cuộc sống không như mình, xuất thân từ làng quê nghèo. Tôi cũng không thấy phiền lòng khi vợ có những nhu cầu cá nhân theo xu hướng và thế hệ của giới trẻ. Tôi không trách cứ vợ yếu ớt vì vợ chồng là duyên nợ. Em là vợ và do tôi chọn lựa thì dù thế nào tôi cũng chấp nhận. Ngoài những thứ đó, tôi không phải người ăn nói bỗ bã, không dễ nổi nóng, không thích kiếm chuyện. Niềm vui và đam mê lớn nhất của tôi là những lúc làm được điều gì đó cho gia đình hoặc gặt hái thành tựu nào đó trong sự nghiệp, đầu tư làm ăn. Tôi từng nhiều lần vay mượn tiền bạc khi khó khăn để giải quyết việc gia đình nhưng năm năm cưới nhau chưa từng để vợ phải làm điều đó. Tôi cũng chưa từng để vợ hết tiền mặt trong bất cứ hoàn cảnh nào. Về quản lý tài chính gia đình, trừ các khoản đầu tư làm ăn, tiền sinh hoạt và chi tiêu gia đình, ngay khi có lương là sẽ chuyển khoản cho vợ giữ, chưa bao giờ trì hoãn hay để vợ phải hỏi han về việc này. >> Tính cách trái ngược, sao tôi lại đồng ý làm vợ anh Về phía vợ, tôi biết em tự hào về chồng, biết ơn những gì tôi làm cho em và gia đình. Nhưng bản ngã và tính khí hay khó chịu của em, đi đôi với đó là luôn chỉ muốn \\"nhận\\" từ người bạn đời mà không biết tôi cũng rất muốn được vợ \\"cho đi\\". Vợ thường xuyên trách cứ tôi vô tâm khi thi thoảng có những lý do hết sức nhỏ nhặt và không đáng. Lắm lúc vợ giận dỗi, tôi cảm thấy mệt mỏi và bế tắc, thấy vợ nói yêu mình nhưng thật ra lại ích kỷ, chỉ nghĩ đến cảm giác của bản thân, chẳn nghĩ đến cảm xúc của chồng, biết công việc chồng vất vả nhưng vợ lại không khống chế được cảm xúc của mình. Vợ khiến tôi có cảm giác mình không được mắc sai lầm, chỉ cần có sai lầm là vợ giận dỗi, không khí gia đình căng thẳng. Vợ luôn muốn tôi thấu hiểu và chủ động, không thích để em nhờ vả, dù rằng vợ nhờ điều gì tôi đều làm và không từ chối. Tôi không nghĩ nhịn vợ là hèn, nhưng tư duy của vợ chỉ có vậy, luôn nghĩ đến cảm giác của bản thân trước khi nghĩ cho tôi. Tôi không biết nên góp ý với em ra sao. Nhiều khi tôi rất cô độc và bế tắc trước thái độ của vợ. Văn Độc giả gọi vào số 024 7300 8899 (máy lẻ 4529) trong giờ hành chính để được hỗ trợ, giải đáp thắc mắc"},{"question":"Siapakah pelakon-pelakon  suara untuk filem Hikayat Sang Kancil?","answer":"Pelakon suara untuk filem Hikayat Sang Kancil adalah seperti berikut: Zainab Wahab sebagai Sang Kancil, Sharifuddin Kahar sebagai Sang Kerbau, Mohd Daud Iman sebagai Sang Buaya dan Maharom Ghani sebagai Tikar Buruk"},{"question":"Parí ìròyìn yìí:Eyi le o, lọjọ kan ṣoṣo, Korona paayan mẹta l’ỌyọọGende Ọlọrun mẹta lajakalẹ arun Korona pa lọjọ Iṣẹgun, Tusidee, ọsẹ yii. O tun sọ eeyan mọkandinlaaadọrin (61) mi-in di alaigbadun ara wọn.Eyi jẹ yọ ninu ikede abajade ayẹwo arun Korona ti ajọ NCDC ṣe lọjọ Iṣẹgun, Tusidee.Gẹgẹ bi akọsilẹ esi ayẹwo ọhun, ipinlẹ Eko lawọn ti kokoro arun yii mu lọjọ naa ti pọ ju lọ gẹgẹ bo ṣe saaba maa n waye lojoojumọ. Eeyan mejilelaaadoje (212) ni jagunlabi tun fọwọ ba l’Ekoo lọjọ naa.Ipinlẹ Ọyọ ni Korona ti ṣoṣẹ ju lọ lọjọ naa pẹlu bo ṣe jẹ pe eeyan mọkandinlaaadọrin (69) lo mu nibẹ, nigba ti awọn to mu nipinlẹ Niger to ṣe ipo kẹta ninu akọsilẹ ọjọ Tusidee ọhun jẹ mọkandinlaaadọta (49).","answer":"Bi kokoro arun ti wọn n pe ni COVID-19 yii ṣe n fojoojumọ pọ si i jake-jado orileede yii ni kinni ọhun tubọ n burẹkẹ nipinlẹ Ọyọ tayọ awọn ẹgbẹ ẹ lorileede yii.Lati inu oṣu kẹta ọdun 2020 yii ti ajakalẹ arun Korona ti wọ Naijiria, Ọyọ yii kan naa ni ipinlẹ to tayọ Eko lọjọ kan ri, iyẹn Jimọ ọsẹ to kọja, nigba iye eeyan ti Korona mu ni ipinlẹ Ọyọ lọjọ naa pọ ju Eko to ti maa n wa nipo kin-in-ni ṣaa tẹlẹ lọ.Apapọ eeyan to ti fara kaaṣa kokoro arun yii ni ipinlẹ ọhun bayii ti di bii ẹgbẹrun mẹta. Iyẹn l’Ọyọọ si ̣ṣe jẹ ipinlẹ kẹta to ni akọsilẹ ajakalẹ arun Korona julọ jakejado orileede yii."},{"question":"\\"Ibu, ini kawan-kawan lama saya. Bolehkah _______ menumpang tidur di rumah kita?\\" kata Rosmaini kepada ibunya.","answer":"mereka"},{"question":"කටුස්සන්ට දත් තිබේද?","answer":"කටුස්සන්ට කේතුකාකාර හෝ තලයක් වැනි බයිකස්පිඩ් හෝ ත්‍රිකෝණාකාර දත් ඇත. සමහර විශේෂවල හකුවල ඉදිරිපස කේතුකාකාර දත් සහ පසුපස දෙසට කූඩ සහිත දත් ඇත, නමුත් දෙවැන්න ක්ෂීරපායීන්ගේ දත් සමඟ ස්වරූපයෙන් හෝ ක්‍රියාකාරීත්වයෙන් සැසඳිය නොහැක. (ඒවා පැතලි ඔටුන්න හිමි හෝ ආහාර ඇඹරීමට භාවිතා නොවේ.)"},{"question":"Nitori ti wọn ko gba a laye lati kawe, Ọmọyẹle Ṣoworẹ kọ ounjẹ silẹ latimọle","answer":"Nítorí tawọn ọlọpaa ko jẹ ki ọkunrin akọroyin to nileeṣẹ iroyin Sahara Reporter, Ọmọyẹle Ṣowore, lanfaani sí ìwé tawọn mọlẹbi ẹ ko wa fun un, ọkunrin naa ti ni ebi loun yóò máa fi pa ara oun bayii.ALAROYE gbọ pe bi awọn eeyan ẹ ṣe ko awọn ìwé ẹ wa, ṣugbọn ti awọn ọlọpaa kọ láti ko o fun un lo fa a ti Ṣowore fi yari pé oun ko ni i jẹ ounjẹ ti wọn ba gbe fún òun, nitori oun ko le máa jẹun sikun, ki oun ma fún ọpọlọ oun lounjẹ.Aja-fẹtọọ-ọmọniyan yii sọ pe bi oun ba ṣe n jẹun, bẹẹ gẹgẹ loun máa n fún ọpọlọ oun lounjẹ, ati pe awọn iwe ti oun máa n ka ni ounjẹ ti ọpọlọ oun máa n jẹ.Ni bayii, ọkunrin oniroyin, to tun jẹ oloṣelu yii, ti sọ pe oun yóò bẹrẹ ifẹhonu han, oun yóò sì bẹrẹ sí i febi nla pa ara oun.Bi Ṣowore ṣe bẹrẹ ifẹhonu hàn yii lawọn ti wọn jọ mu naa ti darapọ mọ ọn, ti gbogbo wọn sì ti lawọn ko ni i jẹun rara.Laipẹ yii lawọn ẹṣọ agbofinro ko Ṣoworẹ atawọn eeyan ẹ nibi ti wọn ti n ṣewode lati wọnu ọdun tuntun.Ṣaaju àsìkò yìí, ìyẹn lọjọ kẹta, oṣu kẹjọ, ọdún, 2019, làwọn ẹṣọ agbofinro DSS mu Ṣoworẹ, ti wọn si fi í sí atimọle wọn fún ọjọ mẹrinlelogoje (144).Ẹsun tí wọn fi kan an ni pe oun naa n kowo pamọ́ lọna eru, ati pe o n gbero lati gbajọba mọ Ààrẹ Muhammadu Buhari, lọwọ.Pẹlu ẹsun yii, ALAROYE gbọ pe awọn ẹṣọ agbofinro ko ri ẹri kan ko kalẹ lati fi ba a fa a.Ninu wahala ọhun náà ni wọn ti gbe e lọ sile-ẹjọ, ṣugbọn ti wọn pada fún un ni beeli logunjọ, oṣu kọkanla, ọdun 2020, ti wọn sì pa a laṣẹ pé kò gbọdọ kúrò nílùú Abuja."},{"question":"Senaraikan kepentingan mewujudkan sebuah negara yang berdaulat.","answer":"Skema jawapanF1 Keberkesanan PentadbiranF2 Kemakmuran ekonomiF3 Kesejateraan 4ocialF4 Kecemerlangan hubungan luar "},{"question":"\\"බෙහෙත් ගතහැකි තැන\\"  යන්නට වඩාත්ම ගැලපෙන කෙටි පදය කුමක්ද? (ඔබට භාවිතා  කල හැක්කේ එක වචනයක් පමණි)","answer":"\\"රෝහල\\" වඩාතම ගැලපෙන තනි පදයයි."},{"question":"anthu a mtundu wa a Lomwe ndi komwe anachokera","answer":"Anthu a mtundu wa Lomwe ndi amodzi mwa mafuko akuluakulu ku Mozambique ndi Malawi; pomalizira pake, iwo ali achiwiri kwa anthu ambiri pambuyo pa Achewa. Chilankhulo chawo chimalankhulidwa kwambiri m’chigawo chapakati cha Mozambique. Ku Malawi, anthu amalankhula chinenero cha Malawi Lomwe. Malemu mtsogoleri wakale wa dziko lino Bingu wa Mutharika ndi mchimwene wake Peter Mutharika (pulezidenti wina wa dziko la Malawi) ndi a fuko limeneli."},{"question":"年齢の違う男女の微妙な恋愛関係が描かれている、今年１月に芥川賞を受賞した大道珠貴（だいどう・たまき）の小説は何でしょう？","answer":"『しょっぱいドライブ』です。"},{"question":"Alger moy péeyu ban réw?","answer":"Alger moy péeyu réwum Algérie"},{"question":"பின்வரும் உரையாடலில் உள்ள பேச்சு வழக்கினை எழுத்து வழக்காக மாற்றுக.பேச்சுவழக்கு:“தம்பீ? எங்க நிக்கிறே?”“நீங்க சொன்ன எடத்துலதாண்ணே ! எதிர்த்தாப்புல ஒரு டீ ஸ்டால் இருக்குது.”“அங்ஙனக்குள்ளயே டீ சாப்டுட்டு, பேப்பரப் படிச்சிட்டு இரு.. நா வெரசா வந்துருவேன்”“அண்ணே! சம்முவத்தையும் கூட்டிக்கிட்டு வாங்கண்ணே! அவனெய் பாத்தே ரொம்ப நாளாச்சு!”“அவம்பாட்டியோட வெளியூர் போயிருக்கான். உங்கூருக்கே அவனேக் கூட்டிக்கிட்டு வர்றேன்.”“ரொம்பச் சின்ன வயசுல பார்த்ததுண்ணே ! அப்ப அவனுக்கு மூணு வயசு இருக்கும்!”“இப்ப ஒசரமா வளந்துட்டான்! ஒனக்கு அடையாளமே தெரியாது! ஊருக்கு எங்கூட வருவாம் பாரேன்! சரி, போனை வையி. நாங கௌம்பிடேன்…”“சரிங்கண்ணே ”","answer":"எழுத்து வழக்கு:“தம்பி எங்கே நிற்கிறாய்?”“நீங்கள் சொன்ன இடத்தில்தான் அண்ணா ! எதிர்ப்புறத்தில் ஒரு தேநீர் கடை இருக்கிறது.”“அங்கேயே தேநீர் சாப்பிட்டுவிட்டு, செய்தித்தாள் படித்துக்கொண்டிரு. நான் விரைவாக வந்து விடுகிறேன்.”“அண்ணா! சண்முகத்தையும் கூட்டிக்கொண்டு வாருங்கள் அண்ணா! அவனைப் பார்த்து அதிக நாட்களாகிவிட்டன.”“அவன் பாட்டியுடன் வெளியூர் சென்றிருக்கிறான். உங்கள் ஊருக்கே அவனைக் கூட்டிக்கொண்டு வருகிறேன்.”“நிறைய நாளுக்கு முன்னால் சின்ன வயதில் பார்த்தது அண்ணா . அப்போது அவனுக்கு மூன்று வயது இருக்கும் ”“இப்போது உயரமாக வளர்ந்துவிட்டான். உனக்கு அடையாளமே தெரியாது. ஊருக்கு என்னுடன் வருவான். பார்த்துக்கொள். சரி. தொலைபேசியை வைத்துவிடு. நான் புறப்படுகிறேன்.”“சரி அண்ணா !”"},{"question":"மனிதனை ஒரு முறை தாக்கிய பிறகு மீண்டும் தாக்காத நோய்?","answer":"விடை: பெரிய அம்மை"},{"question":"السؤال: ما معنى الاتحاد الفدرالي ؟","answer":"الإجابة: هو اتحاد بين دولة بمفردها أو عدة دول ؛ بحيث يكون دولة إتحادية قائمة على الدستورية والوحدة القومية"},{"question":"maraina ve ny andro izao?","answer":"eny"},{"question":"Apakah maksud \\"baik berjagung-jagung, sementara menanti padi masak\\"?","answer":"Ia bermaksud sementara menunggu benda baik, lakukan juga benda berfaedah."},{"question":"ചോദ്യം: എപ്പോഴാണ് എൻഐജി സംവിധാനം എഫ്ബിഐ ആദ്യമായി ഉപയോഗിച്ചത് ഉത്തരം:","answer":"2011 ഫെബ്രുവരിയിലാണ് എഫ്ബിഐ ആദ്യമായി എൻഐജി സംവിധാനം ഉപയോഗിച്ചത്."},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਗਉੜੀ ਮਾਲਾ ਮਹਲਾ ੫ ॥ਭਾਵਨੁ ਤਿਆਗਿਓ ਰੀ ਤਿਆਗਿਓ ॥ਤਿਆਗਿਓ ਮੈ ਗੁਰ ਮਿਲਿ ਤਿਆਗਿਓ ॥ਸਰਬ ਸੁਖ ਆਨੰਦ ਮੰਗਲ ਰਸ ਮਾਨਿ ਗੋਬਿੰਦੈ ਆਗਿਓ ॥੧॥ ਰਹਾਉ ॥ਮਾਨੁ ਅਭਿਮਾਨੁ ਦੋਊ ਸਮਾਨੇ ਮਸਤਕੁ ਡਾਰਿ ਗੁਰ ਪਾਗਿਓ ॥ਸੰਪਤ ਹਰਖੁ ਨ ਆਪਤ ਦੂਖਾ ਰੰਗੁ ਠਾਕੁਰੈ ਲਾਗਿਓ ॥੧॥ਬਾਸ ਬਾਸਰੀ ਏਕੈ ਸੁਆਮੀ ਉਦਿਆਨ ਦ੍ਰਿਸਟਾਗਿਓ ॥ਨਿਰਭਉ ਭਏ ਸੰਤ ਭ੍ਰਮੁ ਡਾਰਿਓ ਪੂਰਨ ਸਰਬਾਗਿਓ ॥੨॥ਜੋ ਕਿਛੁ ਕਰਤੈ ਕਾਰਣੁ ਕੀਨੋ ਮਨਿ ਬੁਰੋ ਨ ਲਾਗਿਓ ॥ਸਾਧਸੰਗਤਿ ਪਰਸਾਦਿ ਸੰਤਨ ਕੈ ਸੋਇਓ ਮਨੁ ਜਾਗਿਓ ॥੩॥ਜਨ ਨਾਨਕ ਓੜਿ ਤੁਹਾਰੀ ਪਰਿਓ ਆਇਓ ਸਰਣਾਗਿਓ ॥ਨਾਮ ਰੰਗ ਸਹਜ ਰਸ ਮਾਣੇ ਫਿਰਿ ਦੂਖੁ ਨ ਲਾਗਿਓ ॥੪॥੨॥੧੬੦॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 214 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਅਰਜਨ ਦੇਵ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਬਾਣੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਹਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"ਹੇ ਭੈਣ! ਗੁਰੂ ਨੂੰ ਮਿਲ ਕੇ (ਸੁੱਖਾਂ ਦੇ ਗ੍ਰਹਣ ਕਰਨ ਤੇ ਦੁੱਖਾਂ ਤੋਂ ਡਰਨ ਦਾ) ਸੰਕਲਪ ਛੱਡ ਦਿੱਤਾ ਹੈ, ਸਦਾ ਲਈ ਛੱਡ ਦਿੱਤਾ ਹੈ । (ਹੁਣ ਗੁਰੂ ਦੀ ਕਿਰਪਾ ਨਾਲ) ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੀ ਰਜ਼ਾ (ਮਿੱਠੀ) ਮੰਨ ਕੇ ਮੈਨੂੰ ਸਾਰੇ ਸੁਖ-ਆਨੰਦ ਹੀ ਹਨ, ਖ਼ੁਸ਼ੀਆਂ ਮੰਗਲ ਹੀ ਹਨ ।੧।ਰਹਾਉ।ਹੇ ਭੈਣ! ਕੋਈ ਮੇਰਾ ਆਦਰ ਕਰੇ, ਕੋਈ ਮੇਰੇ ਨਾਲ ਆਕੜ ਵਾਲਾ ਸਲੂਕ ਕਰੇ, ਮੈਨੂੰ ਦੋਵੇਂ ਇਕੋ ਜਿਹੇ ਜਾਪਦੇ ਹਨ, (ਕਿਉਂਕਿ) ਮੈਂ ਆਪਣਾ ਮੱਥਾ (ਸਿਰ) ਗੁਰੂ ਦੇ ਚਰਨਾਂ ਤੇ ਰੱਖ ਦਿੱਤਾ ਹੋਇਆ ਹੈ । (ਗੁਰੂ ਦੀ ਕਿਰਪਾ ਨਾਲ ਮੇਰੇ ਮਨ ਵਿਚ) ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਪਿਆਰ ਬਣ ਚੁੱਕਾ ਹੈ, ਹੁਣ ਮੈਨੂੰ ਆਏ ਧਨ ਦੀ ਖ਼ੁਸ਼ੀ ਨਹੀਂ ਹੁੰਦੀ, ਤੇ ਆਈ ਬਿਪਤਾ ਤੋਂ ਦੁੱਖ ਨਹੀਂ ਪ੍ਰਤੀਤ ਹੁੰਦਾ ।੧।ਹੇ ਭੈਣ! ਹੁਣ ਮੈਨੂੰ ਸਭ ਘਰਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਇਕ ਮਾਲਕ-ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਹੀ ਦਿੱਸਦਾ ਹੈ, ਜੰਗਲਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਭੀ ਮੈਨੂੰ ਉਹੀ ਨਜ਼ਰੀਂ ਆ ਰਿਹਾ ਹੈ । ਗੁਰੂ-ਸੰਤ (ਦੀ ਕਿਰਪਾ ਨਾਲ) ਮੈਂ ਭਟਕਣਾ ਮੁਕਾ ਲਈ ਹੈ, ਹੁਣ ਸਭ ਦੇ ਦਿਲ ਦੀ ਜਾਣਨ ਵਾਲਾ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਹੀ ਮੈਨੂੰ ਸਰਬ-ਵਿਆਪਕ ਦਿੱਸਦਾ ਹੈ ਤੇ ਮੈਂ ਨਿਡਰ ਹੋ ਗਿਆ ਹਾਂ ।੨।(ਹੇ ਭੈਣ! ਜਦੋਂ ਭੀ) ਜੇਹੜਾ ਹੀ ਸਬੱਬ ਕਰਤਾਰ ਨੇ ਬਣਾਇਆ (ਹੁਣ ਮੈਨੂੰ ਆਪਣੇ) ਮਨ ਵਿਚ (ਉਹ) ਭੈੜਾ ਨਹੀਂ ਲੱਗਦਾ । ਸਾਧ ਸੰਗਤਿ ਵਿਚ ਆ ਕੇ ਸੰਤ ਜਨਾਂ ਦੀ ਕਿਰਪਾ ਨਾਲ (ਮਾਇਆ ਦੇ ਮੋਹ ਵਿਚ) ਸੁੱਤਾ ਹੋਇਆ (ਮੇਰਾ) ਮਨ ਜਾਗ ਪਿਆ ਹੈ ।੩।ੇ ਦਾਸ ਨਾਨਕ! (ਆਖ—ਹੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ! ਗੁਰੂ ਦੀ ਕਿਰਪਾ ਨਾਲ) ਮੈਂ ਤੇਰੀ ਓਟ ਵਿਚ ਆ ਪਿਆ ਹਾਂ, ਮੈਂ ਤੇਰੀ ਸਰਨ ਆ ਡਿੱਗਾ ਹਾਂ ।ਹੁਣ ਮੈਨੂੰ ਕੋਈ ਦੁੱਖ ਨਹੀਂ ਪੋਂਹਦਾ । ਮੈਂ ਤੇਰੇ ਨਾਮ ਦਾ ਆਨੰਦ ਮਾਣ ਰਿਹਾ ਹਾਂ ਮੈਂ ਆਤਮਕ ਅਡੋਲਤਾ ਦੇ ਸੁਖ ਮਾਣ ਰਿਹਾ ਹਾਂ ।੪।੨।੧੬੦।\\""},{"question":"Apakah jawapan untuk teka-teki berikut: Terdapat satu benda, apabila kita berdiri dia baring, apabila kita baring dia berdiri. Apabila kita berjalan dia mengikut bersama dan tidak boleh ditinggalkan.","answer":"Jawapannya ialah tapak kaki. Tapak kaki ialah satu bahagian tubuh badan yang terletak di bawah kaki manusia. "},{"question":"\\"Далы\\" - устуканы  кимге тартылат ?","answer":"Далы – улуулугу боюнча каржиликтен кийин келип, эркекке да, аялга да тартыла берет. "},{"question":"አባይ በመጽሐፍ ቅዱስ ውስጥ ምን ተብሎ ይጠራል?","answer":"ግዮን"},{"question":"भारतीय कृषी संशोधन परिषदेच्या मते, भारतात किती प्रकारची माती आढळते?(A) 4(B) 8(C) 6(D) 5=> ","answer":"(B) 8"},{"question":"🇰🇬Манас эпосу 📚Манас эпосун кара сөз менен айткан сабатсыз манасчы?а) Эргеш Ташимбет уулуб) Матисак Акбай уулув) Калбек Жумагүл уулу г) Шаймерден манасчы","answer":"🇰🇬 Манас эпосу 📚а) Эргеш Ташимбет уулу."},{"question":"با توجه به متن به سوال مورد نظر پاسخ بده:متن: «گیلاس به‌خاطر دارابودن «ملاتونین» به داشتن خواب راحت کمک می‌کند. گیلاس به کاهش سوزش و درد مفاصل در کسانی که کار فیزیکی سنگین دارند، کمک می‌کند. گیلاس می‌تواند از بروز دیابت جلوگیری کند. این میوه تابستانی به تقویت حافظه نیز کمک می‌کند. گیلاس برای کسانی که به‌دنبال لاغری هستند، یک میان وعده خوب محسوب می‌شود.»سؤال: آیا خوردن گیلاس برای افرادی که کار سنگین فیزیکی انجام می‌دهند مفید است؟","answer":"بله. خوردن گیلاس می‌تواند در افرادی که کار سنگین فیزیکی انجام می‌دهند به کاهش سوزش و درد مفاصل کمک کند."},{"question":"je malezi mabaya yanachangia katika kuharibu mahusiano kwa ndoa nyingi leo?","answer":"tatizo la malezi mabaya ni tatizo kubwa ambalo linachangia katika kuharibu familia nyingi, malezi ya wazazi wengi yanachangia kwa kiasi kikubwa katika kuleta migogoro na kupelekea ndoa nyingine kuwa katika taabu kubwa"},{"question":" وظیفه څه ته ویل کیږی ؟","answer":"وظیفه یو څو اړخیز مفهوم لري چې په اخلاقي، قانوني او ټولنیزو مسؤلیتونو کې ریښې لري. په اصل کې، دنده د مسؤلیت احساس او د یو اخلاقي او اخلاقي مکلفیتونو د ترسره کولو لپاره ژمنتیا منعکس کوي. دا کولی شي د ژوند په مختلفو اړخونو کې څرګند شي، لکه د قانون د ساتلو دنده، په مسلکي ترتیباتو کې د اخلاقي عمل کولو دنده، یا په شخصي اړیکو کې د ژمنو او ژمنو د پوره کولو دنده. د انفرادي مسؤلیتونو هاخوا، دنده په ټولنو او ټولنو کې ډله ایزو مسؤلیتونو ته هم غزیږي، یو بنسټیز اصول جوړوي چې د نظم او انصاف ساتلو کې مرسته کوي. که چیرې دا د اخلاقو اصولو ته غاړه کیږدي، د نورو حقونو ته درناوی وکړي، یا د ګډو ګټو سره مرسته وکړي، د وظیفې مفهوم د انفرادي او ټولنیز چلند په جوړولو کې مهم رول لوبوي.\\"په یو ډیر مشخص شرایطو کې، وظیفه کولی شي د دولتونو لخوا لګول شوي مالي مسؤلیتونو ته هم اشاره وکړي. دا کیدای شي د ګمرکي محصولاتو یا په وارداتو او صادر شویو توکو د تعرفو په بڼه وي. دا مالي دندې د حکومتونو لپاره د یو میکانیزم په توګه کار کوي ترڅو تجارت تنظیم کړي، عاید تولید کړي، او د کورنیو صنعتونو ساتنه وکړي. په ځینو توکو باندې د محصولاتو لګول کولی شي په اقتصادي پریکړو اغیزه وکړي، په نړیوالو اړیکو اغیزه وکړي، او د یو هیواد په عمومي مالي پالیسیو کې مرسته وکړي. په دې توګه، د وظیفې اصطلاح د مکلفیتونو پراخه لړۍ پوښي، د شخصي او اخلاقي وظیفو څخه نیولې تر اقتصادي او مالي وظیفو پورې چې حکومتونه د خپلو پولو څخه تیریږي په توکو باندې تحمیلوي."},{"question":"Indro misy lahatsoratra:Na dia nanaraka ny fizaham-pahazam-pahasalamana tao amin’ny hopitalin’i Mahabibo fony izy bevohoka aza ny renin’i Leyannah kely dia tsy maintsy niteraka an-trano ihany tamin’ny alin’ny 12 Mey 2023. Natahotra ny tsy fahandriam-pahalemana ny fianakaviany sady natahotra ny hivoaka ny trano tamin’ny alina ka naleon’izy ireo niantso mpiasan’ny fahasalamana ho any aminy hanampy hampizotra tsara ny fiterahana. Iza no niantso ny mpiasan'ny fahasalamana ho tonga hanampy hampizotra tsara ny fiterahana?","answer":"Ny fianakavian'ny renin'i Leyannah no niantso ny mpiasan'ny fahsalamana ho tonga hanampy hampizotra tsara ny fiterahana."},{"question":"Apakah maksud \\"bagai bunyi perempuan di air\\"?","answer":"Ia bermaksud sangat bising (riuh-rendah)"},{"question":"Gwam ọ napụrụ mmadụ mma n'ubi nna ya","answer":"Mkporogwu "},{"question":" د تصمیم ګيري د مراحلو نومونه واخلئ ؟","answer":"د پریکړې کولو پروسه معمولا په څو مرحلو کې شامله ده. پداسې حال کې چې مختلف ماډلونه کولی شي پروسه په بیلابیلو لارو مات کړي، یو عام چوکاټ لاندې مرحلې لري:1) د ستونزې یا فرصت پیژندنه:په دې پوهیدل چې پریکړه باید وشي، یا د یوې ستونزې له امله چې حل ته اړتیا لري یا یو فرصت چې باید ونیول شي.2) د معلوماتو راټولول:د اړوندو معلوماتو او معلوماتو راټولول چې کولی شي د وضعیت یا مسلې په پوهیدو کې مرسته وکړي. پدې کې کیدای شي څیړنه، تحلیل، او مشورې شاملې وي.3) د بدیلونو پیژندنه:د ستونزې حل کولو یا فرصت څخه د ګټې اخیستنې لپاره د ممکنه انتخابونو یا حلونو لړۍ رامینځته کول.4) د بدیلونو ارزونه:د امکاناتو، خطرونو، ګټو او نورو اړوندو معیارونو له مخې د هر بدیل ګټې او زیانونه ارزول.5) پریکړه کول:د ارزونې او تحلیل پر بنسټ د غوره بدیل غوره کول. دا هغه ټکی دی چیرې چې اصلي پریکړه کیږي.6) د پریکړې پلي کول:غوره شوې پریکړه په عمل کې پلي کول. پدې کې کیدای شي د پلان جوړول، د سرچینو تخصیص، او د اړینو ګامونو پیل کول شامل وي.7) د پریکړې څارنه او ارزونه:د پریکړې د پایلو او پایلو ارزونه. څارنه خورا مهمه ده ترڅو ډاډ ترلاسه شي چې غوره شوی حل اغیزمن دی، او د اړتیا په صورت کې سمونونه کیدی شي.8) فیډبیک او زده کړه:د تطبیق مرحلې څخه د فیډبیک راټولول او د تجربې څخه زده کړه. دا معلومات د راتلونکي پریکړې کولو پروسو لپاره ارزښتناکه کیدی شي.دا مهمه ده چې په یاد ولرئ چې پریکړه کول ډیری وختونه تکراري وي، او افراد یا سازمانونه ممکن ځینې مرحلو ته بیاکتنه وکړي کله چې نوي معلومات شتون ولري یا د وضعیت وده ومومي. مختلف ماډلونه او تیورۍ ممکن مختلف اصطالحات یا ګروپ مرحلې په مختلف ډول وکاروي ، مګر دا عمومي مرحلې د پریکړې کولو پروسې جوهر نیسي."},{"question":"মাদকাসক্তি নিয়ে ১টি অনুচ্ছেদ লিখুন।","answer":"বর্তমান বিশ্ব যে কয়টি মারাত্মক সমস্যার সম্মুখীন তার মধ্যে অন্যতম মাদকাসক্তি। মাদকের ব্যবহার ও অবৈধ বিস্তারে বিশ্ববাসী আজ শঙ্কিত। মাদকদ্রব্য হচ্ছে সেসব বস্তু যা গ্রহণের ফলে স্নায়ুবিক বৈকল্যসহ নেশার সৃষ্টি হয়। নির্দিষ্ট সময় পরপর তা সেবনের আসক্তি অনুভূত হয়। এর কুপ্রভাব ভয়াবহ ও মারাত্মক। আমাদের দেশেও মাদকের ভয়াবহতা সাংঘাতিক। আমাদের দেশে যেসব মাদকদ্রব্যের সেবন সর্বাধিক তা হচ্ছে গাঁজা, ফেনসিডিল, হেরোইন, মদ, বিয়ার, তাড়ি, ঘুমের ঔষধ, প্যাথেড্রিন ইনজেকশন, ইয়াবা ইত্যাদি। এসব মাদকদ্রব্য গ্রহণ করে নেশা সৃষ্টি করাকে মাদকাসক্তি বলা হয়। বিশ্ব স্বাস্থ্য সংস্থার মতে, মাদকাসক্তি হচ্ছে চিকিৎসা গ্রহণযোগ্য নয় এমন দ্রব্য অতিরিক্ত পরিমাণে গ্রহণ করা ও তার ওপর নির্ভরশীল হয়ে পড়া। বিভিন্ন কারণে মানুষ মাদকাসক্ত হয়। এর মধ্যে সঙ্গদোষ, কৌতূহল, পারিবারিক কলহ, ধর্মীয় মূল্যবোধের বিচ্যুতি ও মাদকদ্রব্যের সহজলভ্যতা উল্লেখযোগ্য। বিশেষ করে যুবসমাজই মাদকাসক্তিতে সবচেয়ে বেশি আচ্ছন্ন। বিশ্বব্যাপী মাদকদ্রব্যের অপব্যবহার এবং চোরাচালানের মাধ্যমে এর ব্যাপক প্রসার ভবিষ্যৎ প্রজন্মের জন্য মারাত্মক হুমকি সৃষ্টি করেছে। মাদকের নিষ্ঠুর ছোবলে অকালে ঝরে যাচ্ছে বহু তাজা প্রাণ এবং নষ্ট হচ্ছে বহু তরুণের সম্ভাবনাময় উজ্জ্বল ভবিষ্যৎ। মাদকদ্রব্যের অপব্যবহারজনিত সমস্যা আজ বিশ্বব্যাপী। লাভজনক এ ব্যবসাকে কেন্দ্র করে গড়ে উঠেছে আন্তর্জাতিক চোরাচালানি চক্র। বাংলাদেশের ভবিষ্যৎ প্রজন্মকে এ ধ্বংসের হাত থেকে রক্ষার জন্য মাদকাসক্তি নিরাময় ও প্রতিরোধ আন্দোলনে সকল জনসাধারণকে এগিয়ে আসতে হবে। সরকার থেকে শুরু করে বিভিন্ন গণমাধ্যম, রাজনীতিবিদ, বুদ্ধিজীবী, সমাজকর্মীসহ সকল শ্রেণির মানুষের সক্রিয় অংশগ্রহণের মাধ্যমে মাদকমুক্ত বিশ্ব গড়ে তুলতে হবে।"},{"question":"క్రింద ఇచ్చిన సినిమా పాటలోని ఒక భాగం యొక్క సాహిత్యంపై విశ్లేషణ చెయ్యండి:జగములేలినవాని సగము నివ్వెరబోయెసగము మిగిలినవాని మొగము నగవైపోయె","answer":"ఈ రెండు వాక్యాలు చదివిన వారిలో కొద్దిపాటి సాహిత్య పరిచయం ఉన్నా అర్ధమైపోతుంది ఇది అర్ధనారీశ్వర తత్వానికి సంబంధించినది అని.  ఎంత క్లుప్తంగా అర్ధనారీశ్వర తత్వాన్ని చెప్పేరు. ఆశ్చర్యం జగన్మాతది. ఆనందమైన అవలోకనం మహాదేవునిది.  అతను బయలుదేరాల్సిన అవసరాన్ని ఆమెకు తెలియపరచి భూలోకానికి పయనమౌతాడు మహాదేవుడు.  శంకఅని రుడు భక్తవరదుడే కానీ ఫల్గుణుడు.  ఇవ్వాల్సిందేమో పాశుపతం.  అతని ప్రతాపమెంతటిదో పరీక్షించనిదే పాశుపతం ఇవ్వడం కుదరదు ఆలోచించి ఏంచేశాడు?"},{"question":"TalooyinHadii aad rabto","answer":"Haddii aad rabto in aad waalidkaa daryeeshoKu daryeel waalid adeecnimo baari nimo iyo dhago nuglaan.Haddii aad rabto in aad naftaada daryeesho ku daryeel alle ka cabsi iyo cibaado suuban.Haddii aad rabto in aad mujtamaca ama dadka kugu xeeran aad  daryeeshana ku daryeel ixtiraam iyo hadal wanaagsan."},{"question":"ਸਿਰੀਰਾਗੁ ਮਹਲਾ ੩ ॥ ਜਿਨੀ ਇਕ ਮਨਿ ਨਾਮੁ ਧਿਆਇਆ ਗੁਰਮਤੀ ਵੀਚਾਰਿ ॥ ਤਿਨ ਕੇ ਮੁਖ ਸਦ ਉਜਲੇ ਤਿਤੁ ਸਚੈ ਦਰਬਾਰਿ ॥ ਓਇ ਅੰਮ੍ਰਿਤੁ ਪੀਵਹਿ ਸਦਾ ਸਦਾ ਸਚੈ ਨਾਮਿ ਪਿਆਰਿ ॥੧॥ ਭਾਈ ਰੇ ਗੁਰਮੁਖਿ ਸਦਾ ਪਤਿ ਹੋਇ ॥ ਹਰਿ ਹਰਿ ਸਦਾ ਧਿਆਈਐ ਮਲੁ ਹਉਮੈ ਕਢੈ ਧੋਇ ॥੧॥ ਰਹਾਉ ॥ ਮਨਮੁਖ ਨਾਮੁ ਨ ਜਾਣਨੀ ਵਿਣੁ ਨਾਵੈ ਪਤਿ ਜਾਇ ॥ ਸਬਦੈ ਸਾਦੁ ਨ ਆਇਓ ਲਾਗੇ ਦੂਜੈ ਭਾਇ ॥ ਵਿਸਟਾ ਕੇ ਕੀੜੇ ਪਵਹਿ ਵਿਚਿ ਵਿਸਟਾ ਸੇ ਵਿਸਟਾ ਮਾਹਿ ਸਮਾਇ ॥੨॥ ਤਿਨ ਕਾ ਜਨਮੁ ਸਫਲੁ ਹੈ ਜੋ ਚਲਹਿ ਸਤਗੁਰ ਭਾਇ ॥ ਕੁਲੁ ਉਧਾਰਹਿ ਆਪਣਾ ਧੰਨੁ ਜਣੇਦੀ ਮਾਇ ॥ ਹਰਿ ਹਰਿ ਨਾਮੁ ਧਿਆਈਐ ਜਿਸ ਨਉ ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰੇ ਰਜਾਇ ॥੩॥ ਜਿਨੀ ਗੁਰਮੁਖਿ ਨਾਮੁ ਧਿਆਇਆ ਵਿਚਹੁ ਆਪੁ ਗਵਾਇ ॥ ਓਇ ਅੰਦਰਹੁ ਬਾਹਰਹੁ ਨਿਰਮਲੇ ਸਚੇ ਸਚਿ ਸਮਾਇ ॥ ਨਾਨਕ ਆਏ ਸੇ ਪਰਵਾਣੁ ਹਹਿ ਜਿਨ ਗੁਰਮਤੀ ਹਰਿ ਧਿਆਇ ॥੪॥੫॥੩੮॥ ","answer":" ਹੇ ਭਾਈ! ਗੁਰੂ ਦੀ ਸਰਨ ਪਿਆਂ ਸਦਾ ਇੱਜ਼ਤ ਮਿਲਦੀ ਹੈ। (ਗੁਰੂ ਦੀ ਸਰਨ ਪੈ ਕੇ) ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਸਦਾ ਸਿਮਰਨਾ ਚਾਹੀਦਾ ਹੈ। (ਗੁਰੂ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਦੇ ਮਨ ਵਿਚੋਂ) ਹਉਮੈ ਦੀ ਮੈਲ ਧੋ ਕੇ ਕੱਢ ਦੇਂਦਾ ਹੈ।1। ਰਹਾਉ।ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਮਨੁੱਖਾਂ ਨੇ ਗੁਰੂ ਦੀ ਮਤਿ ਦੀ ਰਾਹੀਂ (ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੇ ਨਾਮ ਨੂੰ ਆਪਣੇ ਸੋਚ-ਮੰਡਲ ਵਿਚ ਟਿਕਾ ਕੇ ਨਾਮ ਨੂੰ ਇਕਾਗ੍ਰ ਮਨ ਨਾਲ ਸਿਮਰਿਆ ਹੈ, ਉਸ ਸਦਾ-ਥਿਰ ਰਹਿਣ ਵਾਲੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੇ ਦਰਬਾਰ ਵਿਚ ਉਹ ਸਦਾ ਸੁਰਖ਼ਰੂ ਹੁੰਦੇ ਹਨ। ਉਹ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਸਦਾ-ਥਿਰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੇ ਨਾਮ ਵਿਚ ਪਿਆਰ ਦੀ ਰਾਹੀਂ ਸਦਾ ਆਤਮਕ ਜੀਵਨ ਦੇਣ ਵਾਲਾ ਨਾਮ-ਜਲ ਪੀਂਦੇ ਹਨ।1।(ਪਰ) ਆਪਣੇ ਮਨ ਦੇ ਪਿਛੇ ਤੁਰਨ ਵਾਲੇ ਬੰਦੇ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੇ ਨਾਮ ਨਾਲ ਸਾਂਝ ਨਹੀਂ ਪਾਂਦੇ, ਨਾਮ ਤੋਂ ਬਿਨਾ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੀ ਇੱਜ਼ਤ ਚਲੀ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ। ਉਹਨਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਸਤਿਗੁਰੂ ਦੇ ਸ਼ਬਦ ਦਾ ਆਨੰਦ ਨਹੀਂ ਆਉਂਦਾ, (ਇਸ ਵਾਸਤੇ) ਉਹ (ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਨੂੰ ਵਿਸਾਰ ਕੇ) ਕਿਸੇ ਹੋਰ ਪਿਆਰ ਵਿਚ ਮਸਤ ਰਹਿੰਦੇ ਹਨ। ਉਹ ਬੰਦੇ (ਵਿਕਾਰਾਂ ਦੇ) ਗੰਦ ਵਿਚ ਲੀਨ ਰਹਿ ਕੇ ਗੰਦ ਦੇ ਕੀੜਿਆਂ ਵਾਂਗ (ਵਿਕਾਰਾਂ ਦੇ) ਗੰਦ ਵਿਚ ਹੀ ਪਏ ਰਹਿੰਦੇ ਹਨ।2।ਜੇਹੜੇ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਗੁਰੂ ਦੇ ਪ੍ਰੇਮ ਵਿਚ ਜੀਵਨ ਬਿਤੀਤ ਕਰਦੇ ਹਨ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦਾ ਜੀਵਨ ਕਾਮਯਾਬ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ, ਉਹ ਆਪਣਾ ਸਾਰਾ ਖ਼ਾਨਦਾਨ (ਹੀ ਵਿਕਾਰਾਂ ਤੋਂ) ਬਚਾ ਲੈਂਦੇ ਹਨ, ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੀ ਜੰਮਣ ਵਾਲੀ ਮਾਂ ਸੋਭਾ ਖੱਟਦੀ ਹੈ। (ਇਸ ਵਾਸਤੇ, ਹੇ ਭਾਈ!) ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਸਿਮਰਨਾ ਚਾਹੀਦਾ ਹੈ (ਪਰ ਉਹੀ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਨਾਮ ਸਿਮਰਦਾ ਹੈ) ਜਿਸ ਉੱਤੇ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਆਪਣੀ ਰਜ਼ਾ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਮਿਹਰ ਕਰਦਾ ਹੈ।3।ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਬੰਦਿਆਂ ਨੇ ਗੁਰੂ ਦੀ ਸਰਨ ਪੈ ਕੇ ਆਪਣੇ ਅੰਦਰੋਂ ਆਪਾ-ਭਾਵ ਦੂਰ ਕਰ ਕੇ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਸਿਮਰਿਆ ਹੈ, ਉਹ ਬੰਦੇ ਸਦਾ-ਥਿਰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਵਿਚ ਲੀਨ ਹੋ ਕੇ ਉਸੇ ਦਾ ਰੂਪ ਬਣ ਕੇ ਅੰਦਰੋਂ ਬਾਹਰੋਂ ਪਵਿਤ੍ਰ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ (ਭਾਵ, ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦਾ ਆਤਮਕ ਜੀਵਨ ਪਵਿਤ੍ਰ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ, ਤੇ ਉਹ ਖ਼ਲਕਤ ਨਾਲ ਭੀ ਵਰਤਣ-ਵਿਹਾਰ ਸੁਚੱਜਾ ਰੱਖਦੇ ਹਨ) ।ਹੇ ਨਾਨਕ! ਜਗਤ ਵਿਚ ਆਏ (ਜੰਮੇ) ਉਹੀ ਬੰਦੇ ਕਬੂਲ ਹਨ ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਨੇ ਗੁਰੂ ਦੀ ਮਤਿ ਲੈ ਕੇ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਸਿਮਰਿਆ ਹੈ।4।5। 38।"},{"question":"问：什么是素食汉堡？","answer":"答：素食汉堡是一种不含肉类的汉堡，主要使用豆类、蔬菜、谷物等制作。"},{"question":"'SesiseMgungundlovana, ngemuva nje kwamasontshwana ngadlala ilotho ngobanganginayo imadlana engangopondo neshumi engathandaza ukuthi kungabesengiqeda okuncane ebesingathenga ngakho isinkwa ngalelo langa. Ngafaka ngingaziukuthi iyozala nkomoni. Ngahamba ngaya ekhaya. Umuzi wethu wawusemuhleezandleni zenono. Usuhalisa. Kwajabula nomakhelwane bethu ababekade basigcina.Sathola imfudumalo esasikade sayigcina. Sasingazi ukuthi abantu babephathekekanjani ngokuhamba kwethu. Ukuba sasazi, ngabe sahlala sazidlela izinkobe nabantubathi asingahambi asihlale siphile njengabo. Kusinda kwehlela endodeni.Ngakusasa zabuya emasisweni, langibheka engangithi selangilahla. Ngayibambangedwa imali eyisizumbulu sezigidi. Sageza sashona khona edolobheni sesiyolandaisheke. Uma sifika lapha, sathathwa ngemoto sayiswa eThekwini lapho umamaengakaze alubhade khona. Uma sifika lapha, sanikwa izinkomishi zetiye eliphambili.Saphuza kwakuhle kwadela. Safika ngesikhathi esimnandi. Sabizwa sekugcweleizintatheli. Kwase kuba ubugqwebegqwebe sithathwa izithombe yiwo wonke umuntuowayephethe ikhamera. Sithathwa izithombe nje, sinikwe elikhulu iheheba leli leshekeokuthiwa asilibambe nomkami. Sasijabuliswe ukuthi sesiphumile osizini, sesizodlaesikuthandayo njengabo bonke abanezingane ezinjengezethu. Ngemuva kwalokhosanikezwa-ke isheke lethu. Sathathwa saphindiselwa ekhaya ngonyanyavu lwemotoebomvu …'1. Ukuba wawunikwe ithuba lokweluleka uManyoba emva kokuba ewine ilotho,wawungathini kuye mayelana nokusebenzisa imali yakhe. Bhala amaphuzuAMATHATHU.","answer":"Amaphuzu AMATHATHU kwalandelayo:Ngangizothi:• Akaxoxisane nabeluleki bezokuphathwa kwezimali.√/• Akalungise umuzi wakhe ube yile nto ayifunayo.√/• Akathathe enye imali ayilondoloze ngendlela ezomakhela inzuzo.√/• Akangaphisani ngemali kubantu abayizihlobo zakhe.√/• Akadle noma yini ayithandayo.√/• Akavakashele amazwe awathandayo.√"},{"question":"வினா: முழுமுதற்  கடவுளான விநாயகரைப் பற்றி அழ. வள்ளியப்பா எழுதிய பாடலை எழுதுக.","answer":"விடை:தொந்திக் கணபதி, வா வா வா.வந்தே ஒருவரம் தா தா தா.கந்தனின் அண்ணா, வா வா வா.கனிவுடன் ஒருவரம் தா தா தா.ஆனை முகத்துடன் வா வா வா.அவசியம் ஒருவரம் தா தா தா.பானை வயிற்றுடன் வா வா வா.பணிந்தேன்; ஒருவரம் தா தா தா.எல்லாம் அறிந்த கணபதியே,எவ்வரம் கேட்பேன், தெரியாதா?நல்லவன் என்னும் ஒருபெயரைநான்பெற நீ வரம் தா தா தா.அழ. வள்ளியப்பா (நவம்பர் 7, 1922- மார்ச் 16, 1989) குழந்தை இலக்கியங்கள் படைத்த மிக முக்கியமான கவிஞர். 2,000 க்கும் மேலான குழந்தைகளுக்கான பாடல்கள் எழுதியுள்ளார்.பிறப்பு:புதுக்கோட்டை மாவட்டத்திலுள்ள இராயவரத்தில் 1922 ஆம் ஆண்டு பிறந்தார். இவர் நகரத்தார் சமூகத்தைச் சேர்ந்த அழகப்ப செட்டியார், உமையாள் ஆச்சி தம்பதியருக்கு மகனாகப் பிறந்தார். பெற்றோர் இவருக்குச் சூட்டிய பெயர் வள்ளியப்பன். ஐந்தாம் வயதில் தான் பிறந்த வீட்டிற்கு அடுத்த வீட்டில் வாழ்ந்த அழகப்பன் என்பவருக்குத் தத்துப்பிள்ளையாகச் சென்றார். இராயவரம் காந்தி ஆரம்பப் பள்ளியில் ஐந்தாம் வகுப்பு வரை படித்தார். பின்னர் இராமச்சந்திரபுரத்தில் உள்ள பூமீசுவரசுவாமி இலவச உயர்நிலைப் பள்ளியில் படித்தார்.எழுத்துப் பணி தொடக்கம்:தொடர்ந்து படிக்க முடியாததால் 1940 ஆம் ஆண்டில் வாழ்வாதாரம் தேடி வை. கோவிந்தனின் சென்னை சக்தி பத்திரிகை அலுவலகத்தில் காசாளராகச் சேர்ந்தார். அப்போது சக்தி ஆசிரியராக இருந்த தி. தி. ஜ. ரங்கநாதனின் ஊக்குவிப்பின் காரணமாக சக்தி இதழிலேயே எழுத ஆரம்பித்தார். \\"ஆளுக்குப் பாதி\\" என்னும் தம் முதல் கதையை எழுதினார்.சக்தியில் பணியாற்றிய போது வள்ளியம்மை என்பாரைத் திருமணம் செய்தார். இவர்களுக்கு ஒரு மகனும், நான்கு மகள்களும் உள்ளனர்.1941 -ல் சக்தியில் இருந்து விலகி இந்தியன் வங்கியில் சேர்ந்தார். வங்கிப் பணியிலிருந்தவாறு கவிதையும் கட்டுரையும் எழுதத் தொடங்கியவர் 1982 -நவம்பரில் வங்கிப் பணியிலிருந்து ஓய்வு பெறும் வரை எழுதினார். ஓய்வுக்குப் பின்பும் எழுதிக் கொண்டுதான் இருந்தார்.செய்தித்தாள் ஆசிரியர்:வங்கிப் பணியில் இருக்கும்போதே பாலர் மலர், டமாரம், சங்கு ஆகிய செய்தித் தாள்களுக்கு கௌரவ ஆசிரியராகப் பணியாற்றினார். 1951 முதல் 1954 வரை பூஞ்சோலை என்ற இதழுக்கும், ஓய்வு பெற்ற பின் 1983 முதல் 1987 வரை, கல்கி வெளியீடான கோகுலம் என்ற இதழிலும் ஆசிரியராக இருந்தார்.குழந்தை எழுத்தாளர் சங்கம்:குழந்தை எழுத்தாளர்கள் பலரைத் திரட்டி 1950 -ல் குழந்தை எழுத்தாளர்கள் சங்கம் என்ற அமைப்பை உருவாக்கினார். சக்தி வை.கோவிந்தன் இச்சங்கத்தின் முதல் தலைவராக இருந்தார். அவரைத் தொடர்ந்து வள்ளியப்பா இந்த அமைப்பின் காரியதரிசியாகவும், தலைவராகவும், வழிகாட்டியாகவும் பல பொறுப்புகளை ஏற்றுச் செயல்பட்டார். காரைக்குடி குழந்தை எழுத்தாளர் சங்கத் தலைவராகப் பொறுப்புவகித்தார்."},{"question":"\\"ઘણાં સમય પહેલાં એક ધોબી પાસે એક ગધેડો હતો. ધોબી આખો દિવસ એ ગધેડા પાસે સખત કામ કરાવતો અને રાતના સમયે એને છૂટો મૂકી દેતો. રાત્રે તે ગધેડો અહીં તહીં ચરીને પોતાનું પેટ ભરતો. એક રાત્રે એ ગધેડાને એક શિયાળ મળ્યું. બન્ને વચ્ચે દોસ્તી થઈ ગઈ. શિયાળે ગધેડાને કહ્યું, ‘ચાલ આજે હું તને સરસ મજાની જગ્યા બતાવું. ત્યાં આપણને ધરાઈને ખાવાનું મળશે.’ શિયાળ ગધેડાને એક ખેતર પાસે લઈ ગયું. જુવારના ખેતરના એક ખૂણે કાકડીના વેલા પથરાયેલા હતા વેલ પર કૂણી કૂણી કાકડીઓ ઉગી હતી. ખેતરની વાડમાં એક છીંડુ હતું એમાંથી બંને અંદર પેઠા. આવી સરસ તાજી કાકડીઓ જોઈને ગધેડાના મોઢામાં તો પાણી આવવા લાગ્યું. ગધેડાએ ધરાઈને કાકડી ખાધી. કાકડી ખાઈને ગધેડો ગેલમાં આવી ગયો. તેને ગાવાની ઈચ્છા થઈ આવી. તેણે શિયાળને કહ્યું, ‘ભાઈ શિયાળ, આજે કેવી રૂપાળી સરસ મજાની પૂનમની રાત છે, આકાશમાં ચાંદો ય કેવો સુંદર લાગે છે ! આવા મજાના વાતાવરણમાં હું ગાઉં અને તું સૂર પૂરાવ તો કેવું ?’ શિયાળ કહે, ‘અરે ગધેડાભાઈ, હાથે કરીને ઉપાધી શીદને વહોરી લેવી? આપણે અત્યારે ચોરની જેમ આ ખેતરમાં છાનામાના પેઠા છીએ. એટલે મૂંગા રહેવામાં જ મજા છે. તમે ગાશો કે તરતજ રખેવાળ તમારો ઉંચો સૂર સાંભળી જાગી જશે. અને આપણા બાર વાગી જશે.’ ગધેડો બોલ્યો, ‘મૂર્ખ, તું તો જંગલી જ રહ્યો. સંગીતના રસને તું શું સમજે?’\\"અહીં ‘ના, હું તો ગાઈશ જ!’ બાળવાર્તાનો શરૂઆત નો ફકરો આપેલ છે, બાકી ની વાર્તા લખો.","answer":"આગળની વાર્તા નીચે મુજબ છે:\\"શિયાળે ગધેડાને ન ગાવા માટે ઘણુંય સમજાવ્યો, પણ હવે ગધેડો તેની હઠ લઈને બેઠો હતો. તે કહે, ‘ના હું તો ગાઈશ જ…’ગધેડો ગાવાનું શરૂ કરે એ પહેલાં ચતુર શિયાળ બોલ્યું, ‘ગધેડાભાઈ, તમે ઘડીવાર થોભો. હું પેલા ઝાંપા પાસે ઉભો રહી રખેવાળનું ધ્યાન રાખું છું. પછી તમે નિરાંતે ગાઓ….’શિયાળ વાડીની બહાર નીકળી ગયું. હવે ગધેડો ડોક ઉંચી રાખીને મોટે મોટેથી ગાવાનું શરૂ કર્યું, ‘હોં… ચી…. હોં…. ચી…’ એના ભૂંકવાનો અવાજ સાંભળીને ખેતરનો રખેવાળ દોડી આવ્યો. તેણે પોતાની જાડી ડાંગ વડે ગધેડાને મારી મારીને અધમૂવો કરી નાંખ્યો. પછી તેના ગળે વજનદાર પથરો બાંધીને તે ચાલ્યો ગયો.થોડીવાર પછી ગધેડો મહામહેનતે ઉભો થયો. તે ગળે લટકાવેલ મોટા પથરા સાથે લંગડાતો લંગડાતો ખેતરની બહાર આવ્યો. શિયાળે પૂછ્યું, ‘ગધેડાભાઈ, આ શું થયું?’ગધેડો હવે શું બોલે ? તેને હવે સમજાઈ ગયું હતું કે તેણે શિયાળની સલાહ માનીને ગાવાનું માંડી વાળ્યું હોત તો આ દશા ન થાત.સારઃ કોઈ પણ કર્ય કરતાં પહેલાં પરિણામનો વિચાર કરવો અને આપેલી સલાહનો ઉદ્દેશ્ય સમજવો.\\""},{"question":"inona no fiantson’ny Malagasy ny mponina anyan-dafy?","answer":"ny fiantson’ny Malagasy ny mponina any an-dafy dia vazaha"},{"question":"ශ්‍රී ලංකාවේ වර්තමානයේ පවතින වනගහනය","answer":"29%"},{"question":"నగదు చిట్టా నిల్వకు, పాస్బుక్ నిల్వ తేడాకు గల కారణాలను వివరించండి.","answer":"ఒక నిర్ణీత తేదీనాడు నగదు పుస్తకములోని బ్యాంకు నిల్వ, పాస్బుక్ నిల్వ, రెండూ ఒకే మొత్తముతో సమానము కాకపోవడానికి అనేక అంశాలు కారణాలుగా ఉంటాయి. అవి.1) వ్యవహారములు నగదు పుస్తకములో బ్యాంకు వరుసలో నమోదై, పాస్బుక్ లో నమోదు కాకపోవడం:సంస్థకు వచ్చిన చెక్కులను నగదు పుస్తకములో నమోదు చేసి, బ్యాంకుకు పంపకపోవడం. ఈ సందర్భములో చెక్కులు నగదు పుస్తకములో డెబిట్ వైపు మాత్రమే నమోదు అవుతాయి.సంస్థ చెక్కులను జారీచేసినా, చెల్లింపుకై బ్యాంకులో దాఖలు కాకపోవడం. ఇవి నగదుచిట్టాలో క్రెడిట్ వైపు మాత్రమే నమోదవుతాయి.వ్యాపారస్తుడు చెక్కులను బ్యాంకుకు వసూలుకు పంపగా, సమన్వయ తేదీనాటికి వసూలు కాకపోవడం. ఇది నగదు పుస్తకములో మాత్రమే డెబిట్వైపు నమోదు అవుతాయి.2) వ్యవహారాలు పాస్బుక్ లో నమోదై నగదు పుస్తకములో నమోదు కాకపోవడం:i) సంస్థ ఖాతాదారుడు నేరుగా సంస్థ బ్యాంకు ఖాతాలో జమకట్టినపుడు. ఇది పాస్బుక్లో క్రెడిట్ వైపు మాత్రమే నమోదు అవుతుంది.ii) బ్యాంకు చార్జీలు: బ్యాంకు ఖాతాదారుకు సేవలను అందించినందుకుగాను కొంత మొత్తము చార్జి చేస్తారు. దీనిని బ్యాంకు చార్జీలు అంటారు. దీనిని పాస్ బుక్ లో డెబిట్ చేసినా ఖాతాదారుకు ఈ విషయం తెలిసేంత వరకు నగదు పుస్తకములో నమోదు కాదు.iii) సంస్థ బ్యాంకుకు ఇచ్చిన స్థాయి ఉత్తర్వుల ప్రకారము బ్యాంకువారు భీమా ప్రీమియం, క్లబ్ బిల్లులు మొదలైన చెల్లింపులు పాస్బుక్ డెబిట్ చేస్తారు. సంస్థకు ఈవిషయం తెలిసేంతవరకు నగదు పుస్తకములో నమోదు చేయరు.iv) నేరుగా చేసిన డెబిట్: రుణదాతలు వ్యాపారస్తుని అనుమతితో నేరుగా అతని బ్యాంకు ఖాతానుంచి సొమ్మును పొందినపుడు, పాస్బుక్ లో డెబిట్ చేయబడుతుంది. కాని నగదు పుస్తక్తములో నమోదుకానందున రెండు పుస్తకాల నిల్వలలో తేడా వస్తుంది.v) ఓవర్ డ్రాఫ్ట్ పై వడ్డీ లేదా అప్పుమీద వడ్డీ: అప్పులమీద లేదా ఓవర్ డ్రాఫ్ట్ప చెల్లించిన వడ్డీ పాస్బుక్ లో డెబిట్ వైపు కనపడుతుంది. ఇది నగదు పుస్తకములో నమోదు కానందున రెండు నిల్వలలో తేడా వస్తుంది.vi) డిపాజిట్లు లేదా పెట్టుబడులపై వడ్డీ: డిపాజిట్ల మీద లేదా పెట్టుబడులపై వసూలు చేసిన వడ్డీ పాస్బుక్లో క్రెడిట్ వైపు ఉంటుంది.vii) చెక్కులు, బిల్లుల అనాదరణ: సంస్థ ఇచ్చిన చెక్కులు లేదా బిల్లులు సంస్థ ఖాతాలో తగినంత నిల్వ లేనందున అనాదరణ జరగవచ్చు. దీనిని సంస్థ ఖాతాకు డెబిట్ చేస్తారు కాని నగదు పుస్తకములో పద్దు ఉండదు.3) తప్పుల వలన ఏర్పడే తేడాలు:సంస్థ కొన్ని తప్పులను చేయవచ్చు. ఉదా: వ్యవహారమును నమోదు చేయకపోవడం, తప్పుగా నమోదు లేదా తప్పుగా నిల్వ తేల్చడం మొదలగునవి.కొన్ని సమయాలలో బ్యాంకు వారు కూడా కొన్ని తప్పులు చేయవచ్చు. వ్యవహారాన్ని తప్పుగా నమోదు చేయడం లేదా వ్యవహారాన్ని వదిలి వేయడం మొదలైనవి. ఈ తప్పుల వలన నగదు పుస్తకము నిల్వ పాస్బుక్ నిల్వతో సమానము కాదు."},{"question":"Шта је потребно да се спакује за камповање?","answer":"Опрема за камповање може варирати у зависности од тога где кампујете, колико дуго желите да останете. Ево неких основних ставки које би могле бити корисне:- Шатор- Врећа за спавање- Душек на надувавање или подлога за спавање- Лампа на батерије- Прибор за јело (кашике, виљушке, решо)- Храна и пиће које може да стоји ван фрижидера и која није лако кварљива- Одећа и обућа прилагођена временским условима- Хигијенске потрепштине (туфери, папирне марамице, сапун)- Прва помоћ"},{"question":"شكون هو النبي اللي تلقب بكليم الله ؟","answer":"سيدنا موسى عليه السلام"},{"question":"నవసమాజంలో విద్యార్థుల పాత్ర అనే అంశంమీద వ్యాసం రాయండి.","answer":"విద్యను అర్థించువారు విద్యార్థులు. సంఘమునకు చేయు సేవ సంఘసేవ. విద్యార్థులు బాల్యము నుండే సంఘమునకు సేవచేయు అలవాటును కలిగియుండ వలెను. నేటి విద్యార్థులే రేపటి పౌరులు. కనుక సంఘసేవ పట్ల ఆసక్తి గల విద్యార్థులు భవిష్యత్తులో ప్రజానాయకులై దేశమును అన్ని రంగములలోనూ అభివృద్ధిలోనికి తీసుకుని రాగలరు.సంఘసేవలో విద్యార్థుల విధులు – పాత్ర :విద్యార్థులలో సేవాభావమును అభివృద్ధి చేయుటకై పాఠశాలలో స్కౌట్స్ మరియు గైడ్స్, ఎన్.సి.సి. వంటి పథకములు ప్రవేశపెట్టబడినవి. ఇవేకాక కళాశాలల యందు జాతీయ సేవా పథకం (ఎన్.ఎస్.ఎస్.) అను దానిని ప్రవేశపెట్టారు. వీటిలో ఉత్సాహవంతులు అయిన విద్యార్థులు సభ్యులుగా చేరవచ్చును. ఆ విద్యార్థుల్ని సేవా పథకంలో పాల్గొనచేయుటకు ఒక ఉపాధ్యాయుడు నాయకత్వము వహించును.విద్యార్థులు అనేక విధాలుగా సంఘసేవ చేస్తూ జాతీయాభ్యుదయానికి సహకరించవచ్చును. తామున్న ప్రాంతములోను, మురికివాడలకును పోయి అక్కడివారికి పరిశుభ్రత యొక్క అవసరమును వివరించి అందరూ శుభ్రముగా ఉండునట్లు చూడవచ్చును. చదువురాని వయోజనులకు విద్య నేర్పవచ్చును. పట్టణాలలో రహదారి నిబంధనలను తప్పకుండా ఉండునట్లు చేయుటలో పోలీసువారికి విద్యార్థులు సహకరించవచ్చును. ఉత్సవాలు, సభలు జరుగునపుడు విద్యార్థులు స్వచ్ఛంద సేవకులుగా పాల్గొని అచ్చటి జనులకు అవసరమైన సేవలు చేయవచ్చును.ముగింపు :ఈ విధంగా విద్యార్థులు బాల్యం నుండి తమ యింటిలో అమ్మ నాన్నలకు వారు చేయు పనిలో సహకరించడంతో పాటు సంఘసేవా కార్యక్రమాలలో పాల్గొనుట వలన మంచి పనులు చేయుచున్నాము అన్న తృప్తి వారికి కలుగుతుంది. దేశానికి సేవ చేసినట్లు అవుతుంది."},{"question":" Sheeg Dagaalkii Khandaq Magaca Kale Ee Loo-Yaqaano","answer":" Dagaalka Khandaq Magaca Kale Ee Loo-Yaqaano Waa Axzaab."},{"question":"પ્રશ્ન: છેલ્લું નામ બકા ક્યાંથી આવે છે?","answer":"ન્યૂ મેક્સિકો"},{"question":"Maxay kukala duwanyihiin erayada Frontend iyo Backend?","answer":"Labada eray waa labo eray oo Ingriis (English) ah. Micnahooda waxa uu kala noqonayaa sida tan soo socota.Frontend: waa waxa kuusoo muuqanaayo ama la arki karo, tusaale markii aad soo booqato website waxaad arkaysaa qoraalo, sawiro iwm. waxaasi ay indhahaagu qabanaayaan ayaa loo yaqanaa Frontend.Backend: waa meesha lagu keedinaayo xogta ama databaseka. sida Sql, Mysql, Firebase iwm."},{"question":"このカテゴリーのトリビアの例を挙げてください：音楽","answer":"長期のリハビリをしたキーンのメンバーはだれですか? トム・チャプリンです"},{"question":"Ariyanjiyan bẹrẹ lori idajọ iku ti wọn fun Sharif-Aminu, ọkunrin ti wọn lo bu Anọbi ni Kano","answer":"Lati irọlẹ ana, ọjọ Aje, Mọnde, ti kootu Sharia kan niluu Kano ti dajọ iku fun Yahaya Sharif-Aminu ti wọn lo bu Anọbi Muhammad ni ariyanjiyan ti n waye lori igbesẹ ile-ẹjọ naa.Sharif-Aminu, ẹni ọdun mejilelogun, ni wọn fẹsun kan pe o sọrọ aidaa si Muhammad ninu orin kan to gbe si ikanni intanẹẹti Whatsapp loṣu kẹta, ọdun yii.Lẹyin ti ọkunrin naa gbe orin ọhun jade lawọn kan lọọ kọlu ile mọlẹbi rẹ, wọn si ba a jẹ gidigidi, ṣugbọn oun funra ẹ ti fara pamọ. Nigba tọwọ awọn ẹṣọ agbofinro Hisbah tẹ ẹ ni wọn wọ ọ lọ si kootu, nibi ti ko ti yi ọrọ rẹ pada.Nigba to n gbe idajọ kalẹ lanaa, Onidaajọ Khadi Aliyu Muhammad Kani ni loootọ ni olujẹjọ naa sọrọ ṣakaṣaka si Anọbi Muhammad to jẹ aṣaaju ẹsin Musulumi, iku lo si tọ si i fun iru iwa ibajẹ bẹẹ. Ṣugbọn o ni ọkunrin naa lanfaani si ẹjọ ko-tẹ-mi-lọrun ti ko ba fara mọ eyi toun gbe kalẹ.Sharif-Aminu jẹ atẹle ikọ Tijjaniya ati ọmọ ẹgbẹ Faidha to gba pe Ibrahim Nyass to jẹ ọmọwe kan lati ilẹ Senegal lagbara ju Muhammad lọ, eyi lo si fi huwa to ṣakoba fun un yii.Latigba ti idajọ naa ti waye lawọn eeyan ti n sọ oriṣiiriṣii ọrọ, bi awọn kan si ṣe gba pe idajọ ika ati ọdaju ni kootu Sharia n gbe kalẹ lawọn kan sọ pe nnkan to tọ si ọkunrin naa loju ẹ ri."},{"question":"Terjemahkanlah penggalan teks Bahasa Inggris yang disadur dari kumpulan cerita anak dunia berikut ke teks dalam Bahasa Indonesia.Shaju calls, \\"Jami, hurry up!\\" Jami yells back from his room, \\"Hold on! I can't find my ball!\\"Terjemahan:","answer":"\\"Jami, ayo, cepat!\\", panggil Shaju.\\"Sebentar! Aku tidak bisa menemukan bolaku!\\", teriak Jami."},{"question":"Ajụjụ:Kedụ mkpụrụokwu nwere ike ịnọchi anya mkpụrụ okwu a \\"Gburugburu?","answer":"Azịza:OkirikiriGburugburu na okirikiri nwere ike ịnọchi anya ibe ya, nke a dabere n'ihe nkọwa ya pụtara n'ahịrị okwu ahụ. "},{"question":"Sejak ditukarkan ke pedalaman, Encik Sarji sering _____________ isterinya dikota.","answer":"teringat"},{"question":"Hãy viết tiếp nội dung cho đoạn văn sau: Tùy vào quy định của mỗi công ty bảo hiểm, thời hạn hoãn đóng phí định kỳ của khách hàng sẽ khác nhau. Thông thường, trường hợp bên mua bảo hiểm không đóng phí theo yêu cầu như đã thỏa thuận khi đến hạn, bên mua sẽ có một khoảng thời gian gia hạn là 60 ngày từ ngày đến hạn đóng phí. Quá thời hạn đóng phí bảo hiểm, nếu bên mua không đóng, công ty sẽ thông báo bằng văn bản đến họ về khoản phí quá hạn và tình trạng của hợp đồng bảo hiểm. Nếu khách hàng không đóng khoản phí đến hạn, đồng thời, không yêu cầu chấm dứt hợp đồng khi hết thời gian gia hạn và hợp đồng có giá trị hoàn lại, công ty sẽ tự động tạm ứng từ giá trị hợp đồng số tiền bằng khoản phí bảo hiểm đến hạn để đóng phí.","answer":"Khoản tạm ứng này không phụ thuộc vào giới hạn 80% của giá trị hợp đồng hoặc giá trị hoàn lại. Đây là nghiệp vụ phổ biến trong ngành bảo hiểm, trên nguyên tắc đặt quyền được bảo vệ của khách hàng lên trên hết. Để tạo sự công bằng giữa các khách hàng, việc tạm ứng phí tự động sẽ phát sinh khoản giảm thu nhập đầu tư (được hiểu là khoản lãi). Vì thế, khi có đủ tài chính, khách hàng nên nhanh chóng thu xếp hoàn trả lại cả khoản phí và khoản giảm thu nhập đầu tư. Nếu không thể xoay sở một số tiền lớn để thanh toán phí bảo hiểm, người mua có thể gửi yêu cầu tới công ty bảo hiểm đề nghị chuyển định kỳ đóng phí từ năm thành nửa năm, hàng quý hoặc hàng tháng. Số tiền cần nộp sẽ được giảm xuống tương ứng và không còn là áp lực với người mua. Lưu ý, yêu cầu này chỉ thực hiện được vào ngày kỷ niệm năm của hợp đồng. Đặng Lâm Chuyên viên tư vấn bảo hiểm"},{"question":"तपाईलाई शिव भगवान को बारेमा थाहा छ?","answer":"शिव भगवान हिन्दू धर्ममा महत्त्वपूर्ण देवता हुनुहुन्छ। उनलाई हिन्दू धर्मका त्रिमूर्ति (Trimurti) को एक प्रमुख भागको रूपमा मानिएको छ, जसमा ब्रह्मा (Brahma), विष्णु (Vishnu), र शिव (Shiva) परमेश्वरका विभिन्न गुण र प्रतिस्थानहरूका प्रतिनिधि हुन्छन्।शिव भगवानको प्रतिस्थानमा विशेष रूपमा उनका त्रिशूल, सर्प, गंधर्व, बुलबुल, जटामुकुट (जुटी), चंद्रमा, धारा, गंगा नदी, र ध्यानका लागि स्माशानमा वास गर्नुहुन्छ। उनको ध्यान गर्दै, शिवको पूजा गरिन्छ र उनले ब्रह्मा र विष्णुसँग समाजका विविध कार्यहरूमा सहयोग पनि गर्दैछन्।शिवको ध्यान गर्दा, हिन्दू भक्तहरूले उनको ध्यानमुखी जीवनप्रणाली, तपस्या, ध्यान, र त्यागको महत्त्वलाई पनि सिक्दछन्। शिवको एक प्रमुख पूजा पर्व पनि महाशिवरात्रि (Mahashivaratri) हो, जसमा भक्तहरू रातभरि मन्दिरमा पूजा गर्दछन् र शिवका गुण र भक्तिका प्रति उनको श्रद्धावान छन्।"},{"question":"*ما الصوت الذي يصدره المريض ؟","answer":"أنين"},{"question":"Жүүнү бош деген сөз эмнени түшүндүрөт?","answer":"Жүүнү бош деген сөздүн мааниси төмөндөгүдөй:Болбураган, жоош, чыйрак эмес, тың эмес, өлжүрөп колунан эч нерсе келбеген.Суук кабарды угузуп алышып, Максаттын жүүнү боштугуна кейишти, аяшты."},{"question":"Hoje, exatamente 20 anos atrás, iniciava a Guerra da Bósnia, uns dos conflitos mais violentos desde final da II Guerra Mundial (1939 a 1945), quando uma passeata em favor da paz em Sarajevo (leia-se \\"Saraiêvo\\") foi atacada a tiros por sérvios e a cidade começou ser cercada.Por favor, me dê uma boa ideia de título para o artigo acima.","answer":"Claro, um exemplo de título adequado para esse artigo é  \\"Bósnia-Herzegóvina lembra os mortos no dia de aniversário de 20 anos do início da Guerra da Bósnia\\"."}]`),I={name:"App",components:{PoemCard:S},data(){return{searchQuery:"",visibleCount:6,poemsData:T,isLoading:!1}},computed:{filteredPoems(){return this.searchQuery.trim()?this.poemsData.filter(e=>{const a=this.searchQuery.toLowerCase();return e.question.toLowerCase().includes(a)||e.answer.toLowerCase().includes(a)}).slice(0,this.visibleCount):this.poemsData.slice(0,this.visibleCount)},hasMorePoems(){return this.visibleCount<this.poemsData.length}},methods:{async loadMore(){this.isLoading=!0,await new Promise(e=>setTimeout(e,1e3)),this.visibleCount+=6,this.isLoading=!1}}},B={class:"search-container"},C={class:"card-container"},K=["disabled"],O={key:0},P={key:1};function L(e,a,s,d,t,u){const m=b("PoemCard");return i(),o("section",null,[a[3]||(a[3]=n("div",{class:"top-banner"},[n("div",{class:"top-banner-title"},[n("div",{class:"top-banner-title-text"},"🤔 AI effective tips collection 🧠")])],-1)),n("div",B,[a[2]||(a[2]=n("span",{class:"search-icon"},null,-1)),y(n("input",{type:"text",class:"search-input","onUpdate:modelValue":a[0]||(a[0]=r=>t.searchQuery=r),placeholder:"Search..."},null,512),[[w,t.searchQuery]])]),n("div",C,[(i(!0),o(c,null,p(u.filteredPoems,(r,g)=>(i(),f(m,{key:g,poem:r},null,8,["poem"]))),128))]),u.hasMorePoems?(i(),o("button",{key:0,class:"load-more-button",disabled:t.isLoading,onClick:a[1]||(a[1]=(...r)=>u.loadMore&&u.loadMore(...r))},[t.isLoading?(i(),o("span",P,"Loading...")):(i(),o("span",O,"See more"))],8,K)):j("",!0)])}const D=k(I,[["render",L],["__scopeId","data-v-da4b11d4"]]),G=JSON.parse('{"title":"","description":"","frontmatter":{"page":true},"headers":[],"relativePath":"chatai/18.md","filePath":"chatai/18.md"}'),H={name:"chatai/18.md"},U=Object.assign(H,{setup(e){return(a,s)=>(i(),o("div",null,[v(D)]))}});export{G as __pageData,U as default};
